<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 The sonnes of Issachar, 6 Of
Beniamin, 13 Of Naphtali, 14 Of Manasseh, 20, 24 And of Ephraim. 21
The calamitie of Ephraim by the men of Gath. 23 Beriah is borne. 28
Ephraims habitations. 30 The sonnes of Asher.</head>

<ab n="1">Now the
sonnes of Issachar were, Tola, and Puah, Iashub, and Shimron,
foure.<note> Gen.46. 13. num. 26.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the
sonnes of Tola: Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Ieriel, and Iahmai, and
Iibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their fathers house, to wit, of Tola,
they were valiant men of might in their generations, whose number
was in the dayes of Dauid two and twentie thousand and sixe
hundred.<note> 2.Sam.24. 1,2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the
sonnes of Uzzi, Izrahiah: and the sonnes of Izrahiah, Michael, and
Obadiah, and Ioel, Ishiah, fiue: all of them chiefe men.</ab>
<ab n="4">And with
them, by their generations, after the house of their fathers, were
bands of souldiers for warre, sixe and thirtie thousand men: for
they had many wiues and sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="5">And their
brethren among all the families of Issachar, were men of might,
reckoned in all by their genealogies, fourescore and seuen
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ The
sonnes of Beniamin: Bela, and Becher, and Iediael,
three.<note> Gen 46. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the
sonnes of Bela: Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Ierimoth, and Iri,
fiue, heads of the house of their fathers, mightie men of valour,
and were reckoned by their genealogies, twentie and two thousand,
and thirtie and foure.</ab>

<fw>Manasseh, and Ephraim.</fw>
<ab n="8">And the
sonnes of Becher: Zemira, and Ioash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and
Omri, and Ierimoth, and Abiah, and Anathoth, and Alameth. All these
are the sonnes of Becher.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the
number of them, after their genealogie by their generations, heads
of the house of their fathers, mightie men of valour, was twentie
thousand and two hundred.</ab>
<ab n="10">The sonnes
also of Iediael, Bilhan: and the sonnes of Bilhan, Ieush, and
Beniamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tharshish, and
Ahishahar.</ab>
<ab n="11">All these
the sonnes of Iediael, by the heads of their fathers, mighty men of
valour, were seuenteene thousand and two hundred souldiers, fit to
goe out for warre and battaile.</ab>
<ab n="12">Shuppim
also, and Huppim, the children of Ir, and Hushim, the sonnes of
Aher.<note> Or, Iri, vers.7. , Or, Ahiram.num. 26.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ The
sonnes of Naphtali, Iahziel, and Guni, and Iezer, and Shallum, the
sonnes of Bilhah.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ The
sonnes of Manasseh: Ashriel, whom shee bare (but his concnbine the
Aramitesse, bare Machir the father of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Machir
tooke to wife the sister of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sisters name
was Maachah) and the name of the second was Zelophehad: and
Zelophehad had daughters.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Maachah
the wife of Machir bare a sonne, and shee called his name Peresh,
and the name of his brother was Sheresh, and his sonnes were Ulam
and Rakem.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the
sonnes of Ulam, Bedan. These were the sonnes of Gilead, the sonne
of Machir, the sonne of Manasseh.<note> 1.Sam.12 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And his
sister Hammoleketh bare Ishad, and Abiezer, and Mahalah.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
sonnes of Shemida were: Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and
Aniam.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
the sonnes of Ephraim: Shuthelah: and Bered his sonne, and Tahath
his sonne, and Eladah his sonne, and Tahath his sonne,</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And
Zabad his sonne, and Shuthelah his sonne, and Ezer, and Elead, whom
the men of Gath, that were borne in that land slewe, because they
came downe to take away their cattell.</ab>

<fw>Manasseh, and Ephraim.</fw>
<ab n="22">And Ephraim
their father mourned many dayes, and his brethren came to comfort
him.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
when hee went in to his wife, shee conceiued and bare a sonne, and
he called his name, Beriah, because it went euill with his
house.</ab>
<ab n="24">(And his
daughter was Sherah, who built Bethoron the nether, and the vpper,
and Uzzen Sherah.)</ab>
<ab n="25">And Rephah
was his sonne, also Rezeph, and Telah his sonne, and Tahan his
sonne,</ab>
<ab n="26">Laadan his
sonne, Amihud his sonne, Elishama his sonne,</ab>
<ab n="27">Non his
sonne, Iehoshua his sonne.<note> Or, Nun. numb. 13,9.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And
their possessions and habitations were, Bethel, and the townes
thereof, and Eastward Naaran, and Westward Gezer with the townes
thereof, Shechem also and the townes thereof, vnto Gaza and the
townes thereof.<note> Iosh. 16.7. , Hebr. daughters. , Or, Adassa, 1. mac.7.45.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And by the
borders of the children of Manasseh, Bethshean and her townes,
Taanach and her townes, Megiddo and her townes, Dor and her townes.
In these dwelt the children of Ioseph the sonne of
Israel.<note> Iosh.17.7 , Iosh.17. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ The
sonnes of Asher: Imnah, and Isuah, and Ishuai, and Beriah, and
Serah their sister.<note> Gen.46. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And the
sonnes of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel, who is the father of
Birzauith.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Heber
begate Iaphlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shuah their
sister.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the
sonnes of Iaphlet: Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashuath. These are the
children of Iaphlet.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the
sonnes of Shamer: Ahi, and Rohgah, Iehubbah, and Aram.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the
sonne of his brother, Helem: Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and
Amal.</ab>
<ab n="36">The sonnes
of Zophah: Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and
Imrah:</ab>
<ab n="37">Bezer, and
Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the
sonnes of Iether: Iephunneh, and Pispa, and Ara.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the
sonnes of Ulla: Arah, and Haniel, and Rezia.</ab>

<fw>The genealogie of Beniamin.</fw>
<ab n="40">All these
were the children of Asher, heads of their fathers house, choice
and mightie men of valour, chiefe of the princes. And the number
throughout the genealogie of them, that were apt to the warre and
to battell, was twentie and sixe thousand men.</ab>



</div>