<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid fetcheth the Arke with great
solemnitie from Kiriath-iearim. 9 Vzza being smitten, the Arke is
left at the house of Obed-Edom.</head>

<ab n="1">And Dauid
consulted with the captaines of thousands, and hundreds, and with
euery leader.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid
said vnto all the Congregation of Israel, If it seeme good vnto
you, and that it be of the Lord our God, let vs send abroad vnto
our brethren euery where, that are left in all the land of Israel,
and with them also to the Priests and Leuites which are in their
cities and suburbs, that they may gather themselues vnto
vs.<note> Hebr. let vs breake foorth and send. , Hebr. in the cities of their suburbs.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And let vs
bring againe the Arke of our God to vs: for wee enquired not at it
in the dayes of Saul.<note> Heb. bring about.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And all the
Congregation saide, that they would doe so: for the thing was right
in the eyes of all the people.</ab>
<ab n="5">So Dauid
gathered all Israel together, from Shihor of Egypt, euen vnto the
entring of Hemath, to bring the Arke of God from
Kiriath-iearim.<note> 1.Sam.7. 1. 2.sam.6.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Dauid
went vp, and all Israel, to Baalah, that is, to Kiriath-iearim,
which belonged to Iudah, to bring vp thence the Arke of God the
Lord, that dwelleth betweene the Cherubims, whose name is called on
it.<note> Iosh.16.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they
caried the Arke of God in a new cart, out of the house of Abinadab:
and Uzza, and Ahio draue the cart.<note> Heb. made the Arke to ride.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Dauid
and all Israel played before God with all their might, and with
singing, and with harpes, and with psalteries, and with tymbrels,
and with cymbals, and with trumpets.<note> Heb. songs.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
when they came vnto the threshing floore of Chidon, Uzza put foorth
his hand to hold the Arke, for the oxen stumbled.<note> Called Nachon, 2.Sam. 6.6. , Or, shooke it.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the
anger of the Lord was kindled against Uzza, and hee smote him,
because hee put his hand to the Arke: and there he died before
God.<note> Num.4. 15.</note></ab>

<fw>Philistines smitten.</fw>
<ab n="11">And Dauid
was displeased, because the Lord had made a breach vpon Uzza;
wherefore that place is called Perez-Uzza, to this day.<note> Heb. breach of Vzza.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And Dauid
was afraide of God that day, saying, How shall I bring the Arke of
God home to me?</ab>
<ab n="13">So Dauid
brought not the Arke home to himselfe to the city of Dauid, but
caried it aside into the house of Obed-Edom the
Gittite.<note> Hebr. remooued.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the
Arke of God remained with the family of Obed-Edom in his house
three moneths. And the Lord blessed the house of Obed-Edom, and all
that he had.<note> As chap. 26.5.</note></ab>



</div>