<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauids messengers sent to comfort
Hanun the sonne of Nahash, are villanously intreated. 6 The
Ammonites strengthened by the Syrians, are ouercome by Ioab and
Abishai. 16 Shophach making a new supply of the Syrians, is slaine
by Dauid.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came
to passe after this, that Nahash the King of the children of Ammon
dyed, &amp; his sonne reigned in his stead.<note> 2.Sam.10. ver.1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid
sayde, I will shewe kindnesse vnto Hanun the sonne of Nahash,
because his father shewed kindnesse to mee. And Dauid sent
messengers to comfort him concerning his father. So the seruants of
Dauid came into the land of the children of Ammon, to Hanun, to
comfort him.</ab>
<ab n="3">But the
Princes of the children of Ammon sayde to Hanun, Thinkest thou that
Dauid doeth honour thy father, that he hath sent comforters vnto
thee? Are not his seruants come vnto thee for to search, and to
ouerthrow, and to spie out the land?<note> Heb. In thine eyes doeth Dauid, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Wherefore
Hanun tooke Dauids seruants, and shaued them, and cut off their
garments in the middest, hard by their buttockes, and sent them
away.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then there
went certeine, and told Dauid, how the men were serued, and hee
sent to meet them (for the men were greatly ashamed) and the King
sayde, Tary at Iericho vntill your beards be growen, and then
returne.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
when the children of Ammon sawe, that they had made themselues
odious to Dauid; Hanun and the children of Ammon sent a thousand
talents of siluer, to hire them charets and horsemen out of
Mesopotamia, and out of Syria-Maachah, and out of
Zobah.<note> Heb. to stinke.</note></ab>

<fw>The Ammonites are ouercome.</fw>
<ab n="7">So they
hired thirtie and two thousand charets, and the king of Maachah and
his people, who came and pitched before Medeba. And the children of
Ammon gathered themselues together from their cities, and came to
battaile.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when
Dauid heard of it, hee sent Ioab, and all the host of the mightie
men.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the
children of Ammon came out, and put the battell in aray before the
gate of the citie, and the kings that were come, were by themselues
in the field.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now when
Ioab saw that the battell was set against him, before and behinde:
hee chose out of all the choice of Israel, and put them in aray
against the Syrians.<note> Hebr. the face of the battell was. , Or, yong men.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the
rest of the people hee deliuered vnto the hand of Abishai his
brother, and they set themselues in aray against the children of
Ammon.<note> Hebr Abshai.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And he
said, If the Syrians bee too strong for me, then thou shalt helpe
me: but if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, then I wil
helpe thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">Be of good
courage, and let vs behaue our selues valiantly for our people, and
for the Cities of our God: and let the Lord do that which is good
in his sight.</ab>
<ab n="14">So Ioab and
the people that were with him, drew nigh before the Syrians, vnto
the battell; and they fled before him.</ab>
<ab n="15">And when
the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fled, they likewise
fled before Abishai his brother, and entred into the city. Then
Ioab came to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
when the Syrians saw that they were put to the worse before Israel,
they sent messengers, and drew forth the Syrians, that were beyond
the Riuer: and Shophach the captaine of the hoste of Hadarezer,
went before them.<note> i.Euphrates. , Or Shobach, 2.sam. 10.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And it was
tolde Dauid, and hee gathered all Israel, and passed ouer Iordane,
and came vpon them, and set the battell in aray against them: so
when Dauid had put the battell in aray against the Syrians, they
fought with him.</ab>

<fw>The Ammonites are ouercome.</fw>
<ab n="18">But the
Syrians fled before Israel, and Dauid slew of the Syrians seuen
thousand men, which fought in charets, and fourty thousand footmen,
and killed Shophach the captaine of the hoste.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when
the seruants of Hadarezer saw that they were put to the worse
before Israel, they made peace with Dauid, and became his seruants:
neither would the Syrians helpe the children of Ammon any
more.</ab>



</div>