<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 The twelue Captaines, for euery
seuerall moneth. 16 The Princes of the twelue Tribes. 23 The
numbring of the people is hindered. 25 Dauids seuerall
Officers.</head>


<fw>Officers appointed for the
King.</fw>
<ab n="1">Nowe the
children of Israel after their number, to wit, the chiefe fathers
and captaines of thousands and hundreds, and their officers that
serued the king in any matter of the courses, which came in, and
went out moneth by moneth, throughout all the moneths of the yeare,
of euery course were twentie and foure thousand.</ab>
<ab n="2">Ouer the
first course for the first moneth was Iashobeam the sonne of
Zabdiel, and in his course were twentie and foure thousand.</ab>
<ab n="3">Of the
children of Perez, was the chiefe of all the captaines of the host,
for the first moneth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And ouer the
course of the second moneth was Dodai an Ahohite, and of his course
was Mikloth also the ruler: In his course likewise were twentie and
foure thousand.<note> Or, Dodo. 2 Sam.23.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The third
captaine of the host for the third month was Benaiah the sonne of
Iehoiada a chiefe priest, and in his course were twenty and foure
thousand.<note> Or, principall officer.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">This is that
Benaiah, who was mightie among the thirtie, and aboue the thirty:
and in his course was Amizabad his sonne.<note> 2.Sam.23. 20.22.23. &amp; 1 Chron. 11.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The fourth
captaine for the fourth moneth was Asahel the brother of Ioab, and
Zebadiah his sonne after him: and in his course were twentie and
foure thousand.</ab>
<ab n="8">The fifth
captaine for the fifth moneth, was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in
his course were twentie and foure thousand.</ab>
<ab n="9">The sixt
captaine for the sixt moneth, was Ira the son of Ikkesh the
Tekoite: and in his course were twentie and foure thousand.</ab>
<ab n="10">The seuenth
captaine for the seuenth moneth was Helez the Pelonite, of the
children of Ephraim: and in his course were twentie and foure
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="11">The eighth
captaine for the eighth moneth, was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the
Zarhites: and in his course were twentie and foure
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="12">The ninth
captaine for the ninth moneth, was Abiezer the Anetothite, of the
Beniamites: and in his course were twentie and foure
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="13">The tenth
captaine for the tenth moneth, was Maharai the Netophathite, of the
Zarhites: and in his course were twentie and foure
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="14">The
eleuenth captaine for the eleuenth moneth was Benaiah the
Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were
twenty and foure thousand.</ab>

<fw>Officers for the Kings seruice.</fw>
<ab n="15">The twelfth
captaine for the twelfth moneth, was Heldai the Netophathite, of
Othniel: and in his course were twentie and foure
thousand.<note> Or, Heled, Chap.11.30</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶
Furthermore, ouer the tribes of Israel: The Ruler of the Reubenites
was Eliezer the sonne of Zichri: of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the
sonne of Maachah.</ab>
<ab n="17">Of the
Leuites: Hashabiah the sonne of Kemuel; of the Aaronites,
Zadok.</ab>
<ab n="18">Of Iudah,
Elihu, one of the brethren of Dauid: of Issachar, Omri the sonne of
Michael.</ab>
<ab n="19">Of Zebulun,
Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah: of Naphtali, Ierimoth the sonne of
Azriel.</ab>
<ab n="20">Of the
children of Ephraim, Hoshea the sonne of Azazziah: of the halfe
tribe of Manasseh, Ioel the sonne of Pedaiah.</ab>
<ab n="21">Of the
halfe tribe of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the sonne of Zechariah: of
Beniamin, Iaasiel the son of Abner.</ab>
<ab n="22">Of Dan,
Azariel the sonne of Ieroham. These were the princes of the tribes
of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ But
Dauid tooke not the number of them from twentie yeeres olde and
vnder: because the Lord had said, hee would increase Israel like to
the starres of the heauens.</ab>
<ab n="24">Ioab the
sonne of Zeruiah began to number, but he finished not, because
there fell wrath for it against Israel, neither was the number put
in the account of the Chronicles of King Dauid.<note> 1. Chron. 21.7. 2.sam. 24.5. &amp;c. , Heb. ascended.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
ouer the Kings treasures, was Azmaueth the sonne of Adiel: and ouer
the store-houses in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages,
and in the castles, was Iehonathan the sonne of Uzziah.</ab>
<ab n="26">And ouer
them that did the worke of the field, for tillage of the ground,
was Ezri the sonne of Chelub.</ab>
<ab n="27">And ouer
the Uineyards, was Shimei the Ramathite: ouer the increase of the
vineyards for the wine cellars, was Sabdi the Ziphmite.<note> Heb. ouer that which was of the vineyards.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And ouer
the Oliue trees, and the Sycomore trees that were in the lowe
plaines, was Baal-hanan the Gederite: and ouer the cellars of oyle
was Ioash.</ab>

<fw>Officers for the Kings seruice.</fw>
<ab n="29">And ouer
the herdes that fed in Sharon, was Shetrai the Sharonite: and ouer
the herds that were in the valleys, was Shaphat the sonne of
Adlai.</ab>
<ab n="30">Ouer the
camels also, was Obil the Ishmaelite: and ouer the Asses, was
Iehdeiah the Meronothite.</ab>
<ab n="31">And ouer
the flockes, was Iaziz the Hagerite. All these were the rulers of
the substance which was king Dauids.</ab>
<ab n="32">Also
Ionathan Dauids uncle, was a counseller, a wise man, and a Scribe:
and Iehiel the sonne of Hachmoni, was with the kings
sonnes.<note> Or, secretarie. , Or, Hachmonite.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And
Ahitophel was the kings counseller, and Hushai the Archite, was the
kings companion.</ab>
<ab n="34">And after
Ahitophel, was Iehoiada the sonne of Benaiah, and Abiathar: and the
general of the Kings armie was Ioab.</ab>



</div>