<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 The diuisions of the sonnes of
Aaron by lot into foure and twenty orders. 20 The Kohathites, 27
and the Merarites diuided by lot.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these
are the diuisions of the sonnes of Aaron. The sonnes of Aaron:
Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.<note> Leui.10.4</note></ab>

<fw>The Priests and Leuites
offices.</fw>
<ab n="2">But Nadab
and Abihu died before their father, and had no children: Therefore
Eleazar and Ithamar executed the Priests office.<note> Num.3.4. and 26.60.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Dauid
distributed them, both Zadok of the sonnes of Eleazar, and
Ahimelech of the sonnes of Ithamar, according to their offices in
their seruice.</ab>
<ab n="4">And there
were moe chiefe men found of the sonnes of Eleazar, then of the
sonnes of Ithamar: and thus were they diuided. Among the sonnes of
Eleazar there were sixteene chiefe men of the house of their
fathers, and eight among the sonnes of Ithamar according to the
house of their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="5">Thus were
they diuided by lot, one sort with another; for the gouernours of
the Sanctuarie, and gouernours of the house of God, were of the
sonnes of Eleazar, and of the sonnes of Ithamar.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Shemaiah
the sonne of Nathanael the Scribe, one of the Leuites, wrote them
before the King and the Princes, and Zadok the Priest, and
Ahimelech the sonne of Abiathar, and before the chiefe of the
fathers of the priests and Leuites: one principall houshold being
taken for Eleazar, and one taken for Ithamar.<note> Heb. house of the father</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Now the
first lot came foorth to Iehoiarib: the second to Iedaiah,</ab>
<ab n="8">The third to
Harim, the fourth to Seorim,</ab>
<ab n="9">The fifth to
Malchiiah, the sixth to Miiamin,</ab>
<ab n="10">The seuenth
to Hakkoz, the eight to Abiiah,<note> Luk.1.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The ninth
to Ieshua, the tenth to Shecaniah,</ab>
<ab n="12">The
eleuenth to Eliashib, the twelfth to Iakim,</ab>
<ab n="13">The
thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Ieshebeab,</ab>
<ab n="14">The
fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer,</ab>
<ab n="15">The
seuenteenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Aphses,</ab>
<ab n="16">The
ninteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Iehezekel,</ab>
<ab n="17">The one and
twentieth to Iachin, the two and twentieth to Gamul,</ab>
<ab n="18">The three
and twentieth to Delaiah, the foure and twentieth to
Maaziah.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites and their offices.</fw>
<ab n="19">These were
the orderings of them in their seruice to come into the house of
the Lord according to their maner, vnder Aaron their father, as the
Lord God of Israel had commanded him.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
the rest of the sonnes of Leui were these: of the sons of Amram,
Shubael: of the sonnes of Shubael, Iedeiah.</ab>
<ab n="21">Concerning
Rehabiah, of the sons of Rehabiah, the first was Isshiah.</ab>
<ab n="22">Of the
Izharites, Shelomoth: of the sonnes of Shelomoth, Iahath.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
sonnes of Hebron, Ieriah the first, Amariah the second, Iahaziel
the third, Iekameam the fourth.<note> Chap.23. 19. and 26. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Of the
sonnes of Uzziel, Michah: of the sonnes of Michah, Shamir.</ab>
<ab n="25">The brother
of Michah was Isshiah: of the sonnes of Isshiah, Zechariah.</ab>
<ab n="26">The sonnes
of Merari were Mahli and Mushi: the sonnes of Iaaziah,
Beno.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ The
sonnes of Merari by Iaaziah, Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and
Ibri.</ab>
<ab n="28">Of Mahli
came Eleazar, who had no sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="29">Concerning
Kish: the sonne of Kish was Ierahmeel.</ab>
<ab n="30">The sonnes
also of Mushi, Mahli, and Eder, and Ierimoth. These were the sonnes
of the Leuites after the house of their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="31">These
likewise cast lots ouer against their brethren the sonnes of Aaron,
in the presence of Dauid the King, and Zadok and Ahimelech, and the
chiefe of the fathers of the priests and Leuites, euen the
principall fathers ouer against their yonger brethren.</ab>



</div>