<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Nathan first approouing the
purpose of Dauid, to build God an house, 3 after by the word of God
forbiddeth him. 11 Hee promiseth him blessings and benefits in his
seed. 16 Dauids prayer and thankesgiuing.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came
to passe, as Dauid sate in his house, that Dauid sayde to Nathan
the Prophet, Loe, I dwell in an house of Cedars, but the Arke of
the Couenant of the Lord remaineth vnder curtaines.<note> 2.Sam. 7. 1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then Nathan
sayd vnto Dauid, Doe all that is in thine heart, for God is with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
it came to passe the same night, that the word of God came to
Nathan, saying,</ab>
<ab n="4">Goe and tell
Dauid my seruant, Thus saith the Lord, Thou shalt not build me an
house to dwell in.</ab>

<fw>Dauids thankes, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="5">For I haue
not dwelt in a house since the day that I brought vp Israel, vnto
this day, but haue gone from tent to tent, and from one Tabernacle
to another.<note> Heb. haue bene.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Wheresoeuer
I haue walked with all Israel, spake I a word to any of the Iudges
of Israel (whom I commanded to feed my people) saying, Why haue ye
not built me an house of Cedars?</ab>
<ab n="7">Now
therefore thus shalt thou say vnto my seruant Dauid, Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, I tooke thee from the Sheep-coat, euen from folowing
the sheep, that thou shouldest be ruler ouer my people
Israel:<note> Heb. from after.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I haue
bene with thee whithersoeuer thou hast walked, and haue cut off all
thine enemies from before thee, and haue made thee a name, like the
name of the great men that are in the earth.</ab>
<ab n="9">Also I will
ordeine a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, and they
shall dwell in their place, and shall be moued no more: neither
shal the children of wickednesse waste them any more (as at the
beginning,</ab>
<ab n="10">And since
the time that I commanded Iudges to bee ouer my people Israel.)
Moreouer, I will subdue all thine enemies. Furthermore I tel thee,
that the Lord will build thee an house.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
it shall come to passe, when thy dayes be expired, that thou must
go to be with thy fathers, that I will raise vp thy seed after
thee, which shall bee of thy sonnes, and I wil stablish his
kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="12">He shall
build me an house, and I will stablish his throne for euer.</ab>
<ab n="13">I will be
his father, and he shall be my sonne, and I will not take my mercie
away from him, as I tooke it from him that was before
thee.<note> 2.King.9. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But I will
settle him in mine house, and in my kingdom for euer, and his
throne shall bee established for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="15">According
to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan
speake vnto Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
Dauid the king came, and sate before the Lord, and said, Who am I,
O Lord God, and what is mine house, that thou hast brought mee
hitherto?</ab>

<fw>Dauids thankes, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="17">And yet
this was a small thing in thine eyes, O God: for thou hast also
spoken of thy seruants house, for a great while to come, and hast
regarded mee according to the estate of a man of high degree, O
Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="18">What can
Dauid speake more to thee for the honour of thy seruant? for thou
knowest thy seruant.</ab>
<ab n="19">O Lord, for
thy seruants sake, and according to thine owne heart, hast thou
done all this greatnesse in making knowen all these great
things.<note> Heb. greatnesses.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">O Lord,
there is none like thee neither is there any God besides thee,
according to all that we haue heard with our eares.</ab>
<ab n="21">And what
one nation in the earth is like thy people Israel, whome God went
to redeeme to be his owne people, to make thee a name of greatnesse
and terriblenesse, by driuing out nations from before thy people
whom thou hast redeemed out of Egypt?</ab>
<ab n="22">For thy
people Israel didst thou make thine owne people for euer, and thou,
Lord, becamest their God.</ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore
now Lord, let the thing that thou hast spoken concerning thy
seruant, and concerning his house, be established for euer, and doe
as thou hast said.</ab>
<ab n="24">Let it euen
bee established, that thy name may bee magnified for euer, saying,
The Lord of hosts is the God of Israel, euen a God to Israel: and
let the house of Dauid thy seruant be established before
thee.</ab>
<ab n="25">For thou, O
my God, hast tolde thy seruant that thou wilt build him an house:
therefore thy seruant hath found in his heart to pray before
thee.<note> Heb. hast reuealed the eare of thy seruant.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And now,
Lord (thou art God, and hast promised this goodnesse vnto thy
seruant.)</ab>
<ab n="27">Now
therefore let it please thee to blesse the house of thy seruant,
that it may bee before thee for euer: for thou blessest, O Lord,
and it shalbe blessed for euer.<note> Or, it hath pleased thee.</note></ab>



</div>