<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-25-25b-1-Chronicles.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Adams line to Noah. 5 The sonnes
of Iapheth. 8 The sonnes of Ham. 17 The sonnes of Shem. 24 Shems
line to Abraham. 29 Ishmaels sonnes. 32 The sonnes of Keturah. 34
The posteritie of Abraham by Esau. 43 The Kings of Edom. 51 The
Dukes of Edom.</head>

<ab n="1">Adam, Sheth,
Enosh,<note> Gen. 5.3,9.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Kenan,
Mahalaleel, Iered,</ab>
<ab n="3">Henoch,
Methushelah, Lamech,</ab>
<ab n="4">Noah, Shem,
Ham, &amp; Iapheth.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ The
sonnes of Iapheth: Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Iauan, and
Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.<note> Gen.10.2</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the
sonnes of Gomer: Ashchenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.<note> Or, Diphath, as it is in some copies.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the
sonnes of Iauan: Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and
Dodanim.<note> Or, Rodanim, accorning to some copies.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ The
sonnes of Ham: Cush, and Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the
sonnes of Cush: Siba, and Hauilah, and Sabta, and Raamah, and
Sabtecha: and the sonnes of Raamah: Sheba, and Dedan.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Cush
begate Nimrod: hee began to be mightie vpon the earth.<note> Gen. 10.8</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Mizraim
begate Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim,</ab>
<ab n="12">And
Pathrusim, and Casluhim (of whome came the Philistines) and
Caphthorim.<note> Deut. 2.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Canaan
begate Zidon his first borne, and Heth.</ab>
<ab n="14">The Iebusite
also, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite,</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
Hiuite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite,</ab>
<ab n="16">And the
Aruadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ The
sonnes of Shem: Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram,
and Uz, &amp; Hul, and Gether, and Meshech.<note> Gen.10.23. &amp; 11.10. , Or, Mash. gen. 10.23</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Arphaxad
begate Shelah, and Shelah begate Eber.</ab>
<ab n="19">And vnto
Eber were borne two sonnes: the name of the one was Peleg, (because
in his dayes the earth was diuided) and his brothers name was
Ioktan.<note> That is division.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Ioktan
begate Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazermaueth, and
Ierah,<note> Gen.10.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Hadoram
also, and Uzal, and Diklah,</ab>
<ab n="22">And Ebal,
and Abimael, and Sheba,</ab>
<ab n="23">And Ophir,
and Hauilah, and Iobab: all these were the sonnes of
Ioktan.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Shem,
Arphaxad, Shelah,<note> Luke 3.24</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Eber, Peleg,
Rehu,<note> Gen.11.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Serug,
Nahor, Terah,</ab>

<fw>Abrahams generations.</fw>
<ab n="27">Abram, the
same is Abraham.<note> Gen.17.5</note></ab>
<ab n="28">The sonnes
of Abraham: Isaac, and Ishmael.<note> Gen.21.2,3. , Gen.16.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ These
are their generations: The first-borne of Ishmael, Nebaioth, then
Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam,<note> Gen.25.13, to 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Mishma, and
Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema,<note> Or, Hadar, Gen. 25.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Ietur,
Naphish, and Kedemah. These are the sonnes of Ishmael.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ Now
the sonnes of Keturah, Abrahams Concubine: she bare Zimran, and
Iokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. And the
sonnes of Iokshan, Sheba, and Dedan.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the
sonnes of Midian: Ephah, and Ephar, and Henoch, and Abida, and
Eldaah. All these are the sonnes of Keturah.</ab>
<ab n="34">And Abraham
begate Isaac. The sonnes of Isaac: Esau, and Israel.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ The
sonnes of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, and Ieush, and Iaalam, and
Korah.<note> Gen.36.9,10.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">The sonnes
of Eliphaz: Teman, and Omar, Zephi, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna,
and Amalek.<note> Or, Zepho, Gen. 36.12</note></ab>
<ab n="37">The sonnes
of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the
sonnes of Seir: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and
Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the
sonnes of Lotan: Hori, and Homam: and Timna was Lotans
sister.<note> Or, Heman, Gen. 36.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">The sonnes
of Shobal: Atian, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And the
sonnes of Zibeon: Aiah, and Anah.<note> Or, Aluan, Gen 36.23. , Or, Sepho, Gen. 36.23</note></ab>
<ab n="41">The sonnes
of Anah: Dishon. And the sonnes of Dishon: Amram, and Eshban, and
Ithran, and Cheran.<note> Chap.2.31. , Or Hemdan, Gen.36.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">The sonnes
of Ezer: Bilham, and Zauan, and Iakan. The sonnes of Dishon: Uz,
and Aran.<note> Or, Akan, Gen. 36.27</note></ab>
<ab n="43">¶ Now
these are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before any
king reigned ouer the children of Israel. Bela the sonne of Beor;
and the name of his citie, was Dinhabah.<note> Gen.36.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And when
Bela was dead, Iobab the sonne of Zerah of Bosrah, reigned in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="45">And when
Iobab was dead, Husham of the land of the Temanits, reigned in his
stead.</ab>

<fw>Abrahams generations.</fw>
<ab n="46">And when
Husham was dead, Hadad, the sonne of Bedad (which smote Midian in
the field of Moab) reigned in his stead: and the name of his citie
was Auith.</ab>
<ab n="47">And when
Hadad was dead, Samlah of Masrekah, reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="48">And when
Samlah was dead, Shaul of Rehoboth by the riuer, reigned in his
stead.<note> Gen.36.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">And when
Shaul was dead, Baal-hanan the sonne of Achbor, reigned in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="50">And when
Baal-hanan was dead, Hadad reigned in his stead: and the name of
his citie was Pai: and his wiues name was Mehetabel the daughter of
Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.<note> Or, Hadar, Gen. 36.39 , Or, Pau, Gen. 36.39</note></ab>
<ab n="51">¶ Hadad
dyed also. And the Dukes of Edom were: Duke Timnah, Duke Aliah,
Duke Ietheth,<note> Gen.36.40.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Duke
Aholibamah, Duke Elah, Duke Pinon,</ab>
<ab n="53">Duke Kenaz,
Duke Teman, Duke Mibzar,</ab>
<ab n="54">Duke
Magdiel, Duke Iram. These are the Dukes of Edom.</ab>



</div>