<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The sonnes of Leui. 4 The line of
the Priests vnto the captiuitie. 16 The families of Gershom,
Merari, and Kohath. 49 The office of Aaron and his line vnto
Ahimaaz. 54 The cities of the Priests and Leuites.</head>


<fw>The genealogie of the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="1">The sonnes of
Leui: Gershon, Kohath &amp; Merari.<note> Gen.46. 11. exod.6.17. , Or, Gershom, ver.16</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the
sonnes of Kohath: Amram, Izahar, &amp; Hebron, &amp;
Uzziel.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the
children of Amram: Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. The sonnes also of
Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.<note> Leuit.10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶
Eleazar begate Phinehas, Phinehas begate Abishua.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Abishua
begate Bukki, and Bukki begate Uzzi,</ab>
<ab n="6">And Uzzi
begate Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begate Meraioth,</ab>
<ab n="7">Meraioth
begate Amariah, and Amariah begate Ahitub,</ab>
<ab n="8">And Ahitub
begate Zadok, and Zadok begate Ahimaaz,<note> 2.Sam.15. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Ahimaaz
begate Azariah, and Azariah begate Iohanan,</ab>
<ab n="10">And Iohanan
begate Azariah, (hee it is that executed the Priests office, in the
temple that Solomon built in Ierusalem)<note> Hebr. in the house. , 2.Chron 3. 1.king.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Azariah
begate Amariah, and Amariah begate Ahitub,</ab>
<ab n="12">And Ahitub
begate Zadok, and Zadok begate Shallum,<note> Or, Meshullam. 1.chro.9.11</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Shallum
begate Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begate Azariah,</ab>
<ab n="14">And Azariah
begate Seraiah, and Seraiah begate Iehozadak,<note> Nehem. 11.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And
Iehozadak went into captiuitie, when the Lord caried away Iudah and
Ierusalem by the hand of Nebuchad-nezzar.<note> 2.Kings 25.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ The
sonnes of Leui: Gershom, Kohath, and Merari.<note> Exod.6. 17. , Or, Geshon, ver. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And these be
the names of the sonnes of Gershom: Libni, &amp; Shimei.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
sonnes of Kohath were: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and
Uzziel.</ab>
<ab n="19">The sonnes
of Merari: Mahli, and Mushi. And these are the families of the
Leuites, according to their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="20">Of Gershom:
Libni his sonne, Iahath his sonne, Zimmah his sonne,<note> Vers.42.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Ioah his
sonne, Iddo his sonne, Zerah his sonne, Ieaterai his
sonne,<note> Or, Ethan. ver. 2. , Or, Adaia. ver.41.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The sonnes
of Kohath: Amminadab his sonne, Korah his sonne, Assir his
sonne,<note> Or, Izahar, ver.2, 18.</note></ab>

<fw>The genealogie of the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="23">Elkanah his
sonne, and Ebiasaph his sonne, and Assir his sonne,</ab>
<ab n="24">Tahath his
sonne, Uriel his sonne, Uzziah his sonne, and Shaul his
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the
sonnes of Elkanah: Amasai, and Ahimoth.<note> See 35. &amp; 36.verses.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">As for
Elkanah: the sonnes of Elkanah, Zophai his sonne, and Nahath his
sonne,<note> Or Zuph, 1.Sam. 1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Eliab his
sonne, Ieroham his sonne, Elkanah his sonne.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the
sonnes of Samuel: the first borne Uashni, and Abiah.<note> Called also Ioel. ver. 33. &amp; 1. Sam. 8.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The sonnes
of Merari: Mahli, Libni his sonne, Shimei his sonne, Uzza his
sonne,</ab>
<ab n="30">Shimea his
sonne, Haggiah his sonne, Asaiah his sonne.</ab>
<ab n="31">And these
are they, whom Dauid set ouer the seruice of song in the house of
the Lord, after that the Arke had rest.<note> Chap. 16.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And they
ministred before the dwelling place of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, with singing, vntill Solomon had built the house of
the Lord in Ierusalem: and then they waited on their office,
according to their order.</ab>
<ab n="33">And these
are they that waited with their children of the sonnes of the
Kohathites, Heman a singer: the sonne of Ioel, the sonne of
Shemuel,<note> Heb. stood.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">The sonne of
Elkanah, the sonne of Ieroham, the sonne of Eliel, the sonne of
Toah,</ab>
<ab n="35">The sonne of
Zuph, the sonne of Elkanah, the sonne of Mahath, the sonne of
Amasai,</ab>
<ab n="36">The sonne of
Elkanah, the sonne of Ioel, the sonne of Azariah, the sonne of
Zephaniah,</ab>
<ab n="37">The sonne of
Tahath, the sonne of Assir, the sonne of Ebiasaph, the sonne of
Korah,<note> Exod.6. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">The sonne of
Izhar, the sonne of Kohath, the sonne of Leui, the sonne of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="39">And his
brother Asaph (who stood on his right hand) euen Asaph the sonne of
Berachiah, the sonne of Shimea,</ab>
<ab n="40">The sonne of
Michael, the sonne of Baasiah, the sonne of Melchiah,</ab>
<ab n="41">The sonne of
Ethni, the sonne of Zerah, the sonne of Adaiah,</ab>
<ab n="42">The sonne of
Ethan, the sonne of Zimmah, the sonne of Shimei,</ab>

<fw>The genealogie of the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="43">The sonne of
Iahath, the sonne of Gershom, the sonne of Leui.</ab>
<ab n="44">And their
brethren the sonnes of Merari, stood on the left hand: Ethan the
sonne of Kishi, the sonne of Abdi, the sonne of
Malluch,<note> Or, Kushaiah. chap. 15.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">The sonne of
Hashabiah, the sonne of Amaziah, the sonne of Hilkiah,</ab>
<ab n="46">The sonne of
Amzi, the sonne of Bani, the sonne of Shamer,</ab>
<ab n="47">The sonne of
Mahli, the sonne of Mushi, the sonne of Merari, the sonne of
Leui.</ab>
<ab n="48">Their
brethren also the Leuits were appointed vnto all maner of seruice
of the Tabernacle of the house of God.</ab>
<ab n="49">¶ But
Aaron, and his sonnes offered vpon the altar of the burnt offering,
and on the altar of incense, and were appointed for all the worke
of the place most holy, and to make an atonement for Israel,
according to all that Moses the seruant of God had
commaunded.<note> Leuit.1.9. , Exod. 30.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">And these
are the sonnes of Aaron: Eleazar his sonne, Phinehas his sonne,
Abishua his sonne,</ab>
<ab n="51">Bukki his
sonne, Uzzi his sonne, Zerahiah his sonne,</ab>
<ab n="52">Meraioth his
sonne, Amariah his sonne, Ahitub his sonne,</ab>
<ab n="53">Zadok his
sonne, Ahimaaz his sonne.</ab>
<ab n="54">¶ Now
these are their dwelling places, throughout their castels in their
coasts, of the sonnes of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites:
for theirs was the lot.</ab>
<ab n="55">And they
gaue them Hebron in the land of Iudah, and the suburbes thereof
round about it.</ab>
<ab n="56">But the
fields of the citie, and the villages thereof, they gaue to Caleb
the sonne of Iephunneh.</ab>
<ab n="57">And to the
sonnes of Aaron they gaue the cities of Iudah, namely Hebron the
citie of refuge, and Libna with her suburbes, and Iattir and
Eshtemoa, with their suburbes,</ab>
<ab n="58">And Hilen
with her suburbes, Debir with her suburbes,<note> Or Holon, Iosh. 21. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">And Ashan
with her suburbes, and Beth-shemesh with her suburbes.<note> Or Ain, Iosh.21.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">And out of
the tribe of Beniamin, Geba with her suburbes, and Alemeth with her
suburbes, Anathoth with her suburbes. All their cities throughout
their families were thirteene cities.<note> Or Almon, Iosh. 21. 18.</note></ab>

<fw>The Leuites cities.</fw>
<ab n="61">And vnto the
sonnes of Rohath, which were left of the family of that tribe, were
cities giuen out of the halfe tribe, namely out of the halfe tribe
of Manasseh, by lot, ten cities.<note> Iosh.21.5</note></ab>
<ab n="62">And to the
sonnes of Gershom throughout their families, out of the tribe of
Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of
Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteene
cities.</ab>
<ab n="63">Unto the
sonnes of Merari were giuen by lot, throughout their families, out
of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the
tribe of Zebulun, twelue cities.<note> Iosh.21. 7, 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">And the
children of Israel gaue to the Leuites these cities, with their
suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="65">And they
gaue by lot, out of the tribe of the children of Iudah, and out of
the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the
children of Beniamin, these cities, which are called by their
names.</ab>
<ab n="66">And the
residue of the families of the sonnes of Kohath, had cities of
their coasts, out of the tribe of Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="67">And they
gaue vnto them of the cities of refuge, Shechem in mount Ephraim,
with her suburbs: they gaue also Gezer with her
suburbs,<note> Iosh.21. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="68">And Iokmeam
with her suburbs, &amp; Beth-horon with her suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="69">And Aialon
with her suburbs, and Gath-rimmon with her suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="70">And out of
the halfe tribe of Manasseh, Aner with her suburbs, and Bileam with
her suburbs, for the family of the remnant of the sonnes of
Kohath.</ab>
<ab n="71">Unto the
sonnes of Gershom, were giuen out of the family of the halfe tribe
of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with her suburbs, and Ashtaroth with
her suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="72">And out of
the tribe of Issachar, Kedesh with her suburbs, Daberath with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="73">And Ramoth
with her suburbs, and Anem with her suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="74">And out of
the tribe of Asher, Mashal with her suburbs, and Abdon with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="75">And Hukok
with her suburbs, and Rehob with her suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="76">And out of
the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee, with her suburbs, and
Hammon with her suburbs, and Kiriathaim with her suburbs.</ab>

<fw>Issachar, Beniamin,</fw>
<ab n="77">Unto the
rest of the children of Merari were giuen out of the tribe of
Zebulun, Rimmon with her suburbs, Tabor with her suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="78">And on the
other side Iorden by Iericho, on the East side of Iorden,were giuen
them out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wildernesse with her
suburbs, &amp; Iahzah with her suburbs,<note> Or, Bozor, Iosh. 21.35</note></ab>
<ab n="79">Kedemoth
also with her suburbs, &amp; Mephaath with her suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="80">And out of
the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with her suburbs, and Mahanaim
with her suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="81">And Heshbon
with her suburbs, and Iazer with her suburbs.</ab>



</div>