<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Hirams kindnesse to Dauid. 2
Dauids felicitie in people, wiues and children. 8 His two victories
against the Philistines.</head>

<ab n="1">Now Hiram
king of Tyre sent messengers to Dauid, and timber of Cedars, with
masons, and carpenters to build him an house.<note> 2.Sam.5. 11. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid
perceiued that the Lord had confirmed him king ouer Israel, for his
kingdome was lift vp on high, because of his people Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
Dauid tooke moe wiues at Ierusalem: and Dauid begate moe sonnes and
daughters.<note> Hebr. yet.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Now these
are the names of his children which hee had in Ierusalem: Shammua,
and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon,</ab>
<ab n="5">And Ibhar,
and Elishua, and Elpalet,</ab>
<ab n="6">And Noga,
and Nepheg, and Iaphia,</ab>
<ab n="7">And
Elishama, and Beeliada, and Elpalet.<note> Or, Eliadæ, 2.Sam. 5. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
when the Philistines heard that Dauid was anoynted king ouer all
Israel, all the Philistines went vp to seeke Dauid: and Dauid heard
of it, and went out against them.<note> 2. Sam. 5.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the
Philistines came &amp; spread themselues in the valley of
Rephaim.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Dauid
enquired of God, saying, Shall I goe vp against the Philistines?
and wilt thou deliuer them into mine hand? And the Lord said vnto
him, Go vp, for I will deliuer them into thine hand.</ab>

<fw>The bringing of the Arke.</fw>
<ab n="11">So they
came vp to Baal-Perazim, and Dauid smote them there. Then Dauid
said, God hath broken in vpon mine enemies by mine hand, like the
breaking foorth of waters: therefore they called the name of that
place, Baal-Perazim.<note> Heb. that is a place of breaches.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And when
they had left their gods there, Dauid gaue a commandement, and they
were burnt with fire.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the
Philistines yet againe spread themselues abroad in the
valley.</ab>
<ab n="14">Therfore
Dauid enquired againe of God, and God said vnto him, Goe not vp
after them, turne away from them, and come vpon them ouer against
the mulbery trees.<note> 2.Sam.5. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And it
shall bee, when thou shalt heare a sound of going in the tops of
the mulbery trees, that then thou shalt goe out to battaile: for
God is gone foorth before thee, to smite the hoste of the
Philistines.</ab>
<ab n="16">Dauid
therefore did as God commanded him: and they smote the hoste of the
Philistines from Gibeon euen to Gazer.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the
fame of Dauid went out into all lands, and the Lord brought the
feare of him vpon all nations.</ab>



</div>