<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The sonnes of Dauid. 10 His line
to Zedekiah. 17 The successors of Ieconiah.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these
were the sonnes of Dauid, which were borne vnto him in Hebron. The
first borne Amnon, of Ahinoam the Iesreelitesse: the second Daniel,
of Abigail the Carmelitesse:<note> 2.Sam.3.2 , Iosh.15.56. , Or, Chileab, 2.sam.3.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The third,
Absalom the sonne of Maacha, the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur:
the fourth, Adoniah the sonne of Haggith:</ab>
<ab n="3">The fifth,
Shephatia of Abital: the sixth, Ithream by Eglah his
wife.<note> 2.Sam.3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">These sixe
were borne vnto him in Hebron, and there hee reigned seuen yeeres,
and sixe moneths: and in Ierusalem he reigned thirty and three
yeres.</ab>

<fw>The genealogie of Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="5">And these
were borne vnto him in Ierusalem. Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan,
and Solomon, foure, of Bathshua the daughter of Ammiel.<note> 2.Sam.5. 14. , Or, Shammua, 2.Sam.5.14. , Or, Bethsabe, 2.Sam. 11.13. , Or, Eliam, 2.Sam.11.3</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Ibhar also,
and Elishama, and Eliphelet,<note> Or, Elishua 2.Sam.5.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Noga, and
Nepheg, and Iaphia,</ab>
<ab n="8">And Elishama,
and Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine.<note> Or, Beliada, 1. Chro. 14.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">These were
all the sonnes of Dauid: beside the sonnes of the concubines, and
Tamar their sister.<note> 2. Sam. 13.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
Solomons sonne was Rehoboam: Abia his sonne: Asa his son:
Iehoshaphat his sonne:<note> 1.King.11 43. &amp; 15.8 , Or, Abiam, 1.king.15.1</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Ioram his
sonne: Ahaziah his sonne: Ioash his sonne:<note> Or, Azariah, 2. chr. 22. 6. &amp; 21.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Amaziah his
sonne: Azariah his sonne: Iotham his sonne:<note> Or, Vzziah 2.king.15.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Ahaz his
sonne: Hezekiah his sonne: Manasseh his sonne:</ab>
<ab n="14">Amon his
sonne: Iosiah his sonne.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
sonnes of Iosiah were: the first borne Iohanan, the second Ioakim,
the third Zedekiah, the fourth Sallum.<note> Or, Ioachaz, 2.king.23.30. , Or, Eliakim, 2.king. 23.34. , Or, Mathania, 2.kin. 24.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the
sonnes of Ioakim: Ieconiah his sonne, Zedekiah his
sonne.<note> Mat.1.11. , Or, Iehoiachin, 2. king. 24.6. , Or, Coniah, ier. 22.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And
the sonnes of Ieconiah, Assir, Salathiel his sonne,<note> Or, Iehoiachin, 2. king. 24.6. , Heb. Shealtiel. , 2.King. 24.17. being his vncle. , Mat.1.12</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Malchiram
also, and Pedaiah, and Shenazar, Iecamiah, Hosama, and
Nedabiah.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
sonnes of Pedaiah were: Zerubbabel, and Shimei: And the sonne of
Zerubbabel, Meshullam, and Hananiah, and Shelomith their
sister.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Hazubah,
and Ohel, and Berechiah, &amp; Hasadiah, Iushabhesed, fiue.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
sonnes of Hananiah, Pelatiah, and Iesaiah: the sonnes of Rephaiah,
the sons of Arnan, the sonnes of Obadiah, the sonnes of
Sechaniah.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the
sonnes of Sechaniah, Semaiah: and the sonnes of Semaiah, Hattush,
and Igeal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, sixe.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
sonnes of Neariah: Elioenai, and Hezekiah, and Azrikam,
three.<note> Heb. Hiskijah.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the
sonnes of Elioenai, were: Hodaiah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and
Akkub, and Iohanan, and Dalaiah, and Anani, seuen.</ab>



</div>