<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in his old age maketh
Solomon King. 2 The number and distribution of the Leuites 7 The
families of the Gershonites. 12 The sonnes of Kohath. 21 The sonnes
of Merari. 24 The office of the Leuites.</head>

<ab n="1">So when
Dauid was old and full of dayes, he made Solomon his sonne king
ouer Israel.<note> Chap. 28. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ And
he gathered together all the Princes of Israel, with the Priests
and the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now the
Leuites were numbred from the age of thirtie yeeres and vpward: and
their number, by their polles, man by man, was thirtie and eight
thousand.<note> Num.4.3.</note></ab>

<fw>Moses his sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="4">Of which,
twentie and foure thousand were to set forward the work of the
house of the Lord: and sixe thousand were Officers and
Iudges.<note> Or, to ouersee.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer,
foure thousand were porters, and foure thousand praised the Lord
with the instruments which I made (said Dauid) to praise
therewith.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Dauid
diuided them into courses among the sonnes of Leui, namely Gershon,
Kohath, and Merari.<note> Exod.6.16 1.chro.6.1. &amp;c. 2.chro. 8.14.and 29.25. , Heb. diuisions.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Of
the Gershonites were Laadan, and Shimei.<note> Chap.26. 21. , Or, Libni, chap.6.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The sonnes
of Laadan, the chiefe was Iehiel, and Zetham, and Ioel,
three.</ab>
<ab n="9">The sonnes
of Shimei: Shelomith, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the
chiefe of the fathers of Laadan.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
sonnes of Shimei were: Iahath, Zina, and Ieush, and Beriah. These
foure were the sonnes of Shimei.<note> Or, Ziza, ver.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Iahath
was the chiefe, and Ziza the second: but Ieush and Beriah had not
many sonnes: therefore they were in one reckoning, according to
their fathers house.<note> Heb. did not multiply sonnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ The
sonnes of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, foure.</ab>
<ab n="13">The sonnes
of Amram: Aaron and Moses: and Aaron was separated, that he should
sanctifie the most holy things, he and his sonnes for euer, to
burne incense before the Lord, to minister vnto him, and to blesse
in his Name for euer.<note> Exo.6.20. , Exod.28. Heb.5.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Now
concerning Moses the man of God, his sonnes were named of the tribe
of Leui.<note> Exo.2.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The sonnes
of Moses were: Gershom and Eliezer.<note> Exo.18.3,4</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Of the
sonnes of Gershom Shebuel was the chiefe.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the
sonnes of Eliezer were: Rehabiah the chiefe. And Eliezer had none
other sonnes: but the sonnes of Rehabiah were very
many.<note> Chap.26. 25. , Or, the first , Heb. were highly multiplied.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Of the
sonnes of Izhar, Shelomith the chiefe.</ab>
<ab n="19">Of the
sonnes of Hebron, Ieriah the first, Amariah the second, Iahaziel
the third, and Iekamiam the fourth.</ab>
<ab n="20">Of the
sonnes of Uzziel: Michah the first, and Iesiah the second.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ The
sonnes of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sonnes of Mahli: Eleazar and
Kish.</ab>

<fw>The Priests and Leuites
offices.</fw>
<ab n="22">And Eleazar
died, and had no sonnes but daughters: and their brethren the
sonnes of Kish tooke them.<note> Or, kinsemen.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The sonnes
of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Ierimoth, three.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶
These were the sonnes of Leui after the house of their fathers,
euen the chiefe of the fathers, as they were counted by number of
names by their polles, that did the worke for the seruice of the
house of the Lord, from the age of twentie yeeres and
vpward.<note> Num.10. 24. , Num.1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For Dauid
sayd, The Lord God of Israel hath giuen rest vnto his people, that
they may dwell in Ierusalem for euer.<note> Or, and he dwelleth in Ierusalem, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And also
vnto the Leuites: they shall no more cary the Tabernacle, nor any
vessels of it for the seruice thereof.</ab>
<ab n="27">For by the
last words of Dauid, the Leuites were numbred from twentie yeeres
olde, and aboue:<note> Heb. number.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Because
their office was to wait on the sonnes of Aaron, for the seruice of
the house of the Lord, in the courts, and in the chambers, and in
the purifying of all holy things, and the worke of the seruice of
the house of God:<note> Heb. their station was at the hand of the sonnes of Aaron.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Both for
the shew-bread, and for the fine floure for meat offering, and for
the vnleauened cakes, and for that which is baked in the panne, and
for that which is fried, and for all maner of measures and
size:<note> Chap.9. 29, &amp;c. leuit.6.21. , Or, flat plate.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And to
stand euery morning to thanke and praise the Lord, and likewise at
Euen:</ab>
<ab n="31">And to
offer all burnt sacrifices vnto the Lord in the Sabbaths, in the
new moones, and on the set feasts, by number, according to the
order commanded vnto them continually before the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="32">And that
they should keepe the charge of the Tabernacle of the Congregation,
and the charge of the holy place, and the charge of the sonnes of
Aaron their brethren, in the seruice of the house of the
Lord.</ab>



</div>