<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Sauls ouerthrow and death. 8 The
Philistines triumph ouer Saul. 11 The kindnes of Iabesh Gilead,
towards Saul and his sonnes. 13 Sauls sinne for which the kingdome
was translated from him to Dauid.</head>


<fw>His death.</fw>
<ab n="1">Nowe the
Philistines fought against Israel, and the men of Israel fled from
before the Philistines, and fell downe slaine in mount
Gilboa.<note> 1.Sam.31. 1,2. , Or, wounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the
Philistines followed hard after Saul, and after his sonnes, and the
Philistines slew Ionathan, and Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sonnes
of Saul.<note> Or, Ieshui, 1.Sam.14. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the
battell went sore against Saul, and the archers hit him, and he was
wounded of the archers.<note> Hebr. shooters with bowes. , Hebr. found him.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then saide
Saul to his armour bearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through
therewith, lest these vncircumcised come, and abuse mee: but his
armour bearer would not, for he was sore afraid. So Saul tooke a
sword, and fell vpon it.<note> Or, mocke me.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And when his
armour bearer saw that Saul was dead, hee fell likewise on the
sword, and died.</ab>
<ab n="6">So Saul
died, and his three sonnes, and all his house died
together.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when all
the men of Israel that were in the valley, saw that they fled, and
that Saul and his sonnes were dead: then they forsooke their
cities, and fled, and the Philistines came and dwelt in
them.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
it came to passe on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip
the slaine, that they found Saul and his sonnes fallen in mount
Gilboa.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when
they had stripped him, they tooke his head, and his armour, and
sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to cary tidings
vnto their idoles, and to the people.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they
put his armour in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in
the temple of Dagon.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
when all Iabesh Gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to
Saul:</ab>
<ab n="12">They arose,
all the valiant men, and tooke away the body of Saul, and the
bodies of his sonnes, and brought them to Iabesh, and buried their
bones vnder the oke in Iabesh, and fasted seuen dayes.</ab>

<fw>Dauid made King.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ So
Saul died for his transgression which hee committed against the
Lord, euen against the word of the Lord which he kept not, and also
for asking counsel of one that had a familiar spirit, to enquire of
it:<note> Heb. transgressed. , 1.Sam.15. 23. , 1.Sam.28. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And
enquired not of the Lord: therefore he slew him, and turned the
kingdome vnto Dauid the sonne of Iesse.<note> Heb. Isai.</note></ab>



</div>