<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 The number &amp; offices of the
singers. 8 Their diuision by lot, into foure and twentie
orders.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer
Dauid and the captaines of the hoste separated to the seruice of
the sonnes of Asaph, and of Heman, and of Ieduthun, who should
prophesie with harps, with psalteries, and with cymbals: and the
number of the workmen, according to their seruice, was:</ab>
<ab n="2">Of the
sonnes of Asaph: Zaccur, and Ioseph, and Nethaniah, and Asarelah,
the sonnes of Asaph vnder the hands of Asaph, which prophesied
according to the order of the king.<note> Otherwise called Iesharelah, v.14. , Heb. by the hand of the king.</note></ab>

<fw>The Leuites and their offices.</fw>
<ab n="3">Of Ieduthun:
the sonnes of Ieduthun, Gedaliah, and Zeri, and Ieshaiah,
Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, sixe, vnder the handes of their father
Ieduthun, who prophesied with a harpe, to giue thankes and to
praise the Lord.<note> Or, Izri, ver.11. , With Shimei mentioned ver. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Of Heman:
the sonnes of Heman, Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shebuel, and
Ierimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliatha, Giddalti, and Romamti-Ezer,
Ioshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, and Mahazioth:<note> Or, Azareel, ver. 18. , Or, Shubael, ver.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">All these
were the sonnes of Heman the kings Seer in the wordes of God, to
lift vp the horne. And God gaue to Heman fourteene sonnes and three
daughters.<note> Or, matters.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">All these
were vnder the hands of their father, for song in the house of the
Lord with cymbals, psalteries and harpes, for the seruice of the
house of God, according to the kings order, to Asaph, Ieduthun, and
Heman.<note> Heb. by the hands of the King.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So the
number of them, with their brethren that were instructed in the
songs of the Lord, euen all that were cunning, was two hundred,
foure score and eight.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
they cast lots ward against ward, as well the small as the great,
the teacher as the scholler.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now the
first lot came foorth for Asaph to Ioseph, the second to Gedaliah,
who with his brethren and sonnes were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="10">The third
to Zaccur, he, his sons, and his brethren were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="11">The fourth
to Izri, he, his sonnes and his brethren were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="12">The fift to
Nethaniah, hee, his sonnes and his brethren were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="13">The sixt to
Bukkiah, he, his sons and his brethren were twelue.</ab>
<ab n="14">The seuenth
to Iesharelah, hee, his sonnes &amp; his brethren were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="15">The eight
to Ieshaiah, hee, his sonnes and his brethren, were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="16">The ninth
to Mattaniah, he, his sonnes and his brethren were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="17">The tenth
to Shimei, he, his sons and his brethren were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="18">The
eleuenth to Azareel, hee, his sonnes and his brethren were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="19">The twelfth
to Hashabiah, he, his sonnes and his brethren, were twelue:</ab>
<ab n="20">The
thirteenth to Shubael, hee, his sonnes and his brethren were
twelue:</ab>

<fw>The Leuites and Porters
offices.</fw>
<ab n="21">The
fourteenth to Mattithiah, hee, his sonnes and his brethren, were
twelue.</ab>
<ab n="22">The
fifteenth to Ierimoth, hee, his sonnes &amp; his brethren, were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="23">The
sixteenth to Hananiah, hee, his sonnes &amp; his brethren, were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="24">The
seuenteenth to Ioshbekashah, he, his sonnes and his brethren, were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="25">The
eighteenth to Hanani: hee, his sonnes &amp; his brethren, were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="26">The
nineteenth to Mallothi, hee, his sonnes &amp; his brethren, were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="27">The
twentieth to Eliathah, hee, his sonnes &amp; his brethren, were
twelue:</ab>
<ab n="28">The one and
twentieth to Hothir, he, his sonnes and his brethren were
twelue.</ab>
<ab n="29">The two and
twentieth to Giddalti, hee, his sonnes and his brethren, were
twelue.</ab>
<ab n="30">The three
and twentieth to Mahazioth, he, his sonnes and his brethren, were
twelue.</ab>
<ab n="31">The foure
and twentieth to Romamti-Ezer, he, his sonnes and his brethren,
were twelue.</ab>



</div>