<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The sonnes of Israel. 3 The
posteritie of Iudah by Tamar. 13 The children of Iesse. 18 The
posteritie of Caleb the sonne of Hesron. 21 Hesrons posteritie by
the daughter of Machir. 25 Ierahmeels posteritie. 34 Sheshans
posteritie. 42 another branch of Calebs posteritie. 50 The
posteritie of Caleb the sonne of Hur.</head>

<ab n="1">These are the
sonnes of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Leui, and Iudah, Issachar, and
Zebulun,<note> Or, Iacob. , Gen.29.32. &amp; 30.5. &amp; 35.18, 22. &amp; 46.8. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Dan, Ioseph,
and Beniamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ The
sonnes of Iudah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah. Which three were borne
vnto him, of the daughter of Shua the Canaanites. And Er the
first-borne of Iudah, was euill in the sight of the Lord, and he
slue him.<note> Gen.38.3. &amp; 46.12. , Gen.38.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Tamar his
daughter-in law bare him Pharez, and Zerah. All the sonnes of Iudah
were fiue.<note> Gen.38.29,30. Mat. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The sonnes of
Pharez: Hezron, and Hamul.<note> Ruth.4.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the
sonnes of Zerah: Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and Dara.
Fiue of them in all.<note> Or, Zabdi, Iosh. 7.1. , 1.Kin. 4.31. , Or, Darda.</note></ab>

<fw>The genealogie of Iudah.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the
sonnes of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who transgressed in
the thing accursed.<note> Or, Achan. , Iosh. 6.19.and 7.1, 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the
sonnes of Ethan: Azariah.</ab>
<ab n="9">The sonnes
also of Hezron, that were borne vnto him: Ierahmeel, and Ram, and
Chelubai.<note> Or, Aram. Mat. 1.3. , Or, Caleb. ver. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Ram
begate Aminadab, and Aminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the children
of Iudah.<note> Ruth.4. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Nahshon
begate Salma, and Salma begate Boaz.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Boaz
begate Obed, and Obed begate Iesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
Iesse begate his first-borne Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and
Shimma the third,<note> 1.Sam.16. 6. , Or, Shamma, 1. Sam. 16.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Nathanael
the fourth, Raddai the fifth,</ab>
<ab n="15">Ozem the
sixth, Dauid the seuenth:</ab>
<ab n="16">Whose
sisters were Zeruiah, and Abigail. And the sonnes of Zeruiah:
Abishai, and Ioab, and Asahel, three.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Abigail
bare Amasa. And the father of Amasa, was Iether the
Ishmeelite.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And
Caleb the sonne of Hezron, begate children of Azubah his wife, and
of Ierioth: her sonnes are these: Iesher, Shobab, and
Ardon.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when
Azubah was dead, Caleb tooke vnto him Ephrath, which bare him
Hur.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Hur
begate Uri, and Uri begate Bezaleel.<note> Exod. 31.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And
afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir, the father of
Gilead, whom hee married when he was threescore yeeres old, and she
bare him Segub.<note> Heb. tooke.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And Segub
begate Iair, who had three and twenty cities in the land of
Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he tooke
Geshur, and Aram, with the townes of Iair, from them, with Kenath,
and the townes thereof, euen threescore cities. All these belonged
to the sonnes of Machir, the father of Gilead.<note> Num.32.41. deut.3.14. iosh.13.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And after
that Hezron was dead in Caleb Ephratah, then Abiah Hezrons wife,
bare him Ashur, the father of Tekoa.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
the sonnes of Ierahmeel the first-borne of Hezron, were Ram the
first-borne, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozen, and Ahiiah.</ab>

<fw>The genealogie of Iudah.</fw>
<ab n="26">Ierahmeel
had also an other wife, whose name was Atarah, she was the mother
of Onam.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the
sonnes of Ram the first-borne of Ierahmeel, were Maaz, and Iamin,
and Ekar.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the
sonnes of Onam were, Shammai, and Iada. And the sonnes of Shammai:
Nadab, and Abishur.</ab>
<ab n="29">And the name
of the wife of Abishur was Abihail, and shee bare him Ahban, and
Molid.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the
sonnes of Nadab: Seled, and Appaim. But Seled died without
children.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the
sonnes of Appaim, Ishi: and the sonnes of Ishi, Sheshan: and the
children of Sheshan, Ahlai.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the
sonnes of Iada the brother of Shammai, Iether, and Ionathan: and
Iether died without children.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the
sonnes of Ionathan, Peleth, and Zaza. These were the sonnes of
Ierahmeel.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Now
Sheshan had no sonnes, but daughters: and Sheshan had a seruant, an
Egyptian, whose name was Iarha.</ab>
<ab n="35">And Sheshan
gaue his daughter to Iarha his seruant to wife, and she bare him
Attai.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Attai
begate Nathan, and Nathan begate Zabad,<note> Chap.11. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And Zabad
begate Ephlal, and Ephlal begate Obed,</ab>
<ab n="38">And Obed
begate Iehu, and Iehu begate Azariah,</ab>
<ab n="39">And Azariah
begate Helez, and Helez begate Eleasah,</ab>
<ab n="40">And Eleasah
begate Sisamai, and Sisamai begate Shallum,</ab>
<ab n="41">And Shallum
begate Iekamiah, and Iekamiah begate Elishama.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶ Now
the sonnes of Caleb the brother of Ierahmeel were, Mesha his
first-borne, which was the father of Ziph: and the sonnes of
Maresha the father of Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="43">And the
sonnes of Hebron: Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema.</ab>
<ab n="44">And Shema
begat Raham, the father of Iorkoam: and Rekem begate
Shammai.</ab>
<ab n="45">And the
sonne of Shammai was Maon: and Maon was the father of
Beth-zur.</ab>

<fw>The genealogie of Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="46">And Ephah
Calebs concubine bare Haran, and Moza, and Gazez: and Haran begate
Gazez.</ab>
<ab n="47">And the
sonnes of Iahdai: Regem, and Iotham, and Geshan, and Pelet, and
Ephah, and Shaaph.</ab>
<ab n="48">Maacha
Calebs concubine, bare Sheber, and Tirhanah.</ab>
<ab n="49">Shee bare
also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheua the father of Machbenah,
&amp; the father of Gibea: And the daughter of Caleb was
Achsah.<note> Iosh.15. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">¶ These
were the sonnes of Caleb, the sonne of Hur, the first borne of
Ephratah: Shobal the father of Kiriath-iearim,</ab>
<ab n="51">Salma the
father of Bethlehem: Hareph the father of Beth-gader.</ab>
<ab n="52">And Shobal
the father of Kiriath-iearim, had sonnes, Haroe, and halfe of the
Manahethites.<note> Or, Reaiah, chap.4. 2. , Or, halfe of the Menuchites, Or Hatsi-hammenuchoth.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">And the
families of Kiriath-iearim, the Ithrites, and the Puhites, and the
Shumathites, and the Mishraites: of them came the Zareathites, and
the Eshtaulites.</ab>
<ab n="54">The sonnes
of Salmah: Bethlehem, and the Netophathites, Ataroth, the house of
Ioab, and halfe of the Manahethites, the Zorites.<note> Or, Atarites, or, crownes of the house of Ioab.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And the
families of the Scribes, which dwelt at Iabez: the Tirathites, the
Shimeathites, and Suchathites. These are the Kenites that came of
Hemath, the father of the house of Rechab.<note> Iud. 1. 16 , Ier. 35. 2.</note></ab>



</div>