<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Rabbah is besieged by Ioab,
spoiled by Dauid, and the people thereof tortured. 4 Three giants
are slaine in three seuerall ouerthrowes of the
Philistines.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came
to passe, that after the yeere was expired, at the time that kings
goe out to battell, Ioab led forth the power of the armie, and
wasted the countrey of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged
Rabbah (but Dauid taried at Ierusalem,) and Ioab smote Rabbah, and
destroyed it.<note> 2.Sam.11. 1. , Hebr. at the returne of the yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid
tooke the crowne of their king from off his head, and found it to
weigh a talent of gold, and there were precious stones in it, and
it was set vpon Dauids head; and hee brought also exceeding much
spoile out of the city.<note> 2.Sam.12. 26. , Hebr. the weight of.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And hee
brought out the people that were in it, and cut them with sawes,
and with harrowes of yron, and with axes: euen so dealt Dauid with
all the cities of the children of Ammon. And Dauid and all the
people returned to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
it came to passe after this, that there arose warre at Gezer with
the Philistines, at which time Sibbechai the Hushathite, slew
Sippai, that was of the children of the giant: and they were
subdued.<note> 2.Sam.21. 18. , Or, continued, Hebr. stood. , Or, Gob. , Or, Rapha.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And there
was warre againe with the Philistines, and Elhanan the sonne of
Iair, slew Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, whose
spearestaffe was like a weauers beame.<note> Called also Iaare-ore-gim, 2.sam. 21. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And yet
againe there was warre at Gath, where was a man of great stature,
whose fingers and toes were foure and twentie, sixe on each hand,
and sixe on each foot. And he also was the sonne of the
giant.<note> 2.Sam.21. 20. , Hebr. a man of measure. , Hebr. borne to the giant Or, Rapha.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But when he
defied Israel, Ionathan the sonne of Shimea Dauids brother, slew
him.<note> Or, reproched. , Called Shammah, 1. Sam.16.9.</note></ab>

<fw>People numbred.</fw>
<ab n="8">These were
borne vnto the Giant in Gath, and they fell by the hand of Dauid,
and by the hand of his seruants.</ab>



</div>