<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid foreknowing the place of the
Temple, prepareth abundance for the building of it. 6 Hee
instructeth Solomon in Gods promises, and his duety in building the
Temple. 17 He chargeth the Princes to assist his
sonne.</head>


<fw>Dauids preparation for the
Temple.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then Dauid
said, This is the house of the Lord God, and this is the Altar of
the burnt offering for Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid
commanded to gather together the strangers that were in the land of
Israel: and hee set masons to hew wrought stones to build the house
of God.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Dauid
prepared yron in abundance for the nailes for the doores of the
gates, and for the ioynings, and brasse in abundance without
weight;</ab>
<ab n="4">Also Cedar
trees in abundance: for the Zidonians, and they of Tyre, brought
much Cedar wood to Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Dauid
said, Solomon my sonne is yong and tender, and the house that is to
be builded for the Lord, must be exceeding magnificall, of fame and
of glory throughout all countreys: I will therefore now make
preparation for it. So Dauid prepared abundantly before his
death.<note> Chap.29. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then
hee called for Solomon his sonne, and charged him to build an house
for the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Dauid
saide to Solomon; My sonne, as for me, it was in my mind to build
an house vnto the Name of the Lord my God.</ab>
<ab n="8">But the word
of the Lord came to mee, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly,
and hast made great warres: thou shalt not build an house vnto my
Name, because thou hast shed much blood vpon the earth in my
sight.<note> Chap. 28. 3. 2.sam. 7. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Behold, a
sonne shall bee borne to thee, who shall bee a man of rest, and I
will giue him rest from all his enemies round about: for his name
shalbe Solomon, and I wil giue peace and quietnesse vnto Israel in
his dayes.<note> That is, peaceable.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee shall
build an house for my Name, and he shal be my sonne, and I will be
his father, and I will establish the throne of his kingdome ouer
Israel for euer.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now my
sonne, The Lord be with thee, and prosper thou, and build the house
of the Lord thy God, as he hath said of thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Onely the
Lord giue thee wisedome and vnderstanding, and giue thee charge
concerning Israel, that thou mayest keepe the Law of the Lord thy
God.</ab>

<fw>Dauids preparation for the
Temple.</fw>
<ab n="13">Then shalt
thou prosper, if thou takest heed to fulfill the Statutes and
Iudgements which the Lord charged Moses with, concerning Israel: be
strong, and of good courage, dread not, nor be dismayed.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now
beholde, in my trouble I haue prepared for the house of the Lord an
hundred thousand talents of gold, and a thousand thousand talents
of siluer, and of brasse and yron without weight: (for it is in
abundance) timber also and stone haue I prepared, and thou mayest
adde thereto.<note> Or, in my pouertie. , As Ver.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Moreouer,
there are workmen with thee in abundance, hewers, and workers of
stone and timber, and all maner of cunning men for euery maner of
worke:<note> That is, Masons and Carpenters.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Of the
gold, the siluer, and the brasse, and the yron, there is no number.
Arise therefore, and be doing, and the Lord be with thee.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶
Dauid also commanded all the Princes of Israel to helpe Solomon his
sonne, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">Is not the
Lord your God with you? and hath he not giuen you rest on euery
side? for he hath giuen the inhabitants of the land into mine hand,
and the land is subdued before the Lord, and before his
people.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now set
your heart and your soule to seeke the Lord your God: arise
therfore, and build ye the Sanctuary of the Lord God, to bring the
Arke of the Couenant of the Lord, &amp; the holy vessels of God,
into the house that is to be built to the Name of the Lord.</ab>



</div>