<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid tempted by Satan, forceth
Ioab to number the people. 5 The number of the people being
brought, Dauid repenteth of it. 9 Dauid hauing three plagues
propounded by Gad, chuseth the pestilence. 14 After the death of
70000, Dauid by repentance preuenteth the destruction of Ierusalem.
18 Dauid by Gads direction, purchaseth Ornans threshing floore,
where hauing built an Altar, God giueth a signe of his fauour by
fire, and stayeth the plague. 28 Dauid sacrificeth there, being
restrained from Gibeon by feare of the Angel.</head>

<ab n="1">And Satan
stoode vp against Israel, and prouoked Dauid to number
Israel.<note> Sam.24. 1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid
saide to Ioab, and to the rulers of the people, Goe, number Israel
from Beer-sheba eueu to Dan: and bring the number of them to me,
that I may know it.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Ioab
answered, The Lord make his people an hundred times so many moe as
they bee: but, my lord the king, are they not al my lords seruants?
why then doeth my lord require this thing? why will hee bee a cause
of trespasse to Israel?</ab>
<ab n="4">Neuerthelesse,
the kings word preuailed against Ioab: wherefore Ioab departed, and
went throughout all Israel, and came to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And
Ioab gaue the summe of the number of the people vnto Dauid: and all
they of Israel were a thousand thousand, and an hundred thousand
men that drew sword: and Iudah was foure hundred threescore and ten
thousand men, that drew sword.</ab>
<ab n="6">But Leui and
Beniamin counted hee not among them: for the kings word was
abominable to Ioab.</ab>
<ab n="7">And God was
displeased with this thing, therefore he smote Israel.<note> And it was euill in the eyes of the LORD concerning this thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Dauid
saide vnto God, I haue sinned greatly, because I haue done this
thing: but uow, I beseech thee, doe away the iniquitie of thy
seruant, for I haue done very foolishly.<note> 2.Sam. 24.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
the Lord spake vnto Gad, Dauids Seer, saying,</ab>

<fw>The pestilence.</fw>
<ab n="10">Goe and
tell Dauid, saying, Thus saith the Lord, I offer thee three things,
choose thee one of them, that I may doe it vnto thee.<note> Hebr. stretch out.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">So Gad came
to Dauid, and said vnto him, Thus saith the Lord, Choose
thee<note> Hebr. take to thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Either
three yeeres famine, or three moneths to bee destroyed before thy
foes (while that the sword of thine enemies ouertaketh thee) or
else three dayes the sword of the Lord, euen the pestilence in the
land, and the Angel of the Lord destroying throughout all the
coasts of Israel. Now therefore aduise thy selfe, what word I shall
bring againe to him that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Dauid
said vnto Gad, I am in a great strait. Let mee fall now into the
hand of the Lord (for very great are his mercies,) but let me not
fall into the hand of man.<note> Or, many.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ So
the Lord sent pestilence vpon Israel: and there fell of Israel,
seuentie thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="15">And God
sent an Angel vnto Ierusalem to destroy it: and as he was
destroying, the Lord beheld, and he repented him of the euill, and
said to the Angel that destroyed, It is ynough, stay now thine
hand. And the Angel of the Lord stood by the threshing floore of
Ornan the Iebusite.<note> 2. Sam. 24.16. , Or, Araunah. 2.sam. 24.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Dauid
lift vp his eyes, and saw the Angel of the Lord stand betweene the
earth and the heauen, hauing a drawen sword in his hand stretched
out ouer Ierusalem. Then Dauid and the Elders of Israel, who were
clothed in sackecloth, fell vpon their faces.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Dauid
said vnto God, Is it not I that commanded the people to be numbred?
euen I it is that haue sinned, and done euill indeed, but as for
these sheepe, what haue they done? Let thine hand, I pray thee, O
Lord my God, be on me, and on my fathers house, but not on thy
people, that they should bee plagued.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then
the Angel of the Lord commanded Gad to say to Dauid, that Dauid
should goe vp and set vp an Altar vnto the Lord, in the threshing
floore of Ornan the Iebusite.<note> 2.Chron. 3.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Dauid
went vp at the saying of Gad, which he spake in the Name of the
Lord.</ab>

<fw>Dauid and Ornan.</fw>
<ab n="20">And Ornan
turned backe and saw the Angel, and his foure sonnes with him, hid
themselues. Now Ornan was threshing wheat.<note> Or, when Ornan turned backe, and saw the Angel, then he and his foure sonnes with him, hid themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And as
Dauid came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw Dauid, and went out of
the threshing floore, and bowed himselfe to Dauid with his face to
the ground.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then Dauid
saide to Ornan, Grant mee the place of this threshing floore, that
I may build an Altar therein vnto the Lord: thou shalt grant it mee
for the full price, that the plague may be stayed from the
people.<note> Heb. giue.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Ornan
saide vnto Dauid, Take it to thee, and let my lord the king do that
which is good in his eyes. Loe, I giue thee the oxen also for burnt
offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat
for the meate offering, I giue it all.</ab>
<ab n="24">And king
Dauid said to Ornan; Nay, but I wil verily buy it for the full
price: for I will not take that which is thine for the Lord, nor
offer burnt offerings without cost.</ab>
<ab n="25">So Dauid
gaue to Ornan for the place, sixe hundred shekels of gold by
weight.<note> 2.Sam.24. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And Dauid
built there an Altar vnto the Lord, and offered burnt offerings,
and peace offerings, and called vpon the Lord, and hee answered him
from heauen by fire vpon the Altar of burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the
Lord commaunded the Angel, and hee put vp his sword againe into the
sheath thereof.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ At
that time, when Dauid saw that the Lord had answered him in the
threshing floore of Ornan the Iebusite, then he sacrificed
there.</ab>
<ab n="29">For the
tabernacle of the Lord which Moses made in the wildernesse, and the
Altar of the burnt offering were at that season, in the high place
at Gibeon:<note> Chap.16. 39. 2.Chro. 1.3. 1.king. 3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But Dauid
could not goe before it to euquire of God; for he was afraid,
because of the sword of the Angel of the Lord.</ab>



</div>