<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Dauids festiual sacrifice. 4 Hee
ordereth a Quire to sing Thankesgiuing. 7 The Psalme of
Thankesgiuing. 37 He appointeth Ministers, Porters, Priests and
Musitians, to attend continually on the Arke.</head>

<ab n="1">So they
brought the Arke of God, and set it in the midst of the tent that
Dauid had pitched for it: and they offered burnt sacrifices, and
peace offerings before God.<note> 2. Sam. 6. 17.</note></ab>

<fw>The song of Asaph.</fw>
<ab n="2">And when
Dauid had made an end of offering the burnt offerings, and the
peace offrings, he blessed the people in the name of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hee
dealt to euery one of Israel, both man and woman, to euery one a
loafe of bread, and a good piece of flesh, and a flagon of
wine.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
he appointed certaine of the Leuites to minister before the Arke of
the Lord, and to record, and to thanke and praise the Lord God of
Israel,</ab>
<ab n="5">Asaph the
chiefe, and next to him Zachariah, Ieiel, and Shemiramoth, and
Iehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obed Edom: and
Ieiel with Psalteries and with harpes: but Asaph made a sound with
cymbals.<note> Heb. with instruments of Psalteries, &amp;c harps</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Benaiah also
and Iahaziel the Priestes, with trumpets continually before the
Arke of the Couenant of God.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Then
on that day, Dauid deliuered first this Psalme to thanke the Lord,
into the hand of Asaph and his brethren:</ab>
<ab n="8">Giue thankes
vnto the Lord, call vpon his name, make knowen his deeds among the
people.<note> Psal. 105. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Sing vnto
him, sing psalmes vnto him, talke you of all his wonderous
workes.</ab>
<ab n="10">Glory yee
in his holy Name, let the heart of them reioyce that seeke the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="11">Seeke the
Lord, and his strength, seeke his face continually.</ab>
<ab n="12">Remember
his marueilous works that he hath done, his wonders, and the
iudgements of his mouth,</ab>
<ab n="13">O ye seed
of Israel his seruant, ye children of Iacob his chosen
ones.</ab>
<ab n="14">He is the
Lord our God, his iudgements are in all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="15">Be ye
mindfull alwayes of his Couenant: the worde which hee commanded to
a thousand generations:</ab>
<ab n="16">Euen of the
Couenant which hee made with Abraham, and of his othe vnto
Isaac:<note> Gen.17.2 and 26.3. &amp; 28.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And hath
confirmed the same to Iacob for a lawe, and to Israel for an
euerlasting Couenant,</ab>
<ab n="18">Saying,
vnto thee will I giue the land of Canaan, the lot of your
inheritance.<note> Heb. the coard.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">When ye
were but few, euen a few, and strangers in it:<note> Heb. men of number. , Gen. 34. 30.</note></ab>

<fw>The song of Asaph.</fw>
<ab n="20">And when
they went from nation to nation, and from one kingdome to another
people:</ab>
<ab n="21">Hee
suffered no man to doe them wrong: yea, hee reprooued kings for
their sakes,<note> Gen. 12. 17.and 20.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Saying,
Touch not mine anointed, and doe my Prophets no harme.<note> Psal. 105. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Sing vnto
the Lord all the earth: shew foorth from day to day his
saluation.<note> Psal.96.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Declare his
glory among the heathen: his marueilous workes among all
nations.</ab>
<ab n="25">For great
is the Lord, and greatly to be praised: he also is to be feared
aboue all gods.</ab>
<ab n="26">For all the
gods of the people are idoles: but the Lord made the
heauens.<note> Leu.19.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Glory and
honour are in his presence: strength and gladnesse are in his
place.</ab>
<ab n="28">Giue vnto
the Lord, yee kinreds of the people: giue vnto the Lord glory and
strength.</ab>
<ab n="29">Giue vnto
the Lord the glory due vnto his Name: bring an offering, and come
before him, worship the Lord in the beautie of holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="30">Feare
before him all the earth: the world also shall be stable, that it
be not mooued.</ab>
<ab n="31">Let the
heauens be glad, and let the earth reioyce: and let men say among
the nations, The Lord reigneth.</ab>
<ab n="32">Let the sea
roare, and the fulnesse thereof: let the fieldes reioyce, and all
that is therein.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then shall
the trees of the wood sing out at the presence of the Lord, because
hee commeth to iudge the earth.</ab>
<ab n="34">O giue
thanks vnto the Lord, for hee is good: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Psa.107.1 and 118.1. and 136.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And say
yee, Saue vs, O God of our saluation, and gather vs together, and
deliuer vs from the heathen, that we may giue thanks to thy holy
Name, and glory in thy praise.</ab>
<ab n="36">Blessed be
the Lord God of Israel for euer and euer: and all the people saide,
Amen, and praised the Lord.<note> Deut.27. 15.</note></ab>

<fw>Priests, Porters, &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="37">¶ So
hee left there before the Arke of the couenant of the Lord, Asaph
and his brethren, to minister before the Arke continually, as euery
dayes worke required:</ab>
<ab n="38">And Obed
Edom with their brethren, threescore and eight: Obed Edom also the
sonne of Ieduthun, and Hosah to be porters:</ab>
<ab n="39">And Zadok
the Priest, and his brethren the Priests, before the Tabernacle of
the Lord, in the high place that was at Gibeon,</ab>
<ab n="40">To offer
burnt offerings vnto the Lord, vpon the Altar of the burnt offering
continually morning and euening, and to doe according to all that
is written in the Lawe of the Lord, which hee commanded
Israel:<note> Heb. in the morning and in the euening.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And with
them Heman and Ieduthun, and the rest that were chosen, who were
expressed by name, to giue thankes to the Lord, because his mercy
endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="42">And with
them Heman and Ieduthun with trumpets and cymbales, for those that
should make a sound, and with musicall instruments of God: and the
sonnes of Ieduthun were Porters.<note> Heb. for the gate.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And all the
people departed euery man to his house, and Dauid returned to
blesse his house.</ab>



</div>