<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid hauing prepared a place for
the Arke, ordereth the Priestes and Leuites to bring it from
Obed-Edom. 25 Hee perfourmeth the solemnitie thereof with great
ioy. 29 Michal despiseth him.</head>

<ab n="1">And Dauid
made him houses in the citie of Dauid, and prepared a place for the
Arke of God, and pitched for it a tent.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then Dauid
sayd, None ought to carie the Arke of God, but the Leuites: for
them hath the Lord chosen to cary the Arke of God, and to minister
vnto him for euer.<note> Heb. It is not to cary the Arke of God, but for the Leuites. , Num.4. 2, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Dauid
gathered all Israel together to Ierusalem, to bring vp the Arke of
the Lord vnto his place, which hee had prepared for it.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Dauid
assembled the children of Aaron, and the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="5">Of the
sonnes of Kohath: Uriel the chiefe, and his brethren an hundred and
twentie.<note> Or, kinsemen.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Of the
sonnes of Merari: Asaiah the chiefe, and his brethren two hundred
and twentie.</ab>

<fw>The bringing of the Arke.</fw>
<ab n="7">Of the
sonnes of Gershom: Ioel the chiefe, and his brethren an hundred and
thirtie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Of the
sonnes of Elizaphan: Shemaiah the chiefe, and his brethren two
hundred.</ab>
<ab n="9">Of the
sonnes of Hebron: Eliel the chiefe, and his brethren
fourescore.</ab>
<ab n="10">Of the
sonnes of Uzziel: Amminadab the chiefe, and his brethren an hundred
and twelue.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Dauid
called for Zadok and Abiathar the Priests, and for the Leuites, for
Uriel, Asaiah and Ioel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab,</ab>
<ab n="12">And said
vnto them, Yee are the chiefe of the fathers of the Leuites:
sanctifie your selues both yee and your brethren, that you may
bring vp the Arke of the Lord God of Israel, vnto the place that I
haue prepared for it.</ab>
<ab n="13">For because
ye did it not at the first, the Lord our God made a breach vpon vs,
for that we sought him not after the due order.</ab>
<ab n="14">So the
Priestes and the Leuites sanctified themselues to bring vp the Arke
of the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
children of the Leuites bare the Arke of God vpon their shoulders,
with the staues thereon, as Moses commanded, according to the word
of the Lord.<note> Exod.25. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Dauid
spake to the chiefe of the Leuites, to appoint their brethren to be
the singers with instruments of musicke, Psalteries, and Harpes,
and Cymbales, sounding, by lifting vp the voice with ioy.</ab>
<ab n="17">So the
Leuites appointed Heman the sonne of Ioel: and of his brethren.
Asaph the sonne of Berechiah: and of the sonnes of Merari their
brethren, Ethan the sonne of Kushaiah.<note> Chap.6. 33. , Vers. 39. , Vers.44.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And with
them their brethren of the second degree, Zachariah, Ben, and
Iaziel, &amp; Shemiramoth, and Iehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and
Benaiah, and Maasiah, and Mattithiah, and Eliphaleh, and Mikniah,
and Obed Edom, and Iehiel the Porters.</ab>
<ab n="19">So the
Singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, were appointed to sound with
cymbales of brasse.</ab>
<ab n="20">And
Zachariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Iehiel, and Unni, and
Eliab, and Maasiah, and Benaiah, with Psalteries on
Alamoth.</ab>

<fw>The Arke brought.</fw>
<ab n="21">And
Mattithiah, and Eliphaleh, and Mikniah, and Obed Edom, and Ieiel,
and Azzaziah, with harpes on the Sheminith to excell.<note> Or, on the eight to ouersee.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And
Chenaniah chiefe of the Leuites was for song: he instructed about
the song, because he was skilfull.<note> Or was for the cariage: he instructed about the cariage. , Heb. lifting vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And
Berechiah, and Elkanah were doore keepers for the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="24">And
Shebaniah, and Iehoshaphat, and Nathaneel, and Amasai, and
Zachariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer the priests, did blow with the
trumpets before the Arke of God: and Obed Edom, and Iehiah were
doore keepers for the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ So
Dauid and the Elders of Israel, and the captaines ouer thousands,
went to bring vp the Arke of the couenant of the Lord, out of the
house of Obed Edom with ioy.<note> 2. Sam. 6. 12, 13. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And it came
to passe when God helped the Leuites that bare the Arke of the
couenant of the Lord, that they offered seuen bullocks, and seuen
rammes.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Dauid
was clothed with a robe of fine linnen, and all the Leuites that
bare the Arke, and the singers, and Chenaniah the master of the
song, with the singers. Dauid also had vpon him, an Ephod of
linnen.<note> Or, cariage</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Thus all
Israel brought vp the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord with
shouting, and with sound of the cornet, and with trumpets, and with
cymbals, making a noise with psalteries and harpes.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And
it came to passe as the Arke of the couenant of the Lord came to
the citie of Dauid, that Michal the daughter of Saul looking out at
a window, saw King Dauid dauncing and playing: and shee despised
him in her heart.</ab>



</div>