<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The line of Reuben (who lost his
birthright) vnto the captiuitie. 9 Their habitation and conquest of
the Hagarites. 11 The chiefe men, and habitations of Gad. 18 The
number and conquest of Reuben, Gad, and the halfe of Manasseh. 23
The habitations and chiefe men of that halfe tribe. 25 Their
captiuitie for their sinne.</head>


<fw>Simeons genealogie, and
Reubens.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now the
sonnes of Reuben the first borne of Israel, (for hee was the first
borne, but, forasmuch as he defiled his fathers bed, his birthright
was giuen vnto the sonnes of Ioseph the sonne of Israel: and the
genealogie is not to be reckoned after the birthright.<note> Gen. 35. 22.and 49. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For Iudah
preuailed aboue his brethren, and of him came the chiefe rulers,
but the birthright was Iosephs.<note> Gen.49. 9,10. , Mich. 5.2. matth.2.6. , Or, Prince. , Gen.46. 9. exod. 6. 14. num.26. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The sonnes, I
say, of Reuben the first borne of Israel were: Hanoch, and Pallu,
Ezron, and Carmi.<note> Gen.46. 9. exod. 6. 14. num.26. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The sonnes of
Ioel: Shemaiah his sonne: Gog his sonne: Shimei his sonne:</ab>
<ab n="5">Micah his
son: Reaia his sonne: Baal his sonne.</ab>
<ab n="6">Beerah his
sonne: whom Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria, carried away captiue:
He was Prince of the Reubenites.<note> Or Tiglath-pilneser, 2 king. 15.29. and 16.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And his
brethren by their families (when the genealogie of their
generations was reckoned) were the chiefe, Ieiel, and
Zechariah,</ab>
<ab n="8">And Bela the
sonne of Azah, the sonne of Shema, the sonne of Ioel, who dwelt in
Aroer, euen vnto Nebo, and Baalmeon.<note> Or, Shemaiah, ver 4. , Iosh.13. 15, 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Eastward
he inhabited vnto the entring in of the wildernes, from the riuer
Euphrates: because their cattell were multiplied in the land of
Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="10">And in the
dayes of Saul, they made warre with the Hagarites, who fell by
their hand: and they dwelt in their tents throughout all the East
land of Gilead.<note> Hebr. vpon all the face of the East.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
the children of Gad dwelt ouer against them, in the land of Bashan
vnto Salchah.<note> Iosh.13. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Ioel the
chiefe, and Shapham the next: and Iaanai, and Shaphat in
Bashan.</ab>
<ab n="13">And their
brethren of the house of their fathers, were: Michael, and
Meshullam, and Sheba, and Iorai, and Iachan, and Zia, and Heber,
seuen.</ab>
<ab n="14">These are
the children of Abihail the sonne of Huri, the sonne of Iaroah, the
sonne of Gilead, the sonne of Michael, the sonne of Ieshishai, the
sonne of Iahdo, the sonne of Buz:</ab>
<ab n="15">Ahi the
sonne of Abdiel, the sonne of Guni, chiefe of the house of their
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they
dwelt in Gilead in Bashan, and in her townes, and in all the
Suburbs of Sharon, vpon their borders.<note> Chap.27. 29. , Hebr. their goings forth.</note></ab>

<fw>The genealogie of the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="17">All these
were reckoned by genealogies in the dayes of Iotham king of Iudah,
and in the dayes of Ieroboam king of Israel.<note> 2.Kings 15.5,32.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ The
sonnes of Reuben, and the Gadites, and halfe the tribe of Manasseh,
of valiant men, men able to beare buckler and sword, and to shoote
with bow, and skilfull in warre, were foure and fourtie thousand,
seuen hundred and threescore, that went out to the
warre.<note> Heb. sons of valour.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And they
made warre with the Hagarites, with Ietur, and Nephish, and
Nodab.<note> Gen.25. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And they
were helped against them, and the Hagarites were deliuered into
their hand, and all that were with them: for they cried to God in
the battell, and he was intreated of them, because they put their
trust in him.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they
tooke away their cattell: of their camels fiftie thousand, and of
sheepe two hundred and fiftie thousand, and of asses two thousand,
and of men an hundred thousand.<note> Heb. led captiue. , Heb. soules of men, as num. 31.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For there
fell downe many slaine, because the warre was of God. And they
dwelt in their steads vntil the captiuity.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
the children of the halfe tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the lande:
they increased from Bashan vnto Baal-hermon, and Senir, and vnto
mount Hermon.</ab>
<ab n="24">And these
were the heads of the house of their fathers, euen Epher, and Ishi,
&amp; Eliel, and Azriel, and Ieremiah, and Hodauiah, and Iahdiel,
mightie men of valour, famous men, &amp; heads of the house of
their fathers.<note> Hebr. men of names.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
they transgressed against the God of their fathers, and went a
whoring after the Gods of the people of the land, whome God
destroyed before them.<note> 2.King. 17.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And the God
of Israel stirred vp the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the
spirit of Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria, and he caried them away
(euen the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the halfe tribe of
Manasseh:) &amp; brought them vnto Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and
to the riuer Gozan, vnto this day.<note> 2.Kings 15.19. , 2.King. 17.6.</note></ab>



</div>