<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid subdueth the Philistines and
the Moabites. 3 He smiteth Hadadezer and the Syrians. 9 Tou sendeth
Hadoram with presents to blesse Dauid. 11 The presents &amp; the
spoile, Dauid dedicateth to God. 13 He putteth garisons in Edom. 14
Dauids officers.</head>


<fw>His victories.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now after
this, it came to passe, that Dauid smote the Philistines &amp;
subdued them, and tooke Gath, and her townes out of the hand of the
Philistines.<note> 2.Sam.8. 1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he smote
Moab, and the Moabites became Dauids seruants, and brought
gifts.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
Dauid smote Hadarezer king of Zobah vnto Hamath, as hee went to
stablish his dominion by the riuer Euphrates.<note> Or. Hadadezer in Sam.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Dauid
tooke from him a thousand charets, and seuen thousand horsemen, and
twentie thousand footmen: Dauid also houghed all the charet horses,
but reserued of them an hundred charets.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when the
Syrians of Damascus came to helpe Hadarezer king of Zobah, Dauid
slew of the Syrians two and twentie thousand men.<note> Heb. Darmesek.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then Dauid
put garisons in Syria Damascus, and the Syrians became Dauids
seruants, and brought giftes. Thus the Lord preserued Dauid,
whithersoeuer he went.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Dauid
tooke the shields of golde that were on the seruants of Hadarezer,
&amp; brought them to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="8">Likewise
from Tibhath, and from Chun, cities of Hadarezer, broght Dauid very
much brasse, wherewith Solomon made the brasen Sea, and the
pillars, and the vessels of brasse.<note> Called in the booke of Sam. Beta and Berothai. , 1.King.7. 23.and 2. chro. 4.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Now
when Tou king of Hamath heard how Dauid had smitten all the hoste
of Hadarezer king of Zobah:<note> Or, Toi, 2. Sam.8.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee sent
Hadoram his sonne to king Dauid, to enquire of his welfare, and to
congratulate him, because hee had fought against Hadarezer, and
smitten him (for Hadarezer had warre with Tou) and with him all
manner of vessels of golde and siluer, and brasse.<note> Or, Ioram, 2. Sam. 8.10. , Or, to salute. , Heb. to blesse. , Heb. was the man of warres.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Them
also king Dauid dedicated vnto the Lord, with the siluer and the
golde that he brought from all these nations: from Edom, and from
Moab, and from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and
from Amalek.</ab>
<ab n="12">Moreouer,
Abishai the sonne of Zeruiah, slew of the Edomites in the valley of
salt, eighteene thousand.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
he put garisons in Edom, and all the Edomites became Dauids
seruants. Thus the Lord preserued Dauid whithersoeuer he
went.</ab>

<fw>Hanuns villenie.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ So
Dauid reigned ouer all Israel, and executed iudgement and iustice
among all his people.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Ioab
the sonne of Zeruiah was ouer the hoste, and Iehoshaphat the sonne
of Ahilud, Recorder.<note> Or, Remembrancer.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Zadok
the sonne of Ahitub, and Abimelech the sonne of Abiathar, were the
Priests, and Shausha was Scribe.<note> Called Ahimelech in Sam. , Called Saraia in Sam. and Sisa, 1. King.4.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Benaiah
the sonne of Iehoiada was ouer the Cherethites, and the Pelethites:
and the sonnes of Dauid were chiefe about the king.<note> Heb. at the hand of the King.</note></ab>



</div>