<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Chronicles_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 The diuisions of the porters. 13
The gates assigned by lot. 20 The Leuites that had charge of the
treasures. 29 Officers and Iudges.</head>

<ab n="1">Concerning
the diuisions of the porters: of the Korhites was Meshelemiah the
sonne of Kore, of the sonnes of Asaph.<note> Or, Shelemiah, ver. 14. , Or, Abiasaph, chap. 9. 19. &amp; 6. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the
sonnes of Meshelemiah were Zechariah the first borne, Iediael the
second, Zebadiah the third, Iathniel the fourth,</ab>
<ab n="3">Elam the
fifth, Iehohanan the sixth, Elioenai the seuenth.</ab>
<ab n="4">Moreouer the
sonnes of Obed-Edom were Shemaiah the first borne, Iehozabad the
second, Ioah the thirde, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethaneel the
fifth.</ab>
<ab n="5">Ammiel the
sixth, Issachar the seuenth, Peulthai the eighth: for God blessed
him.<note> That is, Obed-Edom, as chap. 13.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Also vnto
Shemaiah his sonne were sonnes borne, that ruled throughout the
house of their father: for they were mighty men of valour.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites and Porters
offices.</fw>
<ab n="7">The sonnes
of Shemaiah: Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad, whose brethren
were strong men; Elihu, and Semachiah.</ab>
<ab n="8">All these of
the sonnes of Obed-Edom: they and their sonnes and their brethren,
able men for strength for the seruice, were threescore and two of
Obed-Edom.</ab>
<ab n="9">And
Meshelemiah had sonnes and brethren, strong men, eighteene.</ab>
<ab n="10">Also Hosah
of the children of Merari, had sonnes: Simri the chiefe, (for
though he was not the first borne, yet his father made him the
chiefe)</ab>
<ab n="11">Hilkiah the
second, Tebaliah the thirde, Zechariah the fourth: all the sonnes
and brethren of Hosah, were thirteene.</ab>
<ab n="12">Among these
were the diuisions of the porters, euen among the chiefe men,
hauing wards one against another, to minister in the house of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
they cast lots as well the small as the great, according to the
house of their fathers for euery gate.<note> Or, aswel for the smal as for the great.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the lot
Eastward fel to Shelemiah; then for Zechariah his sonne (a wise
counseller:) they cast lots, and his lot came out
Northward.<note> Called Meshelemiah, ver.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">To
Obed-Edom Southward, and to his sonnes, the house of
Asuppim.<note> Hebr. gatherings.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">To Shuppim
and Hosa, the lot came foorth Westward with the gate Shallecheth,
by the causey of the going vp, ward against ward.<note> See 1. king 10.4. 2.chr. 9.4,11.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Eastward
were sixe Leuites, Northward foure a day, Southward foure a day,
and toward Asuppim two and two.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Parbar
Westward, foure at the causey, and two at Parbar.</ab>
<ab n="19">These are
the diuisions of the porters among the sonnes of Kore, and among
the sonnes of Merari.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
of the Leuites, Ahiiah was ouer the treasures of the house of God,
and ouer the treasures of the dedicate things.<note> Heb, holy things.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">As
concerning the sonnes of Laadan: the sonnes of the Gershonite
Laadan, hiefe fathers; euen of Laadan the Gershonite, were
Iehieli.<note> Or, Libni, chap.6. 17. , Or, Iehiel, chap.23.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The sonnes
of Iehieli, Zetham and Ioel his brother, which were ouer the
treasures of the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">Of the
Amramites, and the Izharites, the Hebronites, and the
Uzzielites:</ab>

<fw>Officers appointed for the
King.</fw>
<ab n="24">And Shebuel
the sonne of Gershom, the sonne of Moses, was ruler of the
treasures.</ab>
<ab n="25">And his
brethren by Eliezer: Rehabiah his sonne, and Ieshaiah his sonne,
and Ioram his sonne, and Zichri his sonne, &amp; Shelomith his
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="26">Which
Shelomith and his brethren, were ouer all the treasures of the
dedicate things, which Dauid the king and the chiefe fathers, the
captaines ouer thousands and hundreds, and the captaines of the
hoste had dedicated.</ab>
<ab n="27">Out of the
spoyles wonne in battels, did they dedicate to maintaine the house
of the Lord.<note> Heb. out of the battels and spoiles.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And all
that Samuel the Seer, and Saul the sonne of Kish, and Abner the
sonne of Ner, and Ioab the sonne of Zeruiah had dedicated, and
whosoeuer had dedicated any thing, it was vnder the hand of
Shelomith and of his brethren.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Of
the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sonnes, were for the outward
busines ouer Israel, for officers and Iudges.</ab>
<ab n="30">And of the
Hebronits, Hashabiah and his brethren, men of valour, a thousand
and seuen hundred, were officers among them of Israel on this side
Iorden westward, in all busines of the Lord, and in the seruice of
the king.<note> Heb. ouer the charge.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Among the
Hebronites was Ieriiah the chiefe, euen among the Hebronits,
according to the generations of his fathers: in the fourtieth yeere
of the reigne of Dauid, they were sought for, and there were found
among them mightie men of valour, at Iazer of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="32">And his
brethren, men of valour, were two thousand and seuen hundred chiefe
fathers, whom King Dauid made rulers ouer the Reubenites, the
Gadites, &amp; the halfe tribe of Manasseh, for euery matter
perteining to God, and affaires of the king.<note> Heb. thing.</note></ab>



</div>