<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>Hee declareth that his preaching, 1
though it bring not excellency of speech, or of 4 humane wisedome:
yet consisteth in the 4. 5 power of God: and so farre excelleth 6
the wisedome of this world, and 9 humane sense, as that 14 the
naturall man cannot vnderstand it.</head>

<ab n="1">And I,
brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellencie of speech,
or of wisedome, declaring vnto you the testimony of
God.<note> Wis.1.17.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wisdome.</fw>
<ab n="2">For I
determined not to know any thing amōg you, saue Iesus Christ,
and him crucified.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I was
with you in weakenesse, and in feare, and in much
trembling.</ab>
<ab n="4">And my
speech, and my preaching was not with entising words of mans
wisedome, but in demonstration of the Spirit, and of
power:<note> 2.Pet.1. 10. , Or, perswasible.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">That your
faith should not stand in the wisdome of men, but in the power of
God.<note> Gr. be.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Howbeit wee
speake wisedome among them that are perfect: yet not the wisedome
of this worlde, nor of the Princes of this worlde, that come to
nought:</ab>
<ab n="7">But wee
speake the wisedome of God in a mysterie, euen the hidden wisedome
which God ordeined before the world, vnto our glory.</ab>
<ab n="8">Which none
of the princes of this world knewe: for had they knowen it, they
would not haue crucified the Lord of glory.</ab>
<ab n="9">But as it is
written, Eye hath not seene, nor eare heard, neither haue entred
into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them
that loue him.<note> Esa. 64.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But God
hath reueiled them vnto vs by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth
all things, yea, the deepe things of God.</ab>
<ab n="11">For what
man knoweth the things of a man, saue the spirit of man which is in
him? Euen so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of
God.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now wee
haue receiued, not the spirit of the world, but the Spirit which is
of God, that wee might know the things that are freely giuen to vs
of God.</ab>
<ab n="13">Which
things also we speake, not in the words which mans wisedome
teacheth, but which the holy Ghost teacheth, comparing spiritual
things with spirituall.<note> 2.Pet.1.16</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But the
naturall man receiueth not the things of the Spirit of God, for
they are foolishnesse vnto him: neither can he know them, because
they are spiritually discerned.</ab>
<ab n="15">But he that
is spirituall, iudgeth all things, yet he himselfe is iudged of no
man.<note> Pro.27.19 , Or, discerneth. , Or, discerned.</note></ab>

<fw>Paul planteth.</fw>
<ab n="16">For who
hath knowen the mind of the Lord that he may instruct him? But we
haue the mind of Christ.<note> Rom.11. 34. esa.40. 13. , Gr. shall.</note></ab>



</div>