<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Spirituall gifts 4 are diuers, 7
yet all to profit withall. 8 And to that ende, are diuersly
bestowed: 12 That by the like proportion, as the members of a
naturall body, tend all to the 16 mutuall decency, 22 seruice, and
26 succour of the same body; 27 so wee should doe one for another,
to make vp the mysticall body of Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">Now
concerning spirituall giftes, brethren, I would not haue you
ignorant.</ab>
<ab n="2">Yee know
that yee were Gentiles, caryed away vnto these dumbe idoles, euen
as ye were led.</ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore I
giue you to vnderstand, that no man speaking by the spirit of God,
calleth Iesus accursed: and that no man can say that Iesus is the
Lord, but by the holy Ghost.<note> Or, Anathema.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Nowe there
are diuersities of gifts, but the same spirit.</ab>
<ab n="5">And there
are differences of administrations, but the same Lord.</ab>

<fw>Spirituall gifts.</fw>
<ab n="6">And there
are diuersities of operations, but it is the same God, which
worketh all in all.</ab>
<ab n="7">But the
manifestation of the spirit, is giuen to euery man to profit
withall.</ab>
<ab n="8">For to one
is giuen by the spirit, the word of wisedome, to another the word
of knowledge, by the same spirit.</ab>
<ab n="9">To another
faith, by the same spirit: to another the gifts of healing, by the
same spirit:</ab>
<ab n="10">To another
the working of miracles, to another prophecie, to another
discerning of spirits, to another diuers kindes of tongues, to
another the interpretation of tongues.</ab>
<ab n="11">But all
these worketh that one and the selfe same spirit, diuiding to euery
man seuerally as he will.</ab>
<ab n="12">For as the
body is one, and hath many members, and all the membrs of that one
body, being many, are one bodie: so also is Christ.</ab>
<ab n="13">For by one
spirit are we all baptized into one bodie, whether wee bee Iewes or
Gentiles, whether wee bee bond or free: and haue beene all made to
drinke into one spirit.<note> Gr. Greeks.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the
body is not one member, but many.</ab>
<ab n="15">If the
foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body: is
it therefore not of the body?</ab>
<ab n="16">And if the
eare shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body: is
it therefore not of the body?</ab>
<ab n="17">If the
whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were
hearing, where were the smelling?</ab>
<ab n="18">But now
hath God set the members, euery one of them in the body, as it hath
pleased him.</ab>
<ab n="19">And if
they were all one member, where were the body?</ab>
<ab n="20">But now
are they many members, yet but one body.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
eye cannot say vnto the hand, I haue no need of thee: nor againe,
the head to the feete, I haue no neede of you.</ab>
<ab n="22">Nay, much
more those members of the bodie, which seeme to bee more feeble,
are necessary.</ab>

<fw>Charitie praised.</fw>
<ab n="23">And those
members of the bodie, which wee thinke to bee lesse honourable,
vpon these we bestow more abundant honour, and our vncomely parts
haue more abundant comelinesse.<note> Or, put on.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For our
comely parts haue no need: but God hath tempered the bodie
together, hauing giuen more abundant honour to that part which
lacked:</ab>
<ab n="25">That there
should be no schisme in the body: but that the members should haue
the same care one for another.<note> Or, diuision.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And
whether one member suffer, all the members suffer with it: or one
member be honoured, all the members reioyce with it.</ab>
<ab n="27">Now yee
are the body of Christ, and members in particular.</ab>
<ab n="28">And God
hath set some in the Church, first Apostles, secondarily Prophets,
thirdly Teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healings,
helpes in gouernmēts, diuersities of tongues.<note> Or, kinds.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Are all
Apostles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers? are all workers of
miracles?<note> Or, powers.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Haue all
the gifts of healing? doe all speake with tongues? doe all
interpret?</ab>
<ab n="31">But couet
earnestly the best gifts: And yet shew I vnto you a more excellent
way.</ab>



</div>