<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 To abstaine from meates offered to
Idoles: 8. 9 We must not abuse our Christian libertie, to the
offence of our brethren: 11 but must bridle our knowledge with
Charitie.</head>

<ab n="1">Now as
touching things offered vnto idoles, wee know that wee all haue
knowledge. Knowledge puffeth vp: but Charitie edifieth.</ab>
<ab n="2">And if any
man thinke that hee knoweth any thing, hee knoweth nothing yet as
he ought to know.</ab>
<ab n="3">But if any
man loue God, the same is knowen of him.</ab>
<ab n="4">As
concerning therefore the eating of those things that are offered in
sacrifice vnto idoles, wee know that an idole is nothing in the
world, and that there is none other God but one.</ab>
<ab n="5">For though
there bee that are called gods, whether in heauen or in earth (as
there be gods many, and lords many:)</ab>
<ab n="6">But to vs
there is but one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we in
him, and one Lord Iesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by
him.<note> Or, for him, Rom.11. 36.</note></ab>

<fw>Of offending our brethren.</fw>
<ab n="7">Howbeit
there is not in euerie man that knowledge: for some with conscience
of the idole vnto this houre, eate it as a thing offred vnto an
idole, and their conscience being weake, is defiled.</ab>
<ab n="8">But meate
commendeth vs not to God: for neither if we eate, are we the
better: neither if wee eate not, are we the worse.<note> Or, haue we the more. , Or, haue we the lesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But take
heed lest by any meanes, this libertie of yours become a stumbling
blocke to them that are weake.<note> Or, power.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For if any
man see thee which hast knowledge, sit at meat in the idols temple:
shall not the conscience of him which is weake, be emboldened to
eat those things which are offered to idols?<note> Gr. edified.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And through
thy knowledge shal the weake brother perish, for whome Christ
died?</ab>
<ab n="12">But when ye
sinne so against the brethren, and wound their weake conscience, ye
sinne against Christ.</ab>
<ab n="13">Wherefore
if meate make my brother to offend, I will eat no flesh while the
world standeth, lest I make my brother to offend.</ab>



</div>