<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-15-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>3 By Christes resurrection, 12 he
proueth the necessitie of our resurrection, against all such as
deny the resurrection of the body. 21 The fruit, 35 and maner
thereof, 51 And of the changing of them, that shall bee found aliue
at the last day.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer
brethren, I declare vnto you the Gospel which I preached vnto you,
which also you haue receiued, and wherein yee stand.</ab>
<ab n="2">By which
also yee are saued, if yee keepe in memorie what I preached vnto
you, vnlesse yee haue beleeued in vaine.<note> Or, hold fast. , Gr. by what speech.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For I
deliuered vnto you first of all, that which I also receiued, how
that Christ died for our sinnes according to the
Scriptures:</ab>
<ab n="4">And that he
was buried, and that he rose againe the third day according to the
Scriptures.</ab>
<ab n="5">And that he
was seene of Cephas, then of the twelue.</ab>
<ab n="6">And that
hee was seene of aboue fiue hundred brethren at once: of whom the
greater part remaine vnto this present, but some are fallen
asleepe.</ab>
<ab n="7">After that,
he was seen of Iames, then of all the Apostles.</ab>
<ab n="8">And last of
all he was seene of me also, as of one borne out of due
time.<note> Or, an abortiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For I am
the least of the Apostles, that am not meet to be called an Apostle
because I persecuted þ<note/> Church of God.</ab>
<ab n="10">But by the
grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed
vpō me, was not in vaine: But I laboured more abundantly then
they all, yet not I, but the grace of God which was with
me:</ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore,
whether it were I or they, so we preach, aud so ye
beleeued.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now if
Christ be preached that he rose from the dead, how say some among
you, that there is no resurrection of the dead?</ab>
<ab n="13">But if
there be no resurrection of the dead, then is Christ not
risen.</ab>
<ab n="14">And if
Christ be not risen, then is our preaching vaine, and your faith is
also vaine:</ab>

<fw>The resurrection is prooued.</fw>
<ab n="15">Yea, and
we are found false witnesses of God, because we haue testified of
God, that he raised vp Christ: whom hee raised not vp, if so bee
that the dead rise not.</ab>
<ab n="16">For if the
dead rise not, then is not Christ raised.</ab>
<ab n="17">And if
Christ be not raised, your faith is vaine, ye are yet in your
sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then they
also which are fallen asleepe in Christ, are perished.</ab>
<ab n="19">If in this
life only we haue hope in Christ, wee are of all men most
miserable.</ab>
<ab n="20">But now is
Christ risen from the dead, and become the first fruits of them
that slept.</ab>
<ab n="21">For since
by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the
dead.</ab>
<ab n="22">For as in
Adam all die, euen so in Christ shall all be made aliue.</ab>
<ab n="23">But euery
man in his owne order. Christ the first fruits, afterward they that
are Christs, at his comming.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then
commeth the end, when he shall haue deliuered vp the kingdome to
God euen the Father, when he shall haue put downe all rule, and all
authority and power.</ab>
<ab n="25">For he
must reigne, till hee hath put all enemies vnder his feete.</ab>
<ab n="26">The last
enemie that shall be destroyed, is death.</ab>
<ab n="27">For he
hath put all things vnder his feete; but when hee saith all things
are put vnder him, it is manifest that he is excepted which did put
all things vnder him.</ab>
<ab n="28">And when
all things shall bee subdued vnto him, then shal the Sonne also
himselfe bee subiect vnto him that put all things vnder him, that
God may be all in all.</ab>
<ab n="29">Else what
shal they do, which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not
at all, why are they then baptized for the dead?</ab>
<ab n="30">And why
stand we in ieopardy euery houre?</ab>
<ab n="31">I protest
by your reioycing which I haue in Christ Iesus our Lord, I die
dayly.<note> Some reade, our.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">If after
the maner of men I haue fought with beasts at Ephesus, what
aduantageth it me, if the dead rise not? let vs eate and drinke,
for to morrowe wee die.<note> Or, to speak after the maner of men.</note></ab>

<fw>The resurrection is prooued.</fw>
<ab n="33">Bee not
deceiued: euill communications corrupt good manners.</ab>
<ab n="34">Awake to
righteousnesse, and sinne not: for some haue not the knowledge of
God, I speake this to your shame.</ab>
<ab n="35">But some
man will say, How are the dead raysed vp? and with what body doe
they come?</ab>
<ab n="36">Thou
foole, that which thou sowest, is not quickened except it
die.</ab>
<ab n="37">And that
which thou sowest, thou sowest not that body that shall be, but
bare graine, it may chance of wheate, or of some other
graine.</ab>
<ab n="38">But God
giueth it a body as it hath pleased him, and to euery seed his owne
body.</ab>
<ab n="39">All flesh
is not the same flesh, but there is one kind of flesh of men,
another flesh of beasts, another of fishes, and another of
birds.</ab>
<ab n="40">There are
also celestiall bodies, and bodies terrestriall: But the glorie of
the celestiall is one, and the glorie of the terrestriall is
another.</ab>
<ab n="41">There is
one glory of the sunne, another of the moone, and another glorie of
the starres: for one starre differeth from another starre in
glorie.</ab>
<ab n="42">So also is
the resurrection of the dead, it is sowen in corruption, it is
raised in incorruption.</ab>
<ab n="43">It is
sowen in dishonour, it is raysed in glorie: it is sowen in
weakenesse, it is raysed in power:</ab>
<ab n="44">It is
sowen a naturall body, it is raised a spirituall bodie. There is a
naturall bodie, and there is a spirituall bodie.</ab>
<ab n="45">And so it
is written: The first man Adam was made a liuing soule, the last
Adam was made a quickening spirit.</ab>
<ab n="46">Howbeit
that was not first which is spirituall: but that which is naturall,
and afterward that which is spirituall.</ab>
<ab n="47">The first
man is of the earth, earthy: The second man is the Lord from
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="48">As is the
earthy, such are they that are earthy, and as is the heauenly, such
are they also that are heauenly.</ab>
<ab n="49">And as we
haue borne the image of the earthy, wee shall also beare the image
of the heauenly.</ab>
<ab n="50">Now this I
say, brethren, that flesh &amp; blood cannot inherite the kingdome
of God: neither doth corruption inherite incorruption.</ab>

<fw>Our victory.</fw>
<ab n="51">Behold, I
shew you a mysterie: we shall not all sleepe, but wee shall all be
changed,</ab>
<ab n="52">In a
moment, in the twinckling of an eye, at the last trumpe, (for the
trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible,
and we shall be changed.)</ab>
<ab n="53">For this
corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortall must put on
immortalitie.</ab>
<ab n="54">So when
this corruptible shall haue put on incorruption, &amp; this mortall
shall haue put on immortality, then shall be brought to passe the
saying that is written, Death is swallowed vp in
victorie.<note> Ose.13.14</note></ab>
<ab n="55">O death,
where is thy sting? O graue, where is thy victorie?<note> Or, hell.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">The sting
of death is sinne, and the strength of sinne is the law.</ab>
<ab n="57">But
thankes bee to God, which giueth vs the victorie, through our Lord
Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="58">Therefore
my beloued brethren, be yee stedfast, vnmoueable, alwayes abounding
in the worke of the Lord, forasmuch as you know that your labour is
not in vaine in the Lord.</ab>



</div>