<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 All giftes, 2. 3 how excellent
soeuer, are nothing worth without charitie. 4 The praises therof,
and 13 prelation before hope &amp; faith.</head>

<ab n="1">Though I
speake with the tongues of men &amp; of Angels, and haue not
charity, I am become as sounding brasse or a tinkling
cymbal.</ab>
<ab n="2">And though
I haue the gift of prophesie, and vnderstand all mysteries and all
knowledge: and though I haue all faith, so that I could remooue
mountaines, and haue no charitie, I am nothing.</ab>
<ab n="3">And though
I bestowe all my goods to feede the poore, and though I giue my
body to bee burned, and haue not charitie, it profiteth me
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="4">Charitie
suffereth long, and is kinde: charitie enuieth not: charitie
vaunteth not it selfe, is not puffed vp,<note> Or, is not rash.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Doeth not
behaue it selfe vnseemly, seeketh not her owne, is not easily
prouoked, thinketh no euill,</ab>
<ab n="6">Reioyceth
not in iniquitie, but reioyceth in the trueth:<note> Or, with the trueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Beareth all
things, beleeueth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all
things.</ab>

<fw>Of prophecying, strange tongues, and
interpretation.</fw>
<ab n="8">Charitie
neuer faileth: but whether there be prophesies, they shall faile;
whether there bee tongues, they shall cease; whether there bee
knowledge, it shall vanish away.</ab>
<ab n="9">For we know
in part, and we prophesie in part.</ab>
<ab n="10">But when
that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part, shalbe
done away.</ab>
<ab n="11">When I was
a childe, I spake as a childe, I vnderstood as a childe, I thought
as a childe: but when I became a man, I put away childish
things.<note> Or, reasoned.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For now we
see through a glasse, darkely: but then face to face: now I know in
part, but then shall I know euen as also I am knowen.<note> Gr. in a riddle.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And now
abideth faith, hope, charitie, these three, but the greatest of
these is charitie.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>