<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-16-16-1-Corinthians.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>After his salutation, and
thankesgiuing, 10 he exhorteth them to vnitie, and 12 reprooueth
their dissentions. 18 God destroyeth the wisedome of the wise, 21
by the foolishnesse of preaching, and 26 calleth not the wise,
mighty, and noble, but 27. 28 the foolish, weake, and men of no
accompt.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul called
to be an Apostle of Iesus Christ, through the will of God, and
Sosthenes our brother,</ab>
<ab n="2">Unto the
Church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are sanctified in
Christ Iesus, called to be Saints, with all that in euery place
call vpon the Name of Iesus Christ our Lord, both theirs and
ours.<note> Acts.15. 9. , Rom. 1.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Grace be
vnto you, and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="4">I thanke my
God alwayes on your behalfe, for the grace of God which is giuen
you by Iesus Christ,</ab>
<ab n="5">That in
euery thing yee are enriched by him, in all vtterance, and in all
knowledge:</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen as the
Testimony of Christ was confirmed in you.</ab>
<ab n="7">So that yee
come behinde in no gift; wayting for the comming of our Lord Iesus
Christ,<note> Gr. Reuelation.</note></ab>

<fw>Against contentions.</fw>
<ab n="8">Who shall
also confirme you vnto the end, that yee may be blamelesse in the
day of our Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="9">God is
faithful by whom ye were called vnto the felowship of his Sonne
Iesus Christ our Lord.<note> 1.Thess. 5. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Now I
beseech you brethren by the Name of our Lord Iesus Christ, that yee
all speake the same thing, and that there be no diuisions among
you: but that ye be perfectly ioyned together in the same minde,
and in the same iudgement.<note> Greeke, schismes.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For it hath
bene declared vnto me of you, my brethren, by them which are of the
house of Cloe, that there are contentions among you.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now this I
say, that euery one of you saith, I am of Paul, and I of Apollo,
and I of Cephas, and I of Christ.<note> Acts.18. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Is Christ
diuided? was Paul crucified for you? or were yee baptized in the
name of Paul?</ab>
<ab n="14">I thanke
God that I baptized none of you, but Crispus and Gaius:<note> Acts.18. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Lest any
should say, that I had baptized in mine owne name.</ab>
<ab n="16">And I
baptized also the household of Stephanas: besides, I know not
whether I baptized any other.</ab>
<ab n="17">For Christ
sent me not to baptize, but to preach the Gospel: not with wisedome
of words, lest the Crosse of Christ should be made of none
effect.<note> 2.Pet.1. 16. , Or, speech.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For the
preaching of the Crosse is to them that perish, foolishnesse: but
vnto vs which are saued, it is the power of God.<note> Rom.1. 16.</note></ab>

<fw>Wherin to glory.</fw>
<ab n="19">For it is
written, I will destroy the wisedome of the wise, and wil bring to
nothing the vnderstanding of the prudent.<note> Esa.29. 14</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Where is
the wise? where is the Scribe? where is the disputer of this world?
Hath not God made foolish the wisedome of this world?<note> Esa.33. 18</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For after
that, in the wisedom of God, the world by wisedome knew not God, it
pleased God by the foolishnesse of preaching, to saue them that
beleeue.<note> Rom.1.20</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For the
Iewes require a signe, and the Greekes seeke after
wisedome.<note> Matt.12. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But wee
preach Christ crucified, vnto the Iewes a stumbling block, and vnto
the Greekes, foolishnesse:</ab>
<ab n="24">But vnto
them which are called, both Iewes and Greekes, Christ, the power of
God, &amp; the wisedome of God.</ab>
<ab n="25">Because the
foolishnesse of God is wiser then men: and the weakenesse of God is
stronger then men.</ab>
<ab n="26">For ye see
your calling, brethren, how that not many wise men after the flesh,
not many mighty, not many noble are called.</ab>
<ab n="27">But God
hath chosen the foolish things of the world, to confound the wise:
and God hath chosen the weake things of the world, to confound the
things which are mighty:</ab>
<ab n="28">And base
things of the world, and things which are despised, hath God
chosen, yea and things which are not, to bring to nought things
that are,</ab>
<ab n="29">That no
flesh should glory in his presence.</ab>
<ab n="30">But of him
are ye in Christ Iesus, who of God is made vnto vs wisedome, and
righteousnesse, and sanctification, and redemption:</ab>
<ab n="31">That
according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the
Lord.<note> Iere.9.23.</note></ab>



</div>