<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 In what account the Ministers
ought to bee had. 7 We haue nothing which wee haue not receiued. 9
The Apostles spectacles to the world, Angels and men, 13 The filth
and off-scouring of the worlde: 15 Yet our fathers in Christ, 16
Whome wee ought to followe.</head>

<ab n="1">Let a man so
account of vs, as of the ministers of Christ, and stewards of the
mysteries of God.</ab>
<ab n="2">Moreouer, it
is required in stewards, that a man be found faithfull.</ab>
<ab n="3">But with mee
it is a very small thing that I should bee iudged of you, or of
mans iudgement: yea, I iudge not mine owne selfe.<note> Gr. day.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For I know
nothing by my selfe, yet am I not hereby iustified: but hee that
iudgeth me is the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Fooles for Christ.</fw>
<ab n="5">Therefore
iudge nothing before the time, vntill the Lord come, who both will
bring to light the hidden things of darkenesse, and will make
manifest the counsels of the hearts: and then shall euery man haue
prayse of God.<note> Matt.7.1 rom.2.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And these
things, brethren, I haue in a figure transferred to my selfe, and
to Apollo, for your sakes: that ye might learne in vs not to thinke
of men, aboue that which is written, that no one of you bee puffed
vp for one against another.</ab>
<ab n="7">For who
maketh thee to differ from another? And what hast thou that thou
didst not receiue? Now if thou didst receiue it, why doest thou
glory as if thou hadst not receiued it?<note> Gr. distinguisheth thee?</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Now ye are
full, now ye are rich, ye haue reigned as kings without vs, and I
would to God ye did reigne, that we also might reigne with
you.</ab>
<ab n="9">For I thinke
that God hath set forth vs the Apostles last, as it were approued
to death. For wee are made a spectacle vnto the world, and to
Angels, and to men.<note> Gr. theater.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">We are
fooles for Christs sake, but ye are wise in Christ. We are weake,
but ye are strong: yee are honourable, but we are despised.</ab>
<ab n="11">Euen vnto
this present houre we both hunger and thirst, and are naked, and
are buffeted, and haue no certaine dwelling place,</ab>
<ab n="12">And labour,
working with our owne hands: being reuiled, wee blesse: being
persecuted, we suffer it:<note> Act.20.34. 1 thess.2.9. 2 thess.3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Being
defamed, we intreate: we are made as the filth of the world, and
are the off-scouring of all things vnto this day.<note> Mat.5.44</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I write not
these things to shame you, but as my beloued sonnes I warne
you.</ab>
<ab n="15">For though
you haue ten thousand instructors in Christ, yet haue yee not many
fathers: For in Christ Iesus I haue begotten you through the
Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="16">Wherefore I
beseech you, be yee followers of me.</ab>
<ab n="17">For this
cause haue I sent vnto you Timotheus, who is my beloued sonne, and
faithfull in the Lord, who shal bring you into remembrance of my
wayes which be in Christ, as I teach euery where in euery
Church.</ab>

<fw>Old leauen.</fw>
<ab n="18">Nowe some
are puffed vp as though I would not come to you.</ab>
<ab n="19">But I wil
come to you shortly, if the Lord will, and will knowe, not the
speach of them which are puffed vp, but the power.<note> Acts 19. 21. iam 4. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For the
kingdome of God is not in word, but in power.</ab>
<ab n="21">What will
ye? Shall I come vnto you with a rod, or in loue, and in the spirit
of meekenesse?</ab>



</div>