<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 He reprooueth them, because in
holy assemblies, 4 their men prayed with their heads couered, and 6
women with their heads vncouered, 17 and because generally their
meetings were not for the better but for the worse, as 21 namely in
profaning with their owne feasts the Lords Supper. 25 Lastly, he
calleth them to the first institution thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">Be yee
followers of mee, euen as I also am of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="2">Now I
prayse you, brethren, that you remember me in all things, and keepe
the ordinances, as I deliuered them to you.<note> Or, traditions.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But I would
haue you knowe, that the head of euery man is Christ: and the head
of the woman is the man, and the head of Christ is God.</ab>
<ab n="4">Euery man
praying or prophecying, hauing his head couered, dishonoureth his
head.</ab>
<ab n="5">But euery
woman that prayeth or prophesieth with her head vncouered,
dishonoureth her head: for that is euen all one as if she were
shauen.</ab>
<ab n="6">For if the
woman be not couered, let her also bee shorne: but if it bee a
shame for a woman to be shorne or shauen, let her be
couered.</ab>

<fw>Christs Supper.</fw>
<ab n="7">For a man
in deede ought not to couer his head, forasmuch as hee is the image
and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man.</ab>
<ab n="8">For the man
is not of the woman: but the woman of the man.</ab>
<ab n="9">Neither was
the man created for the woman: but the woman for the man.</ab>
<ab n="10">For this
cause ought the woman to haue power on her head, because of the
Angels.<note> That is, a couering, in signe that she is vnder the power of her husband</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Neuerthelesse,
neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the
man in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">For as the
woman is of the man: euen so is the man also by the woman; but all
things of God.</ab>
<ab n="13">Iudge in
your selues, is it comely that a woman pray vnto God
vncouered?</ab>
<ab n="14">Doeth not
euen nature it selfe teach you, that if a man haue long haire, it
is a shame vnto him?</ab>
<ab n="15">But if a
woman haue long haire, it is a glory to her: for her haire is giuen
her for a couering.<note> Or, vaile.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But if any
man seeme to be contentious, we haue no such custome, neither the
Churches of God.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now in
this that I declare vnto you, I praise you not, that you come
together not for the better, but for the worse.</ab>
<ab n="18">For first
of all when yee come together in the Church, I heare that there be
diuisions among you, and I partly beleeue it.<note> Or, schismes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For there
must bee also heresies among you, that they which are approued may
be made manifest among you.<note> Or, sects.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">When yee
come together therefore into one place, this is not to eate the
Lords Supper.<note> Or, ye cannot eate.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For in
eating, euery one taketh before other, his owne supper: and one is
hungry, and an other is drunken.</ab>
<ab n="22">What, haue
ye not houses to eate and to drinke in? Or despise yee the Church
of God, and shame them that haue not? What shall I say to you?
shall I praise you in this? I prayse you not.<note> Or, them that are poore.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For I haue
receiued of the Lord that which also I deliuered vnto you, that the
Lord Iesus, the same night in which he was betrayed, tooke
bread:</ab>
<ab n="24">And when
he had giuen thanks, he brake it, and sayd, Take, eate, this is my
body, which is broken for you: this doe in remembrance of
mee.<note> Mat.26.16 mar.14.22. luk. 22.19. , Or, for a rembrance.</note></ab>

<fw>Spirituall gifts.</fw>
<ab n="25">After the
same manner also hee tooke the cup when he had supped, saying, This
cup is the new Testament in my blood: this do ye, as oft as ye
drinke it, in remembrance of me.</ab>
<ab n="26">For as
often as ye eate this bread, and drinke this cup, yee doe shew the
Lords death till he come.<note> Or, shew yee.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore,
whosoeuer shall eate this bread, and drinke this cup of the Lord
vnworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="28">But let a
man examine himselfe, and so let him eate of that bread, and drinke
of that cup.</ab>
<ab n="29">For hee
that eateth and drinketh vnworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation
to himselfe, not discerning the Lords body.<note> Or, iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">For this
cause many are weake and sickly among you, and many sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="31">For if we
would iudge our selues, we should not be iudged.</ab>
<ab n="32">But when
we are iudged, we are chastened of the Lord, that wee should not be
condemned with the world.</ab>
<ab n="33">Wherefore
my brethren, when ye come together to eate, tary one for
another.</ab>
<ab n="34">And if any
man hunger, let him eate at home, that ye come not together vnto
condemnation. And the rest wil I set in order, when I
come.<note> Or iudgement.</note></ab>



</div>