<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The incestuous person 6 is cause
rather of shame vnto them, then of reioycing. 7 The olde leauen is
to be purged out. 10 Heinous offenders are to be shamed &amp;
auoided.</head>

<ab n="1">It is
reported commonly, that there is fornication among you, and such
fornication, as is not so much as named amongst the Gentiles, that
one should haue his fathers wife.</ab>
<ab n="2">And yee are
puffed vp, and haue not rather mourned, that he that hath done this
deed, might bee taken away from among you.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I verily
as absent in body, but present in spirit, haue iudged alreadie, as
though I were present, concerning him that hath so done this
deed,<note> Col.2.5. , Or, determined.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">In the Name
of our Lord Iesus Christ, when yee are gathered together, and my
spirit, with the power of our Lord Iesus Christ,</ab>
<ab n="5">To deliuer
such a one vnto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the
spirit may be saued in the day of the Lord Iesus.<note> 1.Tim. 1 20</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Your
glorying is not good: know ye not that a little leauen leaueneth
the whole lumpe?<note> Gal.5.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Purge out
therefore the olde leauen, that ye may be a new lumpe, as ye are
vnleauened. For euen Christ our Passeouer is sacrificed for
vs.<note> Or, is slain.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore
let vs keepe the Feast, not with old leauen, neither with the
leauen of malice and wickednesse: but with the vnleauened bread of
sinceritie and trueth.<note> Or, holiday.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">I wrote vnto
you in an Epistle, not to company with fornicators.</ab>
<ab n="10">Yet not
altogether with the fornicatours of this world, or with the
couetous, or extortioners, or with idolaters; for then must yee
needs goe out of the world.</ab>

<fw>Going to law.</fw>
<ab n="11">But now I
haue written vnto you, not to keepe company, if any man that is
called a brother bee a fornicator, or couetous, or an idolater, or
a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner: with such a one, no,
not to eate.</ab>
<ab n="12">For what
haue I to doe to iudge them also that are without? doe not ye iudge
them that are within?</ab>
<ab n="13">But them
that are without, God iudgeth. Therefore put away from among your
selues that wicked person.</ab>



</div>