<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Hee exhorteth them to relieue the
want of the brethren at Ierusalem. 10 Commendeth Timothy, 13 And
after friendly admonitions, 16 Shutteth vp his Epistle with diuers
salutations.</head>

<ab n="1">Now
concerning the collection for the Saints, as I haue giuen order to
the Churches of Galatia, euen so doe ye.</ab>
<ab n="2">Upon the
first day of the weeke, let euery one of you lay by him in store,
as God hath prospered him, that there be no gatherings when I
come.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when I
come, whomsoeuer you shall approue by your letters, them wil I send
to bring your liberality vnto Ierusalem.<note> Gr. gift.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And if it
be meet that I goe also, they shall goe with me.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now I wil
come vnto you, when I shall passe through Macedonia: for I doe
passe through Macedonia.</ab>
<ab n="6">And it may
bee that I will abide, yea, and winter with you, that yee may bring
me on my iourny, whithersoeuer I goe.</ab>

<fw>Stand in faith.</fw>
<ab n="7">For I will
not see you now by the way, but I trust to tarry a while with you,
if the Lord permit.</ab>
<ab n="8">But I will
tarry at Ephesus vntill Pentecost.</ab>
<ab n="9">For a great
doore and effectuall is opened vnto mee, and there are many
aduersaries.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now if
Timotheus come, see that he may be with you without feare: for hee
worketh the worke of the Lord, as I also doe.</ab>
<ab n="11">Let no man
therefore despise him: but conduct him forth in peace, that hee may
come vnto me: for I looke for him with the brethren.</ab>
<ab n="12">As
touching our brother Apollos, I greatly desired him to come vnto
you with þ<note/> brethren, but his wil was not at all to
come at this time: but he wil come when hee shall haue conuenient
time.</ab>
<ab n="13">Watch yee,
stand fast in the faith, quit you like men: be strong.</ab>
<ab n="14">Let all
your things be done with charitie.</ab>
<ab n="15">I beseech
you, brethren, (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the
first fruits of Achaia, and that they haue addicted themselues to
the ministery of the Saints,)</ab>
<ab n="16">That ye
submit your selues vnto such, and to euery one that helpeth with vs
and laboureth.</ab>
<ab n="17">I am glad
of the comming of Stephanas, and Fortunatus, and Achaicus: for that
which was lacking on your part, they haue supplied.</ab>
<ab n="18">For they
haue refreshed my spirit and yours: therefore acknowledge yee them
that are such.</ab>
<ab n="19">The
Churches of Asia salute you: Aquila and Priscilla salute you much
in the Lord, with the Church that is in their house.</ab>
<ab n="20">All the
brethren greet you: greet ye one another with an holy
kisse.</ab>
<ab n="21">The
salutation of me Paul, with mine owne hand.</ab>
<ab n="22">If any man
loue not the Lord Iesus Christ, let him bee Anathema
Maranatha.</ab>
<ab n="23">The grace
of our Lord Iesus Christ be with you.</ab>
<ab n="24">My loue be
with you all in Christ Iesus, Amen. The first Epistle to the
Corinthians was written from Philippi by Stephanas, and Fortunatus,
and Achaicus, and Timotheus.</ab>



</div>