<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 He sheweth his libertie, 7 and
that the minister ought to liue by the Gospel: 15 yet that himselfe
hath of his owne accord abstained, 18 to be either chargeable vnto
them: 22 or offensiue vnto any, in matters indifferent. 24 Our life
is like vnto a race.</head>

<ab n="1">Am I not an
Apostle? am I not free? haue I not seene Iesus Christ our Lord? Are
not you my worke in the Lord?</ab>
<ab n="2">If I bee not
an Apostle vnto others, yet doubtlesse I am to you: for the seale
of mine Apostleship are yee in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">Mine answere
to them that doe examine me, is this:</ab>
<ab n="4">Haue wee not
power to eate and to drinke?</ab>
<ab n="5">Haue we not
power to lead about a sister a wife aswel as other Apostles, and as
the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?<note> Or, woman.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Or I onely
and Barnabas, haue not we power to forbeare working?</ab>
<ab n="7">Who goeth a
warfare any time at his owne charges? who planteth a vineyard, and
eateth not of the fruite thereof? or who feedeth a flocke, and
eateth not of the milke of the flocke?</ab>
<ab n="8">Say I these
things as a man? or saith not the Law the same also?</ab>

<fw>True Ministers.</fw>
<ab n="9">For it is
written in the Law of Moyses, Thou shalt not muzzell the mouth of
the oxe that treadeth out the corne: doth God take care for
oxen?<note> Deut. 25. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Or saith
hee it altogether for our sakes? for our sakes, no doubt, this is
written: that hee that ploweth, should plow in hope: and that hee
that thresheth in hope, should bee partaker of his hope.</ab>
<ab n="11">If we haue
sowen vnto you spirituall things, is it a great thing if wee shall
reape your carnall things?<note> Rom.15. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If others
bee partakers of this power ouer you, are not we rather?
Neuerthelesse, we haue not vsed this power: but suffer all things,
lest wee should hinder the Gospel of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="13">Do ye not
know that they which minister about holy things, liue of the things
of the Temple? and they which wait at the altar, are partakers with
the altar?<note> Deut.18. 1. , Or, feed.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Euen so
hath the Lord ordeined, that they which preach the Gospel, should
liue of the Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="15">But I haue
vsed none of these things. Neither haue I written these things,
that it should bee so done vnto me: for it were better for me to
die, then that any man should make my glorying voyd.</ab>
<ab n="16">For though
I preach the Gospel, I haue nothing to glorie of: for necessitie is
laid vpon mee, yea, woe is vnto me, if I preach not the
Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="17">For if I
doe this thing willingly, I haue a reward: but if against my will,
a dispensation of the Gospel is committed vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="18">What is my
reward then? verily that when I preach the Gospel, I may make the
Gospel of Christ without charge, that I abuse not my power in the
Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="19">For though
I bee free from all men, yet haue I made my selfe seruant vnto all,
that I might gaine the more.</ab>
<ab n="20">And vnto
the Iewes, I became as a Iew, that I might gaine the Iewes: to them
that are vnder the Law, as vnder the Law, that I might gaine them
that are vnder the Law:</ab>
<ab n="21">To them
that are without Law, as without Law (being not without Law to God,
but vnder the Law to Christ,) that I might gaine them that are
without Law.</ab>

<fw>Runne, to obteine.</fw>
<ab n="22">To the
weake became I as weake, that I might gaine the weake: I am made
all things to all men, that I might by all meanes saue
some.</ab>
<ab n="23">And this I
doe for the Gospels sake, that I might be partaker thereof with
you.</ab>
<ab n="24">Know yee
not that they which runne in a race, runne all, but one receiueth
the price? So runne, that yee may obtaine.</ab>
<ab n="25">And euery
man that striueth for the masterie, is temperate in all things: Now
they doe it to obtaine a corruptible crowne, but we an
incorruptible.</ab>
<ab n="26">I therefore
so runne, not as vncertainely: so fight I, not as one that beateth
the ayre:</ab>
<ab n="27">But I keepe
vnder my body, and bring it into subiection: lest that by any
meanes when I haue preached to others, I my selfe should be a
castaway.</ab>



</div>