<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Prophecie is commended, 2. 3. 4
and preferred before speaking with tongues, 6 by a comparison
drawen from musicall instruments. 12 Both must bee referred to
edification, 22 as to their true and proper end. 26 The true vse of
each is taught, 27 and the abuse taxed. 34 Women are forbidden to
speake in the Church.</head>

<ab n="1">Follow
after charitie, and desire spirituall giftes, but rather that yee
may prophesie.</ab>
<ab n="2">For he that
speaketh in an vnknowen tongue, speaketh not vnto men, but vnto
God: for no man vnderstandeth him: howbeit in the spirit he
speaketh mysteries.<note> Gr. heareth</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But he that
prophesieth, speaketh vnto men to edification, and exhortation, and
comfort.</ab>
<ab n="4">He that
speaketh in an vnknowen tongue, edifieth himselfe: but hee that
prophesieth, edifieth the Church.</ab>
<ab n="5">I would
that yee all spake with tongues, but rather that ye prophesied: for
greater is hee that prophesieth, then hee that speaketh with
tongues, except hee interprete, that the Church may receiue
edifying.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now
brethren, if I come vnto you speaking with tongues, what shall I
profit you, except I shall speake to you either by reuelation, or
by knowledge, or by prophesying, or by doctrine?</ab>

<fw>Of prophecying, strange tongues, and
interpretation.</fw>
<ab n="7">And euen
things without life giuing sound, whether pipe or harpe, except
they giue a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be knowen what
is piped or harped?<note> Or, tunes.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For if the
trumpet giue an vncertaine sound, who shall prepare himselfe to the
battell?</ab>
<ab n="9">So likewise
you, except ye vtter by the tongue words easie to be vnderstood,
how shall it be knowen what is spoken? for ye shall speake into the
aire.<note> Gr. significant.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">There are,
it may bee, so many kindes of voices in the world, and none of them
are without signification.</ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore
if I know not the meaning of the voyce, I shall bee vnto him that
speaketh, a Barbarian, and he that speaketh shall be a Barbarian
vnto mee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Euen so
ye, forasmuch as yee are zealous of spirituall gifts, seeke that
yee may excell to the edifying of the Church.<note> Gr. of spirite.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Wherefore
let him that speaketh in an vnknowen tongue, pray that he may
interprete.</ab>
<ab n="14">For if I
pray in an vnknowen tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my vnderstanding
is vnfruitfull.</ab>
<ab n="15">What is it
then? I will pray with the spirit, and wil pray with vnderstanding
also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the
vnderstanding also.</ab>
<ab n="16">Else, when
thou shalt blesse with the spirit, how shall hee that occupieth the
roome of the vnlearned, say Amen at thy giuing of thankes, seeing
he vnderstandeth not what thou sayest?</ab>
<ab n="17">For thou
verily giuest thankes well: but the other is not edified.</ab>
<ab n="18">I thanke
my God, I speake with tongues more then you all.</ab>
<ab n="19">Yet in the
Church I had rather speake fiue words with my vnderstanding, that
by my voyce I might teach others also, then ten thousand words in
an vnknowen tongue.</ab>
<ab n="20">Brethren,
bee not children in vnderstanding: how be it, in malice be yee
children, but in vnderstanding be men.<note> Gr. perfect or of a ripe age.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">In the Law
it is written, With men of other tongues, and other lippes will I
speake vnto this people: and yet for all that will they not heare
me, saith the Lord.<note> Esa. 28.11.</note></ab>

<fw>Of prophecying, strange tongues, and
interpretation.</fw>
<ab n="22">Wherfore
tongues are for a signe, not to them that beleeue, but to them that
beleeue not: But prophesying serueth not for them that beleeue not,
but for them which beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="23">If
therefore the whole Church be come together into some place, and
all speake with tongues, &amp; there come in those that are
vnlearned, or vnbeleeuers, will they not say that ye are
mad?</ab>
<ab n="24">But if all
prophesie, and there come in one that beleeueth not, or one
vnlearned: he is conuinced of all, he is iudged of all.</ab>
<ab n="25">And thus
are the secrets of his heart made manifest, and so falling downe on
his face, hee will worship God, and report that God is in you of a
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="26">How is it
then brethren? when ye come together, euery one of you hath a
Psalme, hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a reuelatiō, hath
an interpretatiō: Let all things be done vnto
edifying.</ab>
<ab n="27">If any man
speake in an vnknowen tongue, let it be by two, or at the most by
three, and that by course, and let one interprete.</ab>
<ab n="28">But if
there be no interpreter, let him keepe silence in the Church, and
let him speake to himselfe, and to God.</ab>
<ab n="29">Let the
Prophets speake two or three, and let the other iudge.</ab>
<ab n="30">If any
thing be reueiled to another that sitteth by, let the first hold
his peace.</ab>
<ab n="31">For yee
may all prophesie one by one, that all may learne, and all may be
comforted.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the
spirits of the Prophets are subiect to the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="33">For God is
not the authour of confusion, but of peace, as in all Churches of
the Saints.<note> Gr. tumult, or vnquietnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Let your
women keepe silence in the Churches, for it is not permitted vnto
them to speake; but they are commanded to bee vnder obedience: as
also saith the Law.<note> Gen.3.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And if
they will learne any thing, let them aske their husbands at home:
for it is a shame for women to speake in the Church.</ab>
<ab n="36">What? came
the word of God out from you? or came it vnto you onely?</ab>
<ab n="37">If any man
thinke himselfe to be a Prophet, or spiritual, let him acknowledge,
that the things that I write vnto you, are the commandements of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="38">But if any
man bee ignorant, let him be ignorant.</ab>

<fw>Christ is risen.</fw>
<ab n="39">Wherefore
brethren, couet to prophesie, and forbid not to speake with
tongues.</ab>
<ab n="40">Let all
things be done decently, and in order.</ab>



</div>