<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The Sacraments of the Iewes, 6 are
types of ours, 7 and their punishments, 11 examples for vs. 14 We
must flie from idolatrie. 21 We must not make the Lords Table the
table of deuils: 24 And in things indifferent, we must haue regard
of our brethren.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer
brethren, I would not that yee should be ignorant, how that all our
fathers were vnder the cloud, and all passed thorow the
Sea:</ab>
<ab n="2">And were
all baptized vnto Moyses in the cloud, and in the sea:</ab>
<ab n="3">And did all
eat the same spirituall meat:</ab>
<ab n="4">And did all
drinke the same spirituall drinke: (for they dranke of that
spirituall Rocke that followed them: and that Rocke was
Christ)<note> Or, went with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But with
many of them God was not well pleased: for they were ouerthrowen in
the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now these
things were our examples, to the intent wee should not lust after
euil things, as they also lusted.<note> Gr. our figures.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Neither be
ye idolaters, as were some of them, as it is written, The people
sate downe to eate and drinke, and rose vp to play.<note> Exod.32. 6. psal.106. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Neither let
vs commit fornication, as some of them committed, and fell in one
day three and twentie thousand.<note> Num.25. 9.</note></ab>

<fw>One bread, one body.</fw>
<ab n="9">Neither let
vs tempt Christ, as some of them also tempted, and were destroyed
of serpents.<note> Num.21. 6</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Neither
murmure ye, as some of them also murmured, and were destroyed of
the destroyer.<note> Num.14. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Now all
these things happened vnto them for ensamples: and they are written
for our admonition, vpon whom the ends of the world are
come.<note> Or, Types.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore,
let him that thinketh he standeth, take heed lest he fall.</ab>
<ab n="13">There hath
no temptation taken you, but such as is common to man: but God is
faithfull, who wil not suffer you to bee tempted aboue that you are
able: but will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that
ye may bee able to beare it.<note> Or, moderate.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Wherefore
my dearely beloued, flee from idolatrie.</ab>
<ab n="15">I speake
as to wise men: iudge ye what I say.</ab>
<ab n="16">The cup of
blessing which wee blesse, is it not the communion of the blood of
Christ? The bread which we breake, is it not the communion of the
body of Christ?</ab>
<ab n="17">For we
being many are one bread, and one body: for we are all partakers of
that one bread.</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold
Israel after the flesh: are not they which eat of the sacrifices,
partakers of the Altar?</ab>
<ab n="19">What say I
then? that the idole is any thing? or that which is offered in
sacrifice to idols is any thing?</ab>
<ab n="20">But I say
that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to
deuils, and not to God: and I would not that yee should haue
fellowship with deuils.<note> Deut.32. 17. psal. 106.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Yee cannot
drinke the cup of the Lord, and the cup of deuils: ye cannot be
partakers of the Lords Table, and of the table of deuils.</ab>
<ab n="22">Doe we
prouoke the Lord to iealousie? are we stronger then he?</ab>
<ab n="23">All things
are lawfull for me, but all things are not expedient: All things
are lawfull for mee, but all things edifie not.</ab>
<ab n="24">Let no man
seeke his owne: but euery man anothers wealth.</ab>
<ab n="25">Whatsoeuer
is solde in the shambles, that eate, asking no question for
conscience sake.</ab>
<ab n="26">For the
earth is the Lords, and the fulnesse thereof.<note> Deut.10. 14. psal.24. 1</note></ab>

<fw>Women couered.</fw>
<ab n="27">If any of
them that beleeue not, bid you to a feast, and yee be disposed to
goe, whatsoeuer is set before you, eate, asking no question for
conscience sake.</ab>
<ab n="28">But if any
man say vnto you, This is offered in sacrifice vnto idoles, eate
not for his sake that shewed it, and for conscience sake. The earth
is the Lords, and the fulnesse thereof.<note> Deut.10. 14. psal.24. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Conscience
I say, not thine owne, but of the others: for why is my libertie
iudged of another mans conscience?</ab>
<ab n="30">For, if I
by grace be a partaker, why am I euill spoken of, for that for
which I giue thankes?<note> Or, thankesgiuing.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Whether
therfore ye eat or drinke, or whatsoeuer ye doe, doe all to the
glory of God.</ab>
<ab n="32">Giue none
offence, neither to the Iewes, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the
Church of God:<note> Gr. Greeks</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Euen as I
please all men in all things, not seeking mine owne profit, but the
profit of many, that they may be saued.</ab>



</div>