<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The Corinthians must not vexe
their brethren, in going to law with them: 6 Especially vnder
Infidels. 9 The vnrighteous shall not inherite the kingdome of God.
15 Our bodies are the members of Christ, 19 And Temples of the holy
Ghost. 16.17 They must not therefore be defiled.</head>

<ab n="1">Dare any of
you, hauing a matter against another, goe to law before the vniust,
and not before the Saints?</ab>
<ab n="2">Do ye not
know that the Saints shall iudge the world? And if the world shalbe
iudged by you, are ye vnworthy to iudge the smallest
matters?</ab>
<ab n="3">Know ye not
that we shall iudge Angels? How much more things that perteine to
this life?</ab>
<ab n="4">If then yee
haue iudgements of things perteining to this life, set them to
iudge who are least esteemed in the Church.</ab>
<ab n="5">I speake to
your shame. Is it so, that there is not a wise man amongst you? no
not one that shall bee able to iudge betweene his brethren?</ab>
<ab n="6">But brother
goeth to law with brother, &amp; that before the
vnbeleeuers?</ab>
<ab n="7">Now
therefore, there is vtterly a fault among you, because yee goe to
law one with another: Why doe ye not rather take wrong? Why doe yee
not rather suffer your selues to be defrauded?</ab>
<ab n="8">Nay, you do
wrong and defraud, and that your brethren.</ab>
<ab n="9">Know yee not
that the vnrighteous shall not inherite the kingdome of God? Be not
deceiued: neither fornicatours, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor
effeminate, nor abusers of themselues with mankinde,</ab>
<ab n="10">Nor
theeues, nor couetous, nor drunkards, nor reuilers, nor
extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God.</ab>

<fw>Our price.</fw>
<ab n="11">And such
were some of you: but ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye
are iustified in the Name of the Lord Iesus, and by the Spirit of
our God.</ab>
<ab n="12">All things
are lawfull vnto mee, but all things are not expedient: all things
are lawfull for mee, but I will not bee brought vnder the power of
any.<note> Or, profitable.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Meats for
the belly, and the belly for meates: but God shall destroy both it
and them. Now the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord:
and the Lord for the body.</ab>
<ab n="14">And God
hath both raised vp the Lord, and will also raise vp vs by his owne
power.</ab>
<ab n="15">Know yee
not that your bodies are the members of Christ? Shall I then take
the members of Christ, and make them the members of an harlot? God
forbid.</ab>
<ab n="16">What, know
ye not that he which is ioyned to an harlot, is one body? for two
(saith he) shalbe one flesh.</ab>
<ab n="17">But hee
that is ioyned vnto the Lord, is one spirit.</ab>
<ab n="18">Flee
fornication: Euery sinne that a man doeth, is without the body: but
he that committeth fornication, sinneth against his owne
body.</ab>
<ab n="19">What, know
ye not that your body is the Temple of the holy Ghost which is in
you, which yee haue of God, and ye are not your owne?</ab>
<ab n="20">For yee are
bought with a price: therefore glorifie God in your body, and in
your spirit, which are Gods.</ab>



</div>