<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Corinthians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Corinthians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>2 Milke is fit for children. 3
Strife and diuision, arguments of a fleshly minde. 7 Hee that
planteth, and hee that watereth, is nothing. 9 The ministers are
Gods fellowe workemen. 11 Christ the only foundation. 16 Men the
temples of God, which 17 must bee kept holy. 19 The wisedome of
this world is foolishnesse with God.</head>

<ab n="1">And I,
brethren, could not speake vnto you as vnto spirituall, but as vnto
carnall, euen as vnto babes in Christ.</ab>
<ab n="2">I haue fed
you with milke, and not with meate: for hitherto yee were not able
to beare it, neither yet now are ye able.</ab>
<ab n="3">For ye are
yet carnall: for whereas there is among you enuying, and strife,
and diuisions, are ye not carnall, and walke as men?<note> Or, factions , Gr. according to man.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For while
one saieth, I am of Paul, and another, I am of Apollo, are ye not
carnall?</ab>
<ab n="5">Who then is
Paul? and who is Apollo? but ministers by whom ye beleeued, euen as
the Lord gaue to euery man.</ab>
<ab n="6">I haue
planted, Apollo watered: but God gaue the encrease.</ab>
<ab n="7">So then,
neither is he that planteth any thing, neither hee that watereth:
but God that giueth the increase.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now hee that
planteth, and hee that watereth, are one: and euery man shal
receiue his own reward according to his owne labour.<note> Psal.63.13 gal.6.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For wee are
labourers together with God, ye are Gods husbandry, yee are Gods
building.<note> Or, tillage.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">According
to the grace of God which is giuen vnto mee, as a wise master
builder I haue laid the foundation, and another buildeth thereon.
But let euery man take heede how hee buildeth thereupon.</ab>
<ab n="11">For other
foundation can no man lay, then that is laide, which is Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now if any
man build vpon this foundation, gold, siluer, preciousstones, wood,
hay, stubble:</ab>

<fw>Gods Ministers.</fw>
<ab n="13">Euery mans
worke shall be made manifest. For the day shall declare it, because
it shall bee reuealed by fire, and the fire shall trie euery mans
worke of what sort it is.<note> Gr. is reuealed.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">If any mans
worke abide which he hath built thereupon, he shal receiue a
reward.</ab>
<ab n="15">If any mans
worke shall bee burnt, he shall suffer losse: but he himselfe shall
be saued: yet so, as by fire.</ab>
<ab n="16">Knowe yee
not that yee are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God
dwelleth in you?<note> 1.Cor. 6. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">If any man
defile the Temple of God, him shall God destroy: for the Temple of
God is holy, which Temple ye are.<note> Or, destroy.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Let no man
deceiue himselfe: If any man among you seemeth to bee wise in this
world, let him become a foole, that he may be wise.</ab>
<ab n="19">For the
wisedome of this world is foolishnesse with God: for it is written,
Hee taketh the wise in their owne craftinesse.<note> Iob.5.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And againe,
The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise, that they are
vaine.<note> Psal.94. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Therefore
let no man glory in men, for all things are yours.</ab>
<ab n="22">Whether
Paul, or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or
things present, or things to come, all are yours.</ab>
<ab n="23">And yee are
Christs, and Christ is Gods.</ab>




</div>