<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The second declareth the power of
a King. 14 The third, the force of women: 33 and of Trueth. 41 The
third is iudged to be wisest, 47 and obtaineth Letters of the King
to build Ierusalem. 58 He praiseth God, and sheweth his brethren
what he had done.</head>

<ab n="1">Then the second
that had spoken of the strength of the King, began to say;</ab>
<ab n="2">O yee men, doe
not men excel in strength, that beare rule ouer Sea and land, and
all things in them?<note> Or, haue the command.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But yet the King
is more mighty: for hee is lord of all these things, and hath
dominion ouer them, and whatsoeuer he commandeth them, they
doe:</ab>
<ab n="4">If thee bid them
make warre the one against the other, they doe it: if hee send them
out against the enemies, they goe, and breake downe mountaines,
walles and towres.</ab>
<ab n="5">They slay and are
slaine, and transgresse not the Kings commandement: if they get the
victory, they bring all to the King, as well the spoile as all
things else.</ab>
<ab n="6">Likewise for
those that are no souldiers, and haue not to doe with warres, but
vse husbandrie; when they haue reaped againe, that which they had
sowen, they bring it to the King, and compell one another to pay
tribute vnto the King.</ab>
<ab n="7">And yet he is but
one man; if hee commaund to kill, they kill, if he command to
spare, they spare.</ab>
<ab n="8">If he command to
smite, they smite; if he command to make desolate, they make
desolate; if hee command to build, they build:</ab>
<ab n="9">If he command to
cut downe, they cut downe; if he command to plant, they
plant.</ab>
<ab n="10">So all his
people and his armies obey him; furthermore he lieth downe, he
eateth and drinketh, &amp; taketh his rest.</ab>
<ab n="11">And these keepe
(watch) round about him, neither may any one depart, and doe his
owne businesse, neither disobey they him in any thing.<note> Or, can.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">O yee men, how
should not the King be mightiest, when in such sort he is obeyed?
and he held his tongue.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then the
third, who had spoken of women, and of the truth (this was
Zorobabel) beganne to speake.</ab>
<ab n="14">O yee men, it is
not the great King, nor the multitude of men, neither is it wine
that excelleth; who is it then that ruleth them, or hath the
lordship ouer them, are they not women?<note> Heb. is of force.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Women haue borne
the King and all the people, that beare rule by sea and
land.</ab>
<ab n="16">Euen of thē
came they: &amp; they nourished them vp that planted the vineyards
from whence the wine commeth.</ab>
<ab n="17">These also make
garments for men; these bring glory vnto men, and without women
cannot men be.</ab>
<ab n="18">Yea and if men
haue gathered together gold and siluer, or any other goodly thing,
doe they not loue a woman, which is comely in fauour and
beautie?</ab>
<ab n="19">And letting all
those things goe, doe they not gape, and euen with open mouth fixe
their eyes fast on her; and haue not all men more desire vnto her,
then vnto siluer or gold, or any goodly thing whatsoeuer?</ab>
<ab n="20">A man leaueth
his owne father that brought him vp, and his owne countrie, and
cleaueth vnto his wife.</ab>
<ab n="21">He stickes not
to spend his life with his wife, and remembreth neither father, nor
mother, nor countrey.</ab>
<ab n="22">By this also you
must know, that women haue dominion ouer you: doe yee not labour
and toyle, and giue and bring all to the woman?</ab>
<ab n="23">Yea a man taketh
his sword, and goeth his way to rob, and to steale, to saile vpon
the sea, and vpon riuers,</ab>
<ab n="24">And looketh vpon
a lyon, and goeth in the darknesse, and when he hath stolen,
spoiled and robbed, he bringeth it to his loue.</ab>
<ab n="25">Wherefore a man
loueth his wife better then father and mother.</ab>
<ab n="26">Yea many there
be that haue run out of their wits for women, and become seruants
for their sakes:<note> Or, grouen desperate.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Many also haue
perished, haue erred, and sinned for women.</ab>
<ab n="28">And now doe yee
not belieue me? is not the King great in his power? doe not all
regions feare to touch him?</ab>
<ab n="29">Yet did I see
him and Apame the Kings concubine, the daughter of the admirable
Bartacus, sitting at the right hand of the King,<note> Ioseph. antiq. lib. 11. cap. 4. Rabsaces Themasius.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And taking the
crowne from the Kings head, and setting it vpon her owne head; she
also strooke the King with her left hand.</ab>
<ab n="31">And yet for all
this, the King gaped and gazed vpon her with open mouth: if she
laughed vpon him, hee laughed also: but if she tooke any
displeasure at him, the King was faine to flatter, that she might
be reconciled to him againe.<note> Or, heere at. , Or, be friends with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">O ye men, how
can it be but women should be strong, seeing they doe thus?</ab>
<ab n="33">Then the king
&amp; the princes looked one vpon another: so he began to speake of
the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="34">O ye men, are
not women strong? great is the earth, high is the heauen, swift is
the Sunne in his course, for he compasseth the heauens round about,
and fetcheth his course againe to his owne place in one
day.</ab>
<ab n="35">Is he not great
that maketh these things? therefore great is the truth, and
stronger then all things.</ab>
<ab n="36">All the earth
calleth vpon the truth, &amp; the heauen blesseth it, all works
shake and tremble at it, and with it is no vnrighteous
thing.<note> Or, praiseth the truth. Athanas.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Wine is wicked,
the king is wicked, women are wicked, all the children of men are
wicked, and such are all their wicked workes, and there is no
trueth in them. In their vnrighteousnes also they shall
perish.</ab>
<ab n="38">As for the
trueth it endureth, and is alwayes strong, it liueth and conquereth
for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="39">With her there
is no accepting of persons, or rewards, but she doeth the things
that are iust, and refraineth from all vniust and wicked things,
and all men doe well like of her workes.</ab>
<ab n="40">Neither in her
iudgement is any vnrighteousnesse, &amp; she is the strength,
kingdome, power and maiestie of all ages. Blessed be the God of
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="41">And with that he
held his peace, and al the people then shouted and said, Great is
trueth, and mightie aboue all things.</ab>
<ab n="42">Then saide the
king vnto him, Aske what thou wilt, more then is appointed in the
writing, and we wil giue it thee, because thou art found wisest,
and thou shalt sit next me, and shalt bee called my cousin.</ab>
<ab n="43">Then said hee
vnto the king, Remember thy vow which thou hast vowed to build
Ierusalem in the day when thou camest to the kingdome,</ab>
<ab n="44">And to send away
all the vessels that were taken away out of Ierusalem, which Cyrus
set apart, when hee vowed to destroy Babylon, and to send them
againe thither.</ab>
<ab n="45">Thou also hast
vowed to build vp the Temple, which the Edomites burnt when Iudea
was made desolate by the Chaldees.</ab>
<ab n="46">And now, O lord
the king, this is that which I require, and which I desire of thee,
and this is the princely liberalitie proceeding from thy selfe: I
desire therefore that thou make good the vow, the performance
wherof with thine owne mouth thou hast vowed to the king of
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then Darius the
king stood vp and kissed him, and wrote letters for him vnto all
the treasurers and lieutenants, and captaines and gouernours that
they should safely conuey on their way, both him, and all those
that go vp with him to build Ierusalem.</ab>

<fw>Anocrynha.</fw>
<ab n="48">Hee wrote
letters also vnto the lieutenants that were in Coelosyria and
Phenice, and vnto them in Libanus, that they should bring Cedar
wood from Libanus vnto Ierusalem, and that they should build the
city with him</ab>
<ab n="49">Moreouer he
wrote for all the Iewes that went out of his realme vp into Iurie,
concerning their freedome, that no officer, no ruler, no
lieutenant, nor treasurer, should forcibly enter into their
dores,<note> Or, steward.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">And that all the
countrey which they hold, should be free without tribute, &amp;
that the Edomites should giue ouer the villages of the Iewes which
then they held,</ab>
<ab n="51">Yea that there
should be yereely giuen twentie talents to þ<note/>
building of the Temple, vntill ye time that it were built,</ab>
<ab n="52">And other tenne
talents yeerely, to maintaine the burnt offerings vpon the Altar
euery day (as they had a commandement to offer seuenteene)</ab>
<ab n="53">And that all
they that went from Babylon to build the citie, should haue free
liberty as well they as their posteritie, and all the priests that
went away.</ab>
<ab n="54">He wrote also
concerning the charges, and the priests vestments wherein they
minister:</ab>
<ab n="55">And likewise for
the charges of the Leuites, to be giuen them, vntill the day that
the house were finished, and Ierusalem builded vp.</ab>
<ab n="56">And he commanded
to giue to all that kept the city, pensions and wages.<note> Or, portions of land.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">He sent away
also all the vessels frō Babylon that Cyrus had set apart, and
all that Cyrus had giuen in commandement, the same charged hee also
to be done, and sent vnto Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="58">Now when this
yong man was gone forth, he lifted vp his face to heauen toward
Ierusalem, and praised the king of heauen,</ab>
<ab n="59">And said, From
thee commeth victory, from thee commeth wisedom, and thine is the
glory, &amp; I am thy seruant.</ab>
<ab n="60">Blessed art thou
who hast giuen me wisedom: for to thee I giue thanks, O Lord of our
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="61">And so he tooke
the letters, and went out, and came vnto Babylon, and told it all
his brethren.</ab>
<ab n="62">And they praised
the God of their fathers: because he had giuen them freedome and
libertie</ab>
<ab n="63">To goe vp, and
to build Ierusalem, and the Temple which is called by his Name, and
they feasted with instruments of musick, &amp; gladnes seuen
dayes.</ab>



</div>