<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-3-3b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>4 Three striue to excell each other
in wise speaches. 9 They referre themselues to the iudgement of the
King. 18 The first declareth the strength of Wine.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when Darius
reigned, hee made a great feast vnto all his Subiects and vnto all
his houshold, and vnto all the princes of Media and Persia,</ab>
<ab n="2">And to all the
gouernours and captaines, and lieutenants that were vnder him, from
Iudia vnto Ethiopia, of an hundreth twenty and seuen
prouinces.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when they had
eaten and drunken, and being satisfied were gone home, then Darius
the king went into his bed chamber, and slept, and soone after
awaked.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then three yong
men that were of the guard, that kept the kings body, spake one to
another:</ab>
<ab n="5">Let euery one of
vs speake a sentence: hee that shall ouercome, &amp; whose sentence
shall seeme wiser then the others, vnto him shall the king Darius
giue great gifts, and great things in token of victory:</ab>
<ab n="6">As to be clothed
in purple, to drink in golde, and to sleepe vpon golde, and a
chariot with bridles of golde, and an head-tyre of fine linen, and
a chaine about his necke:</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee shall sit
next to Darius, because of his wisedome, and shalbe called, Darius
his cousin.</ab>
<ab n="8">And then euery
one wrote his sentence, sealed it, and laide it vnder king Darius
his pillow,</ab>
<ab n="9">And sayd, that
when the king is risen, some will giue him the writings, and of
whose side the king, and the three princes of Persia shall iudge,
that his sentence is the wisest, to him shall the victory be giuen
as was appointed.</ab>
<ab n="10">The first wrote:
Wine is the strongest.</ab>
<ab n="11">The second
wrote: The King is strongest.</ab>
<ab n="12">The third wrote;
Women are strongest, but aboue all things trueth beareth away the
victory.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Now when
the king was risen vp, they tooke their writings, and deliuered
them vnto him, and so hee read them.</ab>
<ab n="14">And sending
foorth, hee called all the Princes of Persia and Media, and the
gouernours, and the captaines, and the lieutenants, and the chiefe
officers,</ab>
<ab n="15">And sate him
downe in the royall seate of Iudgement, and the writings were read
before them:<note> Or, counsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And he said,
Call the young men, and they shall declare their owne sentences: so
they were called, and came in.</ab>
<ab n="17">And hee said
vnto them, Declare vnto vs your minde, concerning the writings.
Then began the first, who had spoken of the strength of
wine;</ab>
<ab n="18">And he said
thus: O ye men, how exceeding strong is wine! it causeth all men to
erre that drinke it:</ab>
<ab n="19">It maketh the
minde of the king, and of the fatherlesse childe to be all one of
the bondman and of the freeman, of the poore man and of the
rich:</ab>
<ab n="20">It turneth also
euery thought into iollitie and mirth, so that a man remembreth
neither sorow nor debt:</ab>
<ab n="21">And it maketh
euery heart rich, so that a man remembreth neither king nor
gouernour, and it maketh to speake all things by talents:</ab>
<ab n="22">And when they
are in their cups, they forget their loue both to friends and
brethren, and a litle after draw out swords:</ab>
<ab n="23">But when they
are from the wine, they remember not what they haue done.</ab>
<ab n="24">O ye men, is not
wine the strongest, that enforceth to doe thus? And when hee had so
spoken, hee helde his peace.</ab>



</div>