<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-5-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-5-5b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>4 The names and number of the Iewes
that returned home. 50 The Altar is set vp in his place. 57 The
foundation of the Temple is layd. 73 The worke is hindred for a
time.</head>

<ab n="1">After this were
the principall men of the families chosen according to their
tribes, to go vp with their wiues, and sonnes, and daughters, with
their men-seruants and maid-seruants, and their cattel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Darius sent
with them a thousand horsmen, til they had brought them backe to
Ierusalem safely, and with musicall [instruments,] tabrets and
flutes:</ab>
<ab n="3">And all their
brethren played, and hee made them goe vp together with
them.</ab>
<ab n="4">And these are the
names of the men which went vp, according to their families,
amongst their tribes, after their seuerall heads.</ab>
<ab n="5">The Priestes the
sonnes of Phinees, the sonne of Aaron: Iesus the sonne of Iosedec,
the sonne of Saraias, and Ioachim the sonne of Zorobabel, the sonne
of Salathiel of the house of Dauid, out of the kindred of Phares,
of the tribe of Iuda;<note> Ioachim and Zorobabel. This place is corrupt: For Ioachim was the sonne of Iosedech, Neh.12.10. and not Zorobabel, who was of the tribe of Iuda.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Who spake wise
sentences before Darius the king of Persia, in the second yeere of
his reigne, in the moneth Nisan, which is the first
moneth.<note> Zorobabel.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And these are
they of Iewrie that came vp from the captiuitie, where they dwelt
as strangers, whom Nabuchodonosor the king of Babylon had carried
away vnto Babylon:</ab>
<ab n="8">And they returned
vnto Ierusalem, and to the other parts of Iurie euery man to his
owne city, who came with Zorobabel, with Iesus, Nehemias, and
Zacharias, and Reesaias, Enenius, Mardocheus, Beelsarus,
Aspharasus, Reelius, Roimus, and Baana their guides.<note> Saraiah. , Or Mispar. , Or Reelaiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The number of
them of the nation, and their gouernours: sonnes of Phoros two
thousand an hundred seuentie and two: the sonnes of Saphat foure
hundred seuentie and two;<note> Parosh, Ezra 2. 3. Nehem.7. 9. where for breuity looke for the true numbers of the particulars following: for here they vary much, &amp; the names much more. , Shephatia. , Or, three hundred seuentie two.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The sonnes of
Ares seuen hundred fiftie and sixe:</ab>
<ab n="11">The sonnes of
Phaath Moab, two thousand eight hundred &amp; twelue:</ab>
<ab n="12">The sonnes of
Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and foure: the sonnes of Zathui,
nine hundred fourtie and fiue: the sonnes of Corbe seuen hundred
and fiue: the sonnes of Bani, sixe hundred fourtie and
eight:<note> Zattu. , Zacchai.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The sonnes of
Bebai, sixe hundred twentie and three: the sonnes of Sadas, three
thousand two hundred twentie and two:<note> Asgad.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The sonnes of
Adonican, sixe hundred sixtie and seuen: the sonnes of Bagoi, two
thousand sixtie and sixe: the sonnes of Adin, foure hundred fiftie
and foure:<note> Bigui.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The sonnes of
Aterezias, ninetie and two: the sonnes of Ceilan and Azetas,
threescore and seuen: the sonnes of Azuran, foure hundred thirtie
&amp; two.<note> Alerhezekia.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The sonnes of
Ananias, an hundred and one: the sonnes of Arom thirtie two, and
the sonnes of Bassa, three hundred twentie and three: the sonnes of
Azephurith, an hundred and two:<note> Besai.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The sonnes of
Meterus, three thousand and fiue: the sonnes of Bethlomon, an
hundred twentie and three.<note> Bethlehem.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">They of Netophah
fiftie and fiue: they of Anathoth, an hundred fiftie and eight:
they of Bethsamos, fourtie and two:<note> Asmaneth.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">They of
Kiriathiarius, twentie and fiue: they of Caphira and Beroth, seuen
hundred fourtie and three: they of Pyra, seuen hundred:<note> Kiriashiarim.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">They of Chadias
and Ammidioi, foure hundred twenty and two: they of Cyrama, and
Gabdes, sixe hundred twentie and one:<note> Rama. , Gabah.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">They of Macalon,
an hundred twentie and two: they of Betolius fiftie and two: the
sonnes of Nephis, an hundred fiftie and sixe.<note> Michmas. , Bethel. , Maghbis.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The sonnes of
Calamolalus, and Onus, seuen hundred twentie and fiue: the sonnes
of Ierechus, two hundred fourtie and fiue:<note> Lodhadid.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The sonnes of
Annaas, three thousand three hundred and thirtie:<note> Senaah.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The Priests, the
sonnes of Ieddu, the sonne of Iesus, among the sonnes of Sanasib,
nine hundred seuentie and two: the sonnes of Meruth, a thousand
fiftie and two:<note> Iedaiah. , Immar.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The sonnes of
Phassaron, a thousand fourtie and seuen: the sonnes of Carme a
thousand and seuenteene.<note> Pashur. , Harim. , Or, 217. according to some copies.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The Leuites: the
sonnes of Iessue, and Cadmiel, and Banuas, and Sudias, seuentie and
foure.<note> Thus it is read, Ezra 2.40. the sonnes of Ieshua, and Cadmeel, of the sonnes of Hodouiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">The holy
singers: the sonnes of Asaph an hundred twentie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="28">The porters: the
sonnes of Salum, the sonnes of Iatal, the sonnes of Talmon, the
sonnes of Dacobi, the sonnes of Teta, the sonnes of Sami, in all an
hundred thirty and nine.<note> Shallum. , Ater. , Akkub. , Hatita. , Shebai.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The seruants of
the Temple: the sonnes of Esau, the sonnes of Asipha, the sonnes of
Tabaoth, the sonnes of Ceras: the sonnes of Sud, the sonnes of
Phaleas, the sonnes of Labana, the sonnes of Graba:<note> Zich. , Hasupha. , Keros. , Siaha. , Padon. , Agabah.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The sonnes of
Acua, the sonnes of Uta, the sonnes of Cetab, the sons of Agaba,
the sonnes of Subai, the sonnes of Anan, the sonnes of Cathua, the
sonnes of Geddur:<note> Akkub. , Hagab. , Shamlai. , Giddes. , Gahar.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">The sonnes of
Airus, the sonnes of Daisan, the sonnes of Noeba, the sonnes of
Chaseba, the sonnes of Gazera, the sonnes of Azia, the sonnes of
Phinees, the sonnes of Azara, the sonnes of Bastai, the sonnes of
Asana the sonnes of Meani, the sonnes of Naphisi, the sonnes of
Acub, the sons of Asipha, the sonnes of Assur, the sonnes of
Pharacim, the sons of Basaloth.<note> Reaiah. , Rezin. , Necodah. , Gazam. , Huzza. , Pascah. , Besai. , Asnah. , Neumin. , Nephusin. , Bakbuk , Hacupa. , Harbur. , Bazluth.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">The sonnes of
Meeda: the sons of Coutha, the sonnes of Charea, the sonnes of
Chareus, the sonnes of Aserer, the sonnes of Thomoi, the sonnes of
Nasith, the sons of Atipha.<note> Mehida. , Harsha. , Barcos. , Sisera. , Thamai. , Neziah.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">The sons of the
seruants of Solomon: the sonnes of Azaphion, the sonnes of Pharira,
the sonnes of Ioeli, the sonnes of Lozon, the sonnes of Isdael, the
sonnes of Sapheth:<note> Sophereth. , Peruda. , Iaalah. , Darcon. , Goddet. , Shephatiah</note></ab>
<ab n="34">The sonnes of
Hagia, the sons of Phacareth, the sonnes of Sabie, the sonnes of
Sarothie, the sonnes of Masias, the sonnes of Gar, the sons of
Addus, the sonnes of Suba, the sonnes of Apherra, the sonnes of
Barodis, the sonnes of Sabat, the sonnes of Allom.<note> Hatte. , Phoceroth Hazzebaim, Ezra 2.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">All the
ministers of the Temple, and the sonnes of the seruants of Solomon,
were three hundred seuenty &amp; two.</ab>
<ab n="36">These came vp
from Thermeleth, and Thelersas, Charaathalar leading them and
Aalar.</ab>
<ab n="37">Neither could
they shewe their families, nor their stock, how they were of
Israel: the sonnes of Ladan, the sonnes of Ban, the sonnes of
Necodan, sixe hundred fiftie and two.<note> Delaiah. , Tobiah. , Necodah.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And of the
Priests that vsurped the office of the Priesthood, and were not
found, the sonnes of Obdia: the sonnes of Accoz, the sonnes of
Addus, who married Augia one of the daughters of Berzelus, and was
named after his name.<note> Hobaiah. , Cos. , Barzelai.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And when the
description of the kinred of these men was sought in the Register,
and was not found, they were remooued from executing the office of
the Priesthood.</ab>
<ab n="40">For vnto them
said Nehemias, and Atharias, that they should not be partakers of
the holy things, till there arose vp an high Priest, clothed with
Doctrine and Trueth.<note> Nehemias, who also is Acharias, two of one. Nehe.8.9. and 10.2. chap.2.63. , Heb. Vrim and Thummim.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">So of Israel
from them of twelue yeeres olde and vpward, they were all in number
fourtie thousand, besides men seruants and women seruants, two
thousand three hundred and sixtie.</ab>
<ab n="42">Their men
seruants and handmaids were seuen thousand three hundred fourtie
and seuen: the singing men and singing women, two hundred fortie
and fiue.<note> See Nehe. 7.66.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Foure hundred
thirtie and fiue camels, seuen thousand thirtie and sixe horses,
two hundred fourtie and fiue mules, fiue thousand fiue hundred
twentie &amp; fiue beasts vsed to the yoke.<note> Ezra 2.67. , Asses.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And certaine of
the chiefe of their families, when they came to the Temple of God
that is in Ierusalem, vowed to set vp the house againe in his owne
place according to their abilitie:</ab>
<ab n="45">And to giue into
the holy treasurie of the workes, a thousand pounds of golde, fiue
thousand of siluer, and an hundred priestly vestments.</ab>
<ab n="46">And so dwelt the
Priests, and the Leuites, and the people in Ierusalem, and in the
countrey: the Singers also, and the Porters, and all Israel in
their villages.</ab>
<ab n="47">But when the
seuenth moneth was at hand, and when the children of Israel were
euery man in his owne place, they came all together with one
consent into the open place of the first gate, which is towards the
East.<note> Or, before the East gate.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Then stood vp
Iesus the sonne of Iosedec, and his brethren the Priests, and
Zorobabel the sonne of Salathiel, and his brethren, and made ready
the Altar of the God of Israel,</ab>
<ab n="49">To offer burnt
sacrifices vpon it, according as it is expresly commanded in the
booke of Moses the man of God.</ab>
<ab n="50">And there were
gathered vnto them out of the other nations of the land, and they
erected the Altar vpon his owne place, because all the nations of
the land were at enmitie with them, and oppressed them, and they
offered sacrifices according to the time, and burnt offerings to
the Lord both morning, and euening.</ab>
<ab n="51">Also they held
the feast of Tabernacles, as it is commanded in the law, and
offered sacrifices daily as was meet:</ab>
<ab n="52">And after, that
the continuall oblations, and the sacrifice of the Sabbaths, and of
the new Moones, and of all holy feasts.<note> Or, daily sacrifice.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">And all they
that had made any vow to God, beganne to offer sacrifices to God
from the first day of the seuenth moneth, although the Temple of
the Lord was not yet built.<note> Grek. halowed.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">And they gaue
vnto the Masons and Carpenters, money, meate and drinke with
cheerefulnesse.</ab>
<ab n="55">Unto them of
Sidon also and Tyre, they gaue carres that they should bring Cedar
trees from Libanus, which should bee brought by flotes to the hauen
of Ioppe, according as it was commanded them by Cyrus King of the
Persians.</ab>
<ab n="56">And in the
second yeere and second moneth, after his comming to the Temple of
God at Ierusalem, beganne Zorobabel the sonne of Salathiel, and
Iesus the sonne of Iosedec, and their brethren and the priests, and
the Leuites, and all they that were come vnto Ierusalem out of the
captiuity:</ab>
<ab n="57">And they layd
the foundation of the house of God, in the first day of the second
moneth, in the second yeere after they were come to Iury &amp;
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="58">And they
appointed the Lenites from twenty yeeres old, ouer the workes of
the Lord. Then stood vp Iesus and his sonnes, and brethren, and
Cadmiel his brother, &amp; the sonnes of Madiabun, with the sonnes
of Ioda the sonne of Eliadun, with their sonnes and brethren, all
Leuites, with one accord seters forward of the businesse, labouring
to aduance the workes in the house of God. So the workmen built the
temple of the Lord.<note> See Ezra 3.9. , Or, ouerseers or encouragers of them that wrought in the house of the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">And the Priests
stood arayed in their vestiments with musicall instruments, and
trumpets, and the Leuites the sonnes of Asaph had Cymbals,</ab>
<ab n="60">Singing songs of
thanksgiuing, and praising the Lord according as Dauid the king of
Israel had ordained.<note> Or, after the maner of Dauid king of Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="61">And they sung
with loud voices songs to the praise of the Lord: because his mercy
and glory is for euer in all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="62">And all the
people sounded trumpets, and shouted with a loud voyce, singing
songs of thankesgiuing vnto the Lord for the rearing vp of the
house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="63">Also of the
Priests and Leuites, and of the chiefe of their families the
ancients who had seene the former house, came to the building of
this with weeping and great crying.<note> Ezra 3.12 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">But many with
trumpets and ioy shouted with loud voyce.</ab>
<ab n="65">Insomuch that
the trumpets might not be heard for the weeping of the people: yet
the multitude sounded marueilously, so that it was heard a farre
off.<note> Or, discerned.</note></ab>
<ab n="66">Wherefore when
the enemies of the Tribe of Iuda and Beniamin heard it, they came
to know what that noise of trumpets should meane.</ab>
<ab n="67">And they
perceiued, that they that were of the captiuity did build the
temple vnto the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="68">So they went to
Zorobabel and Iesus, and to the chiefe of the families, and said
vnto them, We will build together with you.</ab>
<ab n="69">For we likewise,
as you, doe obey your Lord, and doe sacrifice vnto him from the
dayes of Asbazareth the king of the Assyrians who brought vs
hither<note> Asar-haddon, chap. 4.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="70">Then Zorobabel
and Iesus, and the chiefe of the families of Israel said vnto them,
It is not for vs and you to build together an house vnto the Lord
our God.</ab>
<ab n="71">We our selues
alone will build vnto the Lord of Israel, according as Cyrus the
King of the Persians hath commanded vs.</ab>
<ab n="72">But the heathen
of the land lying heauy vpon the inhabitants of Iudea, and holding
them straite, hindred their building:</ab>
<ab n="73">And by their
secret plots, and popular perswasions, and commotions, they hindred
the finishing of the building, all the time that king Cyrus liued,
so they were hindered from building for the space of two yeeres,
vntill the reigne of Darius.<note> Vntill the second yeere of Darius. Ezra 4.5, 6, 7.</note></ab>



</div>