<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-9-9b-2-Esdras.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>3 Esdras assembleth all the people.
10 They promise to put away the strange wiues. 20 The names and
number of them that did so. 40 The Law of Moses is read and
declared before all the people. 49 They weepe, and are put in mind
of the Feast day.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Esdras
rising from the court of the Temple, went to the chamber of Ioanan
the sonne of Eliasib,</ab>
<ab n="2">And remained
there, and did eate no meate nor drinke water, mourning for the
great iniquities of the multitude.</ab>
<ab n="3">And there was a
proclamation in all Iury and Ierusalem, to all them that were of
the captiuitie, that they should be gathered together at
Ierusalem:</ab>
<ab n="4">And that
whosoeuer met not there within two or three dayes according as the
Elders that bare rule, appointed, their cattell should be seized to
the vse of the Temple, and himselfe cast out from them that were of
the captiuitie.<note> Vtterly destroyed, Iosh.10.8</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And in three
dayes were all they of the tribe of Iuda and Beniamin gathered
together at Ierusalem the twentieth day of the ninth
moneth.</ab>
<ab n="6">And all the
multitude sate trembling in the broad court of the Temple, because
of the present foule weather.</ab>
<ab n="7">So Esdras arose
vp, and said vnto them, Ye haue transgressed the law in marrying
strange wiues, thereby to increase the sinnes of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">And now by
confessing giue glory vnto the Lord God of our fathers,</ab>
<ab n="9">And doe his will,
and separate your selues from the heathen of the land, and from the
strange women.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then cryed the
whole multitude, and sayd with a loude voice; Like as thou hast
spoken, so will we doe.</ab>
<ab n="11">But forasmuch as
the people are many, and it is foule weather, so that wee cannot
stand without, and this is not a worke of a day or two, seeing our
sinne in these things is spread farre:</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore let
the rulers of the multitude stay, and let all them of our
habitations that haue strange wiues, come at the time
appointed,<note> Or, stand.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And with them
the Rulers and Iudges of euery place, till we turne away the wrath
of the Lord from vs, for this matter.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then Ionathan
the sonne of Azael, and Ezechias the sonne of Theocanus,
accordingly tooke this matter vpon them: and Mosollam, and Leuis,
and Sabbatheus helped them.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they that
were of the captiutie, did according to all these things.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Esdras the
Priest chose vnto him the principal men of their families, all by
name: and in the first day of the tenth moneth, they sate together
to examine the matter.</ab>
<ab n="17">So their cause
that helde strange wiues, was brought to an ende in the first day
of the first moneth.</ab>
<ab n="18">And of the
Priests that were come together, and had strange wiues, there were
found:</ab>
<ab n="19">Of the sonnes of
Iesus the sonne of Iosedec, and his brethren, Matthelas, and
Eleazar, and Ioribus, and Ioadanus.<note> Maasias. , Iarib. , Gedaliah.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And they gaue
their hands to put away their wiues, &amp; to offer rammes, to make
reconcilement for their errors.<note> Hebr. a ramme. , Or, purification.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And of the
sonnes of Emmer, Ananias, and Zabdeus, and Eanes, and Sameius, and
Hierel, and Azarias.<note> Harim. , Maasiah. , Iehiel. , Vzziah.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And of the
sonnes of Phaisur, Ellionas, Massias, Ismael, and Nathanael, and
Oridelus, and Talsas.<note> Pashur. , Iosabad. , Elasah.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And of the
Leuites: Iosabad, and Semis, and Colius who was called Calitas, and
Patheus, and Iudas, and Ionas.<note> Kelaiah. , Kelitah. , Pethahiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Of the holy
Singers: Eleazurus, Bacchurus.<note> Eliashib.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Of the Porters:
Sallumus, and Tolbanes.<note> Telem.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Of them of
Israel, of the sonnes of Phoros, Hiermas, and Eddias, and Melchias,
and Maelus, and Eleazar, and Asibias, and Baanias.<note> Parosh. , Ramiah. , Iesaiah. , Miamin. , Malchuah.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Of the sonnes of
Ela, Matthanias, Zacharias, and Hierielus, and Hieremoth, and
Aedias.<note> Iehiel. , Abdi.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And of the
sonnes of Zamoth, Eliadas, Elisimus, Othonias, Iarimoth, and
Sabatus, and Sardeus.<note> Zattu. , Elioenai. , Eliashib. , Mattaniah. , Sabad. , Aziza.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Of the sonnes of
Bebai, Iohannes, and Ananias, and Iosabad, and
Amatheis.<note> Zabbai. , Athlai.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Of the sonnes of
Many, Olamus, Mamuchus, Iedeus, Iasubus, Iasael, and
Hieremoth.<note> Bani. , Meshullam , Malluch. , Adaiah. , Sheal.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And of the
sonnes of Addi, Naathus, and Moosias, Lacunus, and Naidus, and
Mathanias, and Sesthel, Balunus, and Manasseas.<note> Of the names in vers. 31, 32, 34, 35, See Ezr.10.30, 31.34, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And of the
sonnes of Annas, Elionas, and Aseas, and Milchias, and Sabbeus, and
Simon Chosameus.</ab>
<ab n="33">And of the
sonnes of Asom, Altaneus, and Matthias, and Bannaia, Eliphalat, and
Manasses, and Semei.<note> Mattenai. , Mattithiah , Zabad.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And of the
sonnes of Maani, Ieremias, Momdis, Omaerus, Iuel, Mabdai, and
Pelias, and Anos, Carabasion, and Enasibus, &amp; Mamnitanaimus,
Eliasis, Bannus, Eliali, Samis, Selenias, Nathanias: And of the
sons of Ozora, Sesis, Esril, Azailus, Samatus, Zambis,
Iosiphus,</ab>
<ab n="35">And of the
sonnes of Ethma, Mazitias, Zabadaias, Edes, Iuel, Banaias.</ab>
<ab n="36">All these had
taken strange wiues, and they put them away with their
children.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the priests,
and Leuites, and they that were of Israel dwelt in Ierusalem, and
in the countrey, in the first day of þe seuenth
month: so the children of Israel were in their
habitations.<note> Or, villages.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And the whole
multitude came together with one accord, into the broad place of
the holy porch toward the East.<note> Nehe.8.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And they spake
vnto Esdras the priest and reader, that he would bring the law of
Moses, that was giuen of the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="40">So Esdras the
chiefe priest, brought the law vnto the whole multitude from man to
woman, and to all the priests, to heare the law in the first day of
the seuenth moneth.</ab>
<ab n="41">And hee read in
the broad court before the holy porch from morning vnto midday,
before both men and women; and all the multitude gaue heed vnto the
law.</ab>
<ab n="42">And Esdras the
priest, and reader of the law stood vp, vpon a pulpit of wood which
was made for that purpose.</ab>
<ab n="43">And there stood
vp by him Matathias, Sammus, Ananias, Azarias, Urias, Ezecias,
Balasamus, vpon the right hand.<note> Or, Hilkiah. , Or, Maasiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And vpon his
left hand stood Phaldaius, Misael, Melchias, Lothasubus and
Nabarias.<note> Or, Pedaiah. , Or, Hashum. , See Nehem.8.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Then tooke
Esdras the booke of the law before the multitude: for he sate
honourably in the first place in the sight of them all.<note> Heb. aboue them all.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And when hee
opened the law, they stood all streight vp. So Esdras blessed the
Lord God most high, the God of hostes Almighty.</ab>
<ab n="47">And all the
people answered Amen, and lifting vp their hands they fell to the
ground, &amp; worshipped the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="48">Also Iesus,
Anus, Sarabias, Adinus, Iacubus, Sabateus, Auteas, Maianeas, and
Calitas, Azarias, and Ioazabdus, and Ananias, Biatas, the Leuites
taught the law of the Lord, making them withall to vnderstand
it.<note> Or, Hodiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">Then spake
Attharates vnto Esdras the chiefe priest, and reader, and to the
Leuites that taught the multitude, euen to all, saying,<note> Then Nehemiah and Ezra the priest and Scribe, and the Leuites that instructed the people. said vnto all the people. Nehem. 8.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">This day is holy
vnto þe Lord; for they all wept when they heard the
law.</ab>
<ab n="51">Goe then and
eate the fat, and drinke the sweet, and send part to them that haue
nothing.<note> Or, the poore.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">For this day is
holy vnto the Lord, and be not sorrowfull; for the Lord will bring
you to honour.</ab>
<ab n="53">So the Leuites
published all things to the people, saying: This day is holy to the
Lord, be not sorrowfull.</ab>
<ab n="54">Then went they
their way, euery one to eate and drinke, &amp; make mery, and to
giue part to them that had nothing, and to make great
cheere,</ab>
<ab n="55">Because they
vnderstood the words wherein they were instructed, and for
þe which they had bin assembled.</ab>



</div>