<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Sisinnes and others, helpe forward
the building. 5 The Temple is finished, and dedicated. 10 The
Passeouer is kept.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Sisinnes the
gouernour of Coelosyria, and Phenice, and Sathrabuzanes, with their
companions, following the commandements of king Darius,<note> Ezra 6. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Did very
carefully ouersee the holy workes, assisting the ancients of the
Iewes, &amp; gouernours of the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="3">And so the holy
workes prospered, when Aggeus, and Zacharias the Prophets
prophecied.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they finished
these things, by the commandement of the Lord God of Israel, and
with the consent of Cyrus, Darius, and Artaxerxes, kings of
Persia.<note> Or, the decree.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And thus was the
holy house finished, in the three and twentieth day of the moneth
Adar, in the sixt yeere of Darius king of the Persians.<note> Hebr. the third day, Ezra 6.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the children
of Israel: the Priests, and the Leuites, and other that were of the
captiuitie, that were added vnto them, did according to the things
written in the booke of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="7">And to the
dedication of the Temple of the Lord, they offered an hundred
bullockes, two hundred rammes, foure hundred lambes;</ab>
<ab n="8">And twelue goats
for the sinne of all Israel, according to the number of the chiefe
of the tribes of Israel.<note> Or, tribes.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The Priests also
and the Leuites, stood arayed in their vestments according to their
kinreds, in the seruices of the Lord God of Israel, according to
the booke of Moses: and the porters at euery gate.<note> Hebr. diuisions, Esdr. 6.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the children
of Israel that were of the captiuitie, held the Passeouer the
fourteenth day of the first moueth, after that the Priests and the
Leuites were sanctified.<note> Or, with those that, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They that were
of the captiuitie were not all sanctified together: but the Leuites
were all sanctified together,</ab>
<ab n="12">And so they
offered the Passeouer for all them of the captiuitie, and for their
brethren the Priestes, and for themselues.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the children
of Israel that came out of the captiuitie, did eate, euen all they
that had separated themselues from the abominations of the people
of the land, and sought the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they kept
the feast of vnleauened bread seuen dayes, making mercy before the
Lord,</ab>
<ab n="15">For that he had
turned the counsell of the King of Assyria towards them to
strengthen their hands in the workes of the Lord God of
Israel.<note> Or, mind.</note></ab>



</div>