<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-1-1b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Iosias his charge to the Priests
and Leuites. 7 A great Passeouer is kept. 32 His death is much
lamented: 34 His Successours. 53 The Temple, Citie, and people are
destroyed. 56 The rest are caried vnto Babylon.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iosias helde
the Feast of the Passeouer in Ierusalem vnto his Lord, and offered
the Passeouer the fourteenth day of the first moneth:<note> 2.King.23. 22. 2.chro. 35.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Hauing set the
Priests according to their daily courses, being arayed in long
garments, in the Temple of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hee spake
vnto the Leuites the holy ministers of Israel, that they should
hallow themselues vnto the Lord, to set the holy Arke of the Lord,
in the house that king Solomon the sonne of Dauid had
built:</ab>
<ab n="4">And said, Ye
shall no more beare the Arke vpon your shoulders: now therefore
serue the Lord your God, and minister vnto his people Israel, and
prepare you after your families and kinreds.</ab>
<ab n="5">According as
Dauid the king of Israel prescribed, &amp; according to the
magnificence of Solomon his sonne: &amp; standing in the Temple
according to the seuerall dignitie of the families of you the
Leuites, who minister in the presence of your brethren the children
of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="6">Offer the
Passeouer in order, and make ready the sacrifices for your
brethren, and keepe the Passeouer according to the commaundement of
the Lord, which was giuen vnto Moyses.</ab>
<ab n="7">And vnto the
people that was found there, Iosias gaue thirtie thousand lambes,
and kids, and three thousand calues: these things were giuen of the
kings allowance, according as hee promised to the people, to the
Priestes, and to the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Helkias,
Zacharias, and Sielus the gouernours of the Temple, gaue to the
Priests for the Passeouer, two thousand and sixe hundred sheepe,
and three hundreth calues.<note> Or, Iehiel.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Iechonias,
and Samaias, and Nathanael his brother, and Assabias, and Ochiel,
and Ioram captaines ouer thousands, gaue to the Leuites for the
Passeouer fiue thousand sheepe, and seuen hundreth
calues.<note> Fiue hundred calues, 2.chro.35.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And when these
things were done, the Priests and Leuites hauing the vnleauened
bread, stood in very comely order according to the kinreds,</ab>
<ab n="11">And according to
the seuerall dignities of the fathers, before the people, to offer
to the Lord, as it is written in the booke of Moyses: And thus did
they in the morning.<note> 2. Chron. 35.12. And so of the bullockes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they rosted
the Passeouer with fire, as appertaineth: as for the sacrifices,
they sodde them in brasse pots, and pannes with a good
sauour.<note> With good speed, or willingly, 2. chron.35. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And set them
before all the people, and afterward they prepared for themselues,
and for the Priests their brethren the sonnes of Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="14">For the Priests
offered the fat vntill night: and the Leuites prepared for
themselues, and the Priests their brethren the sonnes of
Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="15">The holy Singers
also, the sonnes of Asaph, were in their order, according to the
appointment of Dauid, to wit, Asaph, Zacharias, and Ieduthun, who
was of the kings retinue.<note> 2.Chron. 35.15. of Dauid and Asaph. , 2. Chro. 35.15. the kings seer.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Moreouer the
porters were at euery gate: it was not lawfull for any to goe from
his ordinary seruice: for their brethren the Leuites prepared for
them.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thus were the
things that belonged to the sacrifices of the Lord accomplished in
that day, that they might hold the Passeouer,</ab>
<ab n="18">And offer
sacrifices vpon the altar of the Lord, according to the
commandement of king Iosias.</ab>
<ab n="19">So the children
of Israel which were present, held the Passeouer at that time, and
the feast of sweet bread seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="20">And such a
Passeouer was not kept in Israel since the time of the Prophet
Samuel.</ab>
<ab n="21">Yea all the
kings of Israel held not such a Passeouer as Iosias, and the
Priests and the Leuites, &amp; the Iewes held with all Israel that
were found dwelling at Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="22">In the
eighteenth yeere of the reigne of Iosias was this Passeouer
kept.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the workes
of Iosias were vpright before his Lord with an heart full of
godlinesse.</ab>
<ab n="24">As for the
things that came to passe in his time, they were written in former
times, concerning those that sinned, and did wickedly against the
Lord aboue all people and kingdomes, and how they grieued him
exceedingly, so that the words of the Lord rose vp against
Israel.<note> Or, were vngodly. , Or, sensibly.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Now after all
these acts of Iosias, it came to passe that Pharao the king of
Egypt came to raise warre at Carchamis vpon Euphrates: and Iosias
went out against him.<note> 2.Chron. 35.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But the king of
Egypt sent to him saying, What haue I to doe with thee, O king of
Iudea?</ab>
<ab n="27">I am not sent
out from the Lord God against thee: for my warre is vpon Euphrates,
and now the Lord is with mee, yea the Lord is with mee hasting me
forward: Depart from me and be not against the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="28">Howbeit Iosias
did not turne backe his chariot from him, but vndertooke to fight
with him, not regarding the words of the Prophet Ieremie, spoken by
the mouth of the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="29">But ioyned
battell with him in the plaine of Magiddo, and the princes came
against king Iosias.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then said the
king vnto his seruants, carry me away out of the battell for I am
very weake: and immediately his seruants tooke him away out of the
battell.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then gate he vp
vpon his second chariot, and being brought backe to Ierusalem,
dyed, and was buried in his fathers sepulchre.</ab>
<ab n="32">And in all Iury
they mourned for Iosias, yea Ieremie the Prophet lamented for
Iosias, and the cheefe men with the women made lamentation for him
vnto this day: and this was giuen out for an ordinance to be done
continually in all the nation of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="33">These things are
written in the booke of the stories of the kings of Iudah, and
euery one of the acts that Iosias did, and his glory, and his
vnderstanding in the law of the Lord, and the things that he had
done before, and the things now recited, are reported in the bookes
of the Kings of Israel and Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the people
tooke Ioachaz the sonne of Iosias, and made him king in stead of
Iosias his father, when hee was twentie and three yeeres
old.<note> 2.King. 23.30. 2. chron. 36.1</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And he reigned
in Iudea and in Ierusalem three moneths: and then the King of Egypt
deposed him from reigning in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he set a
taxe vpon the land of an hundreth talents of siluer, and one talent
of gold.</ab>
<ab n="37">The king of
Egypt also made king Ioacim his brother king of Iudea and
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="38">And hee bound
Ioacim and the nobles: but Zaraces his brother he apprehended, and
brought him out of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="39">Fiue and twentie
yeere old was Ioacim when he was made king in the land of Iudea and
Ierusalem, and he did euill before the Lord.<note> 2. Chro. 36.45. Iehoiakim, or Eliakim.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Wherefore
against him Nabuchodonosor the King of Babylon came vp, and bound
him with a chaine of brasse, and carried him vnto Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="41">Nabuchodonosor
also tooke of the holy vessels of the Lord, and carried them away,
and set them in his owne temple at Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="42">But those things
that are recorded of him, and of his vncleannes, and impietie, are
written in the Chronicles of the kings.</ab>
<ab n="43">And Ioacim his
sonne reigned in his stead: he was made king being eighteene yeeres
old,</ab>
<ab n="44">And reigned but
three moneths and ten dayes in Ierusalem, and did euill before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="45">So after a yere
Nabuchodonosor sent, and caused him to be brought into Babylon with
þ<note/> holy vessels of þ<note/> Lord,</ab>
<ab n="46">And made
Zedechias king of Iudea and Ierusalem, when he was one and twentie
yeeres old, and he reigned eleuen yeeres:</ab>
<ab n="47">And he did euill
also in the sight of the Lord, &amp; cared not for the words that
were spoken vnto him, by the Prophet Ieremie from the mouth of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="48">And after that
king Nabuchodonosor had made him to sweare by the Name of the Lord,
he forswore himselfe, and rebelled, and hardening his necke, and
his heart, hee transgressed the lawes of the Lord God of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="49">The gouernours
also of the people and of the priests did many things against the
lawes, and passed al the pollutions of all nations, and defiled the
Temple of the Lord which was sanctified in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="50">Neuerthelesse,
the God of their fathers sent by his messenger to call them backe,
because he spared them and his tabernacle also:</ab>
<ab n="51">But they had his
messengers in derision, and looke when the Lorde spake vnto them,
they made a sport of his prophets,</ab>
<ab n="52">So farre foorth
that he being wroth with his people for their great vngodlinesse,
commanded the kings of the Caldees to come vp against them.</ab>
<ab n="53">Who flew their
yong men with the sword, yea euen within the compasse of their holy
Temple, &amp; spared neither yong man nor maid, old man nor child
among them, for hee deliuered all into their hands.</ab>
<ab n="54">And they tooke
all the holy vessels of the Lord, both great and small, with the
vessels of the Ark of God, and the kings treasures, and caried them
away into Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="55">As for the house
of the Lord they burnt it, brake downe the walles of Ierusalem, set
fire vpon her towres.</ab>
<ab n="56">And as for her
glorious things, they neuer ceased til they had consumed and
brought them all to nought, and the people that were not slaine
with the sword, he caried vnto Babylon:</ab>
<ab n="57">Who became
seruants to him and his children, till the Persians reigned, to
fulfill the word of the Lord spoken by the mouth of
Ieremie:<note> Ier.25.11 and 29.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">Untill the land
had enioyed her Sabbaths, the whole time of her desolation shal she
rest, vntill the full terme of seuentie yeeres.<note> Or, Keepe Sabbath.</note></ab>



</div>