<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Cyrus is moued by God to build the
Temple, 5 And giueth leaue to the Iewes to returne &amp; contribute
to it. 11 He deliuereth againe the vessels which had bin taken
thence. 25 Artaxerxes forbiddeth the Iewes to build any
more.</head>

<ab n="1">In the first
yeere of Cyrus king of the Persians, that the worde of the Lorde
might bee accomplished, that hee had promised by the mouth of
Ieremie:<note> 2.Chron. 36.22. ezra 1.1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord raised
vp the spirit of Cyrus the king of the Persians, and he made
proclamation thorow al his kingdome, and also by writing,</ab>
<ab n="3">Saying, Thus
saith Cyrus king of the Persians, The Lord of Israel the most high
Lord, hath made me king of the whole world,</ab>
<ab n="4">And commanded me
to build him an house at Ierusalem in Iurie.</ab>
<ab n="5">If therefore
there bee any of you that are of his people, let the Lord, euen his
Lord be with him, and let him goe vp to Ierusalem that is in Iudea,
and build the house of the Lord of Israel: for he is the Lord that
dwelleth in Ierusalem.<note> Or, this.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Whosoeuer then
dwell in the places about, let them helpe him, those I say that are
his neighbours, with gold and with siluer,</ab>
<ab n="7">With gifts, with
horses, and with cattell, and other things, which haue bene set
forth by vowe, for the Temple of the Lord at Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then the
chiefe of the families of Iudea, and of the tribes of Beniamin
stood vp: the priests also and the Leuites, and all they whose
minde the Lord had moued to goe vp, and to build an house for the
Lord at Ierusalem,</ab>
<ab n="9">And they that
dwelt round about them, and helped them in all things with siluer
and gold, with horses and cattell, and with very free gifts of a
great number whose mindes were stirred vp thereto.<note> Hebr. substance, Ezr. 1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">King Cyrus also
brought foorth the holy vessels which Nabuchodonosor had caried
away from Ierusalem, and had set vp in his temple of
idoles.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now when Cyrus
king of the Persians had brought them foorth, hee deliuered them to
Mithridates his treasurer:</ab>
<ab n="12">And by him they
were deliuered to Sanabassar þe gouernour of
Iudea.<note> Shash-bazar. Greek the first part of the word is corruptly ioyned to the word going before, Ezra 1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And this was the
number of them, a thousand golden cuppes, and a thousand of siluer,
censers of siluer twentie nine, vials of gold thirtie, and of
siluer two thousand foure hundred and ten, and a thousand other
vessels.<note> Hebr. kniues, Ezra 1.9. , Ezra.1. 10. but foure hundred and ten.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">So all the
vessels of gold, and of siluer which were caried away, were fiue
thousand, foure hundred, threescore and nine.<note> Ezra.1. 11. but fiue thousand foure hundred.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">These were
brought back by Sanabassar, together with them of the captiuity,
from Babylon to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="16">But in the time
of Artaxerxes king of the Persians, Belemus, and Mithridates, and
Tabellius, and Rathumus, and Beeltethmus, and Semellius the
Secretarie, with others that were in commission with them, dwelling
in Samaria and other places, wrote vnto him against them that dwelt
in Iudea and Ierusalem, these letters following.<note> Ezra 4.6. , Bahumus and the name which followeth, is but an epithete to the former, Ezra 4.9. , Shimshai, Ezra 4.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">To King
Artaxerxes our lord, Thy seruants Rathumus the story writer, and
Semellius the scribe, and the rest of their counsell, and the
Iudges that are in Coelosyria and Phenice.</ab>
<ab n="18">Be it now knowen
to the lord the king, that the Iewes that are come vp from you to
vs, being come into Ierusalem (that rebellious and wicked citie,)
doe build the market places, and repaire the walles of it, and doe
lay the foundation of the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now if this
citie, and the walles thereof be made vp againe, they will not
onely refuse to giue tribute, but also rebell against
kings.</ab>
<ab n="20">And forasmuch as
the things pertaining to the Temple, are now in hand, we thinke it
meete not to neglect such a matter,</ab>
<ab n="21">But to speake
vnto our lord the king, to the intent that if it be thy pleasure,
it may be sought out in the bookes of thy fathers:</ab>
<ab n="22">And thou shalt
finde in the Chronicles, what is written concerning these things,
and shalt vnderstand that that citie was rebellious, troubling both
kings and cities:</ab>
<ab n="23">And that the
Iewes were rebellious, and raised alwayes warres therin, for the
which cause euen this citie was made desolate.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore now
wee doe declare vnto thee, (O lord the king) that if this citie bee
built againe, and the walles thereof set vp anew, thou shalt from
hencefoorth haue no passage into Corlosyria and Phenice.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then the King
wrote backe againe to Rathumus the storie-writer, to Beeltethmus,
to Semellius the scribe, and to the rest that were in commission,
and dwellers in Samaria and Syria, and Phenice, after this
maner.</ab>
<ab n="26">I haue read the
Epistle which ye haue sent vnto mee: therefore I commanded to make
diligent search, and it hath bene found, that that city was from
the beginning practising against Kings.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the men
therein were giuen to rebellion, and warre, and that mightie Kings
and fierce were in Ierusalem, who reigned and exacted tributes in
Coelosyria and Phenice.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now therefore I
haue commanded to hinder those men from building the citie, and
heed to be taken that there be no more done in it,</ab>
<ab n="29">And that those
wicked workers proceed no further to the annoyance of
Kings.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then king
Artaxerxes his letters being read, Rathumus and Semellius the
scribe, and the rest that were in commission with them, remoouing
in hast towards Ierusalem with a troupe of horsemen, and a
multitude of people in battell aray, began to hinder the builders,
and the building of the Temple in Ierusalem ceased vntill the
second yeere of the reigne of Darius King of the
Persians.<note> Or, a great number of souldiers.</note></ab>



</div>