<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-8-8b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Esdras bringeth the Kings
Commission to build. 8 The copy of it. 28 He declareth the names
and number of those that came with him: 61 And his iourney. 71 Hee
lamenteth the sinnes of his people, 96 And sweareth the Priestes to
put away their strange wiues.</head>

<ab n="1">And after these
things, when Artaxerxes the king of the Persians reigned, came
Esdras the sonne of Saraias, the sonne of Ezerias, the sonne of
Helchiah, the sonne of Salum,<note> Azarias.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The sonne of
Sadduc, the sonne of Achitob, the sonne of Amarias, the sonne of
Ozias, the sonne of Memeroth, the sonne of Zaraias, the sonne of
Sauias, the sonne of Boccas, the sonne of Abisum, the sonne of
Phinees, the sonne of Eleasar, the sonne of Aaron the chiefe
Priest.<note> Azarias. , Meraioth. , Vzzi. Some copies want these three names. , Heb. was first, Ezra 7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">This Esdras went
vp from Babylon, as a Scribe being very ready in the Law of Moyses,
that was giuen by the God of Israel,</ab>
<ab n="4">And the king did
him honour: for he found grace in his sight in all his
requests.</ab>
<ab n="5">There went vp
with him also certaine of the children of Israel, of the Priests,
of the Leuites, of the holy Singers, Porters, and Ministers of the
Temple, vnto Ierusalem,<note> Nethinims.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In the seuenth
yere of the reigne of king Artaxerxes, in the fifth moneth, (this
was the kings seuenth yeere) for they went from Babylon in the
first day of the first moneth, and came to Ierusalem, according to
the prosperous iourney which the Lord gaue them.<note> See Ezra 7.7, 8, 9. , Or, successe</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For Esdras had
very great skill, so that he omitted nothing of the Law and
Commaundements of the Lord, but taught all Israel the Ordinances
and Iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now the copy of
the Commission which was written from Artaxerxes the King, and came
to Esdras the priest and reader of the Law of the Lord, is this
that followeth.<note> Or, decree.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">King Artaxerxes
vnto Esdras the Priest and reader of the Law of the Lord, sendeth
greeting.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hauing
determined to deale graciously, I haue giuen order, that such of
the nation of the Iewes, and of the Priests and Leuites being
within our Realme, as are willing and desirous, should goe with
thee vnto Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="11">As many
therefore as haue a minde thereunto, let them depart with thee, as
it hath seemed good both to me, &amp; my seuen friends the
counsellors,</ab>
<ab n="12">That they may
looke vnto the affaires of Iudea and Ierusalem, agreeably to that
which is in the Law of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And cary the
gifts vnto the Lord of Israel to Ierusalem, which I and my friends
haue vowed, and all the golde and siluer that in the countrey of
Babylon can be found, to the Lord in Ierusalem,<note> Or, goe.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">With that also
which is giuen of the people, for the Temple of the Lord their God
at Ierusalem: and that siluer and golde may be collected for
bullocks, rammes and lambes, and things thereunto
appertaining,</ab>
<ab n="15">To the end that
they may offer sacrifices vnto the Lord, vpon the Altar of the Lord
their God, which is in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="16">And whatsoeuer
thou and thy brethren will doe with the siluer and golde, that doe
according to the will of thy God.<note> With the rest of, Ezra 7.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the holy
vessels of the Lord which are giuen thee, for the vse of the Temple
of thy God which is in Ierusalem, thou shalt set before thy God in
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="18">And whatsoeuer
thing else thou shalt remember for the vse of the Temple of thy
God, thou shalt giue it out of the kings treasury.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I, king
Artaxerxes, haue also commaunded the keepers of the treasures in
Syria and Phenice, that whatsoeuer Esdras the priest, and the
reader of the law of the most high God shall send for, they should
giue it him with speed,</ab>
<ab n="20">To the summe of
an hundred talents of siluer: likewise also of wheat euen to an
hundred cores, and an hundred pieces of wine, and other things in
abundance.<note> Or, measures or salt, Ezra 7.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Let all things
be performed after the law of God diligently vnto the most high
God, that wrath come not vpon the kingdome of the King and his
sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="22">I command you
also that yee require no taxe, nor any other imposition of any of
the Priests or Leuites, or holy singers, or porters, or ministers
of the temple, or of any that haue doings in this temple, and that
no man haue authority to impose any thing vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="23">And thou,
Esdras, according to the wisedome of God, ordaine iudges, and
iustices, that they may iudge in all Syria and Phenice, all those
that know the law of thy God, and those that know it not thou shalt
teach.<note> Heb. of those that know Ezra 7.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And whosoeuer
shal transgresse the law of thy God, and of the king, shall be
punished diligently, whether it be by death or other punishment, by
penalty of money, or by imprisonment.<note> Ezra 7.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Then said
Esdras the Scribe, Blessed be the onely Lord God of my fathers, who
hath put these things into the heart of the king, to glorifie his
house that is in Ierusalem;</ab>
<ab n="26">And hath
honoured mee in the sight of the king and his counsellers, and all
his friends and Nobles.</ab>
<ab n="27">Therefore was I
encouraged, by the helpe of the Lord my God, and gathered together
men of Israel to goe vp with me:</ab>
<ab n="28">And these are
the chiefe according to their families and seuerall dignities, that
went vp with me from Babylon in the reigne of king
Artaxerxes.</ab>
<ab n="29">Of the sonnes of
Phinees, Gerson: of the sonnes of Ithamar, Gamael: of the sonnes of
Dauid; Lettus the sonne of Sechenias:<note> Or, Daniel. , Or, Chattus. , Ezra 8.3. of the sons of Secheniah, of the sonnes of Parosh.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Of the sonnes of
Pharez, Zacharias, and with him were counted, an hundred and fifty
men:</ab>
<ab n="31">Of the sonnes of
Pahath, Moab; Eliaonias, the sonne of Zaraias, and with him two
hundred men:<note> Zerachaiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Of the sonnes of
Zathoe, Sechenias, the sonne of Iezelus, and with him three hundred
men, Of the sonnes of Adin, Obeth the sonne of Ionathan, and with
him two hundred and fifty men.<note> Or, of the sonnes of Shecheniah the sonne of Iahaziel. , Heb. fifty men.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Of the sonnes of
Elam, Iosias sonne of Gotholias, and with him seuenty
men:<note> Or, Athaliah.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Of the sonnes of
Saphatias, Zaraias sonne of Michael, and with him threescore and
ten men:<note> Or, Zebadiah. , Or, fourescore men.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Of the sonnes of
Ioab, Abadias sonne of Iezelus, and with him two hundred and twelue
men:<note> Or, Obadiah. , Or, Iehiel. , Or, eighteene men.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Of the sonnes of
Banid, Assalimoth sonne of Iosaphias, and with him an hundred and
threescore men:<note> Or, of the sonnes of Shelomith the sonne of Iosiphiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Of the sonnes of
Babi, Zacharias sonne of Bebai, and with him twentie and eight
men:</ab>
<ab n="38">Of the sonnes of
Astath, Iohannessonne of Acatan, and with him an hundred and ten
men:<note> Or, Az, gad. , Or, Catan.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Of the sonnes of
Adonicam the last, and these are the names of them, Eliphalet,
Ieuel, and Samaias and with them seuenty men:<note> Or, Shemaia. , Or, sixty men.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Of the sonnes of
Bago, Uthi, the sonne of Istalcurus, and with him seuenty
men:</ab>
<ab n="41">And these I
gathered together to the riuer, called Theras, where we pitched our
tents three dayes, and then I suruayed them.<note> Or, to the riuer called Ahaue. Ez. 8.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">But when I had
found there, none of the priests and Leuites,<note> Or, be numbred the people and the priests: but found none of the sonnes of Leui.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Then sent I vnto
Eleazar and Iduel, and Masman,<note> Or, Ariel. , Or, Shemaiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And Alnathan,
and Mamaias, and Ioribas, and Nathan, Eunatan, Zacharias, and
Mosollamon principal men and learned.<note> Or, Iarib. , Or, these mens names with their generations are rightly distinguished Ezra 8.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And I bad them
that they should goe vnto Saddeus the captaine, who was in the
place of the treasury:<note> Or, Iddo. , Or, of , Or, Casiphia.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And commanded
them that they should speake vnto Daddeus, and to his brethren, and
to the treasurers in that place, to send vs such men as might
execute the Priests office in the house of the Lord.<note> Or, the Nethinims at the place of Casiphia. , Or, Machli.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And by the
mighty hand of our Lord they brought vnto vs skilful men of the
sonnes of Moli, the sonne of Leui, the sonne of Israel, Asebebia
and his sonnes and his brethren, who were eighteene.<note> Sherebia Ezra 8.18. , Or, also Hashabia, and with him Ieshaiah of the sonnes of Merari with his brethren Ezra 8.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And Asebia, and
Annuus, and Osaias his brother of the sonnes of Channuneus, and
their sonnes were twentie men.</ab>
<ab n="49">And of the
seruants of the Temple whom Dauid had ordeined, and the principall
men, for the seruice of the Leuites (to wit) the seruants of the
Temple, two hundred and twentie, the catalogue of whose names were
shewed.</ab>
<ab n="50">And there I
vowed a fast vnto the yong men before our Lord, to desire of him a
prosperous iourney, both for vs, and them that were with vs: for
our children and for the cattell:<note> Proclasmed. , Heb. substance.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">For I was
ashamed to aske the king footmen, &amp; horsemen, and conduct for
safegard against our aduersaries:</ab>
<ab n="52">For wee had said
vnto the king, that the power of the Lord our God, should be with
them that seeke him, to support them in all wayes.</ab>
<ab n="53">And againe wee
besought our Lord, as touching these things, &amp; found him
fauourable vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="54">Then I separated
twelue of the chiefe of the priests, Esebrias, &amp; Assanias, and
ten men of their brethren with them.<note> Serenias ad Hassibias.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And I weighed
them the golde, and the siluer, and the holy vessels of the house
of our Lord, which the king and his counsell, and the princes, and
all Israel had giuen.</ab>
<ab n="56">And when I had
weighed it, I deliuered vnto them sixe hundred and fiftie talents
of siluer, and siluer vessels of an hundred talents, and an hundred
talents of gold,</ab>
<ab n="57">And twentie
golden vessels, and twelue vessels of brasse, euen of fine brasse,
glittering like gold.<note> Heb. two vessels, Ezr. 8.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">And I said vnto
them, Both you are holy vnto the Lord, and the vessels are holy,
and the golde, and the siluer isa vowe vnto the Lord, the Lord of
our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="59">Watch ye, and
keepe them till yee deliuer them to the chiefe of the priestes and
Leuites, and to the principall men of the families of Israel in
Ierusalem into the chambers of the house of our God.</ab>
<ab n="60">So the priests
and the Leuites who had receiued the siluer &amp; the golde, and
the vessels, brought them vnto Ierusalem into the Temple of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="61">And from the
riuer Theras wee departed the twelft day of the first moneth, and
came to Ierusalem by the mightie hand of our Lord, which was with
vs: and from the beginning of our iourney, the Lord deliuered vs
from euery enemy, and so wee came to Ierusalem.<note> Dangers in the way.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">And when wee had
bene there three dayes, the golde and siluer that was weighed, was
deliuered in the house of our Lord on the fourth day vnto Marmoth
the priest, the sonne of Iri.<note> Or, vnto Merimoth the sonne of Vriah the Priest.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">And with him was
Eleazar the sonne of Phinees, and with them were Iosabad the sonne
of Iesu, and Moeth the sonne of Sabban, Leuites: all was deliuered
them by number and weight.<note> Noadiah the sonne of Binnui.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">And all the
weight of them was written vp the same houre.</ab>
<ab n="65">Moreouer they
that were come out of the captiuitie offered sacrifice vnto the
Lord God of Israel, euen twelue bullocks for all Israel, fourescore
and sixteene rammes,</ab>
<ab n="66">Threescore and
twelue lambes, goates for a peace offering, twelue, all of them a
sacrifice to the Lord.<note> Heb.77. lambes. 12. hee goats for a sinne offering, Ezra 8.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="67">And they
deliuered the kings commandements vnto the kings stewards, and to
the gouernours of Coelosyria, and Phenice, and they honoured the
people, and the Temple of God.</ab>
<ab n="68">Now when these
things were done, the rulers came vnto me, and said:</ab>
<ab n="69">The nation of
Israel, the princes, the priests, and Leuites haue not put away
from them the strange people of the land: nor the pollutions of the
Gentiles, to wit, of the Chanaanites, Hittites, Pheresites,
Iebusites, and the Moabites, Egyptians, and Edomites.<note> Ezra 9.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="70">For both they,
and their sonnes, haue maried with their daughters, and the holy
seed is mixed with the strange people of the land, and from the
beginning of this matter, the rulers and the great men haue bene
partakers of this iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="71">And assoone as I
had heard these things, I rent my clothes, and the holy garment,
and pulled off the haire from off my head, and beard, and sate me
downe sad, and very heauy.</ab>
<ab n="72">So all they that
were then mooued at the word of the Lord God of Israel, assembled
vnto me, whilest I mourned for the iniquitie: but I sate still full
of heauinesse, vntill the euening sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="73">Then rising vp
from the fast with my clothes and the holy garment rent, and bowing
my knees, and stretching foorth my hands vnto the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="74">I said, O Lord,
I am confounded, and ashamed before thy face;</ab>
<ab n="75">For our sinnes
are multiplied aboue our heads, and our ignorances haue reached vp
vnto heauen.<note> Greeke. haue abounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="76">For euer since
the time of our fathers wee haue bene and are in great sinne, euen
vnto this day:</ab>
<ab n="77">And for our
sinnes and our fathers, we with our brethren, and our kings, and
our priests, were giuen vp vnto the Kings of the earth, to the
sword, and to captiuitie, and for a pray with shame, vnto this
day.</ab>
<ab n="78">And now in some
measure hath mercy bene shewed vnto vs, from thee, O Lord, that
there should be left vs a roote, and a name, in the place of thy
Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="79">And to discouer
vnto vs a light in the house of the Lord our God, and to giue vs
foode in the time of our seruitude.<note> Hebr. life, Ezr.9.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="80">Yea, when we
were in bondage, we were not forsaken of our Lord; but he made vs
gracious before the Kings of Persia, so that they gaue vs
food;</ab>
<ab n="81">Yea, and
honoured the Temple of our Lord, and raised vp the desolate Sion,
that they haue giuen vs a sure abiding in Iurie, and
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="82">And now, O Lord,
what shall wee say hauing these things? for wee haue transgressed
thy Commaundements, which thou gauest by the hand of thy seruants
the Prophets, saying,</ab>
<ab n="83">That the land
which ye enter into to possesse as an heritage, is a land polluted
with the pollutions of the strangers of the land, and they haue
filled it with their vncleannesse.</ab>
<ab n="84">Therefore now
shal ye not ioyne your daughters vnto their sonnes, neither shall
ye take their daughters vnto your sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="85">Moreouer you
shall neuer seeke to haue peace with them, that yee may be strong,
and eate the good things of the land, and that ye may leaue the
inheritance of the land vnto your children for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="86">And all that is
befallen, is done vnto vs for our wicked workes, and great sinnes:
for thou, O Lord, didst make our sinnes light:</ab>
<ab n="87">And didst giue
vnto vs such a roote: but we haue turned backe againe to
transgresse thy Law, and to mingle our selues with the vncleannesse
of the nations of the land.</ab>
<ab n="88">Mightest not
thou be angry with vs to destroy vs, till thou hadst left vs
neither root, seed, nor name?<note> Or, be not angry, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="89">O Lord of
Israel, thou art true: for we are left a root this day.</ab>
<ab n="90">Behold, now are
we before thee in our iniquities, for wee cannot stand any longer
by reason of these things before thee.</ab>
<ab n="91">And as Esdras in
his praier made his confession, weeping, and lying flat vpon the
ground before the Temple, there gathered vnto him from Ierusalem, a
very great multitude of men, and women, &amp; children: for there
was great weeping among the multitude.</ab>
<ab n="92">Then Iechonias
the sonne of Ieelus, one of the sonnes of Israel called out and
saide, O Esdras, wee haue sinned against the Lord God, wee haue
maried strange women of the nations of the land, &amp; now is all
Israel aloft.<note> Or, exalted, Deut. 28. 13. &amp; Baruch.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="93">Let vs make an
oath to the Lord, that wee will put away all our wiues, which we
haue taken of the heathen, with their children,</ab>
<ab n="94">Like as thou
hast decreed, and as many as doe obey the Law of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="95">Arise, and put
in execution: for to thee doeth this matter appertaine, and wee
will bee with thee: doe valiantly.</ab>
<ab n="96">So Esdras arose,
and tooke an oath of the chiefe of the Priestes, and Leuites of all
Israel, to do after these things, and so they sware.<note> Hebr. and of all Israel, Ezr. 10.5.</note></ab>



</div>