<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Esdras_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The Prophets stirre vp the people
to build the Temple. 8 Darius is solicited to hinder it. 27 But he
doth further it by all meanes, 32 and threatneth those that shall
hinder it.</head>

<ab n="1">Now in the second
yeere of the reigne of Darius, Aggeus, and Zacharias the sonne of
Addo, the prophets prophesied vnto the Iewes, in Iurie and
Ierusalem in the Name of the Lord God of Israel which was vpon
them.<note> Or, Iddo. , Or, which was called on them.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then stood vp
Zorobabel the sonne of Salathiel, and Iesus the son of Iosedec, and
beganne to build the house of the Lord at Ierusalem, the prophets
of the Lord being with them,and helping them.</ab>
<ab n="3">At the same time
came vnto them Sisinnes the gouernor of Syria, and Phenice, with
Sathrabuzanes, and his companions, and said vnto them,<note> Ezra.5.3. , Or, Tatnai , Or, Shether-boznai.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">By whose
appointment doe you build this house, and this roofe, and performe
all the other things? and who are the workemen that performe these
things?</ab>
<ab n="5">Neuerthelesse the
Elders of the Iewes obtained fauour: because the Lord had visited
the captiuitie.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they were not
hindred from building vntil such time as signification was giuen
vnto Darius concerning them, and an answere receiued.</ab>
<ab n="7">The copie of the
letters which Sisinnes gouernour of Syria, and Phenice, and
Sathrabuzanes with their companions rulers in Syria and Phenice,
wrote and sent vnto Darius, To king Darius, greeting.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let all things
bee knowen vnto our lord the King, that being come into the
countrey of Iudea, and entred into the citie of Ierusalem, we found
in the citie of Ierusalem the ancients of the Iewes that were of
the captiuitie;</ab>
<ab n="9">Building an house
vnto the Lord, great, and newe, of hewen and costly stones, and the
timber already laid vpon the walles.</ab>
<ab n="10">And those workes
are done with great speede, and the worke goeth on prosperously in
their handes, and with all glory and diligence is it made.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then asked wee
these Elders, saying, By whose commaundement builde you this house,
and lay the foundations of these workes?</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore to the
intent that wee might giue knowledge vnto thee by writing, we
demanded of them who were the chiefe doers, and we required of them
the names in writing of their principall men.</ab>
<ab n="13">So they gaue vs
this answere: We are the seruants of the Lord which made heauen and
earth.</ab>
<ab n="14">And as for this
house, it was builded many yeeres agoe, by a king of Israel great
and strong, and was finished.</ab>
<ab n="15">But when our
fathers prouoked God vnto wrath, and sinned against the Lord of
Israel which is in heauen, hee gaue them ouer into the power of
Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon of the Chaldees:</ab>
<ab n="16">Who pulled downe
the house and burnt it, and caried away the people captiues vnto
Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="17">But in the first
yeere that King Cyrus reigned ouer the country of Babylon, Cyrus
the king wrote to build vp this house.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the holy
vessels of gold and of siluer, that Nabuchodonosor had caried away
out of the house at Ierusalem, and had set them in his owne temple,
those Cyrus the king brought forth againe out of the temple at
Babylon, and they were deliuered to Zorobabel and to Sanabassarus
the ruler,<note> Or, Zorobabel, which is also Sanabassar the ruler, so as Zorobabel seemeth to be added to the text, Ezra 1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">With
commaundement that hee should carrie away the same vessels, and put
them in the Temple at Ierusalem, and that the Temple of
þe Lord should be built in his place.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then the same
Sanabassarus being come hither, laid the foundations of the house
of the Lord at Ierusalem, and from that time to this, being still a
building, it is not yet fully ended.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now therefore if
it seeme good vnto the king, let search be made among the records
of King Cyrus,<note> Or, roules.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And if it be
found, that the building of the house of the Lord at Ierusalem hath
bene done with the consent of King Cyrus, and if our lord the king
be so minded, let him signifie vnto vs thereof.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then commanded
king Darius to seeke among the records at Babylon: and so at
Ecbatana the palace which is in the countrey of Media, there was
found a roule wherein these things were recorded.<note> Or, place.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">In the first
yeere of the reigne of Cyrus, king Cyrus commaunded that the house
of the Lord at Ierusalem should bee built againe where they doe
sacrifice with continuall fire.</ab>
<ab n="25">Whose height
shalbe sixtie cubits, and the breadth sixtie cubits, with three
rowes of hewen stones, and one row of new wood of that countrey,
and the expenses thereof to bee giuen out of the house of king
Cyrus.</ab>
<ab n="26">And that the
holy vessels of the house of the Lord, both of gold and siluer that
Nabuchodonosor tooke out of the house at Ierusalem, and brought to
Babylon, should be restored to the house at Ierusalem, and bee set
in the place where they were before.</ab>
<ab n="27">And also he
commanded that Sisinnes the gouernour of Syria and Phenice, and
Sathrabuzanes, and their companions, and those which were appointed
rulers in Syria, and Phenice should be carefull not to meddle with
the place, but suffer Zorobabel the seruant of the Lord, and
gouernour of Iudea, and the Elders of the Iewes, to build the house
of the Lord in that place.</ab>
<ab n="28">I haue commanded
also to haue it built vp whole againe, and that they looke
diligently to helpe those that be of the captiuitie of the Iewes,
till the house of the Lord be finished.</ab>
<ab n="29">And out of the
tribute of Coelosyria, and Phenice, a portion carefully to be giuen
these men, for the sacrifices of the Lord that is, to Zorobabel the
gouernour, for bullocks, and rammes, and lambes;</ab>
<ab n="30">And also corne,
salt, wine and oile, and that continually euery yeere without
further question, according as the Priests that be in Ierusalem
shall signifie, to be daily spent:</ab>
<ab n="31">That offrings
may be made to the most high God, for the king and for his
children, and that they may pray for their liues.<note> Drinke offerings.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And he
commanded, that whosoeuer should transgresse, yea, or make light of
any thing afore spoken or written, out of his owne house should a
tree be taken, and he thereon be hanged, and all his goods seized
for the king.</ab>
<ab n="33">The Lord
therfore whose Name is there called vpon, vtterly destroy euery
king and nation, that stretcheth out his hand to hinder or
endammage that house of the Lord in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="34">I Darius the
king haue ordeined, that according vnto these things it be done
with diligence.</ab>



</div>