<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-John_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 He comforteth them against the
sinnes of infirmitie. 3 Rightly to know God, is to keepe his
commaundements, 9 to loue our brethren, 15 and not to loue the
world. 18 We must beware of seducers: 20 from whose deceits the
godly are safe preserued by perseuerance in faith, and holinesse of
life.</head>

<ab n="1">My little
children, these things write I vnto you, that ye sinne not. And if
any man sinne, we haue an Aduocate with the Father, Iesus Christ
the righteous:</ab>
<ab n="2">And he is the
propitiation for our sinnes: and not for ours onely, but also for
the sinnes of the whole world.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hereby
wee doe knowe that we know him, if we keepe his
commandements.</ab>
<ab n="4">He that
saith, I knowe him, and keepeth not his commandements, is a lyer,
and the trueth is not in him.</ab>
<ab n="5">But who so
keepeth his word, in him verely is the loue of God perfected:
hereby know we that we are in him.</ab>
<ab n="6">He that
sayeth he abideth in him, ought himselfe also so to walke, euen as
he walked.</ab>
<ab n="7">Brethren, I
write no new commandement vnto you, but an olde commandement which
ye had from the beginning: the old commandement is the word which
ye haue heard from the beginning.</ab>
<ab n="8">Againe, a new
commandement I write vnto you, which thing is true in him and in
you: because the darkenesse is past, and the true light now
shineth.</ab>

<fw>The last time.</fw>
<ab n="9">He that saith
he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is in darkenesse euen
vntill now.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee that loueth
his brother, abideth in the light, and there is none occasion of
stumbling in him.<note> Gr. scandall</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But he that hateth
his brother, is in darknesse, and walketh in darknesse, and knoweth
not whither hee goeth, because that darknesse hath blinded his
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="12">I write vnto you,
little children, because your sinnes are forgiuen you for his Names
sake.</ab>
<ab n="13">I write vnto you,
fathers, because yee haue knowen him that is from the beginning. I
write vnto you, young men, because you haue ouercome the wicked
one. I write vnto you, little children, because yee haue knowen the
Father.</ab>
<ab n="14">I haue written
vnto you, fathers, because ye haue knowen him that is from the
beginning. I haue written vnto you, young men, because yee are
strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and yee haue ouercome
the wicked one.</ab>
<ab n="15">Loue not the
world, neither the things that are in the world. If any man loue
the world, the loue of the Father is not in him.</ab>
<ab n="16">For all that is in
the world, the lust of the flesh, the lust of the eyes, and the
pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the world
passeth away, and the lust thereof, but hee that doeth the will of
God, abideth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">Little children,
it is the last time: and as yee haue heard that Antichrist shall
come, euen now are there many Antichrists, whereby wee know that it
is the last time.</ab>
<ab n="19">They went out from
vs, but they were not of vs: for if they had beene of vs, they
would no doubt haue continued with vs: but they went out that they
might be made manifest, that they were not all of vs.</ab>
<ab n="20">But ye haue an
vnction from the holy One, and ye know all things.</ab>
<ab n="21">I haue not written
vnto you, because yee know not the trueth: but because ye know it,
and that no lie is of the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="22">Who is a lier, but
hee that denieth that Iesus is the Christ? hee is Antichrist, that
denyeth the Father, and the Sonne.</ab>

<fw>Gods great loue.</fw>
<ab n="23">Whosoeuer denieth
the Sonne, the same hath not the Father: but he that acknowledgeth
the Sonne, hath the Father also.</ab>
<ab n="24">Let that therefore
abide in you which yee haue heard from the beginning: if that which
ye haue heard from the beginning shall remaine in you, yee also
shall continue in the Sonne, and in the Father.</ab>
<ab n="25">And this is the
promise that hee hath promised vs, euen eternall life.</ab>
<ab n="26">These things haue
I written vnto you, concerning them that seduce you.</ab>
<ab n="27">But the anointing
which ye haue receiued of him, abideth in you: and yee need not
that any man teach you: But, as the same anointing teacheth you of
all things, and is trueth, and is no lye: and euen as it hath
taught you, ye shall abide in him.<note> Or, it.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And now, little
children, abide in him, that when hee shall appeare, wee may haue
confidence, and not bee ashamed before him at his comming.</ab>
<ab n="29">If ye know that he
is righteous, ye know that euery one which doeth righteousnesse, is
borne of him.<note> Or, know ye</note></ab>



</div>