<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-John_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 He warneth them not to beleeue all
teachers, who boast of the spirit, but to try them by the rules of
the Catholike faith: 7 and by many reasons exhorteth to brotherly
loue.</head>

<ab n="1">Beloued,
beleeue not euery spirit, but trie the spirits, whether they are of
God: because many false prophets are gone out into the
world.</ab>
<ab n="2">Hereby know
ye the spirit of God: euery spirit that confesseth that Iesus
Christ is come in the flesh, is of God.</ab>
<ab n="3">And euery
Spirit that confesseth not that Iesus Christ is come in the flesh,
is not of God: and this is that spirit of Antichrist, whereof you
haue heard, that it should come, and euen now already is it in the
world.</ab>
<ab n="4">Ye are of
God, little children, and haue ouercome them: because greater is he
that is in you, then he that is in the world.</ab>
<ab n="5">They are of
the world: therefore speake they of the world, and the world
heareth them.</ab>
<ab n="6">We are of
God: hee that knoweth God, heareth vs: he that is not of God
heareth not vs, hereby know wee the spirit of trueth, and the
spirit of errour.</ab>
<ab n="7">Beloued, let
vs loue one another; for loue is of God: and euery one that loueth,
is borne of God and knoweth God.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hee that
loueth not, knoweth not God: for God is loue.</ab>
<ab n="9">In this was
manifested the loue of God towards vs, because that God sent his
only begotten Sonne into the world, that we might liue through
him.</ab>
<ab n="10">Herein is loue,
not that wee loued God, but that he loued vs, and sent his Sonne to
be þe propitiation for our sins.</ab>
<ab n="11">Beloued, if God so
loued vs, wee ought also to loue one another.</ab>

<fw>Gods loue.</fw>
<ab n="12">No man hath seene
God at any time. If wee loue one another, God dwelleth in vs, and
his loue is perfected in vs.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hereby know wee
that we dwell in him and he in vs, because hee hath giuen vs of his
Spirit.</ab>
<ab n="14">And we haue seene,
and doe testifie, that the Father sent the Sonne to be the Sauiour
of the world.</ab>
<ab n="15">Whosoeuer shall
confesse that Iesus is the Sonne of God, God dwelleth in him, and
he in God.</ab>
<ab n="16">And we haue knowen
and beleeued the loue that God hath to vs. God is loue, and hee
that dwelleth in loue, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Herein is our loue
made perfect, that wee may haue boldnesse in the day of Iudgement,
because as hee is, so are we in this world.<note> Gr. loue with vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">There is no feare
in loue, but perfect loue casteth out feare: because feare hath
torment: hee that feareth, is not made perfect in loue.</ab>
<ab n="19">We loue him:
because hee first loued vs.</ab>
<ab n="20">If a man say, I
loue God, and hateth his brother, he is a lyar. For hee that loueth
not his brother whom hee hath seene, how can he loue God whom he
hath not seene?</ab>
<ab n="21">And this
commandement haue we from him, that he who loueth God, loue his
brother also.</ab>



</div>