<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-John_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-5-5-2-John.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>Hee that loueth God, loueth his
children, and keepeth his Commandements: 3 which to the faithful
are light, and not grieuous. 9 Iesus is the Sonne of God, able to
saue vs, 14 and to heare our prayers, which we make for our selues,
and for others.</head>

<ab n="1">Whosoeuer
beleeueth that Iesus is the Christ, is borne of God: and euery one
that loueth him that begate, loueth him also that is begotten of
him.</ab>
<ab n="2">By this wee
know that wee loue the children of God, when we loue God and keepe
his commandements.</ab>
<ab n="3">For this is
the loue of God, that we keepe his commandements, and his
commandements are not grieuous.</ab>
<ab n="4">For
whatsoeuer is borne of God, ouercommeth the world, and this is the
victorie that ouercommeth the world, euen our faith.</ab>

<fw>Three witnesses.</fw>
<ab n="5">Who is he
that ouercommeth the world, but he that beleeueth that Iesus is the
Sonne of God?</ab>
<ab n="6">This is hee
that came by water and blood, euen Iesus Christ, not by water
onely, but by water and blood: and it is the Spirit that beareth
witnesse, because the Spirit is trueth.</ab>
<ab n="7">For there are
three that beare record in heauen, the Father, the Word, and the
holy Ghost: and these three are one.</ab>
<ab n="8">And there are
three that beare witnesse in earth, the Spirit, and the Water, and
the Blood, and these three agree in one.</ab>
<ab n="9">If we receiue
the witnesse of men, the witnesse of God is greater: for this is
the witnesse of God, which hee hath testified of his Sonne.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee that beleeueth
on the Sonne of God, hath the witnesse in himselfe: he that
beleeueth not God, hath made him a liar, because he beleeueth not
the record that God gaue of his Sonne.</ab>
<ab n="11">And this is the
record, that God hath giuen to vs eternall life, and this life is
in his Sonne.</ab>
<ab n="12">Hee that hath the
Sonne, hath life; and hee that hath not the Sonne, hath not
life.</ab>
<ab n="13">These things haue
I written vnto you that beleeue on the Name of the Sonne of God,
that ye may know, that ye haue eternall life, and that yee may
beleeue on the Name of the Sonne of God.</ab>
<ab n="14">And this is the
confidence that we haue in him, that if wee aske any thing
according to his will, hee heareth vs.<note> Or, concerning him.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And if we know
that he heare vs, whatsoeuer wee aske, wee know that we haue the
petitions that wee desired of him.</ab>
<ab n="16">If any man see his
brother sinne a sinne which is not vnto death, hee shall aske, and
he shall giue him life for them that sinne not vnto death. There is
a sinne vnto death: I doe not say that he shall pray for
it.</ab>
<ab n="17">All vnrighteousnes
is sinne, and there is a sinne not vnto death.</ab>
<ab n="18">We know that
whosoeuer is borne of God, sinneth not: but hee that is begotten of
God, keepeth himselfe, and that wicked one toucheth him
not.</ab>
<ab n="19">And we know that
we are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickednesse.</ab>

<fw>Walking in trueth and loue.</fw>
<ab n="20">And we know that
the Sonne of God is come, and hath giuen vs an vnderstanding that
wee may know him that is true: and wee are in him that is true,
euen in his Sonne Iesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternall
life.</ab>
<ab n="21">Little children,
keepe your selues from Idoles. Amen.</ab>



</div>