<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Ahab being denied Naboths
vineyard, is grieued. 5 Iezebel writing letters against Naboth, he
is condemned of blasphemie. 15 Ahab taketh possession of the
vineyard. 17 Eliiah denounceth iudgements against Ahab and Iezebel.
25 Wicked Ahab repenting, God deferreth the iudgement.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after these things, that Naboth the Iezreelite had a
vineyard, which was in Iezreel, hard by the palace of Ahab king of
Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Ahab spake
vnto Naboth, saying, Giue me thy vineyard, that I may haue it for a
garden of herbes, because it is neere vnto my house, and I will
giue thee for it a better vineyard then it: or if it seeme good to
thee, I will giue thee the worth of it in money.<note> Hebr. be good in thine eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Naboth said
to Ahab, The Lord forbid it mee, that I should giue the inheritance
of my fathers vnto thee.</ab>

<fw>Naboth stoned.</fw>
<ab n="4">And Ahab came
into his house, heauie, and displeased, because of the word which
Naboth the Iezreelite had spoken to him: for he had saide, I will
not giue thee the inheritance of my fathers: and he laid him downe
vpon his bed, and turned away his face, and would eate no
bread.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ But
Iezebel his wife came to him, and said vnto him, Why is thy spirit
so sad, that thou eatest no bread?</ab>
<ab n="6">And he said vnto
her, Because I spake vnto Naboth the Iezreelite, and said vnto him,
Giue mee thy vineyard for money, or else if it please thee, I will
giue thee another vineyard for it: And he answered, I wil not giue
thee my vineyard.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Iezebel his
wife saide vnto him, Doest thou now gouerne the kingdome of Israel?
Arise, and eate bread, and let thine heart bee merrie: I will giue
thee the vineyard of Naboth the Iezreelite.</ab>
<ab n="8">So shee wrote
letters in Ahabs name, and sealed them with his seale, and sent the
letters vnto the Elders, and to the Nobles that were in his citie
dwelling with Naboth.</ab>
<ab n="9">And she wrote in
the letters, saying, Proclaime a fast, and set Naboth on high among
the people:<note> Heb. in the top of the people.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And set two men,
sonnes of Belial before him, to beare witnes against him, saying,
Thou diddest blaspheme God and the king: and then carie him out,
and stone him that he may die.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the men of
his citie, euen the Elders and the Nobles who were the inhabitants
in his citie, did as Iezebel had sent vnto them, and as it was
written in the letters which she had sent vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="12">They proclaimed
a fast, and set Naboth on high among the people.</ab>
<ab n="13">And there came
in two men, children of Belial, and sate before him: and the men of
Belial witnessed against him, euen against Naboth, in the presence
of the people, saying, Naboth did blaspheme God and the king. Then
they caried him foorth out of the citie, and stoned him with
stones, that hee died.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then they sent
to Iezebel, saying, Naboth is stoned, and is dead.</ab>

<fw>Ahabs wickednes.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ And it
came to passe when Iezebel heard that Naboth was stoned and was
dead, that Iezebel said to Ahab, Arise, take possession of the
Uineyard of Naboth the Iezreelite, which hee refused to giue thee
for money: for Naboth is not aliue, but dead.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it came to
passe when Ahab heard that Naboth was dead, that Ahab rose vp to
goe downe to the Uineyard of Naboth the Iezreelite, to take
possession of it.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
word of the Lord came to Eliiah the Tishbite, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">Arise, goe downe
to meet Ahab king of Israel, which is in Samaria: behold, hee is in
the Uineyard of Naboth, whither he is gone downe to possesse
it.</ab>
<ab n="19">And thou shalt
speake vnto him, saying, Thus saith the Lord, Hast thou killed, and
also taken possession? And thou shalt speake vnto him, saying, Thus
saith the Lord; In the place where dogs licked the blood of Naboth,
shall dogges licke thy blood, euen thine.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Ahab said to
Eliiah, Hast thou found me, O mine enemie? And he answered, I haue
found thee: because thou hast sold thy selfe to worke euill in the
sight of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">Behold, I will
bring euill vpon thee, and will take away thy posteritie, and will
cut off from Ahab him that pisseth against the wall, and him that
is shut vp, and left in Israel,<note> Chap.14. 10. 2.king. 9.8. , 1.Sam. 25.22. , Chap.14. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And will make
thine house like the house of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, and like
the house of Baasha the sonne of Ahiiah, for the prouocation
wherewith thou hast prouoked mee to anger, and made Israel to
sinne.<note> Chap. 15. 29. , Chap.16. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And of Iezebel
also spake the Lord, saying, The dogs shall eate Iezebel by the
wall of Iezreel.<note> 2.King.9. 36. , Or, ditch.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Him that dieth
of Ahab in the citie, the dogs shall eate: and him that dieth in
the field, shall the foules of the aire eat.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ But there
was none like vnto Ahab, which did sell himselfe to worke
wickednesse in the sight of the Lord, whom Iezebel his wife stirred
vp.<note> Or, incited.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And hee did very
abominably in following Idoles, according to all things as did the
Amorites, whom the Lord cast out before the children of
Israel.</ab>

<fw>Iehoshaphat.</fw>
<ab n="27">And it came to
passe when Ahab heard those wordes, that hee rent his clothes, and
put sackecloth vpon his flesh, and fasted, and lay in sackcloth,
and went softly.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the word of
the Lord came to Eliiah the Tishbite, saying,</ab>
<ab n="29">Seest thou how
Ahab humbleth himselfe before mee? because hee humbleth himselfe
before mee, I will not bring the euill in his dayes: but in his
sonnes dayes will I bring the euill vpon his house.</ab>



</div>