<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The Israelites assembled at
Shechem to crowne Rehoboam, by Ieroboam make a suite of relaxation
vnto him. 6 Rehoboam refusing the olde mens counsell, by the aduice
of young men, answereth them roughly. 16 Ten tribes reuolting, kill
Adoram, and make Rehoboam to flee. 21 Rehoboam raising an armie, is
forbidden by Shemaiah. 25 Ieroboam strengtheneth himselfe by
cities, 20 and by the idolatrie of the two calues.</head>

<ab n="1">And Rehoboam went
to Shechem: for all Israel were come to Shechem to make him
king.<note> 2.Chron. 10.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it came to
passe when Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who was yet in Egypt, heard
of it (for hee was fled from the presence of king Solomon, and
Ieroboam dwelt in Egypt:)<note> Chap.11. 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">That they sent,
and called him: and Ieroboam and all the Congregation of Israel
came, and spake vnto Rehoboam, saying;</ab>
<ab n="4">Thy father made
our yoke grieuous: now therefore, make thou the grieuous seruice of
thy father, and his heauy yoke which he put vpon vs, lighter, and
we will serue thee.<note> Chap.4.7</note></ab>

<fw>Rehoboam king.</fw>
<ab n="5">And hee said vnto
them, Depart yet for three daies, then come againe to me. And the
people departed.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And king
Rehoboam consulted with the old men that stood before Solomon his
father, while he yet liued, and said, How doe you aduise, that I
may answere this people?</ab>
<ab n="7">And they spake
vnto him, saying, If thou wilt be a seruant vnto this people this
day, and wilt serue them, and answere them, and speake good words
to them, then they will be thy seruants for euer.</ab>
<ab n="8">But hee forsooke
the counsell of the old men, which they had giuen him, and
consulted with the yong men, that were growen vp with him, and
which stood before him.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee said vnto
them, What counsell giue ye, that we may answere this people, who
haue spoken to mee, saying, Make the yoke which thy father did put
vpon vs, lighter?</ab>
<ab n="10">And the young
men that were growen vp with him, spake vnto him, saying, Thus
shalt thou speake vnto this people that spake vnto thee, saying,
Thy father made our yoke heauy, but make thou it lighter vnto vs;
thus shalt thou say vnto them, My litle finger shall bee thicker
then my fathers loynes.</ab>
<ab n="11">And now whereas
my father did lade you with a heauy yoke, I wil adde to your yoke:
my father hath chastised you with whippes, but I will chastise you
with scorpions.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ So
Ieroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the
king had appointed, saying, Come to me againe the third
day.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the king
answered the people roughly, and forsooke the old mens counsell
that they gaue him:<note> Heb. hardly.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And spake to
them after the counsell of the young men, saying, My father made
your yoke heauy, and I will adde to your yoke; my father also
chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with
scorpions.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wherefore the
king hearkened not vnto the people: for the cause was from the
Lord, that hee might performe his saying, which the Lord spake by
Ahiiah the Shilonite vnto Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat.<note> Chap.11. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>Israel rebelleth.</fw>
<ab n="16">¶ So when
all Israel saw that the king hearkned not vnto them, the people
answered the king, saying, What portion haue we in Dauid? neither
haue we inheritance in the sonne of Iesse: to your tents, O Israel:
nowe see to thine owne house, Dauid. So Israel departed vnto their
tents.</ab>
<ab n="17">But as for the
children of Israel which dwelt in the cities of Iudah, Rehoboam
reigned ouer them.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then king
Rehoboam sent Adoram, who was ouer the tribute, and all Israel
stoned him with stones that hee died: therefore king Rehoboam made
speed to get him vp to his charet, to flee to
Ierusalem.<note> Heb. strengthened himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">So Israel
rebelled against the house of Dauid vnto this day.<note> Or, fell away.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And it came to
passe when all Israel heard that Ieroboam was come againe, that
they sent and called him vnto the Congregation, and made him king
ouer all Israel: there was none that followed the house of Dauid,
but the tribe of Iudah onely.<note> Chap.11. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And when
Rehoboam was come to Ierusalem, hee assembled all the house of
Iudah, with the tribe of Beniamin, an hundred and fourescore
thousand chosen men which were warriers, to fight against the house
of Israel, to bring the kingdome againe to Rehoboam the sonne of
Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="22">But the word of
God came vnto Shemaiah, the man of God, saying,<note> 2. Chron. 11.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Speake vnto
Rehoboam the sonne of Solomon king of Iudah, and vnto all the house
of Iudah and Beniamin, and to the remnant of the people,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="24">Thus saith the
Lord, Ye shall not goe vp, nor fight against your brethren the
children of Israel: returne euery man to his house, for this thing
is from me. They hearkened therefore to the word of the Lord, and
returned to depart, according to the word of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Then
Ieroboam built Shechem in mount Ephraim, and dwelt therein, and
went out from thence, and built Penuel.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Ieroboam
said in his heart, Now shall the kingdome returne to the house of
Dauid:</ab>
<ab n="27">If this people
goe vp, to doe sacrifice in the house of the Lord at Ierusalem,
then shall the heart of this people turne againe vnto their lorde,
euen vnto Rehoboam king of Iudah, and they shall kill mee, and goe
againe to Rehoboam king of Iudah.</ab>

<fw>Ieroboams calues.</fw>
<ab n="28">Whereupon the
king tooke counsell, and made two calues of gold, and said vnto
them, It is too much for you to goe vp to Ierusalem: Behold thy
gods, O Israel, which brought thee vp out of the land of
Egypt.<note> Exod.32. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And he set the
one in Bethel, and the other put he in Dan.</ab>
<ab n="30">And this thing
became a sinne: for the people went to worship before the one, euen
vnto Dan.</ab>
<ab n="31">And he made an
house of hie places, and made priests of the lowest of the people,
which were not of the sonnes of Leui.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Ieroboam
ordeined a feast in the eight moneth, on the fifteenth day of the
moneth, like vnto the feast that is in Iudah, and he offered vpon
the altar (so did he in Bethel,) sacrificing vnto the calues that
he had made: and he placed in Bethel the priests of the high places
which he had made.<note> Or, went vp to the altar &amp;c. , Or to sacrifice.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">So hee offered
vpon the altar, which hee had made in Bethel, the fifteenth day of
the eighth moneth, euen in the moneth which he had deuised of his
owne heart: and ordeined a feast vnto the children of Israel, and
he offered vpon the altar, and burnt incense.<note> Or, went vp to the altar &amp;c. , Hebr. to burne incense.</note></ab>



</div>