<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-22-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-22-22b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Ahab seduced by false prophets,
according to the word of Micaiah, is slaine at Ramoth Gilead. 37
The dogges licke vp his blood, and Ahaziah succeedeth him. 41
Iehoshaphats good reigne, 45 his acts. 50 Iehoram succeedeth him.
51 Ahaziahs euil reigne.</head>

<ab n="1">And they
continued three yeeres without warre betweene Syria and
Israel.<note> 1.Chron. 18.1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it came to
passe on the third yere, that Iehoshaphat the King of Iudah came
downe to the king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">(And the king of
Israel said vnto his seruants, Know ye that Ramoth in Gilead is
ours, and wee be still, and take it not out of the hand of the king
of Syria?)<note> Hebr. silent from taking it.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And hee said vnto
Iehoshaphat, Wilt thou goe with me to battel to Ramoth Gilead? And
Iehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, I am as thou art, my people
as thy people, my horses as thy horses.<note> 2.King.3. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Iehoshaphat
said vnto the king of Israel, Enquire, I pray thee, at the word of
the Lord to day.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then the king of
Israel gathered the prophets together about foure hundred men, and
said vnto them, Shall I goe against Ramoth Gilead to battell, or
shall I forbeare? And they said, Goe vp, for the Lord shall deliuer
it into the hand of the king.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Iehoshaphat
said, Is there not here a Prophet of the Lord besides, that we
might enquire of him?</ab>
<ab n="8">And the king of
Israel said vnto Iehoshaphat, There is yet one man, (Micaiah the
sonne of Imlah) by whom we may enquire of the Lord; but I hate him,
for he doth not prophesie good concerning me, but euill. And
Iehoshaphat said, Let not the King say so.</ab>

<fw>Micaiah prophecieth Ahabs
destruction.</fw>
<ab n="9">Then the king of
Israel called an Officer, and said, Hasten hither Micaiah the sonne
of Imlah.<note> Or, Eunuch.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the King of
Israel and Iehoshaphat the King of Iudah sate each on his throne,
hauing put on their robes, in a voyd place in the entrance of the
gate of Samaria, and all the Prophets prophecied before
them.<note> Heb. floore.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Zedekiah the
sonne of Chenaanah made him hornes of yron: and he sayd, Thus saith
the Lord, With these shalt thou push the Syrians, vntill thou haue
consumed them.</ab>
<ab n="12">And all the
Prophets prophecied so, saying; Goe vp to Ramoth Gilead, and
prosper: for the Lord shall deliuer it into the kings hand.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the
messenger that was gone to call Micaiah, spake vnto him, saying,
Behold now, the words of the prophets declare good vnto the King
with one mouth: let thy word, I pray thee, bee like the word of one
of them, and speake that which is good.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Micaiah
sayde, As the Lord liueth, what the Lord saith vnto me, that will I
speake.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ So he
came to the king, and the king sayd vnto him, Micaiah, shall wee
goe against Ramoth Gilead to battell, or shall we forbeare? And he
answered him, Go, and prosper: for the Lord shall deliuer it into
the hand of the king.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the king
said vnto him, How many times shall I adiure thee, that thou tell
me nothing but that which is true, in the Name of the Lord
?</ab>
<ab n="17">And hee sayd, I
saw all Israel scattered vpon the hilles, as sheepe that haue not a
shepheard. And the Lord said, These haue no master, let them
returne euery man to his house in peace.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the King of
Israel said vnto Iehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee, that he would
prophecie no good concerning me, but euill?</ab>
<ab n="19">And he said,
Heare thou therefore the word of the Lord: I sawe the Lord sitting
on his Throne, and all the hoste of heauen standing by him, on his
right hand and on his left.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord
said, Who shall perswade Ahab, that hee may goe vp and fall at
Ramoth Gilead? And one sayd on this manner, and another said on
that manner.<note> Or, deceiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And there came
forth a spirit, and stood before the Lord, and said, I will
perswade him.</ab>

<fw>Micaiah prophecieth Ahabs
destruction.</fw>
<ab n="22">And the Lord
said vnto him, Wherewith? And hee sayd, I will goe foorth, and I
will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets. And he
said, Thou shalt perswade him, and preuaile also: Goe forth, and
doe so.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now therfore
behold, the Lord hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of all these
thy prophets, and the Lord hath spoken euill concerning
thee.</ab>
<ab n="24">But Zedekiah the
sonne of Chenaanah went neere, and smote Micaiah on the cheeke, and
said, Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me, to speake vnto
thee?<note> 2. Chron. 18.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Micaiah
sayde, Beholde, thou shalt see in that day, when thou shalt goe
into an inner chamber, to hide thy selfe.<note> Or, from chamber to chamber. Heb. chamber in a chamber.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And the King of
Israel sayde, Take Micaiah, and cary him backe vnto Amon the
gouernour of the citie, and to Ioash the kings sonne:</ab>
<ab n="27">And say, Thus
sayth the King, Put this fellow in the prison, and feede him with
bread of affliction, and with water of afflictiō, vntil I come
in peace.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Micaiah
saide, If thou returne at all in peace, the Lord hath not spoken by
me. And he said, Hearken, O people, euery one of you.</ab>
<ab n="29">So the King of
Israel, and Iehoshaphat the king of Iudah, went vp to Ramoth
Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the king of
Israel said vnto Iehoshaphat, I wil disguise my selfe, &amp; enter
into the battell, but put thou on thy robes. And the King of Israel
disguised himselfe, &amp; went into the battell.<note> Or, when he was to disguise himselfe and enter into the battell.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">But the King of
Syria commanded his thirtie and two Captaines that had rule ouer
his charets, saying, Fight neither with small nor great, saue only
with the king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="32">And it came to
passe, when the captaines of the charets saw Iehoshaphat, that they
said, Surely it is the king of Israel. And they turned aside to
fight against him: and Iehoshaphat cryed out.</ab>
<ab n="33">And it came to
passe, when the captaines of the charets perceiued that it was not
the king of Israel, that they turned backe from pursuing
him.</ab>

<fw>Ahab dieth.</fw>
<ab n="34">And a certaine
man drew a bow at a venture, and smote the king of Israel betweene
the ioynts of the harnesse: wherefore hee sayd vnto the driuer of
his charet, Turne thine hand, and cary me out of the hoste, for I
am wounded.<note> Heb. in his simplicitie. , Heb. ioynts and the brestplate. , Heb. made sicke.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And the battell
increased that day: and the king was stayed vp in his charet
against the Syrians, and died at euen: and the blood ranne out of
the wound, into the mids of the charet.<note> Hebr. ascended. , Heb. bosome.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And there went a
proclamation throughout the hoste, about the going downe of the
Sunne, saying, Euery man to his citie, and euery man to his owne
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ So the
King died, and was brought to Samaria, and they buried the king in
Samaria.<note> Heb. came.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And one washed
the charet in the poole of Samaria, and the dogges licked vp his
blood, and they washed his armour, according vnto the word of the
Lord which he spake.<note> Chap. 21. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Now the rest of
the actes of Ahab, and all that he did, and the Iuory house which
he made, and all the cities that he built, are they not written in
the booke of the Chronicles of the Kings of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="40">So Ahab slept
with his fathers, and Ahaziah his sonne reigned in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
Iehoshaphat the sonne of Asa began to reigne ouer Iudah in the
fourth yeere of Ahab King of Israel.<note> 2. Chron. 20.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">Iehoshaphat was
thirtie and fiue yeeres olde when hee began to reigne, and he
reigned twentie and fiue yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name
was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi.</ab>

<fw>Ahaziah. Iehoram.</fw>
<ab n="43">And he walked in
all the wayes of Asa his father, hee turned not aside from it,
doing that which was right in the eyes of the Lord: neuerthelesse,
the high places were not taken away: for the people offered and
burnt incense yet in the high places.</ab>
<ab n="44">And Iehoshaphat
made peace with the king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="45">Now the rest of
the actes of Iehoshaphat, and his might that hee shewed, and how he
warred, are they not written in the booke of the Chronicles of the
Kings of Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="46">And the remnant
of the Sodomites which remained in the dayes of his father Asa, he
tooke out of the land.</ab>
<ab n="47">There was then
no king in Edom: a deputie was king.</ab>
<ab n="48">Iehoshaphat made
shippes of Tharshish to goe to Ophir for golde: but they went not,
for the shippes were broken at Ezion Geber.<note> Or, had ten ships.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">Then said
Ahaziah the sonne of Ahab vnto Iehoshaphat, Let my seruants goe
with thy seruants in the ships: But Iehoshaphat would not.</ab>
<ab n="50">¶ And
Iehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers
in the citie of Dauid his father: and Iehoram his sonne reigned in
his stead.</ab>
<ab n="51">¶ Ahaziah
the sonne of Ahab began to reigne ouer Israel in Samaria the
seuenteenth yeere of Iehoshaphat king of Iudah, and reigned two
yeres ouer Israel.</ab>
<ab n="52">And he did euill
in the sight of the Lord, and walked in the way of his father, and
in the way of his mother, and in the way of Ieroboam the sonne of
Nebat, who made Israel to sinne.</ab>
<ab n="53">For he serued
Baal, and worshipped him, and prouoked to anger the Lord God of
Israel, according vnto all that his father had done.</ab>



</div>