<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-1-1b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Abishag cherisheth Dauid in his
extreame age. 5 Adonijah, Dauids dearling, vsurpeth the kingdome.
11 By the counsel of Nathan, 15 Bath-sheba moueth the king, 22 and
Nathan secondeth her. 28 Dauid reneweth his oath to Bath-sheba. 32
Salomon by Dauids appointment, beeing annointed King by Zadok and
Nathan, the people triumph. 41 Ionathan, bringing these newes,
Adoniiahs guests flie. 50 Adonijah flying to the hornes of the
Altar, vpon his good behauiour is dismissed by
Solomon.</head>

<ab n="1">Now King Dauid was
olde, and striken in yeeres, and they couered him with clothes, but
hee gate no heate.<note> Hebr. entred into dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore his
seruants said vnto him, Let there be sought for my lord the king a
yong virgin, and let her stand before the King, and let her cherish
him, and let her lie in thy bosome, that my lord the King may get
heate.<note> Heb. let them seeke. , Hebr. a damsell, a virgine. , Heb. be a cherisher vnto him.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">So they sought for
a faire damosel throughout all the coasts of Israel, and found
Abishag a Shunammite, and brought her to the King.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the damosell
was very faire, and cherished the king, and ministred to him: but
the king knew her not.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then
Adoniiah the sonne of Haggith exalted himselfe, saying, I wil be
king: And he prepared him charets and horesemen, and fiftie men to
runne before him.<note> Heb. reigne</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And his father had
not displeased him at any time, in saying, Why hast thou done so?
And hee also was a very goodly man, and his mother bare him after
Absalom.<note> Heb. from his dayes.</note></ab>

<fw>Adonijah his treason.</fw>
<ab n="7">And hee conferred
with Ioab the sonne of Zeruiah, and with Abiathar the Priest: and
they following Adoniiah, helped him.<note> Heb. his words were with Ioab. , Heb. helped after Adonijah.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But Zadok the
Priest, and Benaiah the sonne of Iehoiada, and Nathan the Prophet,
and Shimei, and Rei, and the mightie men which belonged to Dauid,
were not with Adoniiah.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Adoniiah slew
sheepe, and oxen, and fat cattell, by the stone of Zoheleth, which
is by En-Rogel, and called all his brethren the kings sonnes, and
all the men of Iudah the kings seruants.<note> Or, the well Rogel.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But Nathan the
Prophet, and Benaiah, and the mightie men, and Solomon his brother
he called not.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Wherefore
Nathan spake vnto Bath-sheba the mother of Solomon, saying, Hast
thou not heard that Adoniiah the son of Haggith doth reigne, and
Dauid our lord knoweth it not?<note> 2.Sam 3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Now therefore
come, let mee, I pray thee, giue thee counsell, that thou mayest
saue thine owne life, and the life of thy sonne Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="13">Goe, and get thee
in vnto King Dauid, and say vnto him, Diddest not thou, my lord, O
king, sweare vnto thine handmaid, saying, Assuredly Solomon thy
sonne shall reigne after mee, and he shall sit vpon my throne? why
then doth Adoniiah reigne?</ab>
<ab n="14">Beholde, while
thou yet talkest there with the king, I also will come in after
thee, and confirme thy words.<note> Heb. fill vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And
Bath-sheba went in vnto the King into the chamber: and the king was
very olde, and Abishag the Shunammite ministred vnto the
king.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Bathsheba
bowed, and did obeysance vnto the king: and the king said, What
wouldest thou?<note> Heb. what to thee?</note></ab>

<fw>It is told Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="17">And she said vnto
him, My lord, thou swarest by the Lord thy God vnto thine handmaid,
saying, Assuredly Solomon thy sonne shall reigne after me, and he
shall sit vpon my throne:</ab>
<ab n="18">And now behold,
Adoniiah reigneth; and now my lord the king, thou knowest it
not.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he hath
slaine oxen, and fat cattell, and sheepe in abundance, and hath
called all the sonnes of the king, and Abiathar the Priest, and
Ioab the captaine of the hoste: but Solomon thy seruant hath he not
called.</ab>
<ab n="20">And thou, my lord
O king, the eyes of all Israel are vpon thee, that thou shouldest
tell them who shall sit on the throne of my lord the king after
him.</ab>
<ab n="21">Otherwise it
shall come to passe, when my lord the king shal sleepe with his
fathers, that I and my sonne Solomon shall be counted
offenders.<note> Hebr. sinners.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And loe,
while shee yet talked with the king, Nathan the Prophet also came
in.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they tolde
the king, saying, Beholde Nathan the Prophet. And when hee was come
in before the king, he bowed himselfe before the king with his face
to the ground.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Nathan said,
My lord O king, hast thou said, Adoniiah shall reigne after mee,
and hee shall sit vpon my throne?</ab>
<ab n="25">For hee is gone
downe this day, and hath slaine oxen, and fat cattel, and sheepe in
abundance, and hath called all the kings sonnes, and the captaines
of the host, and Abiathar the Priest: and behold, they eate and
drinke before him, and say, God saue king Adoniiah.<note> Hebr, Let king Adoniiah liue.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But me, euen me
thy seruant, and Zadok the Priest, and Benaiah the sonne of
Iehoiada, and thy seruant Solomon hath he not called.</ab>
<ab n="27">Is this thing
done by my lord the king, and thou hast not shewed it vnto thy
seruant, who should sit on the throne of my lord the king, after
him?</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Then king
Dauid answered, and said, Call me Bathsheba. And she came into the
kings presence, and stood before the king.<note> Hebr. before the king.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And the king
sware, and said, As the Lord liueth, that hath redeemed my soule
out of all distresse,</ab>

<fw>Solomon anointed.</fw>
<ab n="30">Euen as I sware
vnto thee by the Lord God of Israel, saying, Assuredly Solomon thy
sonne shall reigne after me, and he shal sit vpon my throne in my
stead; euen so wil I certainly doe this day.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then Bathsheba
bowed with her face to the earth, and did reuerence to the king,
and said, Let my lord king Dauid liue for euer.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And king
Dauid said, Call me Zadok the Priest, and Nathan the Prophet, and
Benaiah the sonne of Iehoiada. And they came before the
king.</ab>
<ab n="33">The king also
saide vnto them, Take with you the seruants of your lord, and cause
Solomon my sonne to ride vpon mine owne mule, and bring him downe
to Gihon.<note> Heb. which belongeth to me.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And let Zadok the
Priest, and Nathan the Prophet, anoint him there King ouer Israel:
and blow ye with the trumpet, and say, God saue King
Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="35">Then ye shall
come vp after him, that hee may come and sit vpon my throne; for he
shall be king in my stead: and I haue appointed him to be ruler
ouer Israel, and ouer Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Benaiah the
sonne of Iehoiada answered the King, and said, Amen: The Lord God
of my lord the king say so too.</ab>
<ab n="37">As the Lord hath
bene with my lord the King, euen so be he with Solomon, and make
his throne greater then the throne of my lord King Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="38">So Zadok the
Priest, and Nathan the Prophet, and Benaiah the sonne of Iehoiada,
and the Cherethites, and the Pelethites went downe, and caused
Solomon to ride vpon King Dauids mule, and brought him to
Gihon.</ab>
<ab n="39">And Zadok the
Priest tooke an horne of oile out of the Tabernacle, and anointed
Solomon: and they blew the trumpet, and all the people said, God
saue King Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="40">And all the
people came vp after him, and the people piped with pipes, and
reioyced with great ioy, so that the earth rent with the sound of
them.<note> Or, flutes.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
Adoniiah and all the ghests that were with him, heard it as they
had made an end of eating: and when Ioab heard the sound of the
trumpet, hee said, Wherefore is this noise of the citie, being in
an vproare?</ab>

<fw>Adonijah yeeldeth.</fw>
<ab n="42">And while hee yet
spake, behold, Ionathan the sonne of Abiathar the Priest came, and
Adoniiah sayde vnto him, Come in, for thou art a valiant man, and
bringest good tidings.</ab>
<ab n="43">And Ionathan
answered, and said to Adoniiah, Uerily our lorde king Dauid hath
made Solomon king.</ab>
<ab n="44">And the king hath
sent with him Zadok the Priest, and Nathan the Prophet, and Benaiah
the sonne of Iehoiada, and the Cherethites, and the Pelethites, and
they haue caused him to ride vpon the kings mule.</ab>
<ab n="45">And Zadok the
Priest, and Nathan the Prophet haue anointed him king in Gihon: and
they are come vp from thence reioycing, so that the citie rang
againe: this is the noyse that yee haue heard.</ab>
<ab n="46">And also Solomon
sitteth on the throne of the kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="47">And moreouer, the
kings seruants came to blesse our lorde king Dauid, saying, God
make the name of Solomon better then thy name, and make his throne
greater then thy throne. And the king bowed himselfe vpon the
bed.</ab>
<ab n="48">And also thus
sayde the King, Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, which hath giuen
one to sit on my throne this day, mine eyes euen seeing it.</ab>
<ab n="49">And all the
guests that were with Adoniiah, were afraid, and rose vp, and went
euery man his way.</ab>
<ab n="50">¶ And
Adoniiah feared because of Solomon, and arose, and went, and caught
hold on the hornes of the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="51">And it was tolde
Solomon, saying, Behold, Adoniiah feareth King Solomon: for loe, he
hath caught hold on the hornes of the Altar, saying, Let King
Solomon sweare vnto mee to day, that hee will not slay his seruant
with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="52">And Solomon sayd,
If hee will shewe himselfe a worthy man, there shall not an haire
of him fall to the earth: but if wickednesse shall be found in him,
he shall die.</ab>
<ab n="53">So king Solomon
sent, and they brought him downe from the Altar, and hee came and
bowed himselfe to king Solomou: and Solomon sayde vnto him, Goe to
thine house.</ab>



</div>