<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 The building of Solomons house. 2
Of the house of Lebanon. 6 Of the porch of pillars. 7 Of the porch
of Iudgement. 8 Of the house for Pharaohs daughter. 13 Hirams worke
of the two pillars. 23 Of the molten Sea. 27 Of the ten bases. 38
Of the ten lauers, 40 And all the vessels.</head>

<ab n="1">But Solomon was
building his owne house thirteene yeres, and he finished all his
house.<note> Chap.9. 10.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons house.</fw>
<ab n="2">¶ Hee built
also the house of the forrest of Lebanon; the length thereof was a
hundred cubites, and the breadth thereof fiftie cubites, and the
height thereof thirtie cubites, vpon foure rowes of Cedar pillars,
with Cedar beames vpon the pillars.</ab>
<ab n="3">And it was couered
with Cedar aboue vpon the beames, that lay on fortie fiue pillars,
fifteene in a row.<note> Heb. ribs.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And there were
windowes in three rowes, and light was against light in three
rankes.<note> Hebr. sight against sight.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And all the doores
and postes were square, with the windowes: and light was against
light in three rankes.<note> Or, spaces and pillars were square in prospect.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And he made
a porch of pillars, the length thereof was fiftie cubites, and the
breadth thereof thirtie cubites: and the porch was before them: and
the other pillars, and the thicke beame were before
them.<note> Or, according to them. , Or, according to them.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Then hee
made a porch for the throne where he might iudge, euen the porch of
Iudgement: and it was couered with Cedar from one side of the
floore to the other.<note> Hebr. from floore to floore.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And his
house where he dwelt, had another court within the porch, which was
of the like worke: Solomon made also an house for Pharaohs
daughter, ( whom he had taken to wife) like vnto this
porch.<note> Chap.3.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">All these were of
costly stones, according to the measures of hewed stones, sawed
with sawes, within and without, euen from the foundation vnto the
coping, and so on the outside toward the great court.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
foundation was of costly stones, euen great stones; stones of ten
cubites, and stones of eight cubites.</ab>
<ab n="11">And aboue were
costly stones (after the measures of hewed stones) and
Cedars.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the great
court round about, was with three rowes of hewed stones, and a row
of Cedar beames, both for the inner court of the house of the Lord,
and for the porch of the house.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And king
Solomon sent and fet Hiram out of Tyre.</ab>
<ab n="14">Hee was a widowes
sonne of the tribe of Naphtali, and his father was a man of Tyre, a
worker in brasse, and he was filled with wisedome, and
vnderstanding, and cunning to worke all workes in brasse: and hee
came to king Solomon, and wrought all his worke.<note> Hebr. the sonne of a widow woman.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For he cast two
pillars of brasse of eighteene cubites high a piece: and a line of
twelue cubites did compasse either of them about.<note> Hebr. fashioned.</note></ab>

<fw>The moulten Sea.</fw>
<ab n="16">And hee made two
Chapiters of molten brasse, to set vpon the tops of the pillars:
the height of the one chapiter was fiue cubites, and the height of
the other chapiter was fiue cubites:</ab>
<ab n="17">And nets of
checker worke, and wreathes of chaine worke, for the chapiters
which were vpon the top of the pillars: seuen for the one chapiter,
and seuen for the other chapiter.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he made the
pillars, and two rowes round about vpon the one networke, to couer
the chapiters that were vpon the top, with pomegranates: and so did
he for the other chapiter.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the chapiters
that were vpon the top of the pillars, were of lillie worke in the
porch, foure cubites.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the chapiters
vpon the two pillars had pomegranates also, aboue, ouer against the
belly which was by the networke: and the pomegranates were two
hundred in rowes round about, vpon the other chapiter.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he set vp the
pillars in the porch of the temple: and hee set vp the right
pillar, and called the name therof Iachin: and he set vp the left
pillar, and called the name thereof Boaz.<note> 2.Chr.3. 17. , That is, he shall establish. , That is, in it is strength</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And vpon the top
of the pillars was lillie worke: so was the worke of the pillars
finished.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And he
made a moulten Sea, ten cubites from the one brim to the other: it
was round all about, &amp; his height was fiue cubits: and a line
of thirtie cubites did compasse it round about.<note> Heb. from his brimme, to his brim.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And vnder the
brimme of it round about there were knops compassing it, ten in a
cubite, compassing the sea round about: the knops were cast in two
rowes, when it was cast.<note> 2.Chron. 4.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">It stood vpon
twelue oxen, three looking toward the North, and three looking
toward the West, and three looking toward the South, and three
looking toward the East: and the Sea was set aboue vpon them, and
all their hinder parts were inward.</ab>
<ab n="26">And it was an
hand breadth thicke, and the brimme thereof was wrought like the
brim of a cup, with flowres of lillies: it contained two thousand
Baths.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And he
made ten bases of brasse; foure cubites was the length of one base,
and foure cubites the breadth thereof, and three cubites the height
of it.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the worke of
the bases was on this maner: they had borders, and the borders were
betweene the ledges:</ab>

<fw>The ten bases.</fw>
<ab n="29">And on the
borders that were betweene the ledges were lyons, oxen, and
Cherubims: and vpon the ledges there was a base aboue: and beneath
the lyons and oxen were certaine additions made of thinne
worke.</ab>
<ab n="30">And euery base
had foure brasen wheeles, and plates of brasse: and the foure
corners therof had vndersetters: vnder the lauer were vndersetters
molten, at the side of euery addition.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the mouth of
it within the chapiter, and aboue, was a cubite: but the mouth
thereof was round after the worke of the base, a cubite and an
halfe: and also vpon the mouth of it were grauings with their
borders, foure square not round.</ab>
<ab n="32">And vnder the
borders were foure wheeles: &amp; the axletrees of the wheeles were
ioyned to the base, and the height of a wheele was a cubite and
halfe a cubite.<note> Heb. in the base.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the worke of
the wheeles was like the worke of a charet wheele: their axletrees
and their naues, and their felloes, and their spokes were all
molten.</ab>
<ab n="34">And there were
foure vndersetters to the foure corners of one base: and the
vndersetters were of the very base it selfe.</ab>
<ab n="35">And in the top of
the base was there a round compasse of halfe a cubite high: and on
the top of the base the ledges thereof, and the borders thereof
were of the same.</ab>
<ab n="36">For on the plates
of the ledges thereof, and on the borders thereof, he graued
Cherubims, lions, and palme trees, according to the proportion of
euery one, and additions round about.<note> Heb. nakednesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">After this maner
he made the ten bases: all of them had one casting, one measure,
and one size.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ Then made
hee ten lauers of brasse: one lauer conteined fourtie baths: and
euery lauer was foure cubites, and vpon euery one of the ten bases,
one lauer.</ab>
<ab n="39">And he put fiue
bases on the right side of the house, and fiue on the left side of
the house: and he set the Sea on the right side of the house
Eastward, ouer against the South.<note> Heb. shoulder.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">¶ And Hiram
made the lauers, and the shouels, and the basons: So Hiram made an
ende of doing all the worke that hee made King Solomon, for the
house of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Diuers vessels. The Temple
dedicated.</fw>
<ab n="41">The two pillars,
and the two bowles of the chapiters that were on the top of the two
pillars: and the two networkes, to couer the two bowles of the
chapiters which were vpon the top of the pillars:</ab>
<ab n="42">And foure hundred
Pomegranates for the two networkes, euen two rowes of Pomegranates
for one networke, to couer the two bowles of the chapiters that
were vpon the pillars:<note> Hebr. vpon the face.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And the ten
bases, and ten lauers on the bases.</ab>
<ab n="44">And one Sea, and
twelue oxen vnder the Sea.</ab>
<ab n="45">And the pots, and
the shouels, and the basons: and all these vessels which Hiram made
to King Solomon, for the house of the Lord, were of bright
brasse.<note> Hebr. made bright, or scoured.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">In the plaine of
Iordane did the king cast them in the clay ground, betweene Succoth
and Zarthan.<note> Hebr. in the thicknesse of the ground.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And Solomon left
all the vessels vnweighed, because they were exceeding many:
neither was the weight of the brasse found out.<note> Hebr. for the exceeding multitude. , Hebr. searched.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And Solomon made
all the vessels that pertained vnto the house of the Lord: the
Altar of gold, and the table of gold, whereupon the Shewbread
was:</ab>
<ab n="49">And the
candlesticks of pure gold, fiue on the right side, and fiue on the
left, before the Oracle, with the flowers, and the lampes, and the
tongs of gold,</ab>
<ab n="50">And the boules,
and the snuffers, and the basons, &amp; the spoones, and the
censers of pure gold: and the hindges of gold, both for the doores
of the inner house the most Holy place, and for the doores of the
house, to wit, of the temple.<note> Heb. ash-pans.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">So was ended all
the worke that king Solomon made for the house of the Lord: and
Solomon brought in the things which Dauid his father had dedicated,
euen the siluer, and the gold, &amp; the vessels did he put among
the treasures of the house of the Lord.<note> Heb. things of Dauid. , 2.Chron.5.1.</note></ab>



</div>