<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-20-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Benhadad not content with Ahabs
hommage, besiegeth Samaria. 13 By the direction of a Prophet, the
Syrians are slaine. 22 As the Prophet forewarned Ahab, the Syrians
trusting in the valleys, come against him in Aphek. 28 By the word
of the Prophet, and Gods iudgment, the Syrians are smitten againe.
31 The Syrians submitting themselues, Ahab sendeth Benhadad away
with a couenant. 35 The Prophet vnder the parable of a prisoner,
making Ahab to iudge himselfe, denounceth Gods iudgement against
him.</head>

<ab n="1">And Benhadad the
King of Syria gathered all his hoste together, and there were
thirtie and two kings with him, and horses, and charets: and hee
went vp and besieged Samaria, and warred against it.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee sent
messengers to Ahab king of Israel, into the city, and saide vnto
him, Thus saith Benhadad,</ab>
<ab n="3">Thy siluer and
thy gold is mine, thy wiues also, and thy children, euen the
goodliest, are mine.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the king of
Israel answered, and said, My lord O king, according to thy saying,
I am thine, and all that I haue.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the
messengers came againe, and saide, Thus speaketh Benhadad, saying,
Although I haue sent vnto thee, saying, Thou shalt deliuer me thy
siluer, and thy gold, and thy wiues, and thy children:</ab>

<fw>Benhadads crueltie.</fw>
<ab n="6">Yet I will send
my seruants vnto thee to morrow about this time, and they shall
search thine house, and the houses of thy seruants; and it shall
be, that whatsoeuer is pleasant in thine eies, they shall put it in
their hand, and take it away.<note> Heb desirable.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then the king of
Israel called all the Elders of the land, and saide; Marke, I pray
you, and see how this man seeketh mischiefe: for hee sent vnto me
for my wiues, and for my children, and for my siluer, and for my
gold, and I denied him not.<note> Heb. I kept not backe from him.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And all the
Elders, and all the people said vnto him; Hearken not vnto him, nor
consent.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore hee
said vnto the messengers of Benhadad, Tell my lord the king, All
that thou diddest send for to thy seruant at the first, I will doe:
but this thing I may not doe. And the messengers departed, and
brought him word againe.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Benhadad
sent vnto him, and said, The gods doe so vnto me and more also, if
the dust of Samaria shall suffice for handfuls for all the people
that follow me.<note> Heb. are at my feete.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the king of
Israel answered, and said, Tell him, Let not him that girdeth on
his harnesse, boast himselfe, as he that putteth it off.</ab>
<ab n="12">And it came to
passe, when Benhadad heard this message (as hee was drinking, he
and the kings in the pauilions) that hee said vnto his seruants,
Set yourselues in aray. And they set themselues in aray against the
citie.<note> Heb. word. , Or, Tents. , Or, place the engins: and they placed engines.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
behold, there came a Prophet vnto Ahab king of Israel, saying, Thus
saith the Lord, Hast thou seene all this great multitude? behold, I
will deliuer it into thine hand this day, and thou shalt knowe that
I am the Lord.<note> Heb. approched.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Ahab saide,
By whom? and he saide, Thus saith the Lord, Euen by the young men
of the Princes of the prouinces: Then he said, Who shall order the
battell? And hee answered, Thou.<note> Or, seruants. , Heb. Bynd, or, tie.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then he numbred
the young men of the Princes of the prouinces, and they were two
hundred and thirty two: and after them hee numbred all the people,
euen all the children of Israel, being seuen thousand.</ab>

<fw>The Syrians are put to flight.</fw>
<ab n="16">And they went
out at noone: But Benhadad was drinking himselfe drunke in the
pauilions, hee and the kings, the thirty and two kings that helped
him.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the young
men of the Princes of the Prouinces went out first, and Benhadad
sent out, and they told him, saying, There are men come out of
Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he said,
Whether they be come out for peace, take them aliue: or whether
they be come out for warre, take them aliue.</ab>
<ab n="19">So these yong
men of the princes of the prouinces, came out of the citie, and the
armie which followed them:</ab>
<ab n="20">And they slew
euery one his man: and the Syrians fled, and Israel pursued them:
and Benhadad the king of Syria escaped on an horse, with the
horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the king of
Israel went out, and smote the horses and charets, and slewe the
Syrians with a great slaughter.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
Prophet came to the king of Israel, and said vnto him, Goe,
strengthen thy selfe, and marke and see what thou doest: for at the
returne of the yeere, the king of Syria will come vp against
thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the seruants
of the King of Syria said vnto him, Their gods are gods of the
hilles, therefore they were stronger then wee: but let vs fight
against them in the plaine, and surely we shall be stronger then
they.</ab>
<ab n="24">And doe this
thing, Take the kings away, euery man out of his place, and put
captaines in their roumes.</ab>
<ab n="25">And number thee
an armie, like the armie that thou hast lost, horse for horse, and
charet for charet: and wee will fight against them in the plaine,
and surely wee shall be stronger then they. And hee hearkened vnto
their voice, and did so.<note> Heb. that was fallen.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And it came to
passe at the returne of the yeere, that Benhadad numbred the
Syrians, and went vp to Aphek, to fight against Israel.<note> Heb. to the warre with Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the children
of Israel were numbred, and were all present, and went against
them: and the children of Israel pitched before them, like two
little flockes of kids: but the Syrians filled the
countrey.<note> Or, were victualled.</note></ab>

<fw>The Syrians are put to flight.</fw>
<ab n="28">¶ And there
came a man of God, and spake vnto the king of Israel, and sayd,
Thus sayth the Lord, Because the Syrians haue sayde, The Lord is
God of the hilles, but hee is not God of the valleys: therefore
will I deliuer all this great multitude into thine hand, and yee
shall know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">And they pitched
one ouer against the other seuen daies, and so it was, that in the
seuenth day the battell was ioyned: and the children of Israel
slewe of the Syrians an hundred thousand footmen in one
day.</ab>
<ab n="30">But the rest
fled to Aphek, into the citie, and there a wall fell vpon twentie
and seuen thousand of the men that were left: and Benhadad fled,
and came into the citie, into an inner chamber.<note> Or, from chamber to chamber. Heb. into a chamber within a chamber.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And his
seruants said vnto him, Behold now, wee haue heard that the kings
of the house of Israel are mercifull kings: let vs, I pray thee,
put sackcloth on our loines, and ropes vpon our heads, and goe out
to the king of Israel; peraduenture he will saue thy life.</ab>
<ab n="32">So they girded
sackcloth on their loynes, and put ropes on their heads, and came
to the king of Israel, and said, Thy seruant Benhadad saith, I pray
thee, let me liue. And he said, Is he yet aliue? he is my
brother.</ab>
<ab n="33">Now the men did
diligently obserue whether any thing would come from him, and did
hastily catch it: and they saide, Thy brother Benhadad. Then he
said, Goe ye, bring him: then Benhadad came forth to him: and hee
caused him to come vp into the charet.</ab>
<ab n="34">And Benhadad
said vnto him, The cities which my father tooke from thy father, I
will restore, and thou shalt make streets for thee in Damascus, as
my father made in Samaria. Then, said Ahab, I will send thee away
with this couenant. So he made a couenant with him, and sent him
away.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And a
certaine man of the sonnes of the Prophets, saide vnto his
neighbour in the word of the Lord, Smite me, I pray thee. And the
man refused to smite him.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then said he
vnto him, Because thou hast not obeyed the voyce of the Lord,
beholde, assoone as thou art departed from me, a lyon shal slay
thee. And assoone as hee was departed from him, a lyon found him,
and slew him.</ab>

<fw>Ahab reproued.</fw>
<ab n="37">Then he found
another man, and said, Smite me, I pray thee. And the man smote
him, so that in smiting hee wounded him.<note> Hebr. smiting and wounding.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">So the prophet
departed, and waited for the king by the way, and disguised
himselfe with ashes vpon his face.</ab>
<ab n="39">And as the king
passed by, he cried vnto the king: and he saide, Thy seruant went
out into the mids of the battell, and behold, a man turned aside,
and brought a man vnto me, and said, Keep this man: if by any
meanes he be missing, then shall thy life be for his life, or else
thou shalt pay a talent of siluer.<note> Heb. weigh</note></ab>
<ab n="40">And as thy
seruant was busie here and there, he was gone. And the king of
Israel saide vnto him, So shall thy iudgement bee, thy selfe hast
discided it.<note> Heb. hee was not.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And he hasted,
and tooke the ashes away from his face, and the king of Israel
discerned him that hee was of the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="42">And hee said
vnto him, Thus saith the Lord, Because thou hast let goe out of thy
hand, a man whom I appointed to vtter destruction, therfore thy
life shall goe for his life, and thy people for his
people.<note> Chap.22. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And the king of
Israel went to his house, heauie, and displeased, and came to
Samaria.</ab>



</div>