<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Abiiams wicked reigne. 7 Asa
succeedeth him. 9 Asas good reigne. 16 The warre betweene Baasha
and him, causeth him to make a league with Benhadad. 23 Iehoshaphat
succeedeth Asa. 25 Nadabs wicked reigne. 27 Baasha conspiring
against him executeth Ahiiahs prophecy. 31 Nadabs acts and death.
33 Baashas wicked reigne.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe in the
eighteenth yeere of king Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, reigned
Abiiam ouer Iudah.<note> 2.Chro. 11.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Three yeeres
reigned hee in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was Maachah, the
daughter of Abishalom.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he walked in
all the sinnes of his father, which hee had done before him: and
his heart was not perfect with the Lord his God, as the heart of
Dauid his father.</ab>

<fw>Abijam. Asa. Baasha.</fw>
<ab n="4">Neuerthelesse,
for Dauids sake did the Lord his God giue him a lampe in Ierusalem,
to set vp his sonne after him, and to establish
Ierusalem:<note> Or, candle.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Because Dauid did
that which was right in the eies of the Lord, and turned not aside
from any thing that he commanded him all the daies of his life,
saue onely in the matter of Uriiah the Hittite.<note> 2.Sam.11 4. and 12.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And there was
warre betweene Rehoboam and Ieroboam all the dayes of his
life.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now the rest of
the actes of Abiiam, and all that hee did, are they not written in
the booke of the Chronicles of the Kings of Iudah? And there was
warre betweene Abiiam and Ieroboam.<note> 2. Chron. 13.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Abiiam slept
with his fathers, and they buried him in the citie of Dauid: and
Asa his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And in the
twentieth yeere of Ieroboam king of Israel, reigned Asa ouer
Iudah.<note> 2. Chron. 14.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And forty and
one yeeres reigned hee in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was
Maachah, the daughter of Abishalom.<note> That is, grandmother.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Asa did that
which was right in the eies of the Lord, as did Dauid his
father.</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee tooke
away the Sodomites out of the land, and remooued all the idoles
that his fathers had made.</ab>
<ab n="13">And also Maachah
his mother, euen her hee remoued from being Queene, because she had
made an idole in a groue, and Asa destroyed her idole, and burnt it
by the brooke Kidron.<note> 2. Chron. 15.16. , Heb. cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But the high
places were not remooued: neuerthelesse, Asa his heart was perfect
with the Lord all his dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he brought
in the things which his father had dedicated, and the things which
himselfe had dedicated, into the house of the Lord, siluer, and
gold, and vessels.<note> Heb. holy.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And there
was war betweene Asa and Baasha King of Israel all their
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Baasha king
of Israel went vp against Iudah, and built Ramah, that he might not
suffer any to goe out or come in to Asa king of Iudah.</ab>

<fw>Asa and Benhadad.</fw>
<ab n="18">Then Asa tooke
all the siluer and the golde that were left in the treasures of the
house of the Lord, and the treasures of the kings house, and
deliuered them into the hand of his seruants: and king Asa sent
them to Benhadad the sonne of Tabrimon, the sonne of Hezion king of
Syria, that dwelt at Damascus, saying,<note> 2. Chron. 16. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">There is a
league betweene me and thee, and betweene my father and thy father:
behold, I haue sent vnto thee a present of siluer and gold; come
and breake the league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may
depart from me.<note> Hebr. goe vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">So Benhadad
hearkened vnto king Asa, and sent the captaines of the hosts, which
he had, against the cities of Israel, and smote Iion, and Dan, and
Abel-Bethmaachah, and all Cinneroth, with all the land of
Naphtali.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it came to
passe when Baasha heard thereof, that hee left off building of
Ramah, and dwelt in Tirzah.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then king Asa
made a Proclamation throughout all Iudah, (none was exempted:) and
they tooke away the stones of Ramah, and the timber thereof
wherewith Baasha had builded, and king Asa built with them Geba of
Beniamin, and Mizpah.<note> Hebr. free.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The rest of all
the acts of Asa, and all his might, and all that he did, and the
cities which hee built, are they not written in the booke of the
Chronicles of the Kings of Iudah? Neuerthelesse in the time of his
old age, hee was diseased in his feete.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Asa slept
with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers, in the citie of
Dauid his father: and Iehoshaphat his sonne reigned in his
stead.<note> Matth 1. 8. called Iosaphat.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And Nadab
the sonne of Ieroboam began to reigne ouer Israel, in the second
yeere of Asa king of Iudah, and reigned ouer Israel two
yeeres.<note> Hebr. reigned.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And he did euill
in the sight of the Lord, and walked in the way of his father, and
in his sinne wherewith hee made Israel to sinne.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And
Baasha the sonne of Ahiiah, of the house of Issachar, conspired
against him, and Baasha smote him at Gibbethon, which belongeth to
the Philistines, (for Nadab and all Israel layd siege to
Gibbethon,)</ab>

<fw>Nadab. Baasha.</fw>
<ab n="28">Euen in the
third yeere of Asa king of Iudah, did Baasha slay him, and reigned
in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="29">And it came to
passe when hee raigned, that he smote all the house Ieroboam, hee
left not to Ieroboam any that breathed, vntill hee had destroyed
him, according vnto the saying of the Lord, which hee spake by his
seruant Ahiiah the Shilonite:<note> Chap. 14. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Because of the
sinnes of Ieroboam which he sinned, and which hee made Israel
sinne, by his prouocation wherewith he prouoked the Lord God of
Israel to anger.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Now the
rest of the acts of Nadab, and all that hee did, are they not
written in the booke of the Chronicles of the Kings of
Israel?</ab>
<ab n="32">And there was
warre betweene Asa and Baasha king of Israel al their
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="33">In the third
yeere of Asa King of Iudah, began Baasha the sonne of Ahiiah to
reigne ouer all Israel in Tirzah, twentie and foure yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="34">And hee did
euill in the sight of the Lord, and walked in the way of Ieroboam,
and in his sinne wherewith he made Israel to sinne.</ab>



</div>