<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Solomons wiues and concubines. 4
In his old age they draw him to idolatry. 9 God threatneth him. 14
Solomons aduersaries were Hadad, who was intertained in Egypt, 23
Rezon who reigned in Damascus, 26 And Ieroboam, to whom Ahiiah
prophesied. 41 Solomons actes, reigne, and death: Rehoboam
succeedeth him.</head>

<ab n="1">But King Solomon
loued many strange women, ( together with þe
daughter of Pharaoh) women of the Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites,
Sidonians &amp; Hittites:<note> Deut.17. 17. ecclus. 49.19. , Or, besids</note></ab>

<fw>His wiues, idolatries, and
aduersaries.</fw>
<ab n="2">Of the nations
concerning which the Lord said vnto the children of Israel, Yee
shall not goe in to them, neither shall they come in vnto you, for
surely they will turne away your heart after their gods: Solomon
claue vnto these in loue.<note> Exod. 34. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And he had seuen
hundred wiues, Princesses, and three hundred concubines: and his
wiues turned away his heart.</ab>
<ab n="4">For it came to
passe when Solomon was old, that his wiues turned away his heart
after other gods: and his heart was not perfect with the Lord his
God, as was the heart of Dauid his father.</ab>
<ab n="5">For Solomon went
after Ashtoreth the goddesse of the Zidonians, and after Milcom the
abomination of the Amorites.<note> Iudg.2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Solomon did
euill in the sight of the Lord, and went not fully after the Lord,
as did Dauid his father.<note> Hebr. fulfilled not after.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then did Solomon
build an hie place for Chemosh the abomination of Moab, in the hill
that is before Ierusalem, and for Molech the abomination of the
children of Ammon.</ab>
<ab n="8">And likewise did
hee for all his strange wiues, which burnt incense and sacrificed
vnto their gods.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
Lord was angry with Solomon, because his heart was turned from the
Lord God of Israel which had appeared vnto him twise,<note> Chap.3. 5.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And had
commaunded him concerning this thing, that hee should not goe after
other gods: but hee kept not that which the Lord
commanded.<note> Chap.6. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore the
Lord said vnto Solomon; Forasmuch as this is done of thee, and thou
hast not kept my Couenant, and my Statutes which I haue commanded
thee, I wil surely rend the kingdome from thee, and will giue it to
thy seruant.<note> Hebr. is with thee. , Chap.12.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Notwithstanding
in thy dayes I wil not doe it, for Dauid thy fathers sake: but I
wil rend it out of the hand of thy sonne.</ab>
<ab n="13">Howbeit, I wil
not rend away all the kingdome: but wil giue one tribe to thy
sonne, for Dauid my seruants sake, and for Ierusalems sake, which I
haue chosen.</ab>

<fw>His wiues, idolatries, and
aduersaries.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ And the
Lord stirred vp an aduersary vnto Solomon, Hadad the Edomite: hee
was of the kings seed in Edom.</ab>
<ab n="15">For it came to
passe when Dauid was in Edom, and Ioab the captaine of the host was
gone vp to bury the slaine, after he had smitten euery male in
Edom:<note> 2.Sam.8. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">(For sixe
moneths did Ioab remaine there with all Israel, vntil hee had cut
off euery male in Edom.)</ab>
<ab n="17">That Hadad fled,
he and certaine Edomites of his fathers seruants with him, to goe
into Egypt: Hadad being yet a litle childe.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they arose
out of Midian, and came to Paran, and they tooke men with them out
of Paran, and they came to Egypt, vnto Pharaoh king of Egypt, which
gaue him an house, and appointed him vitailes, and gaue him
land.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Hadad found
great fauour in the sight of Pharaoh, so that he gaue him to wife
the sister of his owne wife, the sister of Tahpenes the
Queene.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the sister
of Tahpenes bare him Genubath his sonne, whom Tahpenes weaned in
Pharaohs house: and Genubath was in Pharaohs houshold among the
sonnes of Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when Hadad
heard in Egypt that Dauid slept with his fathers, and that Ioab the
captaine of the host was dead, Hadad said to Pharaoh, Let me
depart, that I may go to mine owne countrey.<note> Heb. send me away.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then Pharaoh
said vnto him, But what hast thou lacked with mee, that, behold,
thou seekest to goe to thine owne countrey? And hee answered,
Nothing: Howbeit, let mee goe in any wise.<note> Heb. Not.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And God
stirred him vp another aduersary: Rezon, the sonne of Eliadah,
which fled from his lord Hadadezer king of Zobah:<note> 2.Sam.8. 3.and 10. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And he gathered
men vnto him, and became captaine ouer a band, when Dauid slew them
of Zobah: and they went to Damascus, and dwelt therein, and reigned
in Damascus.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he was an
aduersarie to Israel all the dayes of Solomon, beside the mischiefe
that Hadad did: and he abhorred Israel, and reigned ouer
Syria.</ab>

<fw>Ahijah. Ieroboam.</fw>
<ab n="26">¶ And
Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, an Ephrathite of Zereda, Solomons
seruant, (whose mothers name was Zeruah a widow woman) euen he lift
vp his hand against the king.<note> 2. Chron. 13.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And this was the
cause that hee lift vp his hand against the king: Solomon built
Millo, and repaired the breaches of the citie of Dauid his
father.<note> Hebr. closed.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And the man
Ieroboam was a mightie man of valour: and Solomon seeing the young
man that he was industrious, hee made him ruler ouer all the charge
of the house of Ioseph.<note> Heb. did worke. , Hebr. burden.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And it came to
passe at that time when Ieroboam went out of Ierusalem, that the
Prophet Ahiiah the Shilonite found him in the way: and hee had clad
himselfe with a new garment; and they two were alone in the
field.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Ahiiah
caught the new garment that was on him, and rent it in twelue
pieces.</ab>
<ab n="31">And he said to
Ieroboam, Take thee tenne pieces: for thus sayth the Lord the God
of Israel, Behold, I will rent the kingdome out of the hand of
Solomon, and will giue ten tribes to thee:</ab>
<ab n="32">(But hee shall
haue one tribe, for my seruant Dauids sake, and for Ierusalems
sake, the citie which I haue chosen out of all the tribes of
Israel:)</ab>
<ab n="33">Because that
they haue forsaken mee, and haue worshipped Ashtaroth the goddesse
of the Zidonians, Chemosh the god of the Moabites, and Milcom the
god of the children of Anunon, and haue not walked in my wayes, to
doe that which is right in mine eyes, and to keepe my Statutes, and
my Iudgements, as did Dauid his father.</ab>
<ab n="34">Howbeit, I will
not take the whole kingdome out of his hand: but I will make him
Prince all the dayes of his life, for Dauid my seruants sake, whom
I chose, because hee kept my Commandements and my Statutes:</ab>
<ab n="35">But I will take
the kingdome out of his sonnes hand, and will giue it vnto thee,
euen ten tribes.<note> Chap.12. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And vnto his
sonne will I giue one tribe, that Dauid my seruant may haue a light
alway before me in Ierusalem, the citie which I haue chosen me to
put my Name there.<note> Heb. lampe or candle.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And I will take
thee, and thou shalt reigne according to all that thy soule
desireth, and shalt be King ouer Israel.</ab>

<fw>Solomons death.</fw>
<ab n="38">And it shall be,
if thou wilt hearken vnto all that I command thee, and wilt walke
in my wayes, and doe that is right in my sight, to keepe my
Statutes and my Commandements, as Dauid my seruant did; that I will
be with thee, and build thee a sure house, as I built for Dauid,
and will giue Israel vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="39">And I will for
this afflict the seed of Dauid, but not for euer.</ab>
<ab n="40">Solomon sought
therefore to kill Ieroboam, and Ieroboam arose, and fledde into
Egypt, vnto Shishak king of Egypt, and was in Egypt vntill the
death of Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And the
rest of the actes of Solomon, and all that he did, and his
wisedome, are they not written in the booke of the actes of
Solomon?<note> Or, words, or things.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And the time
that Solomon reigned in Ierusalem, ouer all Israel, was fourtie
yeeres.<note> Heb. dayes. , 2.Chron. 9.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And Solomon
slept with his fathers, and was buried in the citie of Dauid his
father: and Rehoboam his sonne reigned in his stead.<note> Mat.1.7. called Roboam.</note></ab>



</div>