<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Eliiah threatned by Iezebel,
fleeth to Beersheba, 4 In the wildernesse being wearie of his life,
is comforted by an Angel. 9 At Horeb God appeareth vnto him,
sending him to anoint Hazael, Iehu, and Elisha. 19 Elisha taking
leaue of his friends, followeth Elijah.</head>

<ab n="1">And Ahab told
Iezebel all that Eliiah had done, and withall, how hee had slaine
all the Prophets with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then Iezebel sent
a messenger vnto Eliiah, saying; So let the gods do to me, and more
also, if I make not thy life as the life of one of them, by to
morrow about this time.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when he saw
that, hee arose, and went for his life, and came to Beersheba,
which belongeth to Iudah, and left his seruant there.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ But he
himselfe went a dayes iourney into the wildernesse, and came and
sate downe vnder a Iuniper tree: and hee requested for himselfe
that hee might die, and sayd, It is enough, now O Lord, take away
my life: for I am not better then my fathers.<note> Heb. for his life.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And as hee lay
and slept vnder a Iuniper tree, behold then, an Angel touched him,
and sayd vnto him, Arise, and eate.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he looked,
and behold, there was a cake baken on the coales, and a cruse of
water at his head: and hee did eate and drinke, and laide him downe
againe.<note> Heb. bolster.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the Angel of
the Lord came againe the second time, and touched him, and sayd,
Arise, and eate, because the iourney is too great for thee.</ab>

<fw>He talketh with God.</fw>
<ab n="8">And hee arose,
and did eate and drinke, and went in the strength of that meate
fourtie dayes and fourtie nights, vnto Horeb the mount of
God.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And he
came thither vnto a caue, and lodged there, and behold, the word of
the Lord came to him, and he said vnto him, What doest thou here,
Eliiah?</ab>
<ab n="10">And hee sayd, I
haue beene very iealous for the Lord God of hostes: for the
children of Israel haue forsaken thy Couenant, throwen downe thine
Altars, and slaine thy Prophets with the sword: and I, euen I onely
am left, and they seeke my life, to take it away.<note> Rom.11.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And he sayd, Goe
forth, and stand vpon the mount before the Lord. And beholde, the
Lord passed by, and a great and strong winde rent the mountaines,
and brake in pieces the rockes, before the Lord; but the Lord was
not in the winde: and after the winde an earthquake, but the Lord
was not in the earthquake.</ab>
<ab n="12">And after the
earthquake, a fire, but the Lord was not in the fire: and after the
fire, a still small voice.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it was so,
when Eliiah heard it, that he wrapped his face in his mantle, and
went out, and stood in the entring in of the caue: and behold,
there came a voice vnto him, and sayd, What doest thou here,
Eliiah?</ab>
<ab n="14">And he sayd, I
haue beene very iealous for the Lord God of hostes, because the
children of Israel haue forsaken thy Couenant, throwen downe thine
Altars, and slaine thy Prophets with the sword, and I, euen I onely
am left, and they seeke my life, to take it away.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Lord
sayd vnto him, Goe, returne on thy way to the wildernesse of
Damascus: and when thou commest, anoint Hazael to be King ouer
Syria.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Iehu the
sonne of Nimshi shalt thou anoint to bee king ouer Israel: and
Elisha the sonne of Shaphat of Abel Meholah, shalt thou annoint to
be Prophet in thy roume.<note> Luk.4.27 called Eliseus.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And it shall
come to passe, that him that escapeth the sword of Hazael, shall
Iehu slay: and him that escapeth from the sword of Iehu, shall
Elisha slay.<note> 2.King. 9.1,3. ecclus.48.8.</note></ab>

<fw>Elisha is called.</fw>
<ab n="18">Yet I haue left
me seuen thousand in Israel, all the knees which haue not bowed
vnto Baal, and euery mouth which hath not kissed him.<note> Rom. 11.4. , Or, I will leaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ So hee
departed thence and found Elisha the sonne of Shaphat, who was
plowing with twelue yoke of oxen before him, and hee with the
twelfth: and Eliiah passed by him, and cast his mantle vpon
him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he left the
oxen, and ranne after Eliiah, and said, Let mee, I pray thee, kisse
my father and my mother, and then I wil follow thee: and he said
vnto him, Goe backe againe; for what haue I done to
thee?<note> Hebr goe returne.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And he returned
backe from him, and tooke a yoke of oxen, &amp; slew them, and
boyled their flesh with the instruments of the oxen, and gaue vnto
the people, and they did eat: then he arose, and went after Eliiah,
and ministred vnto him.</ab>



</div>