<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-18-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 In the extremitie of famine Eliiah
sent to Ahab, meeteth good Obadiah. 9 Obadiah bringeth Ahab to
Eliiah. 17 Eliiah reprouing Ahab, by fire from heauen conuinceth
Baals prophets. 41 Eliiah by prayer obtaining raine, followeth Ahab
to Iezreel.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after many daies, that the word of the Lord came to Eliiah in
the third yeere, saying, Goe shewe thy selfe vnto Ahab, and I will
send raine vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Eliiah went
to shew himselfe vnto Ahab, and there was a sore famine in
Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Ahab called
Obadiah which was the gouernour of his house: (now Obadiah feared
the Lord greatly:<note> Hebr. Obadiahu. , Hebr. ouer his house.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For it was so,
when Iezebel cut off the Prophets of the Lord, that Obadiah tooke
an hundred Prophets, and hid them by fiftie in a caue, and fed them
with bread and water.)<note> Hebr. Izebel.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Ahab said
vnto Obadiah, Goe into the land, vnto all fountaines of water, and
vnto all brookes: peraduenture we may finde grasse to saue the
horses and mules aliue, that we leese not all the
beasts.<note> Hebr. that we cut not off our selues from the beasts.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">So they diuided
the land betweene them to passe throughout it: Ahab went one way by
himselfe, and Obadiah went another way by himselfe.</ab>

<fw>He goeth, and meeteth Ahab.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ And as
Obadiah was in the way, behold, Eliiah met him: and hee knew him,
and fell on his face, and said; Art thou that my lord
Eliiah?</ab>
<ab n="8">And he answered
him, I am: goe, tell thy lord, Behold, Eliiah is here.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he said, What
haue I sinned, that thou wouldest deliuer thy seruant into the hand
of Ahab, to slay mee?</ab>
<ab n="10">As the Lord thy
God liueth, there is no nation or kingdome, whither my lord hath
not sent to seeke thee: and when they said, He is not there, hee
tooke an oath of the kingdome and nation, that they found thee
not.</ab>
<ab n="11">And now thou
sayest, Goe, tell thy lord, Behold, Eliiah is here.</ab>
<ab n="12">And it shall
come to passe, as soone as I am gone from thee, that the spirit of
the Lord shall cary thee whither I know not; and so when I come and
tell Ahab, and he cannot finde thee, he shall slay mee: but I thy
seruant feare the Lord from my youth.</ab>
<ab n="13">Was it not told
my lord, what I did when Iezebel slew the Prophets of the Lord ?
How I hid an hundred men of the Lords Prophets, by fiftie in a
caue, and fedde them with bread and water?</ab>
<ab n="14">And now thou
sayest, Goe, tell thy lord, Behold, Eliiah is here: and hee shall
slay me.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Eliiah said,
As the Lord of hostes liueth, before whom I stand, I will surely
shew my selfe vnto him to day.</ab>
<ab n="16">So Obadiah went
to meete Ahab, and told him: and Ahab went to meete Eliiah.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And it
came to passe when Ahab saw Eliiah, that Ahab saide vnto him, Art
thou hee that troubleth Israel?</ab>
<ab n="18">And hee
answered, I haue not troubled Israel, but thou and thy fathers
house, in that yee haue forsaken the Commandements of the Lord, and
thou hast followed Baalim.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now therefore
send, and gather to mee all Israel vnto mount Carmel, and the
prophets of Baal foure hundred and fiftie, and the prophets of the
groues foure hundred, which eate at Iezebels table.</ab>
<ab n="20">So Ahab sent
vnto all the children of Israel, and gathered the prophets together
vnto mount Carmel.</ab>

<fw>Baals prophets, and Eliiah
sacrifice.</fw>
<ab n="21">And Eliiah came
vnto all the people, and said, how long halt yee betweene two
opinions? If the Lord bee God, follow him: but if Baal, then follow
him: and the people answered him not a word.<note> Or, thoughts.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then said Eliiah
vnto the people, I, euen I onely remaine a Prophet of the Lord: but
Baals prophets are foure hundred and fiftie men.</ab>
<ab n="23">Let them
therefore giue vs two bullocks, and let them chuse one bullocke for
themselues, and cut it in pieces, and lay it on wood, and put no
fire vnder: and I will dresse the other bullocke, and lay it on
wood, and put no fire vnder.</ab>
<ab n="24">And call ye on
the name of your gods, and I will call on the Name of the Lord: and
the God that answereth by fire, let him be God. And all the people
answered, and said, It is well spoken.<note> Hebr. the word is good.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Eliiah said
vnto the prophets of Baal, Chuse you one bullocke for your selues,
and dresse it first, for yee are many: and call on the name of your
gods, but put no fire vnder.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they took
the bullocke which was giuen them, and they dressed it, and called
on the name of Baal from morning, euen vntil noone, saying, O Baal,
heare vs. But there was no voyce, nor any that answered: And they
leapt vpon the altar which was made.<note> Or, answere. , Or, heard. , Or, leaped vp &amp; downe at the altar.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And it came to
passe at noone, that Eliiah mocked them, and saide, Crie aloud: for
he is a god, either he is talking, or he is pursuing, or hee is in
a iourney, or peraduenture he sleepeth, and must be
awaked.<note> Heb. with a great voice , Or, he meditateth. , Heb. hath a pursuit.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And they cried
loud, and cut themselues after their maner, with kniues, and
lancers, till the blood gushed out vpon them.<note> Hebr. powred out blood vpon them.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And it came to
passe when midday was past, and they prophesied vntil the time of
the offering of the euening sacrifice; that there was neither
voice, nor any to answere, nor any that regarded.<note> Hebr. ascending. , Heb. attention.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Eliiah said
vnto all the people, Come neere vnto me. And all the people came
neere vnto him. And he repaired the Altar of the Lord that was
broken downe.</ab>

<fw>Baals prophets, and Eliiah
sacrifice.</fw>
<ab n="31">And Eliiah tooke
twelue stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sonnes
of Iacob, vnto whome the word of the Lord came, saying, Israel
shall bee thy name.<note> Gen.32 28. 2.king 17.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And with the
stones hee built an altar in the Name of the Lord, and hee made a
trench about the altar, as great as would containe two measures of
seed.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he put the
wood in order, and cut the bullocke in pieces, and laide him on the
wood, and said, Fill foure barrels with water, and powre it on the
burnt sacrifice, and on the wood.</ab>
<ab n="34">And hee said,
Doe it the second time. And they did it the second time. And he
said, Doe it the third time. And they did it the third
time.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the water
ran round about the altar, and hee filled the trench also with
water.<note> Heb. went.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And it came to
passe at the time of the offering of the euening sacrifice, that
Eliiah the prophet came neere and said, Lord God of Abraham, Isaac,
and of Israel, Let it bee knowen this day that thou art God in
Israel, and that I am thy seruant, and that I haue done all these
things at thy word.</ab>
<ab n="37">Heare me, O
Lord, heare me, that this people may know that thou art the Lord
God, and that thou hast turned their heart backe againe.</ab>
<ab n="38">Then the fire of
the Lord fell, and consumed the burnt sacrifice, and the wood, and
the stones, and the dust, and licked vp the water that was in the
trench.</ab>
<ab n="39">And when all the
people sawe it, they fell on their faces: and they saide, The Lord,
he is the God, the Lord, he is the God.</ab>
<ab n="40">And Eliiah saide
vnto them, Take the prophets of Baal, let not one of them escape:
And they tooke them, and Eliiah brought them downe to the brooke
Kishon, and slewe them there.<note> Or, apprehend.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
Eliiah said vnto Ahab, Get thee vp, eate and drinke, for there is a
sound of abundance of raine.<note> Or, a sound of a noise of raine.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">So Ahab went vp
to eate and to drinke, and Eliiah went vp to the top of Carmel, and
he cast himselfe downe vpon the earth, and put his face betweene
his knees,</ab>
<ab n="43">And said to his
seruant, Goe vp now, looke toward the Sea. And hee went vp, and
looked, and saide, There is nothing. And he said, Goe againe seuen
times.</ab>

<fw>Elijah fed. He talketh with
God.</fw>
<ab n="44">And it came to
passe at the seuenth time, that he said, Behold, there ariseth a
little cloud out of the Sea, like a mans hand. And he said, Goe vp,
say vnto Ahab, Prepare thy charet, and get thee downe, that the
raine stop thee not.<note> Heb. tie, or binde.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And it came to
passe in the meane while, that the heauen was blacke with cloudes
and winde, and there was a great raine: and Ahab rode and went to
Iezreel.</ab>
<ab n="46">And the hand of
the Lord was on Eliiah; and hee girded vp his loynes, and ranne
before Ahab, to the entrance of Iezreel.<note> Heb. till thou come to Iezreel.</note></ab>



</div>