<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Gods Couenant in a vision, with
Solomon. 10 The mutual presents of Solomon and Hiram. 15 In
Solomons workes the Gentiles were his bondmen, the Israelites
honourable seruants. 24 Pharaohs daughter remooueth to her house.
25 Solomons yeerely solemne sacrifices. 26 His nauie fetcheth golde
from Ophir.</head>


<fw>Salomons vision.</fw>
<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when Solomon had finished the building of the house of the
Lord, and the kings house, and all Solomons desire which hee was
pleased to doe,<note> 2.Chron. 7.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">That the Lord
appeared to Solomon the second time, as hee had appeared vnto him
at Gibeon.<note> Chap.3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the Lord said
vnto him, I haue heard thy prayer and thy supplication that thou
hast made before me: I haue hallowed this house which thou hast
built, to put my Name there for euer, and mine eyes and mine heart
shall be there perpetually.<note> Cha.8.29</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And if thou wilt
walke before me, as Dauid thy father walked, in integritie of
heart, and in vprightnesse, to doe according to all that I haue
commanded thee, and wilt keepe my Statutes, and my
Iudgements:</ab>
<ab n="5">Then I will
establish the throne of thy kingdome vpon Israel for euer, as I
promised to Dauid thy father, saying, There shall not faile thee a
man vpon the throne of Israel.<note> 2.Sam.7. 12. 1.chro.22.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But if you shall
at all turne from following me, you or your children, and will not
keepe my Commandements, and my Statutes, which I haue set before
you, but goe and serue other gods, and worship them:</ab>
<ab n="7">Then will I cut
off Israel out of the land which I haue giuen them; and this house
which I haue hallowed for my Name, will I cast out of my sight, and
Israel shall bee a prouerbe, and a by-word among all
people:<note> Ier.7.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And at this house
which is high, euery one that passeth by it, shalbe astonished, and
shall hisse, and they shal say, Why hath the Lord done thus vnto
this land, and to this house?<note> Deut.29. 24. ierem. 22.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And they shall
answere, Because they forsooke the Lord their God, who brought
forth their fathers out of the land of Egypt, and haue taken hold
vpon other gods, and haue worshipped them, and serued them:
therefore hath the Lord brought vpon them all this euill.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And it
came to passe at the end of twentie yeeres, when Solomon had built
the two houses, the house of the Lord, and the Kings
house,<note> 2.Chron. 8.1.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons buildings.</fw>
<ab n="11">(Now Hiram the
king of Tyre had furnished Solomon with Cedar trees, and firre
trees, and with golde according to al his desire) that then Solomon
gaue Hiram twentie cities in the land of Galile.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Hiram came
out from Tyre to see the cities which Solomon had giuen him, and
they pleased him not.<note> Heb. were not right in his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he said, What
cities are these which thou hast giuen me, my brother? And he
called them the land of Cabul vnto this day.<note> That is, displeasing or, dirtie.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Hiram sent to
the king sixe score talents of gold.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And this
is the reason of the leuie which king Solomon raised, for to build
the house of the Lord, and his owne house, and Millo, and the wall
of Ierusalem, and Hazor, and Megiddo, and Gezer.</ab>
<ab n="16">For Pharaoh king
of Egypt had gone vp, and taken Gezer, and burnt it with fire, and
slaine the Canaanites that dwelt in the citie, and giuen it for a
present vnto his daughter Solomons wife.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Solomon built
Gezer, and Beth-horon the nether,</ab>
<ab n="18">And Baalath, and
Tadmor in the wildernesse, in the land.</ab>
<ab n="19">And all the
cities of store that Solomon had, and cities for his charets, and
cities for his horsemen, and that which Solomon disired to build in
Ierusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his
dominion.<note> Heb. the desire of Solomon which he desired.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And all the
people that were left of the Amorites, Hittittes, Perizzites,
Hiuites, and Iebusites, which were not of the children of
Israel,</ab>
<ab n="21">Their children
that were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel
also were not able vtterly to destroy, vpon those did Solomon leuie
a tribute of bond-seruice vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="22">But of the
children of Israel did Solomon make no bondmen: but they were men
of warre, and his seruants, and his princes, and his captaines, and
rulers of his charets, and his horsemen.<note> Leuit.25. 39.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">These were the
chiefe of the officers that were ouer Solomons worke, fiue hundred
and fiftie, which bare rule ouer the people that wrought in the
worke.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ But
Pharaohs daughter came vp out of the citie of Dauid, vnto her house
which Solomon had built for her: then did he build
Millo.<note> 2.Chron. 8.11.</note></ab>

<fw>His Nauie.</fw>
<ab n="25">¶ And three
times in a yeere did Solomon offer burnt offerings, and peace
offerings vpon the Altar which he built vnto the Lord, and he burnt
incense vpon the altar that was before the Lord: so he finished the
house.<note> Hebr. vpon it.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And king
Solomon made a nauie of ships in Ezion Geber, which is beside
Eloth, on the shoare of the red sea, in the land of
Edom.<note> Heb. lip.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And Hiram sent in
the nauie his seruants, shipmen that had knowledge of the Sea, with
the seruants of Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="28">And they came to
Ophir, and fet from thence gold foure hundred and twentie talents,
and brought it to king Solomon.</ab>



</div>