<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Solomons Princes. 7 His twelue
Officers for prouision. 20. 24 The peace and largenesse of his
kingdome. 22 His daily prouision. 26 His stables. 29 His
wisedome.</head>

<ab n="1">So King Solomon
was king ouer all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And these were the
Princes which he had, Azariah the sonne of Zadok, the
Priest,<note> Or, the chiefe Officer.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Elihoreph, and
Ahiah the sonnes of Shisha, Scribes: Iehoshaphat the sonne of
Ahilud the Recorder;<note> Or, Secretaries. , Or, remembrancer.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons officers, and
prouision.</fw>
<ab n="4">And Benaiah the
sonne of Iehoiada was ouer the host: And Zadok and Abiathar were
the Priests:</ab>
<ab n="5">And Azariah the
sonne of Nathan was ouer the officers: and Zabud the sonne of
Nathan was principall officer, and the kings friend.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Ahishar was
ouer the houshold: and Adoniram the sonne of Abda was ouer the
tribute.<note> Chap.5. 14. , Or, leuie.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And Solomon
had twelue officers ouer all Israel, which prouided victuals for
the king and his houshold: each man his moneth in a yeere made
prouision.</ab>
<ab n="8">And these are
their names: the sonne of Hur in mount Ephraim,<note> Or, Ben-hur.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The sonne of Dekar
in Makaz, and in Shaalbim, and Bethshemesh, and
Elon-Bethhanan.<note> Or, Ben-Dekar.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The sonne of
Heseb in Aruboth, to him pertained Sochoh, and all the land of
Hepher;<note> Or, Ben-Heseb.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The sonne of
Abinadab in all the region of Dor, which had Taphath the daughter
of Solomon to wife:<note> Or, Ben-Abinadab.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Baana the sonne
of Ahilud, to him pertained Taanach and Megiddo, and all
Beth-shean, which is by Zartanah beneath Iezreel, from Beth-shean
to Abel-Meholah, euen vnto the place that is beyond
Iokneam:</ab>
<ab n="13">The sonne of
Geber in Ramoth Gilead, to him pertained the townes of Iair the
sonne of Manasseh, which are in Gilead: to him also pertained the
region of Argob, which is in Bashan, threescore great cities, with
walles, and brasen barres.<note> Or, Ben-Geber.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Ahinadab the
sonne of Iddo had Mahanaim.<note> Or, to Mahanaim.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Ahimaaz was in
Naphtali; he also tooke Basmath the daughter of Solomon to
wife.</ab>
<ab n="16">Baanah the sonne
of Hushai was in Asher and in Aloth:</ab>
<ab n="17">Iehoshaphat the
sonne of Paruah in Issachar:</ab>
<ab n="18">Shimei the sonne
of Elah in Beniamin:</ab>
<ab n="19">Geber the sonne
of Uri was in the countrey of Gilead, in the countrey of Sihon king
of the Amorites, and of Og king of Bashan; and hee was the onely
officer which was in the land.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Iudah and
Israel were many, as the sand which is by the sea in multitude,
eating and drinking and making merrie.</ab>

<fw>Solomons officers, and
prouision.</fw>
<ab n="21">And Solomon
reigned ouer all kingdoms from the riuer vnto the land of the
Philistines, and vnto the border of Egypt: they brought presents,
and serued Solomon all the dayes of his life.<note> Ecclus. 47.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
Solomons prouision for one day, was thirtie measures of fine
floure, and threescore measures of meale,<note> Heb. bread. , Heb, Cors.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Ten fat oxen, and
twentie oxen out of the pastures, and an hundred sheepe, beside
Harts, and Roe-buckes, and fallow Deere, and fatted foule.</ab>
<ab n="24">For he had
dominion ouer all the region on this side the Riuer, from Tiphsah
euen to Azzah ouer all the kings on this side the Riuer: and he had
peace on all sides round about him.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Iudah and
Israel dwelt safely, euery man vnder his Uine, and vnder his
Figtree, from Dan euen to Beer-sheba, all the dayes of
Solomon.<note> Heb. confidently.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And
Solomon had fourtie thousand stalles of horses for his charets, and
twelue thousand horsemen.<note> 2.Chro. 9.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And those
officers prouided victuall for king Solomon, and for all that came
vnto king Solomons table, euery man in his moneth: they lacked
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="28">Barley also and
straw for the horses and dromedaries, brought they vnto the place
where the officers were, euery man according to his
charge.<note> Or, mules, or swift beasts.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And God
gaue Solomon wisdome, and vnderstanding, exceeding much, and
largenesse of heart, euen as the sand that is on the sea
shoare.<note> Eccles. 47.14, 15 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Solomons
wisedome excelled the wisedome of all the children of the East
countrey, and all the wisedome of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="31">For hee was wiser
then all men; then Ethan the Ezrahite, and Heman, and Chalcol, and
Darda the sonnes of Mahol: and his fame was in all nations round
about.</ab>
<ab n="32">And he spake
three thousand prouerbes: and his songs were a thousand and
fiue.</ab>
<ab n="33">And hee spake of
trees, from the Cedar tree that is in Lebanon, euen vnto the
Hyssope that springeth out of the wall: hee spake also of beasts,
and of foule, and of creeping things, and of fishes.</ab>
<ab n="34">And there came of
all people to heare the wisedome of Solomon, from all kings of the
earth, which had heard of his wisedome.</ab>



</div>