<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Hiram sending to congratulate
Solomon, is certified of his purpose to build the Temple, and
desired to furnish him with timber thereto. 7 Hiram blessing God
for Solomon, and requesting food for his family, furnisheth him
with trees. 13 The number of Solomons workemen and
labourers.</head>

<ab n="1">And Hiram king of
Tyre sent his seruants vnto Solomon: (for hee had heard that they
had anointed him King in the roume of his father,) for Hiram was
euer a louer of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Solomon sent
to Hiram, saying,<note> 1.Chro. 2.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thou knowest how
that Dauid my father could not build an house vnto the Name of the
Lord his God, for the warres which were about him on euery side,
vntill the Lord put them vnder the soles of his feet.</ab>
<ab n="4">But now the Lord
my God hath giuen me rest on euery side, so that there is neither
aduersary, nor euill occurrent.</ab>
<ab n="5">And behold, I
purpose to build an house vnto the Name of the Lord my God, as the
Lord spake vnto Dauid my father, saying, Thy sonne, whom I will set
vpon thy throne in thy roume, he shall build an house vnto my
Name.<note> Hebr. say. , 2.Sam. 7. 13. 1.chro. 22.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Now therefore
command thou, that they hew me Cedar trees out of Lebanon, and my
seruants shall bee with thy seruants: and vnto thee will I giue
hire for thy seruants, according to all that thou shalt appoint:
for thou knowest that there is not among vs, any that can skill to
hew timber, like vnto the Sidonians.<note> Hebr. say.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And it came
to passe when Hiram heard the wordes of Solomon, that hee reioyced
greatly, and said, Blessed be the Lord this day, which hath giuen
vnto Dauid a wise sonne ouer this great people.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Hiram sent to
Solomon, saying, I haue considered the things which thou sentest to
me for: and I will doe all thy desire concerning timber of Cedar,
and concerning timber of firre.<note> Hebr. heard.</note></ab>

<fw>Hirams promise to Solomon.</fw>
<ab n="9">My seruants shall
bring them downe from Lebanon vnto the Sea: and I wil conuey them
by sea in flotes, vnto the place that thou shalt appoint me, and
will cause them to be discharged there, and thou shalt receiue
them: and thou shalt accomplish my desire, in giuing food for my
houshold.<note> Hebr. send.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So Hiram gaue
Solomon Cedar trees, and Firre trees, according to all his
desire.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Solomon gaue
Hiram twentie thousand measures of wheate for food to his houshold,
and twentie measures of pure oile: thus gaue Solomon to Hiram yeere
by yeere.<note> Heb. Cors.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Lord gaue
Solomon wisedome, as hee promised him: and there was peace betweene
Hiram and Solomon, and they two made a league together.<note> Cha.3.12</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And King
Solomon raised a leuie out of all Israel, and the leuie was thirtie
thousand men.<note> Heb. tribute of men.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And hee sent them
to Lebanon, ten thousand a moneth by courses: a moneth they were in
Lebanon, and two moneths at home: and Adoniram was ouer the
leuie.<note> Chap.4.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Solomon had
threescore and ten thousand that bare burdens, and fourescore
thousand hewers in the mountaines:</ab>
<ab n="16">Besides the
chiefe of Solomons officers which were ouer the worke, three
thousand and three hundred, which ruled ouer the people that
wrought in the worke.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the king
commanded, and they brought great stones, costly stones, and hewed
stones, to lay the foundation of the house.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Solomons
builders, and Hirams builders, did hewe them, and the
stone-squarers: so they prepared timber and stones to build the
house.<note> Or, Giblites, as Ezek. 27.9.</note></ab>



</div>