<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Elijah hauing prophecied against
Ahab, is sent to Cherith, where the rauens feed him. 8 He is sent
to the widow of Zarephath. 17 Hee raiseth the widowes sonne. 24 The
woman beleeueth him.</head>

<ab n="1">And Eliiah the
Tishbite, who was of the inhabitants of Gilead, said vnto Ahab, As
the Lord God of Israel liueth, before whome I stand, there shall
not be deaw nor raine these yeres, but according to my
word.<note> Heb. Eliiahu. Luke 4.25. he is called Elias. , Ecclus. 48.3. iames 5.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the worde of
the Lord came vnto him, saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Get thee hence,
and turne thee Eastward, and hide thy selfe by the brooke Cherith,
that is before Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="4">And it shall bee,
that thou shalt drinke of the brooke, and I haue commanded the
rauens to feed thee there.</ab>
<ab n="5">So hee went, and
did according vnto the word of the Lord: for hee went and dwelt by
the brooke Cherith, that is before Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the rauens
brought him bread and flesh in the morning, and bread and flesh in
the euening: and hee dranke of the brooke.</ab>

<fw>Elijah fed by a widow.</fw>
<ab n="7">And it came to
passe after a while, that the brooke dryed vp, because there had
beene no raine in the land.<note> Heb. at the end of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the
word of the Lord came vnto him, saying,</ab>
<ab n="9">Arise, get thee
to Zarephath, which belongeth to Zidon, and dwell there: behold, I
haue commaunded a widow woman there to sustaine thee.<note> Luke 4. 26. called Sarepta.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So he arose, and
went to Zarephath: and when he came to the gate of the citie,
behold, the widow woman was there gathering of stickes: and he
called to her, and said, Fetch me, I pray thee, a little water in a
vessell, that I may drinke.</ab>
<ab n="11">And as shee was
going to fetch it, he called to her, and said, Bring mee, I pray
thee, a morsell of bread in thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">And she said, As
the Lord thy God liueth, I haue not a cake, but an handfull of
meale in a barrell, and a little oyle in a cruse: and behold, I am
gathering two stickes, that I may goe in, and dresse it for me and
my sonne, that we may eate it, and die.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Eliiah said
vnto her, Feare not, goe, and doe as thou hast said: but make mee
thereof a little cake first, and bring it vnto mee, and after make
for thee, and for thy sonne.</ab>
<ab n="14">For thus saith
the Lord God of Israel, The barrell of meale shall not waste,
neither shall the cruse of oile faile, vntill the day that the Lord
sendeth raine vpon the earth.<note> Heb. giueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And shee went,
and did according to the saying of Eliiah: and she, and he, and her
house did eate many dayes.<note> Or, a full yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the barrell
of meale wasted not, neither did the cruse of oyle faile, according
to the word of the Lord, which he spake by Eliiah.<note> Heb. by the hand of.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And it
came to passe after these things, that the sonne of the woman, the
mistresse of the house, fell sicke, and his sickenesse was so sore,
that there was no breath left in him.</ab>
<ab n="18">And shee sayd
vnto Eliiah, What haue I to doe with thee? O thou man of God! Art
thou come vnto me to call my sinne to remembrance, and to slay my
sonne?</ab>
<ab n="19">And he said vnto
her, Giue me thy sonne. And he tooke him out of her bosome, and
caried him vp into a loft, where he abode, and laide him vpon his
owne bed.</ab>

<fw>He goeth, and meeteth Ahab.</fw>
<ab n="20">And hee cried
vnto the Lord, and said, O Lord my God, hast thou also brought
euill vpon the widow, with whom I soiourne, by slaying her
sonne?</ab>
<ab n="21">And he stretched
himselfe vpon the child three times, and cried vnto the Lord, and
said; O Lord my God, I pray thee, let this childes soule come into
him againe.<note> Hebr. measured. , Hebr. into his inward parts.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And the Lord
heard the voice of Eliiah, and the soule of the child came into him
againe, and he reuiued.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Eliiah tooke
the childe, and brought him downe out of the chamber into the
house, and deliuered him vnto his mother: and Eliiah said, See, thy
sonne liueth.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
woman said to Eliiah, Now by this I know, that thou art a man of
God, and that the word of the Lord in thy mouth is trueth.</ab>



</div>