<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The building of Solomons Temple. 5
The chambers thereof. 11 Gods promise vnto it. 15 The sieling and
adorning of it: 23 The Cherubims. 31 The doores. 36 The court. 37
The time of building it.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe in the foure hundred and fourescore yeere after the children
of Israel were come out of the land of Egypt, in the fourth yere of
Solomons reigne ouer Israel, in the moneth Zif, which is the second
moneth, that he began to build the house of the Lord.<note> 2.Chron. 3.1. , Heb. built.</note></ab>

<fw>The building of the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="2">And the house
which king Solomon built for the Lord, the length thereof was
threescore cubites, and the breadth thereof twentie cubits, and the
height thereof thirtie cubites.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the porch
before the Temple of the house: twentie cubites was the length
thereof, according to the breadth of the house, and tenne cubites
was the breadth thereof before the house.</ab>
<ab n="4">And for the house
he made windowes of narrow lights.<note> Or, windowes broad within and narrow without: or, skewed and closed.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And against
the wall of the house he built chambers round about, against the
walles of the house round about, both of the Temple and of the
Oracle: and hee made chambers round about.<note> Or, vpon, or ioyning to. , Heb. floores , Heb. ribs.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The nethermost
chamber was fiue cubites broad, and the middle was sixe cubites
broad, and the third was seuen cubites broad: for without in the
wall of the house hee made narrowed rests round about, that the
beames should not bee fastened in the walles of the
house.<note> Heb. narrowings, or, rebatements.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the house when
it was in building, was built of stone, made ready before it was
brought thither: so that there was neither hammer nor axe, nor any
toole of yron heard in the house, while it was in building.</ab>
<ab n="8">The doore for the
middle chamber was in the right side of the house: and they went vp
with winding staires into the middle chamber, and out of the middle
into the third.<note> Heb. shoulder.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So he built the
house and finished it: and couered the house with beams and boards
of Cedar.<note> Or, the vault beams and the sielings with Cedar.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And then hee
built chambers against all the house, fiue cubites high: and they
rested on the house with timber of Cedar.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
word of the Lord came to Solomon, saying;</ab>
<ab n="12">Concerning this
House which thou art in building, if thou wilt walke in my
Statutes, and execute my Iudgments, and keepe all my Commandements
to walke in them: then will I performe my word with thee, which I
spake vnto Dauid thy father.<note> 2.Sam.7. 13. 1.chro. 22.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I will dwell
among the children of Israel, and will not forsake my people
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">So Solomon built
the house, and finished it.</ab>

<fw>The building of the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="15">And hee built the
walles of the house within with boards of Cedar, both the floore of
the house, and the walles of the sieling: and hee couered them on
the inside with wood, and couered the floore of the house with
plankes of firre.<note> Or, from the floore of the house vnto the walles, &amp;c. And so ver. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And hee built
twentie cubites on the sides of the house, both the floore, and the
walles with boards of Cedar: he euen built them for it within, euen
for the Oracle, euen for the most holy place.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the house,
that is, the Temple before it, was fortie cubites long.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Cedar of
the house within was carued with knops, and open flowres: all was
Cedar, there was no stone seene.<note> Or, gourds. , Heb. openings of flowres.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the Oracle he
prepared in the house within, to set there the Arke of the Couenant
of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Oracle in
the forepart, was twenty cubits in length and twentie cubites in
breadth, and twentie cubites in the height thereof: and hee
ouerlayd it with pure golde, and so couered the Altar which was of
Cedar.<note> Heb. shut vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">So Solomon
ouerlayd the house within with pure golde: and he made a partition,
by the chaines of golde before the Oracle, and he ouerlaid it with
gold.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the whole
house he ouerlaid with golde vntill he had finished all the house:
also the whole Altar that was by the Oracle he ouerlaide with
golde.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And within
the Oracle he made two Cherubims of Oliue tree, each ten cubites
high.<note> Or, oylie. Heb. trees of oyle.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And fiue cubits
was the one wing of the Cherub, and fiue cubits the other wing of
the Cherub: from the vttermost part of the one wing, vnto the
vttermost part of the other, were ten cubites.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the other
Cherub was tenne cubites: both the Cherubims were of one measure,
and one size.</ab>
<ab n="26">The height of the
one Cherub was ten cubites, and so was it of the other
Cherub.</ab>
<ab n="27">And he set the
Cherubims within the inner house: and they stretched foorth the
wings of the Cherubims, so that the wing of the one touched the one
wall, and the wing of the other Cherub touched the other wall:
&amp; their wings touched one another in the midst of the
house.<note> Exod.25. 20. , Or, the Cherubims stretched foorth their wings.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And he ouerlayd
the Cherubims with golde.</ab>

<fw>The Cherubims.</fw>
<ab n="29">And he carued all
the walles of the house round about with carued figures of
Cherubims, and palme trees, and open flowers, within &amp;
without.<note> Heb. openings of flowers.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And the floore of
the house hee ouerlayed with gold, within and without.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And for
the entring of the Oracle he made doores of Oliue tree: the lintell
and side posts were a fifth part of the wall.<note> Or, fiue square.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">The two doores
also were of Oliue tree, and he carued vpon them caruings of
Cherubims, and palme trees, and open flowers, and ouerlayd them
with gold, and spread gold vpon the Cherubims, and vpon the palme
trees.<note> Or, leaues of the doores. , Hebr. openings of flowers.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">So also made hee
for the doore of the Temple postes of Oliue tree a fourth part of
the wall.<note> Or, foure square.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And the two
doores were of firre tree: the two leaues of the one doore were
folding, and the two leaues of the other doore were
folding.</ab>
<ab n="35">And he carued
thereon Cherubims, and palme trees, and open flowers: and couered
them with gold, fitted vpon the carued worke.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And hee
built the inner Court with three rowes of hewed stone, and a row of
Cedar beames.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ In the
fourth yeere was the foundation of the house of the Lord layd, in
the moneth Zif.</ab>
<ab n="38">And in the
eleuenth yeere in the moneth Bul (which is the eight moneth) was
the house finished throughout all the parts therof, and according
to all the fashion of it: So was he seuen yeeres in building
it.<note> Or, with all the appurtenances therof, and with all the ordinances therof.</note></ab>



</div>