<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The Queene of Sheba admireth the
wisdome of Solomon. 14 Solomons gold. 16 His targets. 18 The throne
of Iuorie. 21 His vessels. 24 His presents. 26 His chariots and
horse. 28 His tribute.</head>

<ab n="1">And when the
Queene of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, concerning the Name
of the Lord; shee came to prooue him with hard
questions.<note> 2.Chron. 9. 1. mat.12 42. luke 11. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And she came to
Ierusalem with a very great traine, with camels that bare spices,
and very much gold, and precious stones: and when shee was come to
Solomon, she communed with him, of all that was in her
heart.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Solomon tolde
her all her questions: there was not any thing hid from the king,
which hee told her not.<note> Heb. words</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when the
Queene of Sheba had seene all Solomons wisedome, and the house that
he had built,</ab>
<ab n="5">And the meat of
his table, and the sitting of his seruants, and the attendance of
his ministers, and their apparell, and his cup bearers, and his
ascent by which hee went vp vnto the house of the Lord: there was
no more spirit in her.<note> Heb. standing. , Or, Butlers</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And she said to
the king, It was a true report that I heard in mine owne land, of
thy actes and of thy wisedome.<note> Heb. word. , Or, sayings</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Howbeit, I
beleeued not the words, vntill I came and mine eyes had seene it:
and beholde, the halfe was not told me: thy wisedom and prosperitie
exceedeth the fame which I heard.<note> Heb. thou hast added wisedome and goodnes to the fame.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons power, and
magnificence.</fw>
<ab n="8">Happie are thy
men, happy are these thy seruants, which stand continually before
thee, and that heare thy wisedom.</ab>
<ab n="9">Blessed be the
Lord thy God which delighted in thee, to set thee on the throne of
Israel; because the Lord loued Israel for euer, therefore made he
thee King, to doe iudgement and iustice.</ab>
<ab n="10">And she gaue the
king an hundred and twentie talents of gold, and of spices very
great store, &amp; precious stones: there came no more such
abundance of spices, as these, which the Queene of Sheba gaue to
king Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the nauie
also of Hiram that brought gold from Ophir, brought in from Ophir,
great plentie of Almug trees, and precious stones.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the king
made of the Almug trees, pillars for the house of the Lord, and for
the Kings house, Harpes also and Psalteries for singers: there came
no such Almug trees, nor were seene vnto this day.<note> Or, railes. Heb. a prop. , 2.Chron. 9.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And king Solomon
gaue vnto the Queene of Sheba, al her desire whatsoeuer she asked,
besides that which Solomon gaue her of his royall bountie: so she
turned and went to her owne countrey, she and her
seruants.<note> Hebr. according to the hand of king Solomon.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Now the
weight of gold that came to Solomon in one yere, was sixe hundred,
threescore &amp; six talents of gold,</ab>
<ab n="15">Besides that he
had of the merchant men, and of the traffique of the
spicemerchants, and of all the kings of Arabia, and of the
gouernours of the countrey.<note> Or, Captaines.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And king
Solomon made two hundred targets of beaten golde: sixe hundred
shekels of golde went to one target.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he made
three hundred shields of beaten gold, three pound of gold went to
one shield; and the king put them in the house of the forrest of
Lebanon.<note> Chap.7.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Moreouer
the king made a great throne of yuorie, and ouerlaide it with the
best gold.</ab>
<ab n="19">The throne had
sixe steps, and the top of the throne was round behind: and there
were stayes on either side on the place of the seate, and two lyons
stood beside the stayes.<note> Heb. on the hinder part thereof. , Heb. hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And twelue lions
stood there on the one side and on the other vpon the sixe steps:
there was not the like made in any kingdome.<note> Heb. so.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons power, and
magnificence.</fw>
<ab n="21">¶ And all
king Solomons drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of
the house of the forrest of Lebanon were of pure gold, none were of
siluer, it was nothing accounted of in the dayes of
Solomon.<note> Or, there was no siluer in them.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For the king had
at sea a nauie of Tharshish, with the nauie of Hiram: once in three
yeeres came the nauie of Tharshish, bringing golde and siluer,
yuorie, and apes, and peacocks.<note> Or, Elephants teeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">So king Solomon
exceeded all the kings of the earth, for riches and for
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And all
the earth sought to Solomon, to heare his wisedom which God had put
in his heart.<note> Heb. sought the face of.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And they brought
euery man his present, vessels of siluer, and vessels of gold, and
garments, and armour, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate yeere
by yeere.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And
Solomon gathered together charets and horsemen. And hee had a
thousand and foure hundred charets, and twelue thousand horsemen,
whom he bestowed in the cities for charets, and with the king at
Ierusalem.<note> 2.Chron. 1.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the king
made siluer to be in Ierusalem as stones, and Cedars made he to be
as the Sycomore trees, that are in the vale for
abundance.<note> Heb. gaue</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And
Solomon had horses brought out of Egypt, and linen yarne: the kings
merchants receiued the linen yarne at a price.<note> 2.Chron.1. 16. &amp; 9.28. , Heb. and the going forth of the horses which was Solomons.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And a charet
came vp and went out of Egypt for sixe hundred shekels of siluer,
and an horse for an hundred and fiftie: and so for all the kings of
the Hittites, and for the kings of Syria, did they bring them out
by their meanes.<note> Hebr. by their hand.</note></ab>




</div>