<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1. 7 Iehus prophesie against Baasha.
5 Elah succeedeth him. 8 Zimri conspiring against Elah, succeedeth
him. 11 Zimri executeth Iehus prophesie. 15 Omri made King by the
souldiers, forceth Zimri desperatly to burne himselfe. 21 The
kingdome being diuided, Omri preuaileth against Tibni. 23 Omri
buildeth Samaria. 25 His wicked reigne. 27 Ahab succeedeth him. 29
Ahabs most wicked reigne. 34 Ioshuas curse vpon Hiel the builder of
Iericho.</head>

<ab n="1">Then the word of
the Lord came to Iehu the sonne of Hanani, against Baasha,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Forasmuch as I
exalted thee out of the dust, and made thee Prince ouer my people
Israel, and thou hast walked in the way of Ieroboam, and hast made
my people Israel to sinne, to prouoke mee to anger with their
sinnes:</ab>
<ab n="3">Behold, I will
take away the posteritie of Baasha, and the posteritie of his
house: and will make thy house like the house of Ieroboam the sonne
of Nebat.<note> Chap. 15. 29.</note></ab>

<fw>Baasha dieth. Elah.</fw>
<ab n="4">Him that dieth of
Baasha in the citie, shall the dogs eate: and him that dieth of his
in the fields, shall the foules of the aire eate.<note> Chap. 14. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Now the rest of
the actes of Baasha, and what he did, and his might, are they not
written in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of
Israel?<note> 2. Chron. 16.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">So Baasha slept
with his fathers, and was buried in Tirzah, and Elah his sonne
reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="7">And also by the
hand of the prophet Iehu the sonne of Hanani, came the word of the
Lord against Baasha, and against his house, euen for all the euill
that hee did in the sight of the Lord, in prouoking him to anger
with the worke of his hands, in being like the house of Ieroboam,
and because he killed him.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ In the
twentieth and sixt yeere of Asa king of Iudah, began Elah the sonne
of Baasha to reigne ouer Israel in Tirzah, two yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="9">And his seruant
Zimri (captaine of halfe his charets) conspired against him as he
was in Tirzah drinking himselfe drunke in the house of Arza steward
of his house in Tirzah.<note> Heb. which was ouer.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Zimri went
in and smote him, and killed him, in the twentie and seuenth yeere
of Asa king of Iudah, and reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And it
came to passe when hee began to reigne, assoone as hee sate on his
throne, that he slew all the house of Baasha: hee left him not one
that pisseth against a wall, neither of his kinsfolkes, nor of his
friends.<note> Or, both his kinsemen and his friends.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thus did Zimri
destroy all the house of Baasha, according to the word of the Lord,
which he spake against Baasha by Iehu the prophet,<note> Heb. by the hand of.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For all the
sinnes of Baasha and the sinnes of Elah his sonne, by which they
sinned, and by which they made Israel to sinne, in prouoking the
Lord God of Israel to anger with their vanities.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now the rest of
the actes of Elah, and all that he did, are they not written in the
booke of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ In the
twentie and seuenth yeere of Asa king of Iudah, did Zimri reigne
seuen dayes in Tirzah: and the people were encamped against
Gibbethon which belonged to the Philistines.</ab>

<fw>Omri. Tibni.</fw>
<ab n="16">And the people
that were encamped, heard say, Zimri hath conspired, and hath also
slaine the king: Wherfore all Israel made Omri the captaine of the
hoste, king ouer Israel that day, in the campe.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Omri went vp
from Gibbethon, and all Israel with him, and they besieged
Tirzah.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it came to
passe when Zimri saw that the citie was taken, that hee went into
the palace of the kings house, and burnt the kings house ouer him
with fire, and died,</ab>
<ab n="19">For his sinnes
which he sinned in doing euill in the sight of the Lord, in walking
in the way of Ieroboam, and in his sinne which he did, to make
Israel sinne.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now the rest of
the acts of Zimri, and his treason that hee wrought, are they not
written in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of
Israel?</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then were
the people of Israel diuided into two parts: halfe of the people
followed Tibni the sonne of Ginath, to make him king: and halfe
followed Omri.</ab>
<ab n="22">But the people
that followed Omri preuailed against the people that followed Tibni
the sonne of Ginath: so Tibni died, and Omri reigned.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ In the
thirtie and one yeere of Asa king of Iudah, began Omri to reigne
ouer Israel twelue yeeres: sixe yeeres reigned he in
Tirzah.</ab>
<ab n="24">And hee bought
the hill Samaria of Shemer, for two talents of siluer, and built on
the hill, and called the name of the citie which hee built, after
the name of Shemer, owner of the hill, Samaria.<note> Heb. Shomeron.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ But Omri
wrought euil in the eyes of the Lord, and did worse then all that
were before him.</ab>
<ab n="26">For he walked in
all the way of Ieroboam the son of Nebat, and in his sinne
wherewith hee made Israel to sinne, to prouoke the Lord God of
Israel to anger with their vanities.</ab>
<ab n="27">Now the rest of
the acts of Omri, which he did, and his might that he shewed, are
they not written in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of
Israel?</ab>
<ab n="28">So Omri slept
with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria, and Ahab his sonne
reigned in his stead.</ab>

<fw>Iericho built. Elijah fed by a
widow.</fw>
<ab n="29">¶ And in
the thirtie and eight yeere of Asa king of Iudah, began Ahab the
sonne of Omri to reigne ouer Israel, and Ahab the sonne of Omri
reigned ouer Israel in Samaria, twentie and two yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Ahab the
sonne of Omri did euill in the sight of the Lord, aboue all that
were before him.</ab>
<ab n="31">And it came to
passe, as if it had beene a light thing for him to walke in the
sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat; that hee tooke to wife
Iezebel the daughter of Ethbaal king of the Zidonians, and went and
serued Baal, and worshipped him.<note> Heb. was it a light thing? &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And hee reared
vp an Altar for Baal, in the house of Baal, which hee had built in
Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="33">And Ahab made a
groue, and Ahab did more to prouoke the Lord God of Israel to
anger, then all the kings of Israel that were before him.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ In his
dayes did Hiel the Bethelite build Iericho: he laid the foundation
therof in Abiram his first borne, and set vp the gates thereof in
his yongest sonne Segub, according to the word of the Lord, which
hee spake by Ioshua the sonne of Nun.<note> Iosh.6.26.</note></ab>



</div>