<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Kings_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-8-8b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Kings-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The feast of the dedication of the
Temple. 12. and 54. Solomons blessing. 22 Solomons prayer. 62 His
sacrifice of peace offrings.</head>


<fw>The Temple dedicated.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then Solomon
assembled the Elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes,
the chiefe of the fathers of the children of Israel, vnto king
Solomon in Ierusalem, that they might bring vp the Arke of the
Couenant of the Lord, out of the citie of Dauid, which is
Zion.<note> 2.Chron. 5.2. , Hebr. Princes.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And all the men of
Israel assembled themselues vnto king Solomon, at the feast, in the
moneth Ethanim, which is the seuenth moneth.</ab>
<ab n="3">And all the Elders
of Israel came, and the Priests tooke vp the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they brought
vp the Arke of the Lord, and the Tabernacle of the Congregation,
and all the holy vessels that were in the Tabernacle, euen those
did the Priests &amp; the Leuites bring vp.</ab>
<ab n="5">And king Solomon,
and all the Congregation of Israel, that were assembled vnto him,
were with him before the Arke, sacrificing sheepe, and oxen, that
could not bee told nor numbred for multitude.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Priests
brought in the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord vnto his place,
into the Oracle of the house to the most holy place, euen vnder the
wings of the Cherubims.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the Cherubims
spread forth their two wings ouer the place of the Arke, and the
Cherubims couered the Arke, and the staues thereof aboue.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they drew out
the staues, that the ends of the staues were seene out in the Holy
place before the Oracle, and they were not seene without: and there
they are vnto this day.<note> Heb. heads. , Or, Arke, as 2. Chron. 5.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">There was nothing
in the Arke, saue the two Tables of stone, which Moses put there at
Horeb, when the Lord made a Couenant with the children of Israel,
when they came out of the land of Egypt.<note> Deut.10. 5. , Or, where.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe when the Priests were come out of the holy place, that the
cloud filled the house of the Lord;<note> Exod.40. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">So that the
Priests could not stand to minister, because of the cloud: for the
glory of the Lord had filled the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then spake
Solomon; The Lord said that hee would dwell in the thicke
darkenesse.<note> 2.Chro 6. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">I haue surely
built thee an house to dwel in, a setled place for thee to abide in
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the King
turned his face about, and blessed all the Congregation of Israel:
(and all the Congregation of Israel stood.)</ab>

<fw>Solomons blessing, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="15">And he said,
Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, which spake with his mouth vnto
Dauid my father, and hath with his hand fulfilled it,
saying;</ab>
<ab n="16">Since the day
that I brought foorth my people Israel out of Egypt, I chose no
citie out of all the tribes of Israel to build an house that my
Name might be therein; but I chose Dauid to be ouer my people
Israel.<note> 2.Sam. 7. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And it was in the
heart of Dauid my father, to builde an house for the Name of the
Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Lord sayd
vnto Dauid my father, Whereas it was in thine heart to build an
house vnto my Name, thou diddest well that it was in thine
heart.</ab>
<ab n="19">Neuerthelesse,
thou shalt not build the house, but thy sonne that shall come
foorth out of thy loynes, hee shall build the house vnto my
Name.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord hath
perfourmed his word that he spake, and I am risen vp in the roume
of Dauid my father, and sit on the throne of Israel, as the Lord
promised, and haue built an House for the Name of the Lord God of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="21">And I haue set
there a place for the Arke, wherein is the Couenant of the Lord,
which he made with our fathers, when he brought them out of the
land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
Solomon stood before the Altar of the Lord, in the presence of all
the Congregation of Israel, and spread foorth his handes toward
heauen:<note> 2.Chron. 6.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And hee said,
Lord God of Israel, there is no God like thee, in heauen aboue, or
on earth beneath, who keepest couenant and mercy with thy seruants,
that walke before thee with all their heart:<note> 2.Macc. 2.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Who hast kept
with thy seruant Dauid my father that thou promisedst him: thou
spakest also with thy mouth, and hast fulfilled it with thine hand,
as it is this day.</ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore now
Lord God of Israel, keepe with thy seruant Dauid my father, that
thou promisedst him, saying; There shall not faile thee a man in my
sight to sit on the Throne of Israel; so that thy children take
heede to their way, that they walke before me as thou hast walked
before me:<note> Chap.2.4. 2.Sam. 7. 12. , Heb. there shall not be cut off vnto thee a man from my sight. , Heb. onely if.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons blessing, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="26">And now, O God of
Israel, let thy worde (I pray thee) bee verified, which thou
spakest vnto thy seruant Dauid my father.</ab>
<ab n="27">But will God
indeede dwell on the earth? Behold, the heauen, and heauen of
heauens cannot conteine thee: how much lesse this House that I haue
builded?</ab>
<ab n="28">Yet haue thou
respect vnto the prayer of thy seruant, and to his supplication, O
Lord my God, to hearken vnto the crie and to the prayer, which thy
seruant prayeth before thee to day:</ab>
<ab n="29">That thine eyes
may be open toward this house, night and day, euen toward the place
of which thou hast said, My Name shall be there: that thou mayest
hearken vnto the prayer which thy seruant shall make towards this
place.<note> Deut. 12. 11. , Or, in this place.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And hearken thou
to the supplication of thy seruant, and of thy people Israel, when
they shall pray towards this place: and heare thou in heauen thy
dwelling place, and when thou hearest, forgiue.<note> Or, in this place.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ If any man
trespasse against his neighbour, and an oath be laid vpon him to
cause him to sweare, and the oath come before thine Altar in this
house:<note> Heb. and he require an oath of him.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Then heare thou
in heauen, and doe, and iudge thy seruants, condemning the wicked
to bring his way vpon his head, and iustifying the righteous, to
giue him according to his righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ When thy
people Israel bee smitten downe before the enemie, because they
haue sinned against thee, and shall turne againe to thee, and
confesse thy Name, and pray, and make supplication vnto thee in
this house:<note> Or, towards.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Then heare thou
in heauen, and forgiue the sinne of thy people Israel, and bring
them againe vnto the land, which thou gauest vnto their
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ When
heauen is shut vp, and there is no raine, because they haue sinned
against thee: if they pray towards this place, and confesse thy
Name, and turne from their sinne, when thou afflictest
them:</ab>

<fw>Solomons prayer for the people.</fw>
<ab n="36">Then heare thou
in heauen, and forgiue the sinne of thy seruants, and of thy people
Israel, that thou teach them the good way wherein they should
walke, and giue raine vpon thy land which thou hast giuen to thy
people for an inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ If there
be in the land famine, if there be pestilence, blasting, mildew,
locust, or if there be caterpiller: if their enemy besiege them in
the land of their cities, whatsoeuer plague, whatsoeuer sicknes
there be;<note> Or, iurisdiction.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">What prayer and
supplication soeuer be made by any man, or by all thy people
Israel, which shall know euery man the plague of his owne heart,
and spread forth his handes towards this house:</ab>
<ab n="39">Then heare thou
in heauen thy dwelling place, and forgiue, and do, and giue to
euery man according to his wayes, whose heart thou knowest; (for
thou, euen thou onely knowest the hearts of all the children of
men,)</ab>
<ab n="40">That they may
feare thee all the dayes that they liue, in the land which thou
gauest vnto our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="41">Moreouer,
concerning a stranger that is not of thy people Israel, but commeth
out of a farre countrey, for thy Names sake;</ab>
<ab n="42">(For they shall
heare of thy great Name, and of thy strong hand, and of thy
stretched out arme) when hee shall come and pray towards this
house:</ab>
<ab n="43">Heare thou in
heauen thy dwelling place, and doe according to all that the
stranger calleth to thee for: that all people of the earth may know
thy Name, to feare thee, as doe thy people Israel, and that they
may know that this house which I haue builded, is called by thy
Name.<note> Hebr. thy Name is called vpon this house.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ If thy
people goe out to battell against their enemie, whithersoeuer thou
shalt send them, and shall pray vnto the Lord toward the city which
thou hast chosen, and toward the house that I haue built for thy
Name:<note> Hebr. the way of the citie.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Then heare thou
in heauen their prayer &amp; their supplication, and mainteine
their cause.<note> Or, right.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">If they sinne
against thee, ( for there is no man that sinneth not,) and thou be
angry with them, and deliuer them to the enemy, so that they cary
them away captiues, vnto the land of the enemy, farre or
neere;<note> 2.Chron. 6.36. eccles. 7.22. 1.iohn 1.8, 10.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons prayer for the people.</fw>
<ab n="47">Yet if they shall
bethinke themselues, in the land whither they were caried captiues,
and repent, and make supplication vnto thee in the land of them
that caried them captiues, saying, Wee haue sinned, and haue done
peruersly, we haue committed wickednes;<note> Heb. bring backe to their heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And so returne
vnto thee with all their heart, and with all their soule, in the
land of their enemies, which led them away captiue, and pray vnto
thee toward their land, which thou gauest vnto their fathers, the
city which thou hast chosen, and the house which I haue built for
thy Name:</ab>
<ab n="49">Then heare thou
their prayer and their supplication in heauen thy dwelling place,
and mainteine their cause,<note> Or, right.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">And forgiue thy
people that haue sinned against thee, and all their transgressions,
wherein they haue transgressed against thee, and giue them
compassion before them who caried them captiue, that they may haue
compassion on them:</ab>
<ab n="51">For they bee thy
people and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest foorth out of
Egypt, from the mids of the furnace of iron:</ab>
<ab n="52">That thine eyes
may be open vnto the supplication of thy seruant, and vnto the
supplication of thy people Israel, to hearken vnto them in all that
they call for vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="53">For thou didst
separate them from among all the people of the earth, to be thine
inheritance, as thou spakest by the hand of Moses thy seruant, when
thou broughtest our fathers out of Egypt, O Lord God.<note> Exod.19. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">And it was so,
that when Solomon had made an end of praying all this prayer and
supplication vnto the Lord, he arose from before the Altar of the
Lord, from kneeling on his knees, with his handes spread vp to
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="55">And he stood, and
blessed all the Congregation of Israel, with a lowd voice,
saying;</ab>
<ab n="56">Blessed be the
Lord, that hath giuen rest vnto his people Israel, according to all
that he promised: there hath not failed one word of all his good
promise, which he promised by the hand of Moses his
seruant.<note> Heb. fallen.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">The Lord our God
be with vs, as he was with our fathers: let him not leaue vs, nor
forsake vs:</ab>

<fw>Solomons offrings.</fw>
<ab n="58">That hee may
encline our hearts vnto him, to walke in all his wayes, and to
keepe his Commaundements, and his Statutes, and his Iudgements
which hee commaunded our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="59">And let these my
wordes wherewith I haue made supplication before the Lord, be nigh
vnto the Lord our God, day and night, that hee maintaine the cause
of his seruant, and the cause of his people Israel at all times, as
the matter shall require:<note> Heb. the thing of a day in his day.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">That all the
people of the earth may know that the Lord is God: and that there
is none else.</ab>
<ab n="61">Let your heart
therefore be perfect with the Lord your God, to walke in his
Statutes, and to keepe his Commandements, as at this day.</ab>
<ab n="62">¶ And the
king, and all Israel with him, offered sacrifice before the
Lord.<note> 2.Chron. 7.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">And Solomon
offered a sacrifice of peace offerings, which he offered vnto the
Lord, two and twentie thousand oxen, and an hundred and twentie
thousand sheepe: so the king and all the children of Israel
dedicated the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="64">The same day did
the king hallow the middle of the Court that was before the house
of the Lord: for there hee offered burnt offerings, and meat
offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings: because the brasen
Altar that was before the Lord, was too little to receiue the burnt
offerings, and meat offerings, and the fat of the peace
offerings.<note> 2.Chron. 7.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="65">And at that time
Solomon held a feast, and all Israel with him, a great
Congregation, from the entring in of Hamath, vnto the riuer of
Egypt, before the Lord our God, seuen dayes and seuen dayes, euen
fourteene dayes.</ab>
<ab n="66">On the eight day
he sent the people away: and they blessed the King, and went vnto
their tents ioyfull, and glad of heart, for all the goodnesse that
the Lord had done for Dauid his seruant, and for Israel his
people.<note> Or, thanked.</note></ab>



</div>