<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-6-6b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>8 Antiochus dieth, 12 and confesseth
that he is plagued for the wrong done to Ierusalem. 20 Iudas
besiegeth those in the towre at Hierusalem. 28 They procure
Antiochus the yonger to come into Iudea. 51 He besiegeth Sion, 60
and maketh peace with Israel: 62 yet ouerthroweth the wall of
Sion.</head>

<ab n="1">About that
time king Antiochus trauailing through the high countreys, heard
say that Elimais in the countrey of Persia, was a citie greatly
renowned for riches, siluer, and gold,</ab>
<ab n="2">And that there
was in it a very rich temple, wherein were couerings of gold, and
brestplates, and shields which Alexander sonne of Philippe the
Macedonian King, who reigned first among the Grecians, had left
there.<note> Or, shields. , Or, armour</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore he
came and sought to take the citie, and to spoile it, but he was not
able, because they of the citie hauing had warning thereof,</ab>
<ab n="4">Rose vp
against him in battell: So he fled and departed thence with great
heauinesse, and returned to Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer there
came one, who brought in tidings into Persia, that the armies which
went against the land of Iudea, were put to flight:</ab>
<ab n="6">And that
Lysias who went forth first with a great power, was driuen away of
the Iewes, and that they were made strong by the armour, and power,
and store of spoiles, which they had gotten of the armies, whom
they had destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="7">Also that they
had pulled downe the abomination which hee had set vp vpon the
altar in Ierusalem, and that they had compassed about the
Sanctuarie with high wals as before, and his citie
Bethsura.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now when the
king heard these words, he was astonished, and sore moued,
whereupon hee laide him downe vpon his bedde, and fell sicke for
griefe, because it had not befallen him, as hee looked for.</ab>
<ab n="9">And there hee
continued many dayes: for his griefe was euer more and more, and he
made account that he should die.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wherefore he
called for all his friends, and said vnto them, The sleepe is gone
from mine eyes, and my heart faileth for very care.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I thought
with my selfe: Into what tribulation am I come, and how great a
flood [of miserie] is it wherein now I am? for I was bountifull,
and beloued in my power.</ab>
<ab n="12">But now I
remember the euils that I did at Ierusalem, and that I tooke all
the vessels of gold and siluer that were therein, and sent to
destroy the inhabitants of Iudea without a cause.</ab>
<ab n="13">I perceiue
therefore that for this cause these troubles are come vpon me, and
behold I perish through great griefe in a strange land.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then called
he for Philip one of his friends whom he made ruler ouer all his
realme:</ab>
<ab n="15">And gaue him
the crowne and his robe, and his signet, to the end hee should
bring vp his sonne Antiochus, and nourish him vp for the
kingdome.<note> Or, hee should take his sonne Antiochus to him.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">So king
Antiochus died there in the hundreth forty and ninth yeere.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now when
Lysias knew that the king was dead, he set vp Antiochus his sonne
(whom he had brought vp being yong) to reigne in his stead, and his
name he called Eupator.</ab>
<ab n="18">About this
time they that were in the towre shut vp the Israelites round about
the Sanctuarie, and sought alwayes their hurt, and the
strengthening of the heathen.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherefore
Iudas purposing to destroy them, called all the people together to
besiege them.</ab>
<ab n="20">So they came
together, and besieged them in the hundred and fiftith yeere, and
he made mounts for shot against them, and [other] engines:</ab>
<ab n="21">Howbeit
certaine of them that were besieged got forth, vnto whom some
vngodly men of Israel ioyned themselues.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they went
vnto the king and said, How long will it be ere thou execute
iudgement, and auenge our brethren?</ab>
<ab n="23">We haue beene
willing to serue thy father, and to doe as he would haue vs, and to
obey his commandements.</ab>
<ab n="24">For which
cause they of our nation besiege the towre, and are alienated from
vs: Moreouer as many of vs as they could light on, they slew, and
spoiled our inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="25">Neither haue
they stretched out their hand against vs only, but also against all
their borders.</ab>
<ab n="26">And behold
this day are they besieging the towre at Ierusalem to take it: the
Sanctuary also, and Bethsura haue they fortified.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore if
thou doest not preuent them quickly, they wil doe greater things
then these, neither shalt thou be able to rule them.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now when the
king heard this, he was angry, and gathered together all his
friends, and the captaines of his armie, and those that had charge
of the horse.</ab>
<ab n="29">There came
also vnto him from other kingdomes, and from Isles of the Sea bands
of hired souldiers.</ab>
<ab n="30">So that the
number of his armie was an hundred thousand foote men, and twentie
thousand horsemen, and two and thirty Elephants exercised in
battell.</ab>
<ab n="31">These went
through Idumea, and pitched against Bethsura which they assaulted
many daies, making engines of warre: but they [of Bethsura] came
out, and burnt them with fire, and fought valiantly.</ab>
<ab n="32">Upon this
Iudas remoued from the towre, and pitched in Bathzacharias, ouer
against the kings campe.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then the king
rising very earely marched fiercely with his host toward
Bathzacharias, where his armies made them ready to battell, and
sounded the trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="34">And to the
end they might prouoke the elephants to fight, they shewed them the
blood of grapes &amp; mulberies.</ab>
<ab n="35">Moreouer,
they diuided the beasts among the armies, and for euery elephant
they appointed a thousand men, armed with coats of male, and with
helmets of brasse on their heads, and besides this, for euery beast
were ordained fiue hundred horsemen of the best.</ab>
<ab n="36">These were
ready at euery occasion: wheresoeuer the beast was, and
whithersoeuer þe beast went, they went also,
neither departed they from him.</ab>
<ab n="37">And vpon the
beastes were there strong towres of wood, which couered euery one
of them, and were girt fast vnto them with deuices: there were also
vpon euery one two and thirtie strong men that fought vpon them,
besides the Indian that ruled him.</ab>
<ab n="38">As for the
remnant of the horsemen they set them on this side, and that side,
at the two parts of the host giuing them signes what to do, and
being harnessed all ouer amidst the rankes.<note> Or, stirring them vp, and being compassed with the ranckes, or defended with the valleys.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Now when the
Sunne shone vpon the shields of golde, and brasse, the mountaines
glistered therewith, and shined like lampes of fire.</ab>
<ab n="40">So part of
the kings armie being spred vpon the high mountaines, and part on
the valleyes below, they marched on safely, and in order.</ab>
<ab n="41">Wherefore all
that heard the noise of their multitude, and the marching of the
company, and the ratling of the harnesse, were moued: for the army
was very great and mighty.</ab>
<ab n="42">Then Iudas
and his host drew neere, and entred into battell, and there were
slaine of the kings army, sixe hundred men.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶
Eleazar also (syrnamed) Sauaran, perceiuing that one of the beasts,
armed with royall harnesse, was higher then all the rest, and
supposing that the king was vpon him,</ab>
<ab n="44">Put himselfe
in ieopardie, to the end hee might deliuer his people, and get him
a perpetuall name:</ab>
<ab n="45">Wherefore hee
ranne vpon him courageously through the midst of the battell,
slaying on the right hand, and on the left, so that they were
diuided from him on both sides.<note> Or, so that he cut them in pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">Which done,
he crept vnder the Elephant, and thrust him vnder and slew him:
whereupon the Elephant fell downe vpon him, and there he
died.</ab>
<ab n="47">How be it
[the rest of the Iewes] seeing the strength of the king, and the
violence of his forces, turned away from them.</ab>
<ab n="48">¶ Then
the kings armie went vp to Ierusalem to meet them, and the king
pitched his tents against Iudea, and against mount
Sion.<note> Or, in Iudea.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">But with them
that were in Bethsura hee made peace: for they came out of the
citie, because they had no victuals there, to endure the siege, it
being a yeere of rest to the land.<note> Adde out of Iosephus, and yeelded themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">So the King
tooke Bethsura, and set a garison there to keepe it.</ab>
<ab n="51">As for the
Sanctuarie hee besieged it many dayes: and set there artillerie
with engins, and instruments to cast fire and stones, and pieces to
cast darts, and slings.<note> Or, made there mounts for shot.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Whereupon
they also made engins, against their engins, and helde them battell
a long season.<note> Or, the Iewes.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">Yet at the
last their vessels being without victuals, (for that it was the
seuenth yeere, and they in Iudea that were deliuered from the
Gentiles, had eaten vp the residue of the store)</ab>
<ab n="54">There were
but a few left in the Sanctuary, because the famine did so preuaile
against them, that they were faine to disperse themselues, euery
man to his owne place.</ab>
<ab n="55">At that time
Lysias heard say, that Philip (whom Antiochus the King whiles hee
liued had appointed to bring vp his sonne Antiochus, that he might
be king)</ab>
<ab n="56">Was returned
out of Persia, and Media, and the Kings host also that went with
him, and that hee sought to take vnto him the ruling of the
affaires.</ab>
<ab n="57">Wherefore hee
went in all haste, and said to the King, and the captaines of the
host, and the company, Wee decay dayly, and our victuals are but
small, and the place wee lay siege vnto is strong: and the affaires
of the kingdome lie vpon vs.</ab>
<ab n="58">Now therefore
let vs be friends with these men, and make peace with them, and
with all their nation.<note> Gr. giue hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">And couenant
with them, that they shall liue after their Lawes, as they did
before: for they are therefore displeased, &amp; haue done all
these things because wee abolished their Lawes.</ab>
<ab n="60">So the King
and the Princes were content: wherefore hee sent vnto them to make
peace, and they accepted thereof.</ab>
<ab n="61">Also the King
and the Princes made an oath vnto them: whereupon they went out of
the strong hold.</ab>
<ab n="62">Then the King
entred into mount Sion, but when hee saw the strength of the place,
hee brake his oath that hee had made, and gaue commandement to pull
downe the wall round about.</ab>
<ab n="63">Afterward
departed hee in all haste, and returned vnto Antiochia, where hee
found Philip to bee master of the citie; So he fought against him,
and tooke the citie by force.</ab>



</div>