<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Iudas is informed of the power and
policie of the Romanes, 20 and maketh a league with them. 24 The
articles of that league.</head>

<ab n="1">Now Iudas had
heard of the fame of the Romanes, that they were mighty and valiant
men, and such as would louingly accept all that ioyned themselues
vnto them, and make a league of amitie with all that came vnto
them,</ab>
<ab n="2">And that they
were men of great valour: It was told him also of their warres and
noble acts which they had done amongst the Galatians, and how they
had conquered them, and brought them vnder tribute.<note> Or, French men.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And what they
had done in þ<note/> countrey of Spaine, for the winning
of the mines of the siluer &amp; gold which is there</ab>
<ab n="4">And that by
their policie and patience, they had conquered all that place
(though it were very farre from them) and the kings also that came
against them from the vttermost part of the earth, till they had
discomfited them, &amp; giuen them a great ouerthrow, so that the
rest did giue them tribute euery yere.<note> Or, euery place.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Besides this,
how they had discomfited in battell Philip, and Perseus king of the
Citims, with others that lift vp themselues against them, and had
ouercome them.<note> Or, Macedonians.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">How also
Antiochus the great king of Asia that came against them in
battaile, hauing an hundred and twentie Elephants with horsemen and
chariots, and a very great armie, was discomfited by them.</ab>
<ab n="7">And how they
tooke him aliue, and couenanted that hee and such as reigned after
him, should pay a great tribute, and giue hostages, and that which
was agreed vpon,</ab>
<ab n="8">And the
country of India, and Media, and Lidia, and of the goodliest
countries: which they tooke of him, and gaue to king
Eumenes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Moreouer how
the Grecians had determined to come and destroy them.</ab>
<ab n="10">And that they
hauing knowledge thereof sent against them a certaine captaine, and
fighting with them slew many of them, and caried away captiues,
their wiues, and their children, and spoiled them, and tooke
possession of their lands, and pulled downe their strong holds, and
brought them to be their seruants vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="11">[It was told
him besides] how they destroyed and brought vnder their dominion,
all other kingdomes and isles that at any time resisted
them.</ab>
<ab n="12">But with
their friends, and such as relied vpon them they kept amitie: and
that they had conquered kingdomes both farre and nigh, insomuch as
all that heard of their name were afraid of them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Also that
whom they would helpe to a kingdome, those raigne, and whom againe
they would, they displace: finally that they were greatly
exalted.</ab>
<ab n="14">Yet for all
this, none of them wore a crowne, or was clothed in purple to be
magnified thereby.</ab>
<ab n="15">Moreouer how
they had made for themselues a senate house, wherin three hundred
and twentie men sate in counsell daily, consulting alway for the
people, to the end they might be wel ordered</ab>
<ab n="16">And that they
committed their gouernment to one man euery yeere, who ruled ouer
all their countrie, and that all were obedient to that one, and
that there was neither enuy, nor emulation amongst them.</ab>
<ab n="17">In
consideration of these things Iudas chose Eupolemus the sonne of
Iohn, the sonne of Accas, and Iason the sonne of Eleazar, and sent
them to Rome to make a league of amitie and confederacie with
them,</ab>
<ab n="18">[And to
intreate them] that they would take the yoke from them, for they
saw that the kingdome of the Grecians did oppresse Israel with
seruitude</ab>
<ab n="19">They went
therefore to Rome (which was a very great iourney) and came into
the Senate, where they spake and said,</ab>
<ab n="20">Iudas
Maccabeus with his brethren, and the people of the Iewes, haue sent
vs vnto you, to make a confederacie, and peace with you, and that
we might be registred, your confederats and friends.</ab>
<ab n="21">So that
matter pleased the Romanes well.</ab>
<ab n="22">And this is
the copie of the Epistle which (the Senate) wrote backe againe, in
tables of brasse: and sent to Ierusalem, that there they might haue
by them a memorial of peace &amp; confederacy.</ab>
<ab n="23">Good successe
be to the Romans and to the people of the Iewes, by Sea, and by
land for euer: the sword also and enemie, be farre from
them.</ab>
<ab n="24">If there come
first any warre vpon the Romans or any of their confederats
throughout all their dominion,</ab>
<ab n="25">The people of
the Iewes shall helpe them, as the time shall be appointed, with
all their heart.</ab>
<ab n="26">Neither shal
they giue any thing, vnto them that make war vpon them, or aide
them with victuals, weapons, money, or ships, as it hath seemed
good vnto the Romans, but they shall keepe their couenant without
taking any thing therefore.</ab>
<ab n="27">In the same
maner also, if warre come first vpon the nation of the Iewes, the
Romans shall helpe them with all their heart, according as the time
shall be appointed them.</ab>
<ab n="28">Neither shal
victuals be giuen to thē that take part against thē, or
weapons, or money, or ships, as it hath seemed good to the Romanes;
but they shall keepe their couenants, and that without
deceit.</ab>
<ab n="29">According to
these articles did the Romanes make a couenant with the people of
the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="30">Howbeit, if
hereafter the one partie or the other, shall thinke meete to adde
or diminish any thing, they may doe it at their pleasures, and
whatsoeuer they shall adde or take away, shalbe ratified.</ab>
<ab n="31">And as
touching the euils that Demetrius doeth to the Iewes, wee haue
written vnto him, saying, Wherefore hast thou made thy yoke heauie
vpon our friends, and confederats the Iewes?</ab>
<ab n="32">If therefore
they complaine any more against thee: wee will doe them iustice,
and fight with thee by sea and by land.</ab>



</div>