<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-12-12b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Ionathan reneweth his league with
the Romanes and Lacedemonians. 28 The forces of Demetrius thinking
to surprise Ionathan, flee away for feare. 35 Ionathan fortifieth
the castles in Iudea, 48 and is shut vp by the fraud of Tryphon in
Ptolemais.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe when
Ionathan saw that the time serued him, he chose certaine men and
sent them to Rome, for to confirme and renew the friendship that
they had with them.</ab>
<ab n="2">He sent
letters also to the Lacedemonians, and to other places, for the
same purpose.</ab>
<ab n="3">So they went
vnto Rome, and entred into the Senate, and said, Ionathan the high
Priest, and the people of the Iewes sent vs vnto you, to the end
you should renew the friendship which you had with them, and
league, as in former time.</ab>
<ab n="4">Upon this the
Romanes gaue them letters vnto the gouernours of euery place, that
they should bring them into the land of Iudea peaceably.</ab>
<ab n="5">And this is
the copy of the letters which Ionathan wrote to the
Lacedemonians:</ab>
<ab n="6">Ionathan the
hie Priest, and the Elders of the nation, and the Priestes and the
other people of the Iewes, vnto the Lacedemonians their brethren,
send greeting.</ab>
<ab n="7">There were
letters sent in times past vnto Onias the high Priest from Darius,
who reigned then among you, to signifie that you are our brethren,
as the copy here vnder-written doeth specifie.<note> Anew: booke Ioseph. Ant.lib.13. cap.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">At which time
Onias intreated the Embassador that was sent, honourably, and
receiued the letters, wherein declaration was made of the league
and friendship.<note> Or, kinred, Ios. Aur.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore we
also, albeit we need none of these things, for that wee haue the
holy bookes of Scripture in our hands to comfort vs,</ab>
<ab n="10">Haue
neuerthelesse attempted to send vnto you, for the renewing of
brotherhood and friendship, lest we should become strangers vnto
you altogether: for there is a long time passed since you sent vnto
vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">We therefore
at all times without ceasing, both in our Feasts, and other
conuenient dayes, doe remember you in the sacrifices which we
offer, and in our prayers, as reason is, and as it becommeth vs to
thinke vpon our brethren:</ab>
<ab n="12">And wee are
right glad of your honour.</ab>
<ab n="13">As for our
selues, wee haue had great troubles and warres on euery side,
forsomuch as the kings that are round about vs haue fought against
vs.</ab>
<ab n="14">Howbeit wee
would not be troublesome vnto you, nor to others of our
confederates &amp; friends in these warres:</ab>
<ab n="15">For wee haue
helpe from heauen that succoureth vs, so as we are deliuered from
our enemies, and our enemies are brought vnder foote.</ab>
<ab n="16">For this
cause we chose Numenius the son of Antiochus, and Antipater the
sonne of Iason, and sent them vnto the Romanes, to renew the amitie
that we had with them, and the former league.</ab>
<ab n="17">We commanded
them also to goe vnto you, and to salute you, and to deliuer you
our letters, concerning the renewing of our brotherhood.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wherefore
now ye shall doe well to giue vs an answere thereto.</ab>
<ab n="19">And this is
the copy of the letters which Omiares sent:<note> Read out of Ios. which Areus sent to Onias.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Areus king
of the Lacedemonians, to Onias the hie Priest, greeting.</ab>
<ab n="21">It is found
in writing, that the Lacedemonians and Iewes are brethren, and that
they are of the stocke of Abraham:</ab>
<ab n="22">Now
therefore, since this is come to our knowledge, you shall doe well
to write vnto vs of your prosperitie.<note> Gr. peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">We doe write
backe againe to you, that your cattell and goods are ours, and ours
are yours. We doe command therefore [our Embassadours] to make
report vnto you on this wise.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now when
Ionathan heard that Demetrius princes were come to fight against
him with a greater hoste then afore,</ab>
<ab n="25">Hee remooued
from Ierusalem, and met them in the land of Amathis: for he gaue
them no respite to enter his countrey.<note> Or, to set foote in his countrey: or, to inuade his countrey.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He sent
spies also vnto their tents, who came againe, and tolde him, that
they were appointed to come vpon them in the night season.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore so
soone as the Sunne was downe, Ionathan commaunded his men to watch,
and to be in armes, that all the night long they might bee ready to
fight: Also he sent foorth sentinels round about the hoste.</ab>
<ab n="28">But when the
aduersaries heard that Ionathan and his men were ready for battell,
they feared, and trembled in their hearts, and they kindled fires
in their campe.<note> Ioseph. lib. ant.13.9. they went away.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Howbeit
Ionathan and his company knew it not till the morning: for they saw
the lights burning.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then
Ionathan pursued after them, but ouertooke them not: for they were
gone ouer the riuer Eleutherus.</ab>
<ab n="31">Wherefore
Ionathan turned to the Arabians, who were called Zabadeans, and
smote them, and tooke their spoiles.<note> Ios. gr. Nabatheans, or Zabatheans.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And remouing
thence, he came to Damascus, and so passed through all the
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="33">Simon also
went foorth, and passed through the countrey vnto Ascalon, and the
holds there adioyning, from whence he turned aside to Ioppe, and
wanne it.</ab>
<ab n="34">For he had
heard that they would deliuer the hold vnto them that tooke
Demetrius part, wherefore he set a garison there to keepe
it.</ab>
<ab n="35">After this
came Ionathan home againe, and calling the Elders of the people
together, hee consulted with them about building strong holdes in
Iudea,</ab>
<ab n="36">And making
the walles of Ierusalem higher, and raising a great mount betweene
the towre and the city, for to separate it from the city, that so
it might be alone, that men might neither sell nor buy in
it.</ab>
<ab n="37">Upon this
they came together, to build vp the citie forasmuch as [part of]
the wall toward the brooke on the East side was fallen down, &amp;
they repaired that which was called Caphenatha<note> Or, according to the Romane reading, and he came neere to the wall of the brooke toward the East.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Simon also
set vp Adida, in Sephela, and made it strong with gates and
barres.</ab>
<ab n="39">Now Tryphon
went about to get the kingdome of Asia, and to kill Antiochus the
king, that hee might set the crowne vpon his owne head.</ab>
<ab n="40">Howbeit, he
was afraid that Ionathan would not suffer him, and that he would
fight against him, wherefore he sought a way, howe to take
Ionathan, that he might kill him. So he remoued, and came to
Bethsan.</ab>
<ab n="41">Then
Ionathan went out to meet him with fourtie thousand men, chosen for
the battell, and came to Bethsan.</ab>
<ab n="42">Now when
Tryphon saw that Ionathan came with so great a force, hee durst not
stretch his hande against him,</ab>
<ab n="43">But receiued
him honourably, and cōmended him vnto all his friends, and
gaue him gifts, and commaunded his men of warre to be as obedient
vnto him, as to himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="44">Unto
Ionathan also hee said, Why hast thou put all this people to so
great trouble, seeing there is no warre betwixt vs?</ab>
<ab n="45">Therefore
send them now home againe, and chuse a few men to waite on thee,
and come thou with me to Ptolemais, for I will giue it thee and the
rest of the strong holds and forces, and all that haue any charge:
as for me, I will returne and depart: for this is the cause of my
comming.</ab>
<ab n="46">So Ionathan
beleeuing him, did as he bade him, and sent away his host, who went
into the land of Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="47">And with
himselfe hee retained but three thousand men, of whome he sent two
thousand into Galile, and one thousand went with him.<note> Gr. left two thousand in Galile.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Now assoone
as Ionathan entred into Ptolemais, they of Ptolemais shut the
gates, and tooke him, and all them that came with him, they shewe
with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="49">Then sent
Tryphon an hoste of footmen, and horsemen into Galile, and into the
great plaine, to destroy all Ionathans company.</ab>
<ab n="50">But when
they knew that Ionathan and they that were with him were taken and
slaine, they encouraged one another, and went close together,
prepared to fight.</ab>
<ab n="51">They
therfore that followed vpon them, perceiuing þ<note/>
they were ready to fight for their liues, turned back
againe.</ab>
<ab n="52">Whereupon
they all came into the land of Iudea peaceably, and there they
bewailed Ionathan &amp; them that were with him, &amp; they were
sore afraid, wherfore all Israel made great lamentation.</ab>
<ab n="53">Then all the
heathen that were round about them, sought to destroy them. For,
said they, they haue no captaine, nor any to helpe them. Now
therfore let vs make war vpon them, &amp; take away their memorial
frō amongst men.</ab>



</div>