<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-10-10b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-10-10c.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Demetrius maketh large offers to
haue peace with Ionathan. 25 His letters to the Iewes. 47 Ionathan
maketh peace with Alexander, 50 Who killeth Demetrius, 58 and
marieth the daughter of Ptolomeus. 62 Ionathan is sent for by him,
and much honoured, 75 and preuaileth against the forces of
Demetrius the yonger, 84 &amp; burneth the temple of
Dagon.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
hundreth &amp; sixtieth yere, Alexander the sonne of Antiochus
surnamed Epiphanes, went vp and tooke Ptolemais: for the people had
receiued him, by meanes whereof he reigned there.<note> Ios. the sonne of Antiochus Epiphanes.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Now when king
Demetrius heard thereof, he gathered together an exceeding great
host, and went foorth against him to fight.</ab>
<ab n="3">Moreouer
Demetrius sent letters vnto Ionathan with louing wordes, so as he
magnified him.</ab>
<ab n="4">For, said
hee, Let vs first make peace with him before he ioyne with
Alexander against vs.</ab>
<ab n="5">Else he wil
remember all the euils that we haue done against him, and against
his brethren and his people.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore he
gaue him authority to gather together an host, and to prouide
weapons that hee might aide him in battell: he commaunded also that
the hostages that were in the towre, should be deliuered
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then came
Ionathan to Ierusalem, and read the letters in the audience of all
the people, and of them that were in the towre.</ab>
<ab n="8">Who were sore
afraid when they heard that the king had giuen him authoritie to
gather together an host.</ab>
<ab n="9">Whereupon
they of the towre deliuered their hostages vnto Ionathan, &amp; he
deliuered them vnto their parents.</ab>
<ab n="10">This done,
Ionathan setled himselfe in Ierusalem, and began to build and
repaire the citie.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he
commaunded the workemen to build the wals, and the mount Sion round
about with square stones, for fortification, and they did
so.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then the
strangers that were in the fortresses which Bacchides had built,
fled away:</ab>
<ab n="13">Insomuch as
euery man left his place, and went into his owne country.</ab>
<ab n="14">Onely at
Bethsura certaine of those that had forsaken the law, and the
commaundements remained still: for it was their place of
refuge.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now when
king Alexander had heard what promises Demetrius had sent vnto
Ionathan: when also it was told him of the battels and noble acts
which he &amp; his brethren had done, and of the paines that they
had indured,</ab>
<ab n="16">He said,
Shal we find such another man? Now therefore we will make him our
friend, and confederate.</ab>
<ab n="17">Upon this he
wrote a letter and sent it vnto him according to these words,
saying:</ab>
<ab n="18">King
Alexander to his brother Ionathan, sendeth greeting:</ab>
<ab n="19">We haue
heard of thee, that thou art a man of great power, and meete to be
our friend.</ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore
now this day we ordaine thee to bee the high priest of thy nation,
and to be called the kings friend, (and there withall he sent him a
purple robe and a crowne of gold) to take our part, and keepe
friendship with vs.</ab>
<ab n="21">So in the
seuenth moneth of the hundreth and sixtieth yere, at the feast of
the Tabernacles, Ionathan put on the holy robe, and gathered
together forces, and prouided much armour.</ab>
<ab n="22">Wherof when
Demetrius heard, he was very sory, and said,</ab>
<ab n="23">What haue we
done that Alexander hath preuented vs, in making amity with the
Iewes to strengthen himself?</ab>
<ab n="24">I also will
write vnto them words of encouragement [and promise them] dignities
and gifts, that I may haue their ayde.</ab>
<ab n="25">He sent vnto
him therefore, to this effect: King Demetrius vnto the people of
the Iewes, sendeth greeting:</ab>
<ab n="26">Whereas you
haue kept couenants with vs, &amp; continued in our friendship, not
ioyning your selues with our enemies, we haue heard hereof, &amp;
are glad:</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore
now continue yee still to be faithful vnto vs, and we will well
recompence you for the things you doe in our behalfe,</ab>
<ab n="28">And will
grant you many immunities, and giue you rewards.</ab>
<ab n="29">And now I
doe free you, and for your sake I release all the Iewes from
tributes, and from the customes of salt, and from crowne
taxes,</ab>
<ab n="30">And frō
that which appertaineth vnto me to receiue for the third part of
the seed, and the halfe of the fruit of the trees, I release it
from this day forth, so that they shall not be taken of the land of
Iudea, nor of the three gouernments which are added thereunto out
of the country of Samaria and Galile, from this day forth for
euermore.</ab>
<ab n="31">Let
Ierusalem also bee holy and free, with the borders thereof, both
from tenths and tributes.</ab>
<ab n="32">And as for
the towre which is at Ierusalem, I yeeld vp my authoritie ouer it,
and giue it to the high Priest, that he may set in it such men as
he shall choose to keepe it.</ab>
<ab n="33">Moreouer I
freely set at libertie euery one of the Iewes that were carried
captiues out of the land of Iudea, into any part of my kingdome,
and I will that all my officers remit the tributes, euen of their
cattell.</ab>
<ab n="34">Furthermore,
I will that all the Feasts and Sabbaths, &amp; New moones and
solemne dayes, and the three dayes before the Feast, and the three
dayes after the Feast, shall be all dayes of immunitie and freedom
for all the Iewes in my realme.</ab>
<ab n="35">Also no man
shall haue authoritie to meddle with them, or to molest any of them
in any matter.</ab>
<ab n="36">[I will
further] that there be enrolled amongst the kings forces about
thirtie thousand men of the Iewes, vnto whom pay shall be giuen as
belongeth to all the kings forces.</ab>
<ab n="37">And of them
some shalbe placed in the kings strong holds, of whom also some
shall be set ouer the affaires of the kingdome, which are of trust:
and I will that their ouerseers and gouernours be of themselues,
and that they liue after their owne lawes, euen as the King hath
commanded in the land of Iudea.<note> Gr. walke.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And
concerning the three gouernments that are added to Iudea from the
countrey of Samaria, let them be ioyned with Iudea, that they may
be reckoned to be vnder one, nor bound to obey other authoritie
then þ<note/> high priests</ab>
<ab n="39">As for
Ptolemais and the land pertaining thereto, I giue it as a free gift
to the Sanctuary at Ierusalem, for the necessary expences of the
Sanctuary.<note> Or, of the holy things.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Moreouer, I
giue euery yeere fifteene thousand shekels of siluer, out of the
Kings accompts from the places appertaining.</ab>
<ab n="41">And all the
ouerplus which the officers payed not in as in former time, from
henceforth shalbe giuen towards the workes of the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="42">And besides
this, the fiue thousand shekels of siluer, which they tooke from
the vses of the Temple out of the accompts yeere by yeere, euen
those things shall be released, because they appertaine to the
Priests that minister.</ab>
<ab n="43">And
whosoeuer they be that flee vnto the Temple at Ierusalem, or be
within the liberties thereof, being indebted vnto the King, or for
any other matter, let them be at libertie, and all that they haue
in my realme.</ab>
<ab n="44">For the
building also and repairing of the workes of the Sanctuary,
expences shalbe giuen of the Kings accompts.</ab>
<ab n="45">Yea, and for
the building of the walles of Ierusalem, and the fortifying thereof
round about, expences shall bee giuen out of the Kings accompts, as
also for building of the walles in Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="46">Now when
Ionathan and the people heard these words, they gaue no credite
vnto them, nor receiued them, because they remembred the great
euill that he had done in Israel; for hee had afflicted them very
sore.</ab>
<ab n="47">But with
Alexander they were well pleased, because hee was the first that
entreated of peace with them, and they were confederate with him
alwayes.<note> True.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Then
gathered king Alexander great forces, and camped ouer against
Demetrius.</ab>
<ab n="49">And after
the two Kings had ioyned battell, Demetrius hoste fled: but
Alexander followed after him, and preuailed against them.</ab>
<ab n="50">And he
continued the battell very sore vntill the Sunne went downe, and
that day was Demetrius slaine.</ab>
<ab n="51">Afterward
Alexander sent Embassadors to Ptoleme king of Egypt, with a message
to this effect;</ab>
<ab n="52">Forsomuch as
I am come againe to my realme, and am set in the throne of my
progenitors, and haue gotten the dominion, and ouerthrowen
Demetrius, and recouered our countrey,</ab>
<ab n="53">(For after I
had ioyned battell with him, both he, and his hoste was discomfited
by vs, so that we sit in the throne of his kingdome)</ab>
<ab n="54">Now
therefore let vs make a league of amitie together, and giue me now
thy daughter to wife: &amp; I will be thy son in law, and will giue
both thee and her, gifts according to thy dignity.</ab>
<ab n="55">Then Ptoleme
the king gaue answere, saying, Happy be the day wherein thou
diddest returne into the land of thy fathers, and satest in the
throne of their kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="56">And now will
I doe to thee, as thou hast written: meet me therefore at
Ptolemais, that wee may see one another, for I will marry my
daughter to thee according to thy desire.</ab>
<ab n="57">So Ptolome
went out of Egypt with his daughter Cleopatra, and they came vnto
Ptolemais in the hundred threescore and second yeere.</ab>
<ab n="58">Where king
Alexander meeting him, gaue vnto him his daughter Cleopatra, and
celebrated her marriage at Ptolemais with great glory, as the maner
of kings is.</ab>
<ab n="59">Now king
Alexander had written vnto Ionathan, that hee should come and meete
him.</ab>
<ab n="60">Who
thereupon went honourably to Ptolemais, where he met the two kings,
and gaue them and their friends siluer and golde, and many
presents, and found fauour in their sight.</ab>
<ab n="61">At that time
certaine pestilent fellowes of Israel, men of a wicked life,
assembled themselues against him, to accuse him: but the king would
not heare them.</ab>
<ab n="62">Yea more
then that, the king commanded to take off his garments, and clothe
him in purple: and they did so.</ab>
<ab n="63">Also he made
him sit by himselfe, and said vnto his princes, Goe with him into
the midst of the city, and make proclamation, that no man complaine
against him of any matter, and that no man troble him for any maner
of cause.</ab>
<ab n="64">Now when his
accusers sawe that he was honoured according to the proclamation,
and clothed in purple, they fled all away.</ab>
<ab n="65">So the king
honoured him, and wrote him amongst his chiefe friends, and made
him a duke, and partaker of his dominion.<note> Or, gouernor of a prouince.</note></ab>
<ab n="66">Afterward
Ionathan returned to Ierusalem with peace and gladnes.</ab>
<ab n="67">Furthermore,
in the hundreth threescore and fifth yeere, came Demetrius sonne of
Demetrius, out of Crete into the land of his fathers.</ab>
<ab n="68">Whereof when
king Alexander heard tell, he was right sory, and returned into
Antioch.</ab>
<ab n="69">Then
Demetrius made Apollonius the gouernour of Coelosyria his general,
who gathered together a great hoste, and camped in Iamnia and sent
vnto Ionathan the high Priest, saying,</ab>
<ab n="70">Thou alone
liftest vp thy selfe against vs, and I am laughed to scorne for thy
sake, and reproched, and why doest thou vaunt thy power against vs
in the mountaines?</ab>
<ab n="71">Now
therefore if thou trustest in thine owne strength, come downe to vs
into the plaine field, and there let vs trie the matter together,
for with me is the power of the cities.</ab>
<ab n="72">Aske and
learne who I am, and the rest that take our part, and they shal tel
thee that thy foot is not able to stand before our face; for thy
fathers haue bene twice put to flight in their owne land.</ab>
<ab n="73">Wherefore
now thou shalt not be able to abide the horsemen and so great a
power in the plaine, where is neither stone nor flint, nor place to
flee vnto.</ab>
<ab n="74">So when
Ionathan heard these words of Apollonius, he was moued in his mind,
&amp; choosing ten thousand men, he went out of Ierusalē,
where Simon his brother met him for to helpe him.</ab>
<ab n="75">And hee
pitched his tents against Ioppe: but they of Ioppe shut him out of
the citie, because Apollonius had a garison there.</ab>
<ab n="76">Then
Ionathan laid siege vnto it: whereupon they of the city let him in
for feare: &amp; so Ionathan wan Ioppe.</ab>
<ab n="77">Whereof when
Apollonius heard, he tooke three thousand horsemen with a great
hoste of footmen, and went to Azotus as one that iourneyed, &amp;
therewithal drew him forth into the plaine, because he had a great
number of horsemen, in whom he put his trust.<note> Or, as thogh he would passe thorow it. , Or, led his company.</note></ab>
<ab n="78">Then
Ionathan followed after him to Azotus, where the armies ioyned
battell.</ab>
<ab n="79">Now
Apollonius had left a thousand horsemen in ambush.</ab>
<ab n="80">And Ionathan
knew that there was an ambushment behinde him; for they had
compassed in his host, and cast darts at the people, from morning
till euening.</ab>
<ab n="81">But the
people stood still, as Ionathan had commanded them: and so the
enemies horses were tired.<note> Ios. Antiq. lib.13.c.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="82">Then brought
Simon forth his hoste, and set them against the footmen, (for the
horsmen were spent) who were discomfited by him, and fled.</ab>
<ab n="83">The horsemen
also being scattered in the field, fled to Azotus, and went into
Bethdagō their idols temple for safety.</ab>
<ab n="84">But Ionathan
set fire on Azotus, and the cities round about it, and tooke their
spoiles, and the temple of Dagon, with them that were fled into it,
he burnt with fire.</ab>
<ab n="85">Thus there
were burnt and slaine with the sword, well nigh eight thousand
men.</ab>
<ab n="86">And from
thence Ionathan remoued his hoste, and camped against Ascalon,
where the men of the city came forth, and met him with great
pompe.</ab>
<ab n="87">After this,
returned Ionathan and his hoste vnto Ierusalem, hauing many
spoiles.</ab>
<ab n="88">Now when
king Alexander heard these things, he honoured Ionathan yet
more,</ab>
<ab n="89">And sent him
a buckle of golde, as the vse is to be giuen to such as are of the
kings blood: he gaue him also Accaron with the borders thereof in
possession.</ab>




</div>