<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-13-13b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>8 Simon is made captaine in his
brother Ionathans roume. 19 Tryphon getteth two of Ionathans sonnes
into his hands, and slayeth their father. 27 The tombe of Ionathan.
36 Simon is fauoured by Demetrius, 46 and winneth Gaza, and the
towre at Hierusalem.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when
Simon heard that Tryphon had gathered together a great hoste to
inuade the land of Iudea, and destroy it,</ab>
<ab n="2">And saw that
the people was in great trembling and feare, he went vp to
Ierusalem, and gathered the people together,</ab>
<ab n="3">And gaue them
exhortation, saying: Yee your selues know, what great things I and
my brethren, and my fathers house haue done for the lawes, and the
Sanctuarie, the battels also, and troubles which we haue
seene,</ab>
<ab n="4">By reason
whereof all my brethren are slaine for Israels sake, and I am left
alone.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now therefore
be it farre from me, that I should spare mine owne life in any time
of trouble: for I am no better then my brethren.</ab>
<ab n="6">Doubtlesse I
will auenge my nation and the Sanctuarie, &amp; our wiues, and our
children: for all the heathen are gathered to destroy vs, of very
malice.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now as soone
as the people heard these words, their spirit reuiued.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they
answered with a loud voice, saying, Thou shalt bee our leader in
stead of Iudas and Ionathan thy brother.</ab>
<ab n="9">Fight thou
our battels, &amp; what soeuer thou commandest vs, that will we
doe.</ab>
<ab n="10">So then he
gathered together all the men of warre, and made hast to finish the
walles of Ierusalem, and he fortified it round about.</ab>
<ab n="11">Also he sent
Ionathan, the sonne of Absolom, &amp; with him a great power to
Ioppe, who casting out them that were therein, remained there in
it.</ab>
<ab n="12">So Tryphon
remoued from Ptolemais, with a great power to inuade the land of
Iudea, and Ionathan was with him in warde.</ab>
<ab n="13">But Simon
pitched his tents at Adida, ouer against the plaine.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now when
Tryphon knew that Simon, was risen vp in stead of his brother
Ionathan, and meant to ioyne battell with him, he sent messengers
vnto him, saying,</ab>
<ab n="15">Whereas we
haue Ionathan thy brother in hold, it is for money that he is owing
vnto the kings treasure, concerning the businesse that was
committed vnto him.<note> Or, for the affaires, or officers that he had, for the necessary vses which he had.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Wherefore,
now send an hundred talents of siluer, and two of his sonnes for
hostages, that when he is at liberty he may not reuolt from vs, and
we will let him goe.</ab>
<ab n="17">Heereupon
Simon, albeit he perceiued that they spake deceiptfully vnto him,
yet sent he the money, and the children, lest peraduenture he
should procure to himselfe great hatred of the people:</ab>
<ab n="18">Who might
haue said, Because I sent him not the money, and the children,
therefore is [Ionathan] dead.</ab>
<ab n="19">So he sent
them the children, and the hundred talents: Howbeit [Tryphon]
dissembled, neither would he let Ionathan goe.</ab>
<ab n="20">And after
this came Tryphon to inuade the land, and destroy it, going round
about by the way that leadeth vnto Adora, but Simon and his host
marched against him in euery place wheresoeuer he went.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now they
that were in the towre, sent messengers vnto Tryphon, to the end
that he should hasten his comming vnto them by the wildernesse, and
send them victuals.</ab>
<ab n="22">Wherefore
Tryphon made readie all his horsemen to come that night, but there
fell a very great snow, by reason whereof he came not: So he
departed &amp; came into the countrey of Galaad.</ab>
<ab n="23">And when he
came neere to Bascama, he slew Ionathan, who was buried
there.</ab>
<ab n="24">Afterward
Tryphon returned, and went into his owne land.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then sent
Simon and tooke the bones of Ionathan his brother, and buried them
in Modin the citie of his fathers.</ab>
<ab n="26">And all
Israel made great lamentation for him, and bewailed him many
daies.</ab>
<ab n="27">Simon also
built a monument vpon the Sepulchre of his father and his brethren,
and raised it aloft to the sight, with hewen stone behind and
before.</ab>
<ab n="28">Moreouer hee
set vp seuen pyramides one against another, for his father and his
mother, and his foure brethren.</ab>
<ab n="29">And in these
he made running deuices, about the which he set great pillars, and
vpon the pillars he made all their armour for a perpetuall memory,
and by the armour, ships carued, that they might be seene of all
that saile on the sea.</ab>
<ab n="30">This is the
Sepulchre which he made at Modin, and it standeth yet vnto this
day.</ab>
<ab n="31">Now Tryphon
dealt deceitfully with the yong king Antiochus, and slew
him,</ab>
<ab n="32">And he
raigned in his stead, and crowned himselfe king of Asia, and
brought a great calamitie vpō the land.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then Simon
built vp the strong holds in Iudea, and fensed them about with high
towres, and great walles and gates and barres, and layd vp victuals
therein.<note> Gr. in the strong holds.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Moreouer
Simon chose men, and sent to king Demetrius, to the end he should
giue the land an immunitie, because all that Tryphon did, was to
spoyle.<note> Gr. All Tryphons doings were robberies.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Unto whom
king Demetrius answered and wrote after this maner.</ab>
<ab n="36">King
Demetrius vnto Simon the high Priest, and friend of kings, as also
vnto the Elders and nation of the Iewes, sendeth greeting.</ab>
<ab n="37">The golden
crowne, and the scarlet robe which ye sent vnto vs, we haue
receiued, and wee are ready to make a stedfast peace with you, yea
and to write vnto our officers to confirme the immunities which we
haue granted.</ab>
<ab n="38">And
whatsoeuer couenants we haue made with you, shall stand, and the
strong holdes which yee haue builded shalbe your owne.</ab>
<ab n="39">As for any
ouersight or fault committed vnto this day, we forgiue it, and the
crowne taxe also which yee owe vs, if there were any other tribute
paide in Ierusalem, it shall no more be paide.</ab>
<ab n="40">And looke
who are meet among you to be in our court, let them be inrolled,
and let there be peace betwixt vs.</ab>
<ab n="41">Thus the
yoke of the heathen was taken away from Israel, in the hundred and
seuentieth yeere.</ab>
<ab n="42">Then the
people of Israel began to write in their instruments, and
contracts, in the first yeere of Simon the high Priest, the
gouernour, and leader of the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="43">In those
dayes Simon camped against Gaza, and besieged it round about; he
made also an engine of warre, and set it by the city, and battered
a certaine towre, and tooke it.</ab>
<ab n="44">And they
that were in the Engine leapt into the citie, whereupon there was a
great vproare in the citie:</ab>
<ab n="45">Insomuch as
the people of the citie rent their clothes, and climed vpon the
walles, with their wiues and children, and cried with a lowd voice,
beseeching Simon to grant them peace.<note> Gr. to giue them his right hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And they
said, Deale not with vs according to our wickednesse, but according
to thy mercy.</ab>
<ab n="47">So Simon was
appeased towards them, and fought no more against them, but put
them out of the citie, and cleansed the houses wherein the idols
were: and so entred into it, with songs, and thankesgiuing.</ab>
<ab n="48">Yea, he put
all vncleannesse out of it, and placed such men there, as would
keepe the Law, and made it stronger then it was before, and built
therein a dwelling place for himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="49">They also of
the towre in Ierusalem were kept so strait, that they could neither
come foorth, nor goe into the countrey, nor buy, nor sell,
wherefore they were in great distresse for want of victuals, and a
great number of them perished through famine.</ab>
<ab n="50">Then cried
they to Simon, beseeching him to bee at one with them, which thing
hee graunted them, and when he had put them out from thence, he
cleansed the towre from pollutions:<note> Or, to make peace with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And entred
into it the three and twentieth day of the second moneth, in the
hundred seuentie and one yere, with thankesgiuing, and branches of
palme trees, and with harpes, and cymbals, and with viols and
hymnes, and songs: because there was destroyed a great enemy out of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="52">Hee ordained
also that that day should be kept euery yeere with gladnes.
Moreouer, the hill of the Temple that was by the towre he made
stronger then it was, and there hee dwelt himselfe with his
company.</ab>
<ab n="53">And when
Simon sawe that Iohn his sonne was a valiant man, he made him
captaine of all the hostes and dwelt in Gazara.</ab>



</div>