<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-11-11b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>12 Ptolomeus taketh away his
daughter from Alexander, and entreth vpon his kingdome. 17
Alexander is slaine, and Ptolemeus dieth within three dayes. 20
Ionathan besiegeth the towre at Ierusalem. 26 The Iewes and he are
much honoured by Demetrius, 48 Who is rescued by the Iewes from his
owne subiects in Antioch. 57 Antiochus the yonger honoureth
Ionathan. 61 His exploits in diuers places</head>

<ab n="1">And the king
of Egypt gathered together a great host like the sand that lieth
vpon the Sea shore, and many ships, and went about through deceit
to get Alexanders kingdome, and ioyne it to his owne.</ab>
<ab n="2">Whereupon he
tooke his iourney into Syria in peaceable maner, so as they of the
cities opened vnto him, and met him: for king Alexander had
commanded them so to doe, because he was his father in law.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now as
Ptolomee entred into the cities, he set in euery one of them a
garison of souldiers to kepe it.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when he
came neere to Azotus, they shewed him the temple of Dagon that was
burnt, and Azotus, and the suburbs thereof that were destroyed, and
the bodies that were cast abroad, and them that he had burnt in the
battell, for they had made heapes of them by the way where he
should passe.</ab>
<ab n="5">Also they
told the king whatsoeuer Ionathan had done, to the intent he might
blame him: but the king helde his peace.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Ionathan
met the king with great pompe at Ioppa, where they saluted one
another, and lodged.<note> Gr. slept.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Afterward
Ionathan when he had gone with the king to the riuer called
Eleutherus, returned againe to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="8">King Ptolomee
therefore hauing gotten the dominion of the cities by the sea, vnto
Seleucia vpon the sea coast, imagined wicked counsels against
Alexander.</ab>
<ab n="9">Whereupon he
sent embassadours vnto king Demetrius, saying, Come, let vs make a
league betwixt vs, and I will giue thee my daughter whome Alexander
hath, and thou shalt reigne in thy fathers kingdome:</ab>
<ab n="10">For I repent
þe I gaue my daughter vnto him, for he sought to
slay me.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus did he
slander him, because he was desirous of his kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore he
tooke his daughter from him, and gaue her to Demetrius, and
forsooke Alexander, so that their hatred was openly knowen.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then
Ptolomee entred into Antioch, where he set two crownes vpō his
head, the crowne of Asia, and of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="14">In the meane
season was king Alexander in Cilicia, because those
þe dwelt in those parts, had reuolted from
him.</ab>
<ab n="15">But when
Alexander heard of this, hee came to warre against him, whereupon
king Ptolomee brought forth his hoste, and met him with a mightie
power, and put him to flight.</ab>
<ab n="16">So Alexander
fled into Arabia, there to be defended, but king Ptolomee was
exalted.</ab>
<ab n="17">For Zabdiel
the Arabian tooke off Alexanders head, and sent it vnto
Ptolomee.</ab>
<ab n="18">King
Ptolemee also died the third day after, &amp; they that were in the
strong holds, were slaine one of another.<note> Gr. and those that were in the holds were slaine of those that were in the holds.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">By this
meanes Demetrius reigned in the hundreth, threescore and seuenth
yeere.</ab>
<ab n="20">At the same
time Ionathan gathered together them that were in Iudea, to take
the towre that was in Ierusalem, and he made many engines of warre
against it.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then
certaine vngodly persons who hated their owne people, went vnto the
king, and told him that Ionathan besieged the towre.</ab>
<ab n="22">Whereof when
he heard, he was angry, and immediately remouing, he can to
Ptolemais, and wrote vnto Ionathan, that he should not lay siege to
the towre, but come and speake with him at Ptolemais in great
haste.</ab>
<ab n="23">Neuerthelesse
Ionathan when he heard this, commanded to besiege it [still] and he
chose certaine of the Elders of Israel, and the priests, and put
himselfe in perill.</ab>
<ab n="24">And tooke
siluer and gold, and rayment, and diuers presents besides, and went
to Ptolemais, vnto the king, where he found fauour in his
sight.</ab>
<ab n="25">And though
certaine vngodly men of the people, had made complaints against
him,</ab>
<ab n="26">Yet the king
entreated him as his predecessors had done before, &amp; promoted
him in the sight of all his friends,</ab>
<ab n="27">And
confirmed him in the high priesthood, and in all the honours that
hee had before, and gaue him preeminence among his chiefe
friends.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then
Ionathan desired the king, that hee would make Iudea free from
tribute, as also the three gouernments with the countrey of
Samaria, &amp; he promised him three hundred talents</ab>
<ab n="29">So the king
consented and wrote letters vnto Ionathan, of all these things
after this maner.</ab>
<ab n="30">King
Demetrius vnto his brother Ionathan, and vnto the nation of the
Iewes, sendeth greeting.</ab>
<ab n="31">We send you
heere a copie of the letter, which we did write vnto our cousin
Lasthenes, concerning you, that you might see it.</ab>
<ab n="32">King
Demetrius vnto his father Lasthenes, sendeth greeting:</ab>
<ab n="33">We are
determined to doe good to the people of the Iewes, who are our
friends, and keepe couenants with vs, because of their good will
towards vs.</ab>
<ab n="34">Wherefore we
haue ratified vnto them the borders of Iudea, with the three
gouernments of Apherema, and Lidda, and Ramathem, that are added
vnto Iudea, from the countrie of Samaria, and all things
appertaining vnto them, for all such, as doe sacrifice in
Ierusalem, in stead of the paiments, which the king receiued of
them yeerely aforetime out of the fruits of the earth, and of
trees.<note> Iosep. antiq.lib. 13. cap.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And as for
other things that belong vnto vs of the tithes and customes
pertaining vnto vs, as also the salt pits, and the crowne taxes,
which are due vnto vs, we discharge them of them all for their
reliefe.</ab>
<ab n="36">And nothing
heereof shall be reuoked from this time foorth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="37">Now
therefore see that thou make a copie of these things, and let it be
deliuered vnto Ionathan, and set vpon the holy mount in a
conspicuous place.</ab>
<ab n="38">After this,
when king Demetrius saw that the land was quiet before him, and
that no resistance was made against him, he sent away all his
forces euery one to his owne place, except certaine bands of
strangers, whom he had gathered from the iles of the heathen,
wherefore all the forces of his fathers hated him.</ab>
<ab n="39">Moreouer
there was one Tryphon, that had beene of Alexanders part afore, who
seeing that all the hoste murmured against Demetrius, went to
Simalcue the Arabian, that brought vp Antiochus þe
yong sonne of Alexander,</ab>
<ab n="40">And lay sore
vpon him, to deliuer him [this young Antiochus] that he might
raigne in his fathers stead: he told him therefore all that
Demetrius had done, and how his men of warre were at enmitie with
him, and there he remained a long season.</ab>
<ab n="41">In the meane
time Ionathan sent vnto king Demetrius, that hee would cast those
of the towre out of Ierusalem, and those also in the fortresses.
For they fought against Israel.</ab>
<ab n="42">So Demetrius
sent vnto Ionathan, saying, I will not onely doe this for thee, and
thy people, but I will greatly honour thee and thy nation, if
opportunitie serue.</ab>
<ab n="43">Now
therefore thou shalt do wel if thou send me men to helpe me; for
all my forces are gone from me.</ab>
<ab n="44">Upon this
Ionathan sent him three thousand strong men vnto Antioch, and when
they came to þe king, the king was very glad of
their comming.</ab>
<ab n="45">Howbeit,
they that were of the citie, gathered themselues together into the
midst of the citie, to the number of an hundreth and twentie
thousand men, and would haue slaine the king.</ab>
<ab n="46">Wherefore
the king fled into the court, but they of the citie kept the
passages of the citie, and began to fight.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then the
king called to the Iewes for helpe, who came vnto him all at once,
and dispersing themselues through the city, slew that day in the
citie to the number of an hundred thousand.</ab>
<ab n="48">Also they
set fire on the citie, and gat many spoiles that day, and deliuered
the king.</ab>
<ab n="49">So when they
of the city saw, that the Iewes had got the city as they would,
their courage was abated, wherefore they made supplication to the
king, and cried, saying:</ab>
<ab n="50">Graunt vs
peace, and let the Iewes cease from assaulting vs and the
citie.<note> Or, bee friends with vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">With that
they cast away their weapons, and made peace, and the Iewes were
honoured in the sight of the king, and in the sight of all that
were in his realme, and they returned to Ierusalem hauing great
spoiles.</ab>
<ab n="52">So king
Demetrius sate on the throne of his kingdome, and the land was
quiet before him.</ab>
<ab n="53">Neuerthelesse
hee dissembled in all that euer hee spake, and estranged himselfe
from Ionathan, neither rewarded he him, according to the benefits
which hee had receiued of him, but troubled him very sore.</ab>
<ab n="54">After this
returned Tryphon, and with him the yong childe Antiochus, who
reigned and was crowned.</ab>
<ab n="55">Then there
gathered vnto him all the men of warre whom Demetrius had put away,
and they fought against Demetrius, who turned his backe and
fled.</ab>
<ab n="56">Moreouer
Triphon tooke the Elephants, and wonne Antioch.<note> Gr. beasts.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">At that time
yong Antiochus wrote vnto Ionathan, saying; I confirme thee in the
high Priesthood, and appoint thee ruler ouer the foure gouernments,
and to be one of the kings friends.</ab>
<ab n="58">Upon this he
sent him golden vessels to be serued in, and gaue him leaue to
drinke in gold, and to bee clothed in purple, and to weare a golden
buckle.<note> Gr. and seruice.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">His brother
Simon also he made captaine from the place called the ladder of
Tyrus, vnto the borders of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="60">Then
Ionathan went foorth and passed through the cities beyond the
water, and all the forces of Syria, gathered themselues vnto him
for to helpe him: and when he came to Ascalon, they of the city met
him honorably.<note> Or, went beyond the riuer, and passed through the cities: Or, went and passed beyond the riuer, and through the cities, Gr.</note></ab>
<ab n="61">From whence
he went to Gaza, but they of Gaza shut him out; wherefore hee layd
siege vnto it, and burned the suburbs thereof with fire, and
spoiled them.<note> Or, the places thereabout.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">Afterward
when they of Gaza made supplication vnto Ionathan, he made peace
with them, and tooke the sonnes of the chiefe men for hostages, and
sent them to Ierusalem, and passed through the countrey vnto
Damascus.<note> Gr. he gaue them the right hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">Now when
Ionathan heard that Demetrius Princes were come to Cades which is
in Galilee, with a great power, purposing to remoue him out of the
countrey,<note> Or, to remooue him from the affaires of the kingdome.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">Hee went to
meet them, and left Simon his brother in the countrey.</ab>
<ab n="65">Then Simon
encamped against Bethsura, and fought against it a long season, and
shut it vp:</ab>
<ab n="66">But they
desired to haue peace with him, which he granted them, and then put
them out from thence, and tooke the city, and set a garrison in
it.</ab>
<ab n="67">As for
Ionathan and his hoste, they pitched at the water of Gennesar, from
whence betimes in the morning they gate them to the plaine of
Nasor.</ab>
<ab n="68">And behold,
the hoste of strangers met them in the plaine, who hauing layed men
in ambush for him in the mountaines, came themselues ouer against
him.</ab>
<ab n="69">So when they
that lay in ambush rose out of their places, and ioyned battel, al
that were of Ionathans side fled.</ab>
<ab n="70">In so much
as there was not one of them left, except Mattathias the sonne of
Absolon, and Iudas the sonne of Calphi the captaines of the
hoste.</ab>
<ab n="71">Then
Ionathan rent his clothes, and cast earth vpon his head, and
prayed.</ab>
<ab n="72">Afterwards
turning againe to battell, he put them to flight, and so they ranne
away.</ab>
<ab n="73">Now when his
owne men that were fled saw this, they turned againe vnto him, and
with him pursued them to Cades, euen vnto their owne tents, and
there they camped.</ab>
<ab n="74">So there
were slaine of the heathen that day, about three thousand men, but
Ionathan returned to Ierusalem.</ab>



</div>