<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Antiochus is slaine, and Demetrius
reigneth in his stead. 5 Alcimus would be hie Priest, and
complaineth of Iudas to the king. 16 He slayeth threescore
Asideans. 43 Nicanor is slaine, and the kings forces are defeated
by Iudas. 49 The day of this victorie is kept holy euery
yeere.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
hundreth and one and fiftieth yeere, Demetrius the sonne of
Seleucus departed from Rome, and came vp with a fewe men vnto a
citie of the Sea coast, and reigned there.<note> Tripolis: Ioseph. Ant. lib.10,12. cap.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And as he
entred into the palace of his ancestors, so it was, that his forces
had taken Antiochus and Lysias to bring them vnto him.<note> Gr. house of the kingdome of his father.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore when
he knew it, hee said; Let me not see their faces.</ab>
<ab n="4">So his hoste
slewe them. Now when Demetrius was set vpon the throne of his
kingdome,</ab>
<ab n="5">There came
vnto him all the wicked and vngodly men of Israel, hauing Alcimus
(who was desirous to be high Priest) for their captaine.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they
accused the people to the king, saying; Iudas and his brethren haue
slaine all thy friends, and driuen vs out of our owne land.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
send some man whom thou trustest, and let him goe and see what
hauocke he hath made amongst vs, and in the kings land, and let him
punish them with all them that aide them.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then the king
chose Bacchides a friend of the king, who ruled beyond the flood,
and was a great man in the kingdome, and faithfull to the
king.</ab>
<ab n="9">And him hee
sent with that wicked Alcimus, whom hee made high Priest, and
commanded that he should take vengeance of the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="10">So they
departed, and came with a great power into the land of Iudea, where
they sent messengers to Iudas and his brethren with peaceable words
deceitfully.</ab>
<ab n="11">But they gaue
no heede to their words, for they sawe that they were come with a
great power.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then did
there assemble vnto Alcimus and Bacchides, a company of Scribes, to
require iustice.<note> Or, officers. gouernment, chiefemen, or men in aythoritie.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Now the
Assideans were the first among the children of Israel, that sought
peace of them:</ab>
<ab n="14">For, said
they, one that is a Priest of the seede of Aaron, is come with this
armie, and he will doe vs no wrong.</ab>
<ab n="15">So he spake
vnto them peaceably, and sware vnto them, saying; We will procure
the harme neither of you nor your friends.</ab>
<ab n="16">Whereupon
they beleeued him: howbeit hee tooke of them threescore men, and
slewe them in one day, according to the words which he
wrote:</ab>
<ab n="17">The flesh of
thy Saints [haue they cast out] and their blood haue they shed
round about Ierusalem, and there was none to bury them.<note> Psal.79. 2,3.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Wherefore the
feare and dread of them fell vpon all the people, who said, There
is neither trueth, nor righteousnesse in them; for they haue broken
the couenant and othe that they made.<note> Gr. iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">After this
remooued Bacchides from Ierusalem, and pitched his tents in Bezeth,
where he sent and tooke many of the men that had forsaken him, and
certaine of the people also, and when he had slaine them, [he cast
them] into the great pit.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then
committed he the countrey to Alcimus, and left with him a power to
aide him: so Bacchides went vnto the king.</ab>
<ab n="21">But Alcimus
contended for the high Priesthood.<note> Or, laboured to defend his high Priesthood.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And vnto him
resorted all such as troubled the people, who after they had gotten
the land of Iuda into their power, did much hurt in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now when
Iudas saw all the mischiefe that Alcimus and his company had done
among the Israelites, euen aboue the heathen,</ab>
<ab n="24">He went out
into all the coast of Iudea round about, and tooke vengeance of
them that had reuolted from him, so that they durst no more goe
foorth into the countrey.<note> Or, fledde from him to the enemie. , Or, inuade the countrey.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">On the other
side, when Alcimus saw that Iudas and his company had gotten the
vpper hand, and knew that he was not able to abide their force, he
went againe to the king, and said all the worst of them that he
could.<note> Or, were growen very strong. , Gr. to abide them.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Then the king
sent Nicanor one of his honourable princes, a man that bare deadly
hate vnto Israel, with commandement to destroy the people.</ab>
<ab n="27">So Nicanor
came to Ierusalem with a great force: and sent vnto Iudas and his
brethren deceitfully with friendly words, saying,<note> Gr. peaceable.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Let there be
no battell betweene me and you, I will come with a fewe men, that I
may see you in peace.<note> Gr. see your faces.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">He came
therefore to Iudas, and they saluted one another peaceably. Howbeit
the enemies were prepared to take away Iudas by violence.</ab>
<ab n="30">Which thing
after it was knowen to Iudas (to wit) that he came vnto him with
deceit, he was sore afraid of him, and would see his face no
more.</ab>
<ab n="31">Nicanor also
when he saw that his counsell was discouered, went out to fight
against Iudas besides Capharsalama.<note> Gr. meet Iudas in battell. , Or, Carphasalama.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Where there
were slaine of Nicanors side, about fiue thousand men, and [the
rest] fled into the citie of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="33">After this
went Nicanor vp to mount Sion, and there came out of the Sanctuarie
certaine of the priestes, and certaine of the elders of the people
to salute him peaceably, and to shewe him the burnt sacrifice that
was offred for the king.</ab>
<ab n="34">But he mocked
them, and laughed at them, and abused them shamefully, and spake
proudly,<note> Gr. defiled them.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And swore in
his wrath, saying, vnlesse Iudas and his hoste be now deliuered
into my hands, if euer I come againe in safetie, I will burne vp
this house: and with that he went out in a great rage.<note> Gr. in peace</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Then the
priests entred in, and stood before the altar, and the Temple,
weeping, and saying,</ab>
<ab n="37">Thou O Lord
didst choose this house, to be called by thy Name, and to be a
house of prayer and petition for thy people.</ab>
<ab n="38">Be auenged of
this man and his hoste, and let them fall by the sword: Remember
their blasphemies, and suffer them not to continue any
longer.</ab>
<ab n="39">So Nicanor
went out of Ierusalem, &amp; pitched his tents in Bethoron, where
an hoste out of Syria met him.</ab>
<ab n="40">But Iudas
pitched in Adasa with three thousand men, and there he prayed,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="41">O Lord, when
they that were sent from the king of the Assyrians blasphemed,
thine Angel went out, and smote a hundred, fourescore, and fiue
thousand of them.<note> 2.Kings 19.35. esai. 37.36. ecclus.48.22. 2.mac.8.19</note></ab>
<ab n="42">Euen so
destroy thou this host before vs this day, that the rest may know
that he hath spoken blasphemously against thy Sanctuary, and iudge
thou him according to his wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="43">So the
thirteenth day of the moneth Adar, the hostes ioyned battell, but
Nicanors host was discomfited, &amp; he himselfe was first slaine
in the battell.</ab>
<ab n="44">Now when
Nicanors host saw that he was slaine, they cast away their weapons,
and fled.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then they
pursued after them a dayes iourney from Adasa, vnto Gasera,
sounding an alarme after them with their trumpets.<note> Or, the Iewes,</note></ab>
<ab n="46">Whereupon
they came forth out of all the townes of Iudea round about, and
closed them in, so that they turning backe vpon them that pursued
them, were all slaine with the sword, and not one of them was
left.</ab>
<ab n="47">Afterwards
they tooke þe spoiles, and the pray, and smote off
Nicanors head, &amp; his right hand, which he stretched out so
proudly, and brought them away; and hanged them vp, towards
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="48">For this
cause the people reioyced greatly, and they kept that day, a day of
great gladnesse.</ab>
<ab n="49">Moreouer they
ordeined to keepe yeerely this day, being the thirteenth of
Adar.</ab>
<ab n="50">Thus the land
of Iuda was in rest a litle while.</ab>



</div>