<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-5-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-5-5b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>3 Iudas smiteth the children of Dan,
Bean, and Ammon. 17 Simon is sent into Galile. 15 The exploits of
Iudas in Galaad. 51 He destroyeth Ephron, for denying him to passe
through it. 56 Diuerse, that in Iudas absence would fight with
their enemies, are slaine.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when the
nations round about heard that the Altar was built, &amp; the
Sanctuarie renewed as before, it displeased them very much.</ab>
<ab n="2">Wherfore they
thought to destroy the generation of Iacob that was among them, and
thereupon they began to slay and destroy the people.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then Iudas
fought against the children of Esau in Idumea at Arabattine,
because they besieged Israel: and hee gaue them a great ouerthrow,
and abated their courage, and tooke their spoiles.<note> Or, Arabathene, or Arabattan, or Arabestins.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Also he
remembred the iniurie of the children of Bean, who had bene a snare
and an offence vnto the people, in that they lay in waite for them
in the wayes.<note> Or, malice. , Or, Haran, Gene. 36. 27. &amp; num. 33.3,32.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Hee shut them
vp therefore in the towres, and incamped against them, and
destroyed them vtterly, and burnt the towers of that place with
fire, and all that were therein.</ab>
<ab n="6">Afterward he
passed ouer to the children of Ammon, where he found a mighty
power, and much people, with Timotheus their captaine.</ab>
<ab n="7">So he fought
many battels with them, till at length they were discomfited before
him; and he smote them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when hee
had taken Iazar, with the townes belonging thereto, he returned
into Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then the
heathen that were at Galead, assembled themselues together against
the Israelites that were in their quarters to destroy them: but
they fled to the fortresse of Dathema;</ab>
<ab n="10">And sent
letters vnto Iudas and his brethren: The heathen that are round
about vs, are assembled together against vs to destroy vs;</ab>
<ab n="11">And they are
preparing to come and take the fortresse whereunto wee are fled,
Timotheus being captaine of their host.</ab>
<ab n="12">Come now
therefore and deliuer vs from their handes, for many of vs are
slaine.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yea all our
brethren that were in the places of Tobie, are put to death, their
wiues and their children; Also they haue caried away captiues, and
borne away their stuffe, and they haue destroied there about a
thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="14">While these
letters were yet reading, behold there came other messengers from
Galilee with their clothes rent, who reported on this wise,</ab>
<ab n="15">And said:
They of Ptolemais, and of Tyrus, and Sidon, and all Galilee of the
Gentiles are assembled together against vs to consume vs.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now when
Iudas and the people heard these wordes, there assembled a great
congregation together, to consult what they should doe for their
brethren, that were in trouble and assaulted of them.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then said
Iudas vnto Simon his brother, Choose thee out men, and goe, and
deliuer thy brethren that are in Galilee, for I and Ionathan my
brother, will goe into the countrey of Galaad.</ab>
<ab n="18">So hee left
Ioseph the sonne of Zacharias, and Azarias captaines of the people,
with the remnant of the hoste in Iudea to keepe it,</ab>
<ab n="19">Unto whom he
gaue commandement, saying, Take yee the charge of this people, and
see that you make not warre against the heathen, vntill the time
that we come againe.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now vnto
Simon were giuen three thousand men to goe into Galilee, and vnto
Iudas eight thousand men for the countrey of Galaad.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then went
Simon into Galilee, where hee fought many battels with the heathen,
so that the heathen were discomfited by him.</ab>
<ab n="22">And hee
pursued them vnto the gate of Ptolemais; And there were slaine of
the heathen about three thousand men, whose spoiles he
tooke.</ab>
<ab n="23">And those
that were in Galilee and in Arbattis, with their wiues and their
children, and all that they had, tooke he away [with him] and
brought them into Iudea, with great ioy.<note> Or, captiue Iewes.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Iudas
Maccabeus also and his brother Ionathan, went ouer Iordan, and
trauailed three dayes iourney in the wildernesse,</ab>
<ab n="25">Where they
met with the Nabathites, who came vnto them in peaceable maner, and
told them euery thing that had happened to their brethren in the
land of Galaad,</ab>
<ab n="26">And how that
many of them were shut vp in Bosora, and Bosor, in Alema, Casphor,
Maked &amp; Carnaim (all these cities are strong and
great.)<note> Or, Bosora. , Or, Chascor.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And that they
were shut vp in the rest of the cities of the countrey of Galaad,
and that against to morrow they had appointed to bring their host
against the forts, and to take them, and to destroy them all in one
day.<note> Or, the heathen.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Hereupon
Iudas and his host turned suddenly by the way of the wildernesse
vnto Bosorra, and when he had wonne the citie, hee slew all the
males with the edge of the sword, and tooke all their spoiles, and
burnt the citie with fire.<note> Or, Bosor.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">From whence
hee remooued by night, and went till he came to the
fortresse.</ab>
<ab n="30">And betimes
in the morning they looked vp, &amp; behold, there was an
innumerable people bearing ladders, and other engines of warre, to
take the fortresse: for they assaulted them.<note> Gr. lift vp their eyes. , The heathen assaulted the Iewes.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">When Iudas
therefore saw that the battaile was begun, and that the cry of the
citie went vp to heauen, with trumpets, and a great sound,</ab>
<ab n="32">He said vnto
his hoste, Fight this day for your brethren.</ab>
<ab n="33">So he went
foorth behinde them in three companies, who sounded their trumpets,
and cryed with prayer.</ab>
<ab n="34">Then the
hoste of Timotheus knowing that it was Maccabeus, fled from him:
wherefore hee smote them with a great slaughter: so that there were
killed of them that day about eight thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="35">This done,
Iudas turned aside to Maspha, and after he had assaulted it, hee
tooke it, and slewe all the males therein, and receiued the spoiles
therof, and burnt it with fire.</ab>
<ab n="36">From thence
went he, and tooke Casphon, Maged, Bosor, and the other cities of
the countrey of Galaad.</ab>
<ab n="37">After these
things, gathered Timotheus another hoste, and encamped against
Raphon beyond the brooke.</ab>
<ab n="38">So Iudas sent
[men] to espie the hoste, who brought him word, saying; All the
heathen that be round about vs, are assembled vnto them, euen a
very great hoste.</ab>
<ab n="39">Hee hath also
hired the Arabians to helpe them, and they haue pitched their tents
beyond the brooke, readie to come and fight against thee: vpon this
Iudas went to meet them.</ab>
<ab n="40">Then
Timotheus said vnto the captaines of his hoste, When Iudas and his
hoste come neere the brooke, if he passe ouer first vnto vs, we
shall not be able to withstand him, for hee will mightily preuaile
against vs.</ab>
<ab n="41">But if he be
afraid, and campe beyond the riuer, we shall goe ouer vnto him, and
preuaile against him.</ab>
<ab n="42">Now when
Iudas came neere the brooke, he caused the Scribes of the people to
remaine by the brooke: vnto whom hee gaue commandement, saying,
Suffer no man to remaine in the campe, but let all come to the
battell.</ab>
<ab n="43">So he went
first ouer vnto them, and all the people after him: then all the
heathen being discomfited before him, cast away their weapons, and
fled vnto the Temple that was at Carnaim.</ab>
<ab n="44">But they
tooke the citie, and burnt the Temple, with all that were therein.
Thus was Carnaim subdued, neither could they stand any longer
before Iudas.<note> Iudas and his company.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Then Iudas
gathered together all the Israelites that were in the countrey of
Galaad from the least vnto the greatest, euen their wiues and their
children, and their stuffe, a very great hoste, to the ende they
might come into the land of Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="46">Now when they
came vnto Ephron (this was a great city in the way as they should
goe, very well fortified) they could not turne from it, either on
the right hand or the left, but must needs passe through the midst
of it.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then they of
the city shut them out, and stopped vp the gates with
stones.</ab>
<ab n="48">Whereupon
Iudas sent vnto them in peaceable maner, saying; Let vs passe
through your land to goe into our owne countrey, and none shall doe
you any hurt, we will onely passe thorow on foote: howbeit they
would not open vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="49">Wherefore
Iudas commaunded a proclamation to be made throughout the hoste,
that euery man should pitch his tent in the place where he
was.</ab>
<ab n="50">So the
souldiers pitched, and assaulted the city all that day, and all
that night, till at the length the city was deliuered into his
hands:</ab>
<ab n="51">Who then slew
all the males with the edge of the sword, and rased the city, and
tooke the spoiles therof, and passed through the city ouer them
that were slaine.</ab>
<ab n="52">After this
went they ouer Iordan, into the great plaine before
Bethsan.</ab>
<ab n="53">And Iudas
gathered together those that came behind, and exhorted the people
all the way through, till they came into the land of
Iudea.<note> Or, went hindmost, Num. 10.25 , Or, comforted, or encouraged.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">So they went
vp to mount Sion with ioy and gladnesse, where they offered burnt
offerings, because not one of them were slaine, vntill they had
returned in peace.<note> Peace offerings, Ioseph. Antiq. 12. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">Now what time
as Iudas and Ionathan were in the land of Galaad, and Simon his
brother in Galilee before Ptolemais,</ab>
<ab n="56">Ioseph the
sonne of Zacharias, and Azarias, captaines of the garisons, heard
of the valiant actes and warlike deeds which they had done.</ab>
<ab n="57">Wherefore
they said, Let vs also get vs a name, and goe fight against the
heathen that are round about vs.</ab>
<ab n="58">So when they
had giuen charge vnto the garison that was with them, they went
towards Iamnia.</ab>
<ab n="59">Then came
Gorgias and his men out of the citie to fight against
them.<note> Gr. to meet them in battell.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">And so it
was, that Ioseph and Azarias were put to flight, and pursued vnto
the borders of Iudea, and there were slaine that day of the people
of Israel about two thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="61">Thus was
there a great ouerthrow among the children of Israel, because they
were not obedient vnto Iudas, and his brethren, but thought to doe
some valiant act.</ab>
<ab n="62">Moreouer
these men came not of the seed of those, by whose hand deliuerance
was giuen vnto Israel.</ab>
<ab n="63">Howbeit the
man Iudas and his brethren were greatly renowned in the sight of
all Israel, and of all the heathen wheresoeuer their name was heard
of,</ab>
<ab n="64">Insomuch as
the people assembled vnto them with ioyfull acclamations.</ab>
<ab n="65">Afterward
went Iudas foorth with his brethren, and fought against the
children of Esau in the land toward the South, where he smote
Hebron, and the townes thereof, and pulled downe the fortresse of
it, and burnt the townes thereof round about.<note> Gr. daughters.</note></ab>
<ab n="66">From thence
he remoued to goe into the land of the Philistines, and passed
through Samaria.<note> Gr. strangers.</note></ab>
<ab n="67">At that time
certaine priests desirous to shew their valour, were slaine in
battell, for that they went out to fight vnaduisedly.</ab>
<ab n="68">So Iudas
turned to Azotus in the land of the Philistines, and when he had
pulled downe their altars, and burnt their carued images with fire,
and spoiled their cities, he returned into the land of
Iudea.</ab>



</div>