<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-9-9b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Alcimus and Bacchides come againe
with new forces into Iudea. 7 The armie of Iudas flee from him, 17
and he is slaine. 30 Ionathan is in his place, 40 and reuengeth his
brother Iohns quarrell. 55 Alcimus is plagued, and dieth. 70
Bacchides maketh peace with Ionathan.</head>

<ab n="1">Furthermore,
when Demetrius heard that Nicanor and his hoste were slaine in
battell, hee sent Bacchides and Alcimus into the land of Iudea the
second time, and with them the chiefe strength of his
hoste.<note> Gr. he added or proceeded to send. , Or, the right wing.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Who went forth
by the way that leadeth to Galgala, and pitched their tents before
Masaloth, which is in Arbela, and after they had wonne it, they
slew much people.<note> Or, Galilea.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Also the first
moneth of the hundred fiftie and second yeere, they encamped before
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="4">From whence
they remoued and went to Berea, with twentie thousand footmen, and
two thousand horsemen.<note> Or, Berretho. Ios.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Now Iudas had
pitched his tents at Eleasa, and three thousand chosen men with
him.</ab>
<ab n="6">Who seeing the
multitude of the other army to be so great, were sore afraide,
whereupon many conueyed themselues out of the hoste, insomuch as
there abode of them no moe but eight hundred men.</ab>
<ab n="7">When Iudas
therefore saw that his hoste slipt away, and that the battell
pressed vpon him, he was sore troubled in mind, and much distressed
for that he had no time to gather them together.</ab>
<ab n="8">Neuerthelesse
vnto them that remained, he said; Let vs arise and goe vp against
our enemies, if peraduenture we may be able to fight with
them.</ab>
<ab n="9">But they
dehorted him, saying, Wee shall neuer be able: Let vs now rather
saue our liues, and hereafter we will returne with our brethren,
and fight against them: for we are but few.<note> We follow here the Romane copie.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then Iudas
said, God forbid that I should doe this thing, and flee away from
them: If our time be come, let vs die manfully for our brethren,
and let vs not staine our honour.<note> Gr. let vs not leaue any iust cause behinde vs, why our glory should be spoken against.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">With that the
hoste [of Bacchides] remoued out of their tents, and stood ouer
against them, their horsemen being diuided into two troupes, and
their slingers and archers going before the hoste, and they that
marched in the foreward were all mighty men.<note> Or the Iewes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">As for
Bacchides, hee was in the right wing, so the hoste drew neere on
the two parts, and sounded their trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="13">They also of
Iudas side, euen they sounded their trumpets also, so that the
earth shooke at the noise of the armies, and the battell continued
from morning till night.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now when
Iudas perceiued that Bacchides and the strength of his armie were
on the right side, he tooke with him all the hardy men,</ab>
<ab n="15">Who
discomfited the right wing, and pursued them vnto the mount
Azotus.</ab>
<ab n="16">But when they
of the left wing, saw that they of the right wing were discomfited,
they followed vpon Iudas and those that were with him hard at the
heeles from behinde:</ab>
<ab n="17">Whereupon
there was a sore battell, insomuch as many were slaine on both
parts.</ab>
<ab n="18">Iudas also
was killed, and the remnant fled.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then Ionathan
and Simon tooke Iudas their brother, and buried him in the
sepulchre of his fathers in Modin.</ab>
<ab n="20">Moreouer they
bewailed him, and all Israel made great lamentation for him, and
mourned many dayes, saying;</ab>
<ab n="21">How is the
valiant man fallen, that deliuered Israel?</ab>
<ab n="22">As for the
other things concerning Iudas and his warres, and the noble actes
which he did, and his greatnesse, they are not written: for they
were very many.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Now
after the death of Iudas, the wicked began to put foorth their
heads in all the coasts of Israel, and there rose vp all such as
wrought iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="24">In those
dayes also was there a very great famine, by reason whereof the
countrey reuolted, and went with them.<note> Bacchis and his company.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then
Bacchides chose the wicked men, and made them lordes of the
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they made
enquirie &amp; search for Iudas friends, and brought them vnto
Bacchides, who tooke vengeance of them, and vsed them
despitefully.<note> Gr. mocked them.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">So was there
a great affliction in Israel, the like whereof was not since the
time that a Prophet was not seene amongst them.</ab>
<ab n="28">For this
cause all Iudas friends came together, &amp; said vnto
Ionathan,</ab>
<ab n="29">Since thy
brother Iudas died, we haue no man like him to goe foorth against
our enemies, and Bacchides, and against them of our nation that are
aduersaries to vs.</ab>
<ab n="30">Now therefore
wee haue chosen thee this day to be our prince, and captaine in his
stead, that thou mayest fight our battels.</ab>
<ab n="31">Upon this,
Ionathan tooke the gouernance vpon him at that time, and rose vp in
stead of his brother Iudas.</ab>
<ab n="32">But when
Bacchides gat knowledge thereof, he sought for to slay him.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then Ionathan
and Simon his brother, and all that were with him, perceiuing that,
fled into the wildernes of Thecoe, and pitched their tents by the
water of the poole Asphar.</ab>
<ab n="34">Which when
Bacchides vnderstood, he came neere to Iordan with all his hoste
vpon the Sabbath day.<note> Or, Which when Bacchides understood, or the Sabbath day he came neere.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Now Ionathan
had sent his brother [ Iohn] a captaine of the people, to pray his
friendes the Nabbathites that they might leaue with them their
cariage, which was much.<note> Ios. Antiq. lib.13. c.1. , Gr. that he might leaue with them their cariage or stuffe.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">But the
children of Iambri came out of Medaba, and tooke Iohn and all that
hee had, and went their way with it.</ab>
<ab n="37">After this
came word to Ionathan and Simon his brother, that the children of
Iambri made a great mariage, and were bringing the bride from
Nadabatha with a great traine, as being the daughter of one of the
great princes of Canaan.<note> Or, Medaba.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Therfore they
remembred Iohn their brother, and went vp and hidde themselues
vnder the couert of the mountaine.</ab>
<ab n="39">Where they
lift vp their eyes, and looked, &amp; behold, there was much adoe
and great cariage: and the bridegrome came foorth, and his friends
&amp; brethren to meet them with drums and instruments of musicke,
and many weapons.<note> Or, timbrels , Or, musicians.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Then Ionathan
and they that were with him, rose vp against them from the place
where they lay in ambush, and made a slaughter of them in such
sort, as many fell downe dead, and the remnant fledde into the
mountaine, and they tooke all their spoiles.</ab>
<ab n="41">Thus was the
mariage turned into mourning, and the noise of their melody into
lamentation.</ab>
<ab n="42">So when they
had auenged fully the blood of their brother, they turned againe to
the marish of Iordan.</ab>
<ab n="43">Now when
Bacchides heard hereof, hee came on the Sabbath day vnto the banks
of Iordan with a great power.</ab>
<ab n="44">Then Ionathan
sayde to his company, Let vs goe vp now and fight for our liues,
for it standeth not with vs to day, as in time past:</ab>
<ab n="45">For behold,
the battell is before vs and behinde vs, and the water of Iordan on
this side and that side, the marish likewise and wood, neither is
there place for vs to turne aside.</ab>
<ab n="46">Wherefore cry
ye now vnto heauen, that ye may be deliuered from the hand of your
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="47">With that
they ioyned battel, and Ionathan stretched foorth his hand to smite
Bacchides, but hee turned backe from him.</ab>
<ab n="48">Then Ionathan
and they that were with him, leapt into Iordan, and swamme ouer
vnto the farther banke: howbeit the other passed not ouer Iordan
vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="49">So there were
slaine of Bacchides side that day about a thousand men<note> Two thousand men. Ioseph.ant. lib. 13. cap. 1</note></ab>
<ab n="50">Afterward
returned [Bacchides] to Ierusalem, and repaired the strong cities
in Iudea: the fort in Iericho, and Emmaus, and Bethoron, and
Bethel, and Thamnatha, Pharathoni, and Taphon (these did he
strengthen with high wals, with gates, &amp; with
barres.)<note> Or, built. , Ioseph.Techoa.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And in them
he set a garison, that they might worke malice vpon Israel.</ab>
<ab n="52">He fortified
also the citie Bethsura, and Gazara, and the towre, and put forces
in them, and prouision of victuals.<note> Gr. the citie in Bethsura.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">Besides, he
tooke the chiefe mens sonnes in the country for hostages, and put
them into the towre at Ierusalem to be kept.</ab>
<ab n="54">Moreouer, in
the hundred, fiftie and third yere, in the second moneth, Alcimus
commanded that the wall of the inner court of the Sanctuarie should
be pulled downe, he pulled downe also the works of the
prophets.</ab>
<ab n="55">And as he
began to pull downe, euen at that time was Alcimus plagued, and his
enterprises hindered: for his mouth was stopped, and he was taken
with a palsie, so that hee could no more speake any thing, nor giue
order concerning his house.</ab>
<ab n="56">So Alcimus
died at that time with great torment.</ab>
<ab n="57">Now when
Bacchides saw that Alcimus was dead, he returned to the king,
wherupon the land of Iudea was in rest two yeere.</ab>
<ab n="58">Then all the
vngodly men held a counsell, saying, Behold, Ionathan and his
companie are at ease, and dwell without care: now therefore wee
will bring Bacchides hither, who shall take them all in one
night.</ab>
<ab n="59">So they went,
and consulted with him.</ab>
<ab n="60">Then remoued
he, and came with a great hoste, and sent letters priuily to his
adherents in Iudea, that they should take Ionathan, and those that
were with him: Howbeit they could not, because their counsell was
knowen vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="61">Wherefore
they tooke of the men of the countrey that were authours of that
mischiefe, about fiftie persons, and slew them.</ab>
<ab n="62">Afterward
Ionathan and Simon, and they that were with him, got them away to
Bethbasi, which is in the wildernesse, and they repaired the
decayes thereof, and made it strong.</ab>
<ab n="63">Which thing
when Bacchides knew, he gathered together all his host, and sent
word to them that were of Iudea.<note> Or, to such of the countrey as were his friends to take his part.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">Then went he
and laid siege against Bethbasi, &amp; they fought against it a
long season, and made engines of warre.</ab>
<ab n="65">But Ionathan
left his brother Simon in the citie, and went forth himselfe into
the countrey, and with a certaine number went he forth.</ab>
<ab n="66">And he smote
Odonarkes and his brethren, and the children of Phasiron in their
tent.<note> Or, Odomarra.</note></ab>
<ab n="67">And when he
began to smite them, and came vp with his forces, Simon and his
company went out of the citie, and burnt vp the engines of
warre,</ab>
<ab n="68">And fought
against Bacchides, who was discomfited by them, and they afflicted
him sore. For his counsell and trauaile was in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="69">Wherefore he
was very wroth at the wicked men that gaue him counsell to come
into the countrey, insomuch as he slew many of them, and purposed
to returne into his owne countrey.</ab>
<ab n="70">Whereof when
Ionathan had knowledge, he sent ambassadours vnto him, to the end
he should make peace with him, &amp; deliuer them the
prisoners.</ab>
<ab n="71">Which thing
hee accepted, and did according to his demaunds, and sware vnto him
that hee would neuer doe him harme all the dayes of his
life.</ab>
<ab n="72">When
therefore hee had restored vnto him the prisoners that he had taken
aforetime out of the land of Iudea, he returned and went his way
into his owne land, neither came he any more into their
borders.<note> Gr. added he to come any more.</note></ab>
<ab n="73">Thus the
sword ceased from Israel: but Ionathan dwelt at Machmas, and began
to gouerne the people, and he destroyed the vngodly men out of
Israel.<note> Gr. iudge</note></ab>



</div>