<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>6 Iudas defeateth the plot 14 and
forces of Gorgias, 23 and spoileth their tents, 34 and ouerthroweth
Lysias. 45 He pulleth downe the Altar which the heathen had
prophaned, and setteth vp a newe, 60 and maketh a wall about
Sion.</head>

<ab n="1">Then tooke
Gorgias fiue thousand footmen, and a thousand of the best horsemen,
and remooued out of the campe by night:</ab>
<ab n="2">To the end he
might rush in vpon the camp of the Iewes, and smite them suddenly.
And the men of the fortresse were his guides.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now when Iudas
heard thereof, hee himselfe remooued, and the valiant men with him,
that hee might smite the Kings armie which was at Emmaus,</ab>
<ab n="4">While as yet
the forces were dispersed from the campe.</ab>
<ab n="5">In the meane
season came Gorgias by night into the campe of Iudas: and when hee
found no man there, hee sought them in the mountaines: for said
hee, these fellowes flee from vs.</ab>
<ab n="6">But assoone as
it was day, Iudas shewed himselfe in the plaine with three thousand
men, who neuerthelesse had neither armour, nor swordes to their
mindes.<note> Or, targets.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they sawe
the campe of the heathen, that it was strong, and well harnessed,
and compassed round about with horsemen; and these were expert of
warre.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then said
Iudas to the men that were with him: feare ye not their multitude,
neither be ye afraid of their assault</ab>
<ab n="9">Remember how
our fathers were deliuered in the red Sea, when Pharao pursued them
with an armie.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now therfore
let vs crie vnto heauen, if peraduenture the Lord wil haue mercie
vpon vs, and remember the couenant of our fathers, and destroy this
hoste before our face this day.</ab>
<ab n="11">That so all
the heathen may know that there is one, who deliuereth and saueth
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then the
strangers lift vp their eyes, &amp; saw them comming ouer against
them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Wherefore
they went out of the campe to battell, but they that were with
Iudas sounded their trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="14">So they
ioyned battell, and the heathen being discomfited, fled into the
plaine.</ab>
<ab n="15">Howbeit all
the hindmost of them were slaine with the sword: for they pursued
them vnto Gazera, and vnto the plaines of Idumea, and Azotus, and
Iamnia, so that there were slaine of them, vpon a three thousand
men.</ab>
<ab n="16">This done,
Iudas returned againe with his hoste frō pursuing
them,</ab>
<ab n="17">And said to
the people, Bee not greedie of the spoiles, in as much as there is
a battell before vs,</ab>
<ab n="18">And Gorgias
and his hoste are here by vs in the mountaine, but stand ye now
against your enemies, and ouercome them, &amp; after this you may
boldly take the spoiles.</ab>
<ab n="19">As Iudas was
yet speaking these words, there appeared apart of them looking out
of the mountaine.</ab>
<ab n="20">Who when they
perceiued that the Iewes had put their hoste to flight, and were
burning the tents: (for the smoke that was seene declared what was
done)</ab>
<ab n="21">When
therefore they perceiued these things, they were sore afraid, and
seeing also the hoste of Iudas in the plaine ready to
fight:</ab>
<ab n="22">They fled
euery one into the land of strangers.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then Iudas
returned to spoile the tents, where they got much golde, and
siluer, and blew silke, and purple of the sea, and great
riches.</ab>
<ab n="24">After this,
they went home, and sung a song of thankesgiuing, &amp; praised the
Lord in heauen: because it is good, because his mercie endureth for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thus Israel
had a great deliuerance that day.</ab>
<ab n="26">Now all the
strangers that had escaped, came and told Lysias what had
happened.</ab>
<ab n="27">Who when hee
heard thereof, was confounded, and discouraged, because neither
such things as he would, were done vnto Israel, nor such things as
the king commanded him were come to passe.</ab>
<ab n="28">The next
yeere therefore following, Lysias gathered together threescore
thousand choice men of foote, and fiue thousand horsemen, that he
might subdue them.</ab>
<ab n="29">So they came
into Idumea, and pitched their tents at Bethsura, and Iudas met
with them ten thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="30">And when he
saw that mighty armie, he prayed, and said, Blessed art thou, O
sauiour of Israel, who diddest quaile the violence of the mighty
man by the hand of thy seruant Dauid, and gauest, the host of
strangers into the hands of Ionathan the sonne of Saul, and his
armour bearer.<note> 1.Sam.17 50,51. , Or, Philistines, , 1.Sam.14 13,14.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Shut vp this
armie in the hand of thy people Israel, and let them be confounded
in their power and horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="32">Make them to
be of no courage, and cause the boldnesse of their strength to fall
away, &amp; let them quake at their destruction.<note> Gr. melt.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Cast them
downe with the sword of them that loue thee, and let all those that
know thy name, praise thee with thanksgiuing.</ab>
<ab n="34">So they
ioyned battaile, and there were slaine of the host of Lysias about
fiue thousand men, euen before them were they slaine.</ab>
<ab n="35">Now when
Lysias saw his armie put to flight, and the manlinesse of Iudas
souldiers, and how they were ready, either to liue or die
valiantly, he went into Antiochia, and gathered together a company
of strangers, and hauing made his armie greater then it was, he
purposed to come againe into Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then saide
Iudas and his brethren, behold our enemies are discomfited: let vs
goe vp to cleanse, and dedicate the Sanctuarie.<note> Or, repaire</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Upon this all
the host assembled themselues together, and went vp into mount
Sion.</ab>
<ab n="38">And when they
saw the sanctuarie desolate, and the altar prophaned, and the gates
burnt vp, and shrubs growing in the courts, as in a forrest, or in
one of the mountaines, yea and the priests chambers pulled
downe,</ab>
<ab n="39">They rent
their clothes, and made great lamentation, and cast ashes vpon
their heads,</ab>
<ab n="40">And fell
downe flat to the ground vpon their faces, and blew an alarme with
the trumpets, and cried towards heauen.</ab>
<ab n="41">Then Iudas
appointed certaine men to fight against those that were in the
fortresse, vntill he had clensed the Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="42">So he chose
priests of blamelesse conuersation, such as had pleasure in the
law.</ab>
<ab n="43">Who cleansed
the Sanctuarie, and bare out the defiled stones into an vncleane
place.</ab>
<ab n="44">And when as
they consulted what to doe with the altar of burnt offrings which
was prophaned,</ab>
<ab n="45">They thought
it best to pull it downe, lest it should be a reproch to them,
because the heathen had defiled it; wherefore they pulled it
downe,</ab>
<ab n="46">And laide vp
the stones in the mountaine of the temple in a conuenient place,
vntill there should come a Prophet, to shew what should be done
with them.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then they
tooke whole stones according to the law, and built a new altar,
according to the former:<note> Exod. 20 25. deut 27 5, &amp; Iosh. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And made vp
the Sanctuarie, and the things that were within the temple, and
hallowed the courts.</ab>
<ab n="49">They made
also new holy vessels, and into the temple they brought the
candlesticke, and the altar of burnt offerings, and of incense, and
the table.</ab>
<ab n="50">And vpon the
altar they burnt incense, and the lamps that were vpon the
candlesticke they lighted, that they might giue light in the
temple.</ab>
<ab n="51">Furthermore
they set the loaues vpon the table, and spread out the veiles, and
finished all the workes which they had begunne to make.<note> Or, spread abroad the hangings, or hanged vp the uailes.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Now on the
fiue and twentieth day of the ninth moneth, (which is called the
moneth Casleu) in the hundreth fourty and eight yeere they rose vp
betimes in the morning,</ab>
<ab n="53">And offered
sacrifice according to the law vpon the new altar of burnt
offerings, which they had made.</ab>
<ab n="54">Looke at what
time, and what day the heathen had prophaned it, euen in that was
it dedicated with songs, and cittherns, and harpes, &amp;
cimbals.</ab>
<ab n="55">Then all the
people fell vpon their faces, worshipping and praising the God of
heauen, who had giuen them good successe.</ab>
<ab n="56">And so they
kept the dedication of the altar eight dayes, and offered burnt
offerings with gladnesse, and sacrificed the sacrifice of
deliuerance and praise.<note> Or, peace offerings.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">They deckt
also the forefront of the temple with crownes of gold; and with
shields, and the gates, and the chambers they renewed and hanged
doores vpon them.<note> Or, dedicated. , Or, made doores for them.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">Thus was
there very great gladnesse among the people, for that the reproch
of the heathen was put away.</ab>
<ab n="59">Moreouer
Iudas and his brethren with the whole congregation of Israel
ordained that the daies of the dedication of the altar, should be
kept in their season from yeere to yeere by the space of eight
dayes, from the fiue and twentieth day of the moneth Casleu, with
mirth and gladnesse.</ab>
<ab n="60">At that time
also they builded vp the mount Sion with high walles, and strong
towres round about, lest the Gentiles should come &amp; tread it
downe, as they had done before.</ab>
<ab n="61">And they set
there a garison to keepe it: and fortified Bethsura to preserue it,
that the people might haue a defence against Idumea.</ab>



</div>