<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The valour and fame of Iudas
Maccabeus. 10 He ouerthroweth the forces of Samaria and Syria. 27
Antiochus sendeth a great power against him. 44 He and his fall to
fasting and prayer, 58 and are encouraged.</head>

<ab n="1">Then his sonne
Iudas, called Maccabeus, rose vp in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="2">And all his
brethren helped him, and so did all they that held with his father,
and they fought with cheerefulnesse, the battaile of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">So he gate his
people great honor, and put on a brestplate as a giant, and girt
his warlike harnesse about him, and he made battels, protecting the
host with his sword.</ab>
<ab n="4">In his acts he
was like a lyon, and like a lyons whelp roaring for his
pray.</ab>
<ab n="5">For hee
pursued the wicked, and sought them out, and burnt vp those that
vexed his people.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore the
wicked shrunke for feare of him, and all the workers of iniquity
were troubled, because saluation prospered in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="7">He grieued
also many kings, and made Iacob glad with his acts, and his
memoriall is blessed for euer.</ab>
<ab n="8">Moreouer he
went through the citties of Iuda, destroying the vngodly out of
them, and turning away wrath from Israel.</ab>
<ab n="9">So that he was
renowned vnto the vtmost part of the earth, &amp; he receiued vnto
him such as were ready to perish.<note> Gre. gathered together.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then
Apollonius gathered the Gentiles together, and a great host out of
Samaria to fight against Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">Which thing
when Iudas perceiued he went forth to meete him, and so he smote
him, and slew him, many also fell downe slaine, but the rest
fled.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore
Iudas tooke their spoiles, and Apollonius sword also, and therewith
he fought, all his life long.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now when
Seron a prince of the armie of Syria, heard say that Iudas had
gathered vnto him a multitude and company of the faithfull, to goe
out with him to warre.</ab>
<ab n="14">He said, I
will get me a name and honour in the kingdome, for I will goe fight
with Iudas, and them that are with him, who despise the kings
commandement.</ab>
<ab n="15">So he made
him ready to goe vp, and there went with him a mighty host of the
vngodly to helpe him, and to be auenged of the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when hee
came neere to the going vp of Bethoron, Iudas went forth to meet
him with a smal company.</ab>
<ab n="17">Who when they
saw the host comming to meet them, said vnto Iudas; How shall wee
be able, being so few to fight against so great a multitude, and so
strong, seeing wee are ready to faint with fasting all this
day?</ab>
<ab n="18">Unto whom
Iudas answered: It is no hard matter for many to bee shut vp in the
hands of a few; and with the God of heauen it is all one, to
deliuer with a great multitude, or a small company:<note> 1.Sam.14. 6. 2. chron. 14.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For the
victory of battell standeth not in the multitude of an hoste, but
strength commeth from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="20">They come
against vs in much pride and iniquitie to destroy vs, and our wiues
&amp; children, and to spoile vs:<note> Or, vnto vs. , Greek in multitude of pride, or enuie, and iniquitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But wee fight
for our liues, and our Lawes.</ab>
<ab n="22">Wherefore the
Lord himselfe will ouerthrow them before our face: and as for you,
be ye not afraid of them.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now as soone
as hee had left off speaking, he lept suddenly vpon them, and so
Seron and his host was ouerthrowen before him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they
pursued them from the going downe of Bethoron, vnto the plaine,
where were slaine about eight hundred men of them; and the residue
fledde into the land of the Philistines.<note> Gr. in the going downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then began
the feare of Iudas and his brethren, &amp; an exceeding great dread
to fall vpon the nations round about them:</ab>
<ab n="26">In so much,
as his fame came vnto the king, and all nations talked of the
battels of Iudas.</ab>
<ab n="27">Now when King
Antiochus heard these things, he was full of indignation: wherefore
hee sent and gathered together all the forces of his realme [euen]
a very strong armie.</ab>
<ab n="28">He opened
also his treasure, and gaue his souldiers pay for a yeere,
commanding them to be ready, whensoeuer he should need
them.<note> Gr. or at euery need.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Neuerthelesse,
when he saw that the money of his treasures failed, and that the
tributes in the countrey were small, because of the dissention, and
plague which he had brought vpon the land, in taking away the Lawes
which had bene of old time,<note> Gr. that the collectors of tribute in the countrey were few. , Or, for the taking away of the Lawes</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Hee feared
that he should not be able to beare the charges any longer, nor to
haue such gifts to giue so liberally, as he did before: for hee had
abounded aboue the Kings that were before him.<note> Gr. that he should not haue.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Wherefore,
being greatly perplexed in his minde, hee determined to goe into
Persia, there to take the tributes of the countreys, and to gather
much money.</ab>
<ab n="32">So hee left
Lysias a noble man, and one of the blood royall, to ouersee the
affaires of the King, from the riuer Euphrates, vnto the borders of
Egypt:</ab>
<ab n="33">And to bring
vp his sonne Antiochus, vntill he came againe.</ab>
<ab n="34">Moreouer he
deliuered vnto him the halfe of his forces, and the Elephants, and
gaue him charge of all things that he would haue done, as also
concerning them that dwelt in Iuda and Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="35">To wit, that
he should send an armie against them, to destroy and root out the
strength of Israel, and the remnant of Ierusalem, and to take away
their memoriall from that place:</ab>
<ab n="36">And that he
should place strangers in all their quarters, and diuide their land
by lot.</ab>
<ab n="37">So the king
tooke the halfe of the forces that remained, and departed from
Antioch his royall city, the hundreth fourtie and seuenth yeere,
and hauing passed the riuer Euphrates, hee went through the high
countreys.<note> Gr. a citie of his kingdome.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Then Lysias
chose Ptoleme, the son of Dorymenes and Nicanor, &amp; Gorgias,
mighty men of the kings friends:</ab>
<ab n="39">And with them
hee sent fourtie thousand footmen, and seuen thousand horsemen to
goe into the land of Iuda, and to destroy it as the king
cōmanded.</ab>
<ab n="40">So they went
forth with all their power, and came and pitched by Emmaus in the
plaine countrey.</ab>
<ab n="41">And the
merchants of the countrey, hearing the fame of them, tooke siluer,
&amp; gold very much, with seruants, and came into the campe to buy
the children of Israel for slaues; A power also of Syria, and of
the land of the Philistines, ioyned themselues vnto
them.<note> Or, fetters. , Or, of strangers.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">Now when
Iudas and his brethren saw that miseries were multiplied, &amp;
that the forces did encampe themselues in their borders, (for they
knewe how the king had giuen commaundement to destroy the people,
and vtterly abolish them.)</ab>
<ab n="43">They said one
to another, Let vs restore the decayed estate of our people, and
let vs fight for our people and the Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="44">Then was the
Congregation gathered together, that they might be ready for
battell, and that they might pray, and aske mercy and
compassion.</ab>
<ab n="45">Now Ierusalem
lay voide as a wildernesse, there was none of her children that
went in or out: the Sanctuarie also was troden downe, and aliens
kept the strong holde: the heathen had their habitation in that
place, and ioy was taken from Iacob, and the pipe with the harpe
ceased.</ab>
<ab n="46">Wherefore the
Israelites assembled themselues together, and came to Maspha
ouer-against Ierusalem; for in Maspha was the place where they
prayed aforetime in Israel.<note> Or, Muspa.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Then they
fasted that day, and put on sackecloth, and cast ashes vpon their
heads, and rent their clothes:</ab>
<ab n="48">And laide
open the booke of the Law, wherein þe heathen had
sought to paint the likenesse of their images.<note> Or, for the which the heathen had made diligent search that they might paint therein the likenesse of their idols.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">They brought
also the Priestes garments, and the first fruits, and the tithes,
and the Nazarites they stirred vp, who had accomplished their
dayes.<note> Num.6.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">Then cried
they with a loud voice toward heauen, saying, What shall we doe
with these, and whither shall wee cary them away?</ab>
<ab n="51">For thy
Sanctuarie is troden downe and profaned, and thy Priestes are in
heauinesse, and brought low.</ab>
<ab n="52">And loe, the
heathen are assembled together against vs, to destroy vs: what
things they imagine against vs, thou knowest.</ab>
<ab n="53">How shall wee
be able to stand against them, except thou (O God) be our
helpe?</ab>
<ab n="54">Then sounded
they with trumpets, and cryed with a loude voice.</ab>
<ab n="55">And after
this, Iudas ordained captains ouer the people, euen captains ouer
thousands, and ouer hundreds, and ouer fifties, and ouer
tennes.</ab>
<ab n="56">But as for
such as were building houses, or had betrothed wiues, or were
planting vineyards, or were fearefull, those hee commanded that
they should returne, euery man to his owne house, according to the
Law.<note> Deu.20.5. , Iudg.7.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">So the campe
remooued, and pitched vpon the South side of Emmaus.</ab>
<ab n="58">And Iudas
sayde, Arme your selues, and be valiant men, and see that ye be in
readinesse against the morning, that yee may fight with these
nations, that are assembled together against vs, to destroy vs and
our Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="59">For it is
better for vs to die in battell, then to behold the calamities of
our people, and our Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="60">Neuerthelesse,
as the will [of God] is in heauen, so let him doe.</ab>



</div>