<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>3 Demetrius is taken by the King of
Persia. 4 The good deedes of Simon to his countrey. 18 The
Lacedemonians and Romans renew their league with him. 26 A
memoriall of his actes is set vp in Sion.</head>

<ab n="1">Now in the
hundred threescore and twelfth yeere, king Demetrius gathered his
forces together, and went into Media, to get him helpe to fight
against Tryphon.</ab>
<ab n="2">But when
Arsaces the king of Persia &amp; Media, heard that Demetrius was
entred within his borders, he sent one of his princes to take him
aliue.</ab>
<ab n="3">Who went and
smote the hoste of Demetrius, and tooke him and brought him to
Arsaces, by whom hee was put in warde.</ab>
<ab n="4">As for the
land of Iudea, that was quiet all the dayes of Simon: for he sought
the good of his nation, in such wise, as that euermore his
authoritie and honour pleased them well.</ab>
<ab n="5">And as he was
honourable (in all his acts) so in this, that he tooke Ioppe for an
hauen, and made an entrance to the yles of the Sea,</ab>
<ab n="6">And enlarged
the boundes of his nation, and recouered the countrey,</ab>
<ab n="7">And gathered
together a great number of captiues, and had the dominion of Gazara
and Bethsura, and the towre, out of the which he tooke all
vncleannesse, neither was there any that resisted him.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then did they
till their ground in peace, and the earth gaue her increase, and
the trees of the field their fruit.</ab>
<ab n="9">The ancient
men sate all in the streetes, communing together of good things,
and the young men put on glorious and warrelike
apparell.<note> Or, the wealth of the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">He prouided
victuals for the cities, and set in them all maner of munition, so
that his honourable name was renowmed vnto the end of the
world.</ab>
<ab n="11">He made
peace in the land, and Israel reioyced with great ioy:</ab>
<ab n="12">For euery
man sate vnder his vine, and his figgetree, and there was none to
fray them:<note> 1.Kings 4.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Neither was
there any left in the lande to fight against them: yea, the Kings
themselues were ouerthrowen in those dayes.</ab>
<ab n="14">Moreouer hee
strengthened all those of his people that were brought low: the Law
he searched out, and euery contemner of the Law, and wicked person,
he tooke away.</ab>
<ab n="15">He
beautified the Sanctuary, and multiplied the vessels of the
Temple.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now when it
was heard at Rome, &amp; as far as Sparta, that Ionathan was dead,
they were very sorie.</ab>
<ab n="17">But assoone
as they heard that his brother Simon was made high Priest in his
stead, and ruled the countrey, and the cities therein,</ab>
<ab n="18">They wrote
vnto him in tables of brasse, to renew the friendship &amp; league
which they had made with Iudas and Ionathan his brethren:</ab>
<ab n="19">Which
writings were read before the Congregation at Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="20">And this is
the copy of the letters that the Lacedemonians sent: The rulers of
the Lacedemonians, with the city, vnto Simon the high Priest, and
the Elders and Priestes, and residue of the people of the Iewes,
our brethren, send greeting.</ab>
<ab n="21">The
Embassadors that were sent vnto our people, certified vs of your
glory and honour, wherefore we were glad of their comming,</ab>
<ab n="22">And did
register the things that they spake, in the counsell of the people,
in this maner: Numenius sonne of Antiochus, and Antipater sonne of
Iason, the Iewes Embassadours, came vnto vs, to renew the
friendship they had with vs.</ab>
<ab n="23">And it
pleased the people to entertaine the men honourably, and to put the
copy of their embassage in publike records, to the end the people
of the Lacedemonians might haue a memoriall therof: furthermore we
haue written a copy thereof vnto Simon the hie Priest.</ab>
<ab n="24">After this,
Simon sent Numenius to Rome, with a great shield of golde of a
thousand pound weight, to confirme the league with them.</ab>
<ab n="25">Whereof when
the people heard, they said, What thankes shall wee giue to Simon
and his sonnes?</ab>
<ab n="26">For hee and
his brethren, and the house of his father, haue established Israel,
and chased away in fight their enemies from them, and confirmed
their libertie.</ab>
<ab n="27">So then they
wrote [it] in tables of brasse, which they set vpon pillars in
mount Sion, and this is the copie of the writing. The eighteenth
day of the moneth Elul, in the hundred threescore and twelft yeere,
being the third yeere of Simon the hie priest,</ab>
<ab n="28">At Saramel
in the great congregation of the priests and people, and rulers of
the nation, &amp; elders of the country, were these things notified
vnto vs.<note> Or, Ierusalem, peraduenture by corruption and transposition of letters, or as some thinke, the common hall where they met to consult of matters of estate.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Forsomuch as
often times there haue bin warres in the countrey, wherin for the
maintenance of their Sanctuarie, and the law, Simon the sonne of
Mattathias of the posteritie of Iarib, together with his brethren,
put themselues in ieopardie, and resisting the enemies of their
nation, did their nation great honour.</ab>
<ab n="30">(For after
that Ionathan hauing gathered his nation together, and bene their
hie priest, was added to his people,</ab>
<ab n="31">Their
enemies purposed to inuade their countrey that they might destroy
it, and lay hands on the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="32">At which
time Simon rose vp, and fought for his nation, and spent much of
his own substance, &amp; armed the valiant men of his nation, &amp;
gaue them wages,<note> Or, the men of warre.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And
fortified the cities of Iudea, together with Bethsura that lieth
vpon the borders of Iudea, where the armour of the enemies had bin
before, but he set a garison of Iewes there.<note> Or, weapons.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Moreouer,
hee fortified Ioppe which lieth vpon the Sea, and Gazara that
bordereth vpon Azotus, where the enemies had dwelt before: but hee
placed Iewes there, and furnished them with all things conuenient
for the reparation thereof.)<note> Or, Gaza.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">The people
therefore seeing the acts of Simon, and vnto what glory he thought
to bring his nation, made him their gouernor and chiefe priest,
because he had done all these things, and for the iustice and faith
which hee kept to his nation, and for that hee sought by all meanes
to exalt his people.</ab>
<ab n="36">For in his
time things prospered in his hands, so that the heathen were taken
out of their countrey, and they also that were in the citie of
Dauid in Ierusalem, who had made themselues a towre, out of which
they issued, and polluted all about the Sanctuarie, and did much
hurt in the holy place.<note> Or, vnto religion.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">But he
placed Iewes therein, and fortified it for the safetie of the
countrey, and the city, and raised vp the wals of
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="38">King
Demetrius also confirmed him in the high priesthood, according to
those things,</ab>
<ab n="39">And made him
one of his friends, and honoured him with great honour.</ab>
<ab n="40">For he had
heard say, that the Romanes had called the Iewes their friends, and
confederates, and brethren, and that they had entertained the
Embassadours of Simon honourably.</ab>
<ab n="41">Also that
the Iewes &amp; priests were wel pleased that Simon should be their
gouernour, and high priest for euer vntil there should arise a
faithfull prophet.</ab>
<ab n="42">Moreouer,
that he should be their captaine, and should take charge of the
Sanctuarie, to set them ouer their workes, and ouer the countrey,
and ouer the armour, and ouer the fortresses, that (I say) he
should take charge of the Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="43">Besides
this, that he should be obeyed of euery man, and that all the
writings in the countrey should be made in his name, and that he
should be clothed in purple, and weare gold.</ab>
<ab n="44">Also that it
should be lawfull for none of the people or priests, to breake any
of these things, or to gainesay his words, or to gather an assembly
in the countrey without him, or to bee clothed in purple, or weare
a buckle of gold.</ab>
<ab n="45">And
whosoeuer should do otherwise, or breake any of these things, he
should be punished.</ab>
<ab n="46">Thus it
liked all þ<note/> people to deale with Simon, &amp; to
do as hath bene said.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then Simon
accepted hereof, and was well pleased to be high Priest, and
captaine, and gouernour of the Iewes, &amp; priests, &amp; to
defend them all.</ab>
<ab n="48">So they
commanded that this writing should be put in tables of brasse, and
that they should be set vp within the compasse of the Sanctuary in
a conspicuous place.</ab>
<ab n="49">Also
þ<note/> the copies therof should be laid vp in the
treasurie, to the ende that Simon &amp; his sonnes might haue
them.</ab>



</div>