<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-16-16-2-Maccabees.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>3 Iudas and Iohn preuaile against
the forces sent by Antiochus. 11 The captaine of Hierico inuiteth
Simon and two of his sonnes into his castle, and there
treacherously murdereth them. 19 Iohn is sought for, 22 and
escapeth, and killeth those that sought for him.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came vp
Iohn from Gazara, and told Simon his father, what Cendebeus had
done.</ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore
Simon called his two eldest sonnes, Iudas and Iohn, and said vnto
them, I and my brethren, and my fathers house haue euer from our
youth vnto this day fought against the enemies of Israel, and
things haue prospered so well in our hands, that wee haue deliuered
Israel oftentimes.</ab>
<ab n="3">But now I am
old, and yee [by Gods mercy] are of a sufficient age: Be ye in
stead of mee, and my brother, and goe and fight for our nation, and
the helpe from heauen be with you.</ab>
<ab n="4">So hee chose
out of the countrey twentie thousand men of warre with horsemen,
who went out against Cendebeus, and rested that night at
Modin.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when as
they rose in the morning, and went into the plaine, behold, a
mighty great hoste both of footmen, and horsmen, came against them:
Howbeit there was a water brooke betwixt them.</ab>
<ab n="6">So hee and
his people pitched ouer against them, and when hee saw that the
people were afraid to goe ouer the water brooke, hee went first
ouer himselfe, and then the men seeing him, passed through after
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">[That done]
he diuided his men, and set the horsemen in the midst of the
footemen: for the enemies horsemen were very many.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then sounded
they with the holy Trumpets: whereupon Cendebeus and his hoste were
put to flight, so that many of them were slaine, and the remnant
gat them to the strong hold.</ab>
<ab n="9">At that time
was Iudas Iohns brother wounded: But Iohn still followed after
them, vntill he came to Cedron which [Cendebeus] had built.</ab>
<ab n="10">So they fled
euen vnto the towres in the fields of Azotus, wherefore hee burnt
it with fire: So that there were slaine of them about two thousand
men. Afterward hee returned into the land of Iudea in
peace.<note> Or, which when he had set fire, they fled vnto the towres in the fields of A. Lotus, and there were slaine, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Moreouer, in
the plaine of Iericho was Ptolomeus the sonne of Abubus made
captaine, and hee had abundance of siluer and golde.</ab>
<ab n="12">For he was
the hie Priests sonne in lawe.</ab>
<ab n="13">Wherefore
his heart being lifted vp, hee thought to get the countrey to
himselfe, and thereupon consulted deceitfully against Simon and his
sons, to destroy them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now Simon
was visiting the cities that were in the countrey, and taking care
for the good ordering of them, at which time hee came downe
himselfe to Iericho with his sons, Mattathias and Iudas, in the
hundreth threescore and seuenth yeere, in the eleuenth moneth
called Sabat.</ab>
<ab n="15">Where the
sonne of Abubus receiuing them deceitfully into a little holde
called Docus, which he had built, made them a great banquet:
howbeit he had hidde men there.</ab>
<ab n="16">So when
Simon and his sonnes had drunke largely, Ptolome and his men rose
vp, and tooke their weapons, and came vpon Simon into the
banketting place, and slewe him and his two sonnes, and certaine of
his seruants.</ab>
<ab n="17">In which
doing, he committed a great treachery, and recompensed euill for
good.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then Ptolome
wrote these things, and sent to the king, that he should send him
an hoste to aide him, and he would deliuer him the countrey and
cities.</ab>
<ab n="19">He sent
others also to Gazara to kill Iohn, &amp; vnto the tribunes he sent
letters to come vnto him, that he might giue them siluer, and
golde, &amp; rewards.<note> Gr. captaines of thousands.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And others
he sent to take Ierusalem, and the mountaine of the temple.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now one had
runne afore to Gazara, and tolde Iohn that his father and brethren
were slaine, and [quoth he] Ptolome hath sent to slay thee
also.</ab>
<ab n="22">Hereof when
he heard, hee was sore astonished: So he laide hands on them that
were come to destroy him, and slew them, for hee knew that they
sought to make him away.</ab>
<ab n="23">As
concerning the rest of the actes of Iohn, and his wars &amp; worthy
deeds which hee did, and the building of the walles which he made,
and his doings,</ab>
<ab n="24">Behold,
these are written in the Chronicles of his Priesthood, from the
time he was made high Priest after his father.</ab>



</div>