<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-15-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>4 Antiochus desireth leaue to passe
through Iudea, &amp; granteth great honours to Simon and the Iewes.
16 The Romanes write to diuerse kings &amp; nations to fauour the
Iewes. 27 Antiochus quarrelleth with Simon, 38 and sendeth some to
annoy Iudea.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer
Antiochus sonne of Demetrius the king, sent letters from the isles
of the Sea, vnto Simon the priest, and prince of the Iewes, and to
all the people.</ab>
<ab n="2">The contents
whereof were these: King Antiochus, to Simon the high Priest, and
prince of his nation, and to the people of the Iewes,
greeting,</ab>
<ab n="3">For as much
as certaine pestilent men, haue vsurped the kingdome of our
fathers, and my purpose is to chalenge it againe, that I may
restore it to the old estate, and to that end haue gathered a
multitude of forraine souldiers together, and prepared shippes of
warre,</ab>
<ab n="4">My meaning
also being to goe through the countrey, that I may be auenged of
them that haue destroyed it, and made many cities in the kingdome
desolate:</ab>
<ab n="5">Now therefore
I confirme vnto thee, all the oblations which the kings before me
granted thee, and whatsoeuer gifts besides they granted.</ab>
<ab n="6">I giue thee
leaue also to coine money for thy countrey with thine owne
stampe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And as
concerning Ierusalem, and the Sanctuarie, let them be free, and al
the armour that thou hast made, and fortresses that thou hast
built, and keepest in thy hands, let them remaine vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">And if any
thing bee, or shall be owing to the king, let it be forgiuen thee,
from this time forth for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="9">Furthermore,
when we haue obtained our kingdome, we will honour thee, and thy
nation, and thy temple with great honour, so that your honour shall
bee knowen throughout the world.</ab>
<ab n="10">In the
hundred threescore and fourteenth yeere, went Antiochus into the
land of his fathers, at which time all the forces came together
vnto him, so that few were left with Tryphon.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore
being pursued by king Antiochus, he fled vnto Dora, which lieth by
the Seaside.</ab>
<ab n="12">For he saw,
that troubles came vpon him all at once, and that his forces had
forsaken him.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then camped
Antiochus against Dora, hauing with him, an hundred and twentie
thousand men of warre, and eight thousand horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when he
had compassed the citie round about, and ioyned ships close to the
towne on the Sea side, hee vexed the citie by land, and by Sea,
neither suffered he any to goe out or in.</ab>
<ab n="15">In the meane
season came Numenius, &amp; his company from Rome hauing letters to
the kings and countries, wherein were written these things.</ab>
<ab n="16">Lucius,
Consul of the Romanes, vnto king Ptolomee greeting.</ab>
<ab n="17">The Iewes
Embassadors our friends and confederates, came vnto vs to renew the
old friendship and league, being sent from Simon the high Priest,
and from the people of the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they
brought a shield of gold, of a thousand pound:</ab>
<ab n="19">We thought
it good therefore, to write vnto the kings and countries, that they
should doe them no harme, nor fight against them, their cities, or
countries, nor yet aide their enemies against them.</ab>
<ab n="20">It seemed
also good to vs, to receiue the shield of them.</ab>
<ab n="21">If therefore
there be any pestilent fellowes, that haue fled from their countrie
vnto you, deliuer them vnto Simon the high priest, that hee may
punish them according to their owne lawe.</ab>
<ab n="22">The same
thing wrote hee likewise vnto Demetrius the king, and Attalus, to
Ariarathes, and Arsaces,<note> Or, Arathes.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And to all
the countries, and to Sampsames, &amp; the Lacedemonians, and to
Delus, and Myndus, and Sycion, and Caria, and Samos, and Pamphylia,
and Lycia, and Halicarnassus, and Rhodus, and Phaseilis, and Cos,
and Sidee, and Aradus, and Gortina, and Cnidus, and Cyprus, and
Cyrene.<note> Or, Sampsaces. , Or, Basilis.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the copy
heereof they wrote, to Simon the high Priest.</ab>
<ab n="25">So Antiochus
the king camped against Dora, the second day, assaulting it
continually, and making engins, by which meanes he shut vp Tryphon,
that he could neither goe out nor in.<note> Gre. bringing his forces to it.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">At that time
Simon sent him two thousand chosen men to aide him: siluer also,
and gold, and much armour.</ab>
<ab n="27">Neuerthelesse,
he would not receiue them, but brake all the couenants which he had
made with him afore, and became strange vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="28">Furthermore
hee sent vnto him Athenobius, one of his friends to commune with
him and say: you withhold Ioppe and Gazara with the towre that is
in Ierusalem, which are cities of my realme.</ab>
<ab n="29">The borders
thereof yee haue wasted and done great hurt in the land, and got
the dominion of many places within my kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="30">Now
therefore deliuer the cities which ye haue taken, and the tributes
of the places whereof yee haue gotten dominion without the borders
of Iudea.<note> Or, except the borders, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Or else giue
me for them fiue hundred talents of siluer, and for the harme that
you haue done, and the tributes of the cities other fiue hundred
talents: if not, we wil come and fight against you.<note> Or, subdue you in fight.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">So
Athenobius the kings friend came to Ierusalem, and when hee saw the
glory of Simon, and the cupboard of gold, and siluer plate, and his
great attendance, he was astonished and told him the kings
message.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then
answered Simon, and said vnto him, We haue neither taken other mens
land, nor holden that which apperteineth to others, but the
inheritance of our fathers, which our enemies had wrongfully in
possession a certaine time.</ab>
<ab n="34">Wherefore we
hauing opportunitie, hold the inheritance of our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="35">And whereas
thou demaundest Ioppe and Gazara; albeit they did great harme vnto
the people in our countrey, yet will we giue an hundred talents for
them. Hereunto Athenobius answered him not a word,</ab>
<ab n="36">But returned
in a rage to the king, and made report vnto him of these speaches,
and of the glory of Simon, and of all that hee had seene: whereupon
the king was exceeding wroth.</ab>
<ab n="37">In the meane
time fled Tryphon by ship vnto Orthosias.</ab>
<ab n="38">Then the
king made Cendebeus captaine of the sea coast, and gaue him an
hoste of footmen and horsemen,</ab>
<ab n="39">And
commanded him to remoue his hoste toward Iudea: also hee commanded
him to build vp Cedron, and to fortifie the gates, &amp; to warre
against the people, but as for the king [himselfe] he pursued
Tryphon.</ab>
<ab n="40">So Cendebeus
came to Iamnia, and began to prouoke the people, and to inuade
Iudea, and to take the people prisoners, and slay them.</ab>
<ab n="41">And when hee
had built vp Cedron, he set horsemen there, and an host [of
footmen] to the end that issuing out, they might make outroades
vpon the wayes of Iudea, as the king had commanded him.</ab>



</div>