<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-1-1b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>14 Antiochus gaue leaue to set vp
the fashions of the Gentiles in Hierusalem, 22 And spoiled it,
&amp; the temple in it, 57 And set vp therin the abomination of
desolation, 63 And slew those that did circumcise their
children.</head>

<ab n="1">And it
happened, after that Alexander sonne of Philip, the Macedonian, who
came out of the land of Chettum, had smitten Darius king of the
Persians and Medes, that hee reigned in his stead, the first ouer
Greece,<note> Or. Chethum.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And made many
wars, and wan many strong holds, and slew the kings of the
earth,</ab>
<ab n="3">And went
through to the ends of the earth, and tooke spoiles of many
nations, insomuch, that the earth was quiet before him, whereupon
he was exalted, and his heart was lifted vp.<note> Or, his heart was exalted and lifted vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And he
gathered a mighty strong hoste, and ruled ouer countries, and
nations and kings, who became tributaries vnto him.<note> Or, kingdomes which became &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And after
these things he fell sicke, and perceiued that he should
die.<note> Gre that he dieth.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore he
called his seruants, such as were honourable, and had bin brought
vp with him from his youth, and parted kis kingdome among them,
while he was yet aliue:</ab>
<ab n="7">So Alexander
reigned twelue yeeres, and (then) died.</ab>
<ab n="8">And his
seruants bare rule euery one in his place.</ab>
<ab n="9">And after his
death they all put crownes [vpon themselues] so did their sonnes
after them, many yeeres, and euils were multiplied in the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="10">And there
came out of them a wicked roote, Antiochus [surnamed] Epiphanes,
sonne of Antiochus the king, who had beene an hostage at Rome, and
he reigned in the hundreth and thirty and seuenth yeere of the
kingdome of the Greekes.</ab>
<ab n="11">In those
daies went there out of Israel wicked men, who perswaded many,
saying, Let vs goe, and make a couenant with the heathen, that are
round about vs: for since we departed from them, we haue had much
sorrow.<note> Gre. many euils haue found vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So this
deuise pleased them well.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then certaine
of the people were so forward heerein, that they went to the king,
who gaue them licence to doe after the ordinances of the
heathen.</ab>
<ab n="14">Whereupon
they built a place of exercise at Ierusalem, according to the
customes of the heathen,<note> Or, set vp an open schoole at Ierusalem.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And made
themselues, vncircumcised, and forsooke the holy couenant, and
ioyned themselues to the heathen, and were sold to doe
mischiefe.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now when the
kingdome was established, before Antiochus, hee thought to reigne
ouer Egypt, that he might haue þ<note/> dominion of two
realms:</ab>
<ab n="17">Wherefore he
entred into Egypt with a great multitude, with chariots, and
elephants, and horsemen, and a great nauie,</ab>
<ab n="18">And made
warre against Ptolomee king of Egypt, but Ptolomee was afraide of
him, and fled: and many were wounded to death.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thus they got
the strong cities in the land of Egypt, and hee tooke the spoiles
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="20">And after
that Antiochus had smitten Egypt, he returned againe in the
hundreth fortie and third yeere, and went vp against Israel and
Ierusalem with a great multitude,</ab>
<ab n="21">And entred
proudly into the sanctuarie, and tooke away the golden altar, and
the candlesticke of light, and all the vessels thereof,</ab>
<ab n="22">And the table
of the shewbread, and the powring vessels, and the vials, and the
censers of gold, &amp; the vaile, and the crownes, &amp; the golden
ornaments that were before the temple, all which he pulled
off.<note> Or, he pilled all things.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Hee tooke
also the siluer and the gold, and the pretious vessels: also he
tooke the hidden treasures which hee found:<note> Gr. desireable.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And when hee
had taken all away, he went into his owne land, hauing made a great
massacre, and spoken very proudly.</ab>
<ab n="25">Therfore
there was great mourning in Israel, in euery place where they
were;</ab>
<ab n="26">So that the
Princes and Elders mourned, the virgines and yong men were made
feeble, and the beautie of women was changed.</ab>
<ab n="27">Euery
bridegrome tooke vp lamentation, and she that sate in the marriage
chamber, was in heauinesse.</ab>
<ab n="28">The land also
was moued for the inhabitants thereof, and all the house of Iacob
was couered with confusion.</ab>
<ab n="29">And after two
yeeres fully expired, the king sent his chiefe collectour of
tribute vnto the cities of Iuda, who came vnto Ierusalem with a
great multitude,</ab>
<ab n="30">And spake
peaceable wordes vnto them, but [all was] deceit: for when they had
giuen him credence, he fell suddenly vpon the citie, and smote it
very sore, &amp; destroyed much people of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="31">And when hee
had taken the spoiles of the citie, hee set it on fire, and pulled
downe the houses, and walles thereof on euery side.</ab>
<ab n="32">But the women
&amp; children tooke they captiue, and possessed the
cattell.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then builded
they the citie of Dauid with a great and strong wall, [and] with
mightie towers, and made it a strong hold for them,</ab>
<ab n="34">And they put
therein a sinfull nation, wicked men, and fortified [themselues]
therein.</ab>
<ab n="35">They stored
it also with armour and victuals, and when they had gathered
together the spoiles of Ierusalem, they layd them vp there, and so
they became a sore snare:</ab>
<ab n="36">For it was a
place to lie in wait against the Sanctuary, and an euill aduersary
to Israel.</ab>
<ab n="37">Thus they
shed innocent blood on euery side of the Sanctuary, and defiled
it.</ab>
<ab n="38">In so much
that the inhabitants of Ierusalem fledde because of them, whereupon
[the citie] was made an habitation of strangers, &amp; became
strange to those that were borne in her, and her owne children left
her:</ab>
<ab n="39">Her Sanctuary
was laid waste like a wildernesse, her feasts were turned into
mourning, her Sabbaths into reproch, her honour into
contempt.</ab>
<ab n="40">As had bene
her glory, so was her dishonour encreased, and her excellencie was
turned into mourning.</ab>
<ab n="41">Moreouer king
Antiochus wrote to his whole kingdome, that all should be one
people,</ab>
<ab n="42">And euery one
should leaue his lawes: so all the heathen agreed, according to the
commandement of the king.</ab>
<ab n="43">Yea many also
of the Israelites consented to his religion, and sacrificed vnto
idols, and prophaned the Sabbath.</ab>
<ab n="44">For the king
had sent letters by messengers vnto Ierusalem, and the cities of
Iuda, that they should follow the strange lawes of the
land,<note> Or, the lawes and rites of the strangers of the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And forbid
burnt offerings, and sacrifice, and drinke offerings in the temple;
and that they should prophane the Sabbaths, and festiuall
dayes:</ab>
<ab n="46">And pollute
the Sanctuarie and holy people:</ab>
<ab n="47">Set vp
altars, and groues, and chappels of idols, and sacrifice swines
flesh, and vncleane beasts:</ab>
<ab n="48">That they
should also leaue their children vncircumcised, and make their
soules abominable with all maner of vncleannesse, and
prophanation:</ab>
<ab n="49">To the end
they might forget the Law, and change all the ordinances.</ab>
<ab n="50">And whosoeuer
would not doe according to the commandement of the king [he said]
he should die.</ab>
<ab n="51">In the selfe
same maner wrote he to his whole kingdome, and appointed ouerseers
ouer all the people, commanding the cities of Iuda to sacrifice,
citie by citie.</ab>
<ab n="52">Then many of
the people were gathered vnto them, to wit, euery one that forsooke
the Lawe, and so they committed euils in the land:</ab>
<ab n="53">And droue the
Israelites into secret places, euen wheresoeuer they could flie for
succour.<note> Or, and they made Israel hide themselues in holes, in euery place of succour.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">Now the
fifteenth day of the moneth Casleu, in the hundreth fourtie and
fift yeere, they set vp the abomination of desolation vpon the
Altar, and builded idole altars throughout the cities of Iuda, on
euery side:</ab>
<ab n="55">And burnt
incense at the doores of their houses, and in the streetes.</ab>
<ab n="56">And when they
had rent in pieces the bookes of the Lawe which they found, they
burnt them with fire.</ab>
<ab n="57">And
wheresoeuer was found with any, the booke of the Testament, or if
any consented to the Lawe, the kings commandement was, that they
should put him to death.<note> Gr. the kings commandement put him to death.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">Thus did they
by their authority, vnto the Israelites euery moneth, to as many as
were found in the cities.</ab>
<ab n="59">Now the fiue
and twentieth day of the moneth, they did sacrifice vpon the idole
altar, which was vpon the Altar of God.</ab>
<ab n="60">At which
time, according to the commandement, they put to death certaine
women that had caused their children to be circumcised.<note> Or, that had circumcised their children.</note></ab>
<ab n="61">And they
hanged the infants about their neckes, and rifled their houses, and
slewe them that had circumcised them.</ab>
<ab n="62">Howbeit, many
in Israel were fully resolued and confirmed in themselues, not to
eate any vncleane thing.</ab>
<ab n="63">Wherfore they
chose rather to die, that they might not be defiled with meats, and
that they might not profane the holy Couenant: So then they
died.</ab>
<ab n="64">And there was
very great wrath vpon Israel.</ab>



</div>