<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Maccabees_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>6 Mattathias lamenteth the case of
Ierusalem. 24 He slayeth a Iewe that did sacrifice to Idoles in his
presence, and the Kings messenger also. 34 He and his are assailed
vpon the Sabbath, and make no resistance. 50 Hee dieth, and
instructeth his sons: 66 and maketh their brother Iudas Maccabeus
generall.</head>

<ab n="1">In those daies
arose Mattathias the son of Iohn, the sonne of Simeon, a Priest of
the sonnes of Ioarib, from Ierusalem, and dwelt in
Modin.<note> Or Mattathias the son of Iohn, [illeg.] arose from Ierusalem, or out of Ierusalem</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he had
fiue sonnes, Ioannan called Caddis:<note> Or, who was called: and so afterward in the rest. , Gaddis.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Simon, called
Thassi:</ab>
<ab n="4">Iudas, who was
called Maccabeus:</ab>
<ab n="5">Eleazar,
called Auaran, and Ionathan, whose surname was Apphus.<note> Or, Auaron, or Abaron.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And when hee
saw the blasphemies that were committed in Iuda and
Ierusalem,</ab>
<ab n="7">He said, Woe
is me, wherfore was I borne to see this misery of my people, and of
the holy citie, and to dwell there, when it was deliuered into the
hand of the enemie, and the Sanctuary into the hand of
strangers?</ab>
<ab n="8">Her Temple is
become as a man without glory.</ab>
<ab n="9">Her glorious
vessels are caried away into captiuitie, her infants are slaine in
the streets, her yong men with the sword of the enemie.</ab>
<ab n="10">What nation
hath not had a part in her kingdome, and gotten of her
spoiles?</ab>
<ab n="11">All her
ornaments are taken away, of a free-woman shee is become a
bondslaue.</ab>
<ab n="12">And behold,
our Sanctuarie, euen our beautie, aud our glory is laid waste,
&amp; the Gentiles haue profaned it.<note> Or, holy thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">To what ende
therefore shall we liue any longer?</ab>
<ab n="14">Then
Mattathias and his sons rent their clothes, and put on sackcloth,
and mourned very sore.</ab>
<ab n="15">In the meane
while the kings officers, such as compelled the people to reuolt,
came into the city Modin to make them sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when many
of Israel came vnto them, Mattathias also and his sonnes came
together.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then answered
the kings officers, and said to Mattathias on this wise; Thou art a
ruler, and an honourable and great man in this citie, and
strengthened with sons and brethren:</ab>
<ab n="18">Now therefore
come thou first and fulfill the kings commandement, like as all the
heathen haue done; yea and the men of Iuda also, and such as
remaine at Ierusalem: so shalt thou and thine house be in the
number of the kings friends, and thou and thy children shall be
honoured with siluer, and golde, and many rewards.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then
Mattathias answered, and spake with a loude voice, Though all the
nations that are vnder the kings dominion obey him, and fall away
euery one from the religion of their fathers, and giue consent to
his commandements:</ab>
<ab n="20">Yet will I,
and my sonnes, and my brethren walke in the couenant of our
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="21">God forbid
that we should forsake the Law, and the ordinances:</ab>
<ab n="22">We will not
hearken to the kings words, to goe from our religion, either on the
right hand, or the left.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now when he
had left speaking these words, there came one of the Iewes in the
sight of all, to sacrifice on the altar, which was at Modin,
according to the kings commandement.</ab>
<ab n="24">Which thing
when Mattathias saw, he was inflamed with zeale, and his reines
trembled, neither could hee forbeare to shew his anger according to
iudgement: wherefore he ranne, and slew him vpon the altar.</ab>
<ab n="25">Also the
kings commissioner who compelled men to sacrifice, he killed at
that time, &amp; the altar he pulled downe.</ab>
<ab n="26">Thus dealt he
zealously for the Law of God, like as Phineas did vnto Zambri the
sonne of Salom.<note> Num.25. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And
Mattathias cried throughout the citie with a loud voyce, saying,
Whosoeuer is zealous of the law, and maintaineth the couenant, let
him follow me.</ab>
<ab n="28">So he and his
sonnes fled into the mountaines, and left all that euer they had in
the citie.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then many
that sought after iustice and iudgement, went downe into the
wildernesse to dwell there.<note> Gr. sit, abide.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Both they and
their children, and their wiues, and their cattell, because
afflictions increased sore vpon them.<note> Gr. euils were multiplied vpon them.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Now when it
was told the kings seruants, and the hoste that was at Ierusalem,
in the citie of Dauid, that certaine men, who had broken the kings
commandement, were gone downe into the secret places in the
wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="32">They pursued
after them, a great number, and hauing ouertaken them, they camped
against them, and made war against them on the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they said
vnto them, Let that which you haue done hitherto, suffice: Come
foorth, and doe according to the commandement of the king, and you
shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="34">But they
said, We will not come forth, neither will we do the kings
commandement to profane the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="35">So then they
gaue them the battell with all speed.<note> Gr. the Iewes.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Howbeit, they
answered them not, neither cast they a stone at them, nor stopped
the places where they lay hid,</ab>
<ab n="37">But said, Let
vs die all in our innocencie: heauen and earth shall testifie for
vs, that you put vs to death wrongfully.<note> Gr. simplicitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">So they rose
vp against them in battell on the Sabbath, and they slew them with
their wiues &amp; children, and their cattell, to the number of a
thousand people.<note> Gr. soules of men.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Now when
Mattathias and his friends vnderstood hereof, they mourned for them
right sore.</ab>
<ab n="40">And one of
them said to another: If we all do as our brethren haue done, and
fight not for our liues, and lawes against the heathen, they wil
now quickly root vs out of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="41">At that time
therfore they decreed, saying, Whosoeuer shall come to make battell
with vs on the Sabbath day, we will fight against him, neither will
wee die all, as our brethren that were murdered in the secret
places.</ab>
<ab n="42">Then came
there vnto him a company of Assideans, who were mightie men of
Israel, euen all such as were voluntarily deuoted vnto the
Lawe.</ab>
<ab n="43">Also all they
that fled for persecution ioyned themselues vnto them, and were a
stay vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="44">So they
ioyned their forces, and smote sinfull men in their anger, and
wicked men in their wrath: but the rest fled to the heathen for
succour.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then
Mattathias &amp; his friends went round about, and pulled downe the
altars.</ab>
<ab n="46">And what
children soeuer they found within the coast of Israel
vncircumcised, those they circumcised valiantly.<note> Or, by force</note></ab>
<ab n="47">They pursued
also after þe proud men, &amp; the work prospered
in their hand.</ab>
<ab n="48">So they
recouered the Law out of the hand of the Gentiles, and out of the
hande of Kings, neither suffered they the sinner to
triumph.<note> Gr. gaue they the horse to the sinner.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">Now when the
time drew neere, that Mattathias should die, he said vnto his
sonnes, Now hath pride &amp; rebuke gotten strength, and the time
of destruction, and the wrath of indignation:</ab>
<ab n="50">Now
therefore, my sonnes, be ye zealous for the Law, &amp; giue your
liues for the couenant of your fathers.</ab>
<ab n="51">Call to
remembrance what actes our fathers did in their time, so shall ye
receiue great honour, &amp; an euerlasting name.<note> Gr. generations.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Was not
Abraham found faithfull in tentation, and it was imputed vnto him
for righteousnesse?<note> Gene.22 9, 10. rom. 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">Ioseph in the
time of his distresse kept the commaundement, and was made Lord of
Egypt.<note> Gene.41. 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">Phineas our
father in being zealous and feruent, obtained the couenant of an
euerlasting priesthood.<note> Num.25.18. ecclus. 45.23.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">Iesus for
fulfilling the word, was made a iudge in Israel.<note> Iosh.1.2</note></ab>
<ab n="56">Caleb for
bearing witnesse, before the congregation, receiued the heritage of
the land.<note> Num.14. 6.7. Iosh. 14.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">Dauid for
being mercifull, possessed the throne of an euerlasting
kingdome.<note> 2.Sam. 2. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">Elias for
being zealous and feruent for the law, was taken vp into
heauen.<note> 2 Kin. 2. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">Ananias,
Azarias, and Misael, by beleeuing were saued out of the
flame<note> Dan 3.16. 17. 18, and 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">Daniel for
his innocencie was deliuered from the mouth of Lyons.<note> Dan.6.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="61">And thus
consider ye throughout all ages, that none that put their trust in
him shall be ouercome.</ab>
<ab n="62">Feare not
then the words of a sinfull man: for his glory shall bee dung and
wormes.</ab>
<ab n="63">To day he
shall be lifted vp, and to morrow hee shall not be found, because
he is returned into his dust, and his thought is come to
nothing.<note> Psal.146. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">Wherefore you
my sonnes be valiant, and shew your selues men in the behalfe of
the law, for by it shall you obtaine glory.</ab>
<ab n="65">And behold, I
know that your brother Simon is a man of counsell, giue eare vnto
him alway: he shall be a father vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="66">As for Iudas
Maccabeus hee hath bin mighty and strong, euen from his youth vp,
let him be your captaine, and fight the battaile of the
people.<note> To fight yee the battaile of the people.</note></ab>
<ab n="67">Take also
vnto you, all those that obserue the law, and auenge ye the wrong
of your people.</ab>
<ab n="68">Recompence
fully the heathen, and take heed to the commandements of the
law.</ab>
<ab n="69">So he blessed
them, and was gathered to his fathers.</ab>
<ab n="70">And he died
in the hundreth fortie, and sixth yeere, and his sonnes buried him
in the Sepulchre of his fathers, at Modin, and all Israel made
great lamentation for him.</ab>



</div>