<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Peter_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Hee teacheth the duetie of wiues
and husbands to each other, 8 exhorting all men to vnitie, and
loue, 14 and to suffer persecution. 19 Hee declareth also the
benefits of Christ toward the old world.</head>

<ab n="1">Likewise, ye
wiues, be in subiection to your owne husbands, that if any obey not
the word, they also may without the word be wonne by the
conuersation of the wiues:</ab>
<ab n="2">While they beholde
your chaste conuersation coupled with feare:</ab>
<ab n="3">Whose adorning,
let it not bee that outward adorning, of plaiting the haire, and of
wearing of gold, or of putting on of apparell.</ab>
<ab n="4">But let it bee the
hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, euen the
ornament of a meeke and quiet spirit, which is in the sight of God
of great price.</ab>
<ab n="5">For after this
manner in the olde time, the holy women also who trusted in God
adorned themselues, beeing in subiection vnto their owne
husbands.</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen as Sara
obeyed Abraham, calling him Lord, whose daughters ye are as long as
ye doe well, and are not afraid with any amazement.<note> Gr. children.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Likewise ye
husbands, dwel with them according to knowledge, giuing honour vnto
the wife as vnto the weaker vessel, and as being heires together of
the grace of life, that your prayers be not hindered.</ab>
<ab n="8">Finally be ye all
of one minde, hauing compassion one of another, loue as brethren,
be pitifull, be courteous,<note> Or, louing to the brethren.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Not rendring euill
for euill, or railing for railing: but contrarywise blessing,
knowing that yee are thereunto called, that ye should inherite a
blessing.</ab>
<ab n="10">For hee that will
loue life, and see good dayes, let him refraine his tongue from
euil, and his lips that they speake no guile:<note> Psal.34. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Let him eschew
euil and do good, let him seeke peace and ensue it.</ab>

<fw>How to suffer.</fw>
<ab n="12">For the eyes of
the Lord are ouer the righteous, and his eares are open vnto their
prayers: but the face of the Lord is against them that doe
euill.<note> Gr. vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And who is hee
that will harme you, if ye bee followers of that which is
good?</ab>
<ab n="14">But and if ye
suffer for righteousnes sake, happy are ye, and be not afraid of
their terrour, neither be troubled:<note> Esa. 8. 12, 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But sanctifie the
Lord God in your hearts, &amp; be ready alwayes to giue an answere
to euery man that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you,
with meekenesse and feare:<note> Or, reuerence.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Hauing a good
conscience, that whereas they speake euill of you, as of euill
doers, they may bee ashamed that falsly accuse your good
conuersation in Christ.</ab>
<ab n="17">For it is better,
if the will of God be so, that yee suffer for well doing, then for
euill doing.</ab>
<ab n="18">For Christ also
hath once suffered for sinnes, the iust for the vniust, that he
might bring vs to God, being put to death in the flesh, but
quickened by the Spirit.</ab>
<ab n="19">By which also he
went and preached vnto the spirits in prison,</ab>
<ab n="20">Which sometime
were disobedient, when once the long-suffering of God waited in the
dayes of Noah, while the Arke was a preparing: wherein few, that
is, eight soules were saued by water.</ab>
<ab n="21">The like figure
whereunto, euen Baptisme, doth also now saue vs, (not the putting
away of the filth of the flesh, but the answere of a good
conscience toward God,) by the resurrection of Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="22">Who is gone into
heauen, and is on the right hand of God, Angels, and authorities,
and powers being made subiect vnto him.</ab>



</div>