<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Peter_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-5-5-2-Peter.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 He exhorteth the Elders to feede
their flocks, 5 the yonger to obey, 8 and all to bee sober,
watchfull, and constant in the faith: 9 to resist the cruell
aduersarie the deuill.</head>

<ab n="1">The Elders which
are among you I exhort, who am also an Elder, and a witnesse of the
sufferings of Christ, and also a partaker of the glory that shall
be reuealed.</ab>
<ab n="2">Feede the flocke
of God which is among you, taking the ouersight thereof, not by
constraint, but willingly: not for filthy lucre, but of a ready
minde:<note> Or, as much as in you is.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Neither as being
lords ouer Gods heritage: but being ensamples to the
flocke.<note> Or, ouerruling.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when the
chiefe shepheard shall appeare, ye shall receiue a crowne of glory
that fadeth not away.</ab>
<ab n="5">Likewise ye
yonger, submit your selues vnto the elder: yea, all of you bee
subiect one to another, and bee clothed with humilitie: for God
resisteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.</ab>
<ab n="6">Humble yourselues
therefore vnder the mighty hand of God, that hee may exalt you in
due time,</ab>
<ab n="7">Casting all your
care vpon him, for he careth for you.</ab>
<ab n="8">Be sober, be
vigilant: because your aduersary the deuill, as a roaring Lion
walketh about, seeking whom he may deuoure.</ab>
<ab n="9">Whom resist
stedfast in the faith, knowing that the same afflictions are
accomplished in your brethren that are in the world.</ab>
<ab n="10">But the God of
all grace who hath called vs into his eternall glory by Christ
Iesus, after that ye haue suffered a while, make you perfect,
stablish, strengthen, settle you.</ab>
<ab n="11">To him bee glory
and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</ab>

<fw>Precious faith.</fw>
<ab n="12">By Syluanus a
faithfull brother vnto you, (as I suppose) I haue written briefly,
exhorting, &amp; testifying, that this is the true grace of God
wherein ye stand.</ab>
<ab n="13">The Church that
is at Babylon elected, together with you, saluteth you, and so doth
Marcus my sonne.</ab>
<ab n="14">Greete yee one
another with a kisse of charity: Peace bee with you all that are in
Christ Iesus. Amen.</ab>



</div>