<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Peter_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>Hee exhorteth them to cease from
sinne by the example of Christ, and the consideration of the
generall end, that now approcheth: 12 and comforteth them against
persecution.</head>

<ab n="1">For asmuch then as
Christ hath suffered for vs in the flesh, arme your selues likewise
with the same minde: for hee that hath suffered in the flesh, hath
ceassed from sinne:</ab>

<fw>Watch in prayer.</fw>
<ab n="2">That he no longer
should liue the rest of his time in the flesh, to the lusts of men,
but to the will of God.</ab>
<ab n="3">For the time past
of our life may suffice vs to haue wrought the will of the
Gentiles, when we walked in lasciuiousnes, lusts, excesse of wine,
reuellings, banquetings, and abhominable idolatries.</ab>
<ab n="4">Wherein they
thinke it strange, that you runne not with them to the same excesse
of riot, speaking euil of you:</ab>
<ab n="5">Who shal giue
accompt to him that is ready to iudge the quicke &amp; the
dead.</ab>
<ab n="6">For, for this
cause was the Gospel preached also to them that are dead, that they
might bee iudged according to men in the flesh, but liue according
to God in the spirit.</ab>
<ab n="7">But the ende of
all things is at hand: be ye therefore sober and watch vnto
prayer.</ab>
<ab n="8">And aboue all
things haue feruent charitie among your selues: for charity shall
couer the multitude of sinnes.<note> Or, will.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Use hospitalitie
one to another without grudging.</ab>
<ab n="10">As euery man hath
receiued the gift, euen so minister the same one to another, as
good stewards of the manifold grace of God.</ab>
<ab n="11">If any man
speake, let him speake as the oracles of God: if any man minister,
let him doe it as of the ability which God giueth, that God in all
things may bee glorified through Iesus Christ, to whom be praise
and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</ab>
<ab n="12">Beloued, thinke
it not strange concerning the fiery triall, which is to try you, as
though some strange thing happened vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="13">But reioyce in as
much as yee are partakers of Christes sufferings; that when his
glory shalbe reueiled, ye may be glad also with exceeding
ioy.</ab>
<ab n="14">If ye be
reproched for the Name of Christ, happie are ye, for the spirit of
glory, and of God resteth vpon you: on their part hee is euill
spoken of, but on your part he is glorified.</ab>
<ab n="15">But let none of
you suffer as a murtherer, or as a theefe, or as an euill doer, or
as a busibody in other mens matters.</ab>
<ab n="16">Yet if any man
suffer as a Christian, let him not be ashamed, but let him glorifie
God on this behalfe.</ab>

<fw>Feede the flocke.</fw>
<ab n="17">For the time is
come that iudgement must begin at the house of God: and if it first
begin at vs, what shall the ende bee of them that obey not the
Gospel of God?</ab>
<ab n="18">And if the
righteous scarcely be saued, where shall the vngodly and the sinner
appeare?</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherfore, let
them that suffer according to the will of God, commit the keeping
of their soules to him in well doing, as vnto a faithfull
Creator.</ab>



</div>