<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Peter_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>He dehorteth them from the breach of
charitie: 4 shewing that Christ is the foūdation wherupon they
are built. 11 He beseecheth them also to abstaine from fleshly
lustes, 13 To bee obedient to magistrates, 18 and teacheth seruants
how to obey their masters, 20 patiently suffering for well doing
after the example of Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">Wherefore laying
aside all malice, and all guile, and hypocrisies, and enuies, and
euill speakings,</ab>
<ab n="2">As new borne babes
desire the sincere milke of the word, that ye may grow
thereby,</ab>
<ab n="3">If so bee yee haue
tasted that the Lord is gracious.</ab>
<ab n="4">To whom comming as
vnto a liuing Stone, disallowed in deed of men, but chosen of God,
and precious,</ab>
<ab n="5">Ye also as liuely
stones, are built vp a spirituall house, an holy Priesthood to
offer vp spirituall sacrifice, acceptable to God by Iesus
Christ.<note> Or, be ye built.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore it is
conteined in the Scripture, Beholde, I lay in Sion a chiefe corner
stone, elect, precious, and he that beleeueth on him, shall not be
confounded.<note> Esa.28.16 psa.118.22 mat.21.42 actes 4.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Unto you therfore
which beleeue hee is precious; but vnto them which be disobedient,
the stone which the builders disallowed, the same is made the head
of the corner,<note> Or, he is an honour.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And a Stone of
stumbling, and a Rocke of offence, euen to them which stumble at
the word, being disobedient, whereunto also they were
appointed.<note> Esa.8.14.</note></ab>

<fw>Christes example.</fw>
<ab n="9">But yee are a
chosen generation, a royall Priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar
people, that yee should shewe forth the praises of him, who hath
called you out of darknes into his marueilous light:<note> Or, a purchased people. , Or, vertues</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Which in time
past were not a people, but are now the people of God: which had
not obteined mercie, but now haue obteined mercy.<note> Ose. 2.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Dearely beloued,
I beseech you as strangers and pilgrimes, abstaine from fleshly
lusts, which warre against the soule,</ab>
<ab n="12">Hauing your
conuersation honest among the Gentiles, that whereas they speake
against you as euill doers, they may by your good works which they
shall behold, glorifie God in the day of visitation.<note> Or, wherin.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Submit your
selues to euery ordinance of man for the Lordes sake, whether it be
to the King, as supreme,</ab>
<ab n="14">Or vnto
gouernours, as vnto them that are sent by him, for the punishment
of euil doers, and for the praise of them that doe well.</ab>
<ab n="15">For so is the
will of God, that with well doing yee may put to silence the
ignorance of foolish men.</ab>
<ab n="16">As free, and not
vsing your libertie for a cloake of maliciousnesse, but as the
seruants of God.<note> Gr. hauing</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Honour all men.
Loue the brotherhood. Feare God. Honour the King.<note> Or, esteeme.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Seruants, be
subiect to your masters with al feare, not only to the good and
gentle, but also to the froward.</ab>
<ab n="19">For this is
thanke-worthie, if a man for conscience toward God endure griefe,
suffering wrongfully.</ab>
<ab n="20">For what glory is
it, if when yee be buffeted for your faults, ye shall take it
patiently: but if when yee doe well, and suffer for it, ye take it
patiently, this is acceptable with God.<note> Or, thanke.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For euen hereunto
were ye called: because Christ also suffered for vs, leauing vs an
example, that yee should follow his steps.<note> Some, reade, for you.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Who did no sinne,
neither was guile found in his mouth.</ab>
<ab n="23">Who when hee was
reuiled, reuiled not againe; when hee suffered, hee threatned not,
but committed himselfe to him that iudgeth righteously.<note> Or, committed his cause.</note></ab>

<fw>Wiues behauiour.</fw>
<ab n="24">Who his owne
selfe bare our sinnes in his owne body on the tree, that wee being
dead to sinnes, should liue vnto righteousnesse, by whose stripes
ye were healed.<note> Or, to.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For yee were as
sheepe going astray, but are now returned vnto the shepheard and
Bishop of your soules.</ab>



</div>