<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Samuel testifieth his integritie.
6 Hee reprooueth the people of ingratitude. 16 He terrifieth them
with thunder in haruest time. 20 He comforteth them in Gods
mercy.</head>

<ab n="1">And Samuel saide
vnto all Israel, Beholde, I haue hearkned vnto your voice in all
that ye said vnto mee, and haue made a King ouer you.</ab>
<ab n="2">And now behold,
the King walketh before you: and I am olde, and gray headed, and
behold, my sonnes are with you: and I haue walked before you from
my childhood vnto this day.</ab>

<fw>Samuels vprightnes:</fw>
<ab n="3">Behold, here I
am, witnesse against me before the Lord, and before his Anoynted:
Whose oxe haue I taken? or whose asse haue I taken? or whom haue I
defrauded? whom haue I oppressed? or of whose hand haue I receiued
any bribe to blinde mine eyes therewith? and I will restore it
you.<note> Ecclus. 46. 10. , Hebr. ransome. , Or, that I should hide mine eyes at at him.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And they said,
Thou hast not defrauded vs, nor oppressed vs, neither hast thou
taken ought of any mans hand.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee said
vnto them, The Lord is witnesse against you, and his Anointed is
witnesse this day, that ye haue not found ought in my hand: And
they answered, He is witnesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
Samuel said vnto the people, It is the Lord that aduanced Moses and
Aaron, and that brought your fathers vp out of the land of
Egypt.<note> Or, made.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
stand still, that I may reason with you before the Lord, of all the
righteous acts of the Lord, which he did to you and your
fathers.<note> Hebr. righteousnesses, Or, benefits. , Heb. with.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">When Iacob was
come into Egypt, and your fathers cried vnto the Lord, then the
Lord sent Moses and Aaron, which brought foorth your fathers out of
Egypt, and made them dwell in this place.<note> Gen. 46. 5,6. , Exod.4. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And when they
forgat the Lord their God, he sold them into the hand of Sisera
captaine of the hoste of Hazor, and into the hand of the
Philistines, and into the hand of the king of Moab, and they fought
against them.<note> Iudg.4.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And they cried
vnto the Lord, and said, Wee haue sinned, because we haue forsaken
the Lord, and haue serued Baalim and Ashtaroth: but now deliuer vs
out of the hand of our enemies, and we will serue thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord
sent Ierubbaal, and Bedan, and Iephthah, and Samuel, and deliuered
you out of the hand of your enemies on euery side, and yee dwelled
safe.<note> Iudg. 11. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And when ye saw
that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon came against you, ye
said vnto me, Nay, but a King shall reigne ouer vs, when the Lord
your God was your King.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now therefore,
behold the King whom yee haue chosen, and whom yee haue desired:
and behold, the Lord hath set a King ouer you.</ab>

<fw>His exhortation.</fw>
<ab n="14">If ye will
feare the Lord, and serue him, and obey his voice, and not rebell
against the Commandement of the Lord, then shall both ye and also
the King that reigneth ouer you, continue following the Lord your
God.<note> Hebr. mouth. , Hebr. be after.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But if ye wil
not obey the voice of the Lord, but rebel against the Commandement
of the Lord, then shall the hand of the Lord be against you, as it
was against your fathers.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Now
therefore stand and see this great thing which the Lord will doe
before your eyes.</ab>
<ab n="17">Is it not wheat
haruest to day? I will call vnto the Lord, and hee shall send
thunder and raine, that ye may perceiue and see that your
wickednesse is great, which ye haue done in the sight of the Lord,
in asking you a King.</ab>
<ab n="18">So Samuel
called vnto the Lord, and the Lord sent thunder and raine that day:
and all the people greatly feared the Lord and Samuel.</ab>
<ab n="19">And all the
people said vnto Samuel, Pray for thy seruants vnto the Lord thy
God, that we die not: for we haue added vnto all our sinnes, this
euil, to aske vs a King.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
Samuel saide vnto the people, Feare not: (ye haue done al this
wickednesse, yet turne not aside from following the Lord, but serue
the Lord with all your heart:</ab>
<ab n="21">And turne ye
not aside, for then should ye goe after vaine things, which cannot
profit, nor deliuer, for they are vaine.)</ab>
<ab n="22">For the Lord
wil not forsake his people, for his great Names sake: because it
hath pleased the Lord to make you his people.</ab>
<ab n="23">Moreouer, as
for me, God forbid that I should sin against the Lord, in ceasing
to pray for you: but I will teach you the good and the right
way.<note> Hebr. from ceasing.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Onely feare the
Lord, and serue him in trueth with all your heart: for consider how
great things he hath done for you.<note> Or, what a great thing &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But if yee
shall still doe wickedly, yee shall be consumed, both yee and your
King.</ab>



</div>