<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Samuel sendeth Saul to destroy
Amalek. 6 Saul fauoureth the Kenites. 8 Hee spareth Agag and the
best of the spoile. 10 Samuel denounceth vnto Saul commending and
excusing himselfe, Gods reiection of him for his disobedience. 24
Sauls humiliation. 32 Samuel killeth Agag. 34 Samuel and Saul
part.</head>


<fw>Saul spareth Agag.</fw>
<ab n="1">Samuel also
saide vnto Saul, The Lord sent me to annoint thee to bee king ouer
his people, ouer Israel: nowe therefore hearken thou vnto the voyce
of the words of the Lord.<note> Chap.9. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, I remember that which Amalek did to Israel, how he
laid wait for him in the way when he came vp from
Egypt.<note> Exod.17. 8. num.24. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now goe, and
smite Amalek, and vtterly destroy all that they haue, and spare
them not; but slay both man and woman, infant and suckling, oxe and
sheepe, camell and asse.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Saul
gathered the people together, and numbred them in Telaim, two
hundred thousand footmen, and ten thousand men of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Saul came to
a citie of Amalek, and laid waite in the valley.<note> Or, fought.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Saul
saide vnto the Kenites, Goe, depart, get you downe from among the
Amalekites, lest I destroy you with them: for yee shewed kindnesse
to all the children of Israel when they came vp out of Egypt. So
the Kenites departed from among the Amalekites.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Saul smote
the Amalekites from Hauilah, vntill thou commest to Shur, that is
ouer against Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee tooke
Agag the king of the Amalekites aliue, and vtterly destroyed all
the people with the edge of the sword.</ab>
<ab n="9">But Saul and the
people spared Agag, and the best of the sheepe, and of the oxen,
and of the fatlings, and the lambes, and all that was good, and
would not vtterly destroy them: but euery thing that was vile, and
refuse, that they destroyed vtterly.<note> Or, of the second sort.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Then
came the word of the Lord vnto Samuel, saying;</ab>
<ab n="11">It repenteth me
that I haue set vp Saul to be king: for hee is turned backe from
following me, and hath not performed my commandements. And it
grieued Samuel; and he cried vnto the Lord all night.</ab>

<fw>Saul reproued.</fw>
<ab n="12">And when Samuel
rose early to meet Saul in the morning, it was tolde Samuel,
saying, Saul came to Carmel, and behold, he set him vp a place, and
is gone about, and passed on, and gone downe to Gilgal.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Samuel came
to Saul, and Saul said vnto him, Blessed be thou of the Lord: I
haue performed the commandement of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Samuel
said, What meaneth then this bleating of the sheepe in mine eares,
and the lowing of the oxen which I heare?</ab>
<ab n="15">And Saul sayde,
They haue brought them from the Amalekites: for the people spared
the best of the sheepe, and of the oxen, to sacrifice vnto the Lord
thy God, and the rest we haue vtterly destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then Samuel
sayd vnto Saul, Stay, and I will tell thee what the Lord hath said
to mee this night. And he said vnto him, Say on.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Samuel
said, When thou wast litle in thine owne sight, wast thou not made
the Head of the tribes of Israel, and the Lord anointed thee King
ouer Israel?</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Lord
sent thee on a iourney, and said, Goe, and vtterly destroy the
sinners the Amalekites, and fight against them, vntill they be
consumed.<note> Heb. they consume them.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Wherefore then
didst thou not obey the voice of the Lord, but didst flie vpon the
spoile, and didst euill in the sight of the Lord ?</ab>
<ab n="20">And Saul said
vnto Samuel; Yea, I haue obeyed the voice of the Lord, and haue
gone the way which the Lord sent me, and haue brought Agag the king
of Amalek, and haue vtterly destroyed the Amalekites.</ab>
<ab n="21">But the people
tooke of the spoile, sheepe and oxen, the chiefe of the things
which should haue bene vtterly destroyed, to sacrifice vnto the
Lord thy God in Gilgal.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Samuel
saide, Hath the Lord as great delight in burnt offerings and
sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the Lord ? Behold, to obey,
is better then sacrifice: and to hearken, then the fat of
rammes.<note> Eccles. 4.17. ose.6. 7. matt.9. 13.and 12. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For rebellion
is as the sin of witchcraft, and stubburnnesse is as iniquitie and
idolatrie: because thou hast reiected the word of the Lord, he hath
also reiected thee from being king.<note> Heb. diuination.</note></ab>

<fw>Agag slaine.</fw>
<ab n="24">¶ And Saul
said vnto Samuel, I haue sinned: for I haue transgressed the
Commandement of the Lord, and thy wordes; because I feared the
people, and obeyed their voice.</ab>
<ab n="25">Now therefore,
I pray thee, pardon my sinne, and turne againe with me, that I may
worship the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Samuel said
vnto Saul, I will not returne with thee: for thou hast reiected the
word of the Lord, and the Lord hath reiected thee from being king
ouer Israel.</ab>
<ab n="27">And as Samuel
turned about to goe away, he laid hold vpon the skirt of his
mantle, and it rent.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Samuel said
vnto him, The Lord hath rent the kingdome of Israel from thee this
day, and hath giuen it to a neighbour of thine, that is better then
thou.</ab>
<ab n="29">And also the
strength of Israel will not lie, nor repent: for he is not a man
that he should repent.<note> Or, eternitie: or, victory.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Then he said, I
haue sinned; yet honour me now, I pray thee, before the Elders of
my people, and before Israel, and turne againe with me, that I may
worship the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="31">So Samuel
turned againe after Saul, and Saul worshipped the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ Then
said Samuel, Bring you hither to me Agag the king of the
Amalekites: and Agag came vnto him delicately. And Agag said,
Surely the bitternesse of death is past.</ab>
<ab n="33">And Samuel
said, As thy sword hath made women childlesse, so shall thy mother
bee childlesse among women. And Samuel hewed Agag in pieces before
the Lord in Gilgal.<note> Exod.17. 11. num. 14.45.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Then
Samuel went to Ramah, and Saul went vp to his house to Gibeah of
Saul.</ab>
<ab n="35">And Samuel came
no more to see Saul vntill the day of his death: neuerthelesse,
Samuel mourned for Saul: and the Lord repented that he had made
Saul king ouer Israel.</ab>



</div>