<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Hannahs song in thankefulnesse. 12
The sinne of Elies sonnes. 18 Samuels ministerie. 20 By Elies
blessing, Hannah is more fruitfull. 22 Eli reprooueth his sonnes.
28 A prophecie against Elies house.</head>

<ab n="1">And Hannah
prayed, and said, My heart reioyceth in the Lord, mine horne is
exalted in the Lord: my mouth is inlarged ouer mine enemies:
because I reioyce in thy saluation.</ab>
<ab n="2">There is none
holy as the Lord: for there is none beside thee: neither is there
any Rocke like our God.</ab>
<ab n="3">Talke no more so
exceeding proudly, let not arrogancie come out of your mouth: for
the Lord is a God of knowledge, and by him actions are
weighed.<note> Hebr. hard.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The vowes of the
mightie men are broken, and they that stumbled are girt with
strength.</ab>

<fw>Elis sonnes wicked.</fw>
<ab n="5">They that were
full, haue hired out themselues for bread: and they that were
hungry, ceased: so that the barren hath borne seuen, and she that
hath many children, is waxed feeble.</ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord killeth
and maketh aliue, he bringeth downe to the graue, and bringeth
vp.<note> Deut. 32. 39. wisd. 16.13. tob. 13.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The Lord maketh
poore, and maketh rich: he bringeth low, and lifteth vp.</ab>
<ab n="8">He raiseth vp the
poore out of the dust, and lifteth vp the begger from the dunghill,
to set them among princes, and to make them inherit the throne of
glory: for the pillars of the earth are the Lords, and hee hath set
the world vpon them.<note> Psal.113. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">He will keepe the
feet of his saints, and the wicked shall bee silent in darkenesse;
for by strength shall no man preuaile.</ab>
<ab n="10">The aduersaries
of the Lord shalbe broken to pieces: out of heauen shal he thunder
vpon them: the Lord shall iudge the ends of the earth, and he shal
giue strength vnto his king, and exalt the horne of his
Anointed.<note> Chap.7. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Elkanah went
to Ramah to his house, and the child did minister vnto the Lord
before Eli the Priest.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Now the
sonnes of Eli were sonnes of Belial, they knewe not the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the priests
custome with the people was, that when any man offred sacrifice,
the priestes seruant came, while the flesh was in seething, with a
fleshhooke of three teeth in his hand,</ab>
<ab n="14">And he strooke
it into the panne, or kettle, or caldron, or pot: all that the
flesh-hooke brought vp, the priest tooke for himselfe: so they did
in Shiloh vnto all the Israelites that came thither.</ab>
<ab n="15">Also before they
burnt the fat, the priests seruant came, &amp; said to the man that
sacrificed, Giue flesh to roste for the priest, for he wil not haue
sodden flesh of thee, but raw.</ab>
<ab n="16">And if any man
said vnto him, Let them not faile to burne the fat presently, and
then take as much as thy soule desireth: then hee would answere
him, Nay, but thou shalt giue it mee now: and if not, I will take
it by force.<note> Hebr. as on the day.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Wherefore the
sinne of the yong men was very great before the Lord: for men
abhorred the offering of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ But
Samuel ministred before the Lord, being a child, girded with a
linnen Ephod.<note> Exod. 28. 4.</note></ab>

<fw>Eli therefore is threatened.</fw>
<ab n="19">Moreouer, his
mother made him a litle coate, and brought it to him from yeere to
yeere, when she came vp with her husband, to offer the yeerely
sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And Eli
blessed Elkanah, and his wife, and said, The Lord giue thee seed of
this woman, for the loane which is lent to the Lord. And they went
vnto their owne home.<note> Or, petition which hee asked, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the Lord
visited Hannah, so that shee conceiued, and bare three sonnes, and
two daughters: and the child Samuel grew before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Now Eli
was very olde, and heard all that his sonnes did vnto all Israel,
and how they lay with the women that assembled at the doore of the
Tabernacle of the Congregation<note> Hebr. assembled by troupes.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And he said vnto
them, Why doe ye such things? for I heare of your euil dealings, by
all this people.<note> Or, I hear euill words of you.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Nay my sonnes:
for it is no good report that I heare; yee make the Lords people to
transgresse.<note> Or, to cry out.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">If one man sinne
against another, the Iudge shall iudge him: but if a man sinne
against the Lord, who shall intreat for him? Notwithstanding they
hearkened not vnto the voice of their father, because the Lord
would slay them.</ab>
<ab n="26">(And the child
Samuel grew on, and was in fauour, both with the Lord, and also
with men.)</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And there
came a man of God vnto Eli, and saide vnto him, Thus saith the
Lord, Did I plainely appeare vnto the house of thy father, when
they were in Egypt in Pharaohs house?</ab>
<ab n="28">And did I chuse
him out of all the tribes of Israel, to be my Priest, to offer vpon
mine altar, to burne incense, to weare an Ephod before me? and did
I giue vnto the house of thy father, all the offerings made by fire
of the children of Israel?<note> Leuit.10. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Wherefore kicke
ye at my sacrifice, and at mine offering, which I haue commaunded
in my habitation, and honourest thy sonnes aboue mee, to make your
selues fat with the chiefest of all the offrings of Israel my
people?</ab>

<fw>Eli therefore is threatened.</fw>
<ab n="30">Wherefore the
Lord God of Israel saith, I sayd indeede that thy house, &amp; the
house of thy father should walke before me for euer: but now the
Lord saith, Be it farre from mee; for them that honour me, I will
honour, and they that despise me, shall be lightly
esteemed.</ab>
<ab n="31">Behold, the
dayes come, that I will cut off thine arme, and the arme of thy
fathers house, that there shall not be an old man in thine
house.</ab>
<ab n="32">And thou shalt
see an enemie in my habitation, in all the wealth which God shall
giue Israel, and there shall not bee an olde man in thine house for
euer.<note> Or, the affliction of the Tabernacle, for all the wealth which God would haue giuen Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the man of
thine, whom I shall not cut off from mine Altar, shall be to
consume thine eyes, and to grieue thine heart: and all the increase
of thine house shall die in the floure of their age.<note> Heb. men.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And this shall
bee a signe vnto thee, that shall come vpon thy two sonnes, on
Hophni and Phinehas: in one day they shall die both of
them.</ab>
<ab n="35">And I will raise
me vp a faithfull Priest, that shall doe according to that which is
in my heart and in my mind, and I will build him a sure house, and
hee shall walke before mine Anointed for euer.</ab>
<ab n="36">And it shall
come to passe, that euery one that is left in thine house, shal
come and crouch to him for a piece of siluer, and a morsel of
bread, and shall say, Put me (I pray thee) into one of the Priests
offices, that I may eat a piece of bread.<note> Heb. ioyne. , Or, Somewhat about the Priesthood.</note></ab>



</div>