<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Samuel anoynteth Saul. 2 Hee
confirmeth him by prediction of three signes. 9 Sauls heart is
changed, and he prophecieth. 14 He concealeth the matter of the
kingdome from his vncle. 17 Saul is chosen at Mizpeh by lot. 26 The
different affections of his subiects.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Samuel
tooke a viall of oile, and powred it vpon his head, &amp; kissed
him, and said, Is it not because the Lord hath anoynted thee to be
captain ouer his inheritance?</ab>

<fw>Saul prophecieth, and is chosen
king.</fw>
<ab n="2">When thou art
departed from me to day, then thou shalt find two men by Rachels
sepulchre in the border of Beniamin, at Zelzah: and they will say
vnto thee, The asses which thou wentest to seeke, are found: and
loe, thy father hath left the care of the asses, and sorroweth for
you, saying, What shall I doe for my sonne?<note> Gen. 35. 20. , Heb. the businesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then shalt thou
goe on forward from thence, and thou shalt come to the plaine of
Tabor, and there shall meete thee three men, going vp to God to
Bethel, one carying three kids, and another carying three loaues of
bread, and another carying a bottle of wine.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they will
salute thee, and giue thee two loaues of bread, which thou shalt
receiue of their hands.<note> Heb. aske thee of peace</note></ab>
<ab n="5">After that thou
shalt come to the hill of God, where is the garison of the
Philistines: and it shall come to passe when thou art come thither
to the citie, that thou shalt meet a company of prophets comming
downe from the high place, with a psalterie, and a tabret, and a
pipe, and a harpe before them, and they shall prophecie.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Spirit
of the Lord will come vpon thee, and thou shalt prophecie with
them, and shalt be turned into another man.</ab>
<ab n="7">And let it be
when these signes are come vnto thee, that thou doe as occasion
serue thee, for God is with thee.<note> Heb. and it shall come to passe that when these signes &amp;c. , Heb. do for thee as thine hand shall finde.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And thou shalt
goe downe before me to Gilgal, and behold, I will come downe vnto
thee, to offer burnt offerings, and to sacrifice sacrifices of
peace offerings: seuen dayes shalt thou tarie, till I come to thee,
and shew thee what thou shalt doe.<note> Chap. 13. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And it
was so that when he had turned his backe to go from Samuel, God
gaue him another heart: and all those signes came to passe that
day.<note> Heb. shoulder. , Heb. turned.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And when they
came thither to the hill, behold, a company of the prophets met
him, and the spirit of God came vpon him, and hee prophesied among
them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it came to
passe when all that knew him beforetime, saw, that behold, hee
prophesied among the prophets, then the people said one to another,
What is this that is come vnto the sonne of Kish? Is Saul also
among the prophets?<note> Heb. A man to his neighbour. , Chap. 19. 24.</note></ab>

<fw>Saul prophecieth, and is chosen
king.</fw>
<ab n="12">And one of the
same place answered, and sayd, But who is their father? Therefore
it became a prouerbe, Is Saul also among the Prophets?<note> Heb. from thence.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And when he had
made an end of prophesying, he came to the high place.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
Sauls vncle saide vnto him, and to his seruant, Whither went ye?
And he said, To seeke the asses: and when we saw that they were no
where, we came to Samuel.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Sauls vncle
said, Tell me, I pray thee, what Samuel said vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Saul sayd
vnto his vncle; He told vs plainely that the asses were found. But
of the matter of the kingdome, whereof Samuel spake, he told him
not.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And
Samuel called the people together vnto the Lord to Mizpeh;</ab>
<ab n="18">And said vnto
the children of Israel, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, I
brought vp Israel out of Egypt, and deliuered you out of the hand
of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all kingdomes, and of them
that oppressed you.</ab>
<ab n="19">And ye haue
this day reiected your God, who himselfe saued you out of all your
aduersities &amp; your tribulations: and ye haue said vnto him,
Nay, but set a king ouer vs. Now therefore present your selues
before the Lord by your tribes, and by your thousands.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when Samuel
had caused all the tribes of Israel to come neere, the tribe of
Beniamin was taken.</ab>
<ab n="21">When he had
caused the tribe of Beniamin to come neere by their families, the
familie of Matri was taken, and Saul the sonne of Kish was taken:
and when they sought him, he could not be found.</ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore they
enquired of the Lord further, if the man should yet come thither:
and the Lord answered, Behold, hee hath hid himselfe among the
stuffe.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they ranne,
and fetched him thence, and when he stood among the people, he was
higher then any of the people, from the shoulders &amp;
vpward.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Samuel said
to all the people, See ye him whome the Lord hath chosen, that
there is none like him among all the people? And all the people
shouted, and saide, God saue the King.<note> Heb. let the king liue</note></ab>

<fw>The Ammonites are discomfited.</fw>
<ab n="25">Then Samuel
tolde the people the maner of the kingdome, and wrote it in a
booke, and layd it vp before the Lord, and Samuel sent all the
people away, euery man to his house.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And Saul
also went home to Gibeah, and there went with him a band of men,
whose hearts God had touched.</ab>
<ab n="27">But the
children of Belial sayd, Howe shall this man saue vs? and they
despised him, and brought him no presents: but he held his
peace.<note> Or, he was, as though he had beene deafe.</note></ab>



</div>