<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Ionathan discloseth his fathers
purpose to kill Dauid. 4 Hee perswadeth his father to
reconciliation. 8 By reason of Dauids good successe in a new warre,
Sauls malicious rage breaketh out against him. 12 Michal deceiueth
her father with an image in Dauids bed. 18 Dauid commeth to Samuel
in Naioth. 20 Sauls messengers sent to take Dauid, 22 and Saul
himselfe, prophesie.</head>

<ab n="1">And Saul spake
to Ionathan his sonne, and to all his seruants, that they should
kill Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="2">But Ionathan
Sauls sonne delighted much in Dauid, and Ionathan told Dauid,
saying, Saul my father seeketh to kill thee: Now therefore, I pray
thee, take heed to thy selfe vntill the morning, and abide in a
secret place, and hide thy selfe:</ab>
<ab n="3">And I will goe
out and stand beside my father in the field where thou art, and I
will commune with my father of thee, and what I see, that I will
tell thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
Ionathan spake good of Dauid vnto Saul his father, and said vnto
him, Let not the King sinne against his seruant, against Dauid:
because hee hath not sinned against thee, and because his workes
haue bene to thee ward very good.</ab>
<ab n="5">For he did put
his life in his hand, and slew the Philistine, &amp; the Lord
wrought a great saluation for all Israel: thou sawest it, and didst
reioyce: Wherefore then wilt thou sinne against innocent blood, to
slay Dauid without a cause?<note> Iudg. 9. 17. and 12. 3. chap. 28. 21. psalm. 119.109.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Saul
hearkened vnto the voyce of Ionathan; and Saul sware, As the Lord
liueth, he shall not be slaine.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Ionathan
called Dauid, and Ionathan shewed him all those things: and
Ionathan brought Dauid to Saul, and he was in his presence, as in
times past.<note> Hebr. yesterday, third day.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauid escapeth.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ And there
was warre againe, and Dauid went out, and fought with the
Philistines, and slew them with a great slaughter, &amp; they fled
from him.<note> Heb. his face.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the euill
spirit from the Lord was vpon Saul, as he sate in his house with
his iauelin in his hand: and Dauid played with his hand.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Saul sought
to smite Dauid euen to the wall with the iauelin: but hee slipt
away out of Sauls presence, and he smote the iauelin into the wall:
and Dauid fled, and escaped that night.</ab>
<ab n="11">Saul also sent
messengers vnto Dauids house, to watch him, and to slay him in the
morning: and Michal Dauids wife tolde him, saying, If thou saue not
thy life to night, to morrow thou shalt be slaine.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ So
Michal let Dauid downe thorow a window: and hee went and fled, and
escaped.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Michal
tooke an image, and laid it in the bedde, and put a pillow of goats
haire for his bolster, and couered it with a cloth.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when Saul
sent messengers to take Dauid, she said, He is sicke.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Saul sent
the messengers againe to see Dauid, saying, Bring him vp to me in
the bedde, that I may slay him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when the
messengers were come in, behold, there was an image in the bed,
with a pillow of goates haire for his bolster.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Saul said
vnto Michal, Why hast thou deceiued me so, and sent away mine
enemie, that he is escaped? And Michal answered Saul, Hee said vnto
me, Let mee goe; Why should I kill thee?</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ So Dauid
fledde, and escaped, and came to Samuel to Ramah, and told him all
that Saul had done to him: and hee and Samuel went, and dwelt in
Naioth.</ab>
<ab n="19">And it was told
Saul, saying, Behold, Dauid is at Naioth in Ramah.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Saul sent
messengers to take Dauid: and when they sawe the company of the
Prophets prophecying, and Samuel standing as appointed ouer them,
the Spirit of God was vpon the messengers of Saul, and they also
prophecied.</ab>

<fw>Saul prophesieth.</fw>
<ab n="21">And when it was
tolde Saul, he sent other messengers, and they prophecied likewise:
and Saul sent messengers againe the third time, and they prophecied
also.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then went hee
also to Ramah, and came to a great well that is in Sechu: and he
asked, and said, Where are Samuel and Dauid? And one said, Behold,
they be at Naioth in Ramah.</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee went
thither to Naioth in Ramah: and the Spirit of God was vpon him
also, and he went on and prophecied vntill hee came to Naioth in
Ramah:</ab>
<ab n="24">And he stript
off his clothes also, and prophecied before Samuel in like manner,
and lay downe naked all that day, and all that night: wherefore
they say, Is Saul also among the Prophets?<note> Heb. fell. , Chap. 10. 11.</note></ab>



</div>