<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in a caue at Engedi, hauing
cut off Sauls skirt, spareth his life. 8 Hee sheweth thereby his
innocencie. 16 Saul acknowledging his fault, taketh an oath of
Dauid, and departeth.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe when Saul was returned from folowing the Philistines, that it
was told him, saying, Behold, Dauid is in the wildernesse
En-gedi.<note> Heb. after.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then Saul tooke
three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and went to secke
Dauid and his men vpon the rockes of the wilde goates.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hee came to
the sheepe coates by the way, where was a caue, and Saul went in to
couer his feete: and Dauid and his men remained in the sides of the
caue.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the men of
Dauid sayd vnto him, Beholde the day of which the Lord sayd vnto
thee, Behold, I wil deliuer thine enemy into thine hand, that thou
mayest doe to him as it shall seeme good vnto thee. Then Dauid
arose, and cut off the skirt of Sauls robe priuily.<note> Hebr. the robe, which was Sauls.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And it came to
passe afterward, that Dauids heart smote him, because he had cut
off Sauls skirt.</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee sayd
vnto his men, The Lord forbid that I should doe this thing vnto my
master the Lords Anoynted, to stretch forth mine hand against him,
seeing he is the Anoynted of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">So Dauid stayed
his seruants with these wordes, and suffered them not to rise
against Saul: but Saul rose vp out of the caue, and went on his
way.<note> Hebr. cut off.</note></ab>

<fw>Sauls confession.</fw>
<ab n="8">Dauid also rose
afterward, and went out of the caue, and cryed after Saul, saying,
My lord the king. And when Saul looked behinde him, Dauid stouped
with his face to the earth, and bowed himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Dauid
said to Saul, Wherfore hearest thou mens words, saying, Behold,
Dauid seeketh thy hurt?</ab>
<ab n="10">Behold, this
day thine eyes haue seene, how that the Lord had deliuered thee to
day into mine hand in the caue: and some bade me kill thee, but
mine eye spared thee, and I said, I will not put foorth mine hand
against my lord, for hee is the Lords Anointed.</ab>
<ab n="11">Moreouer my
father, See, yea see the skirt of thy robe in my hand: for in that
I cut off the skirt of thy robe, and killed thee not, know thou and
see, that there is neither euill nor transgression in mine hand,
and I haue not sinned against thee; yet thou huntest my soule, to
take it.</ab>
<ab n="12">The Lord iudge
betweene me and thee, and the Lord auenge me of thee: but mine hand
shall not be vpon thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">As saith the
prouerbe of the ancients, Wickednesse proceedeth from the wicked:
but mine hand shall not be vpon thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">After whom is
the king of Israel come out? after whom doest thou pursue? After a
dead dogge, after a flea.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Lord
therfore be Iudge, and iudge betweene me and thee, and see, and
plead my cause, and deliuer me out of thine hand.<note> Heb. iudge</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And it
came to passe when Dauid had made an ende of speaking these words
vnto Saul, that Saul said, Is this thy voice, my sonne Dauid? And
Saul lift vp his voice, and wept.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said to
Dauid, Thou art more righteous then I: for thou hast rewarded mee
good, whereas I haue rewarded thee euill.</ab>
<ab n="18">And thou hast
shewed this day how that thou hast dealt well with me: forasmuch as
when the Lord had deliuered me into thine hand, thou killedst me
not.<note> Heb. shut vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For if a man
finde his enemie, will hee let him goe well away? wherefore the
Lord reward thee good, for that thou hast done vnto me this
day.</ab>

<fw>Samuel dieth.</fw>
<ab n="20">And now behold,
I know well that thou shalt surely be King, and that the kingdome
of Israel shall be established in thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="21">Sweare now
therefore vnto me by the Lord, that thou wilt not cut off my seede
after mee, and that thou wilt not destroy my name out of my fathers
house.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Dauid sware
vnto Saul, and Saul went home: but Dauid and his men gate them vp
vnto the holde.</ab>



</div>