<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Ionathan, vnwitting to his father,
the Priest, or the people, goeth and miraculously smiteth the
Philistines garrison. 15 A diuine terrour maketh them beate
themselues. 17 Saul not staying the Priests answere, setteth on
them. 21 The captiuated Hebrewes, and the hidden Israelites, ioyne
against them. 24 Sauls vnaduised adiuration, hindreth the victory.
32 Hee restraineth the people from eating blood. 35 He buildeth an
Altar. 36 Ionathan taken by lot, is saued by the people. 47 Sauls
strength and family.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe vpon a day, that Ionathan the sonne of Saul said vnto the
yong man that bare his armour, Come, and let vs goe ouer to the
Philistines garison, that is on the other side: but hee told not
his father.<note> Or, there was a day.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Saul taried
in the vttermost part of Gibeah, vnder a Pomegranate tree, which is
in Migron: and the people that were with him, were about sixe
hundred men:</ab>
<ab n="3">And Ahiah the
sonne of Ahitub, Ichabods brother, the sonne of Phinehas, the sonne
of Eli, the Lords Priest in Shiloh, wearing an Ephod: and the
people knew not that Ionathan was gone.<note> Chap. 4. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
betweene the passages, by which Ionathan sought to go ouer vnto the
Philistines garison, there was a sharpe rocke on the one side, and
a sharp rocke on the other side: and the name of the one was Bozez,
and the name of the other Seneh.</ab>
<ab n="5">The forefront of
the one was situate Northward ouer against Michmash, and the other
Southward ouer against Gibeah.<note> Heb. tooth.</note></ab>

<fw>Ionathan and his armour-bearer:</fw>
<ab n="6">And Ionathan
said to the young man that bare his armour, Come, and let vs goe
ouer vnto the garison of these vncircumcised; it may be that the
Lord will worke for vs: for there is no restraint to the Lord, to
saue by many, or by few.<note> 2. Chron. 14.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And his armour
bearer sayd vnto him, Doe all that is in thine heart: turne thee,
behold, I am with thee, according to thy heart.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then said
Ionathan, Behold, we will passe ouer vnto these men, and we will
discouer our selues vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="9">If they say thus
vnto vs, Tary vntill we come to you: then wee will stand still in
our place, and will not goe vp vnto them.<note> Heb. be still.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But if they say
thus, Come vp vnto vs: then we will goe vp; for the Lord hath
deliuered them into our hand: and this shall be a signe vnto
vs.<note> 1. Macc. 4.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And both of
them discouered themselues vnto the garison of the Philistines: and
the Philistines sayd, Behold, the Hebrewes come foorth out of the
holes, where they had hid themselues.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the men of
the garison answered Ionathan and his armour bearer, and said, Come
vp to vs, and wee will shew you a thing. And Ionathan said vnto his
armour bearer, Come vp after me; for the Lord hath deliuered them
into the hand of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Ionathan
climed vp vpon his hands, and vpon his feete, and his armour bearer
after him: and they fell before Ionathan; and his armour bearer
slew after him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And that first
slaughter which Ionathan and his armour-bearer made, was about
twentie men, within as it were an halfe acre of land, which a yoke
of oxen might plow.<note> Or, halfe a furrow of an acre of land.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And there was
trembling in the hoste, in the field, and among all the people: the
garison and the spoilers, they also trembled, and the earth quaked:
so it was a very great trembling.<note> Hebr. a trembling of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the
watchmen of Saul in Gibeah of Beniamin looked: and behold, the
multitude melted away, and they went on beating downe one
another.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then said Saul
vnto the people that were with him, Number now, and see who is gone
from vs. And when they had numbred, behold, Ionathan and his armour
bearer were not there.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Saul said
vnto Ahiah, Bring hither the Arke of God: (for the Arke of God was
at that time with the children of Israel.)</ab>

<fw>He tasteth honie.</fw>
<ab n="19">¶ And it
came to passe while Saul talked vnto the Priest, that the noise
that was in the hoste of the Philistines went on, and increased:
And Saul said vnto the Priest, Withdraw thine hand.<note> Or, tumult.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Saul and
all the people that were with him assembled themselues, and they
came to the battel, and behold, euery mans sword was against his
fellow, and there was a very great discomfiture.<note> Heb. were cryed together. , Iudg.7.22. 2.chro. 20.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Moreouer, the
Hebrewes that were with the Philistines before that time, which
went vp with them into the campe from the countrey round about;
euen they also turned to be with the Israelites, that were with
Saul and Ionathan.</ab>
<ab n="22">Likewise all
the men of Israel, which had hid themselues in mount Ephraim, when
they heard that the Philistines fled, euen they also followed hard
after them in the battell.</ab>
<ab n="23">So the Lord
saued Israel that day: and the battell passed ouer vnto
Beth-auen.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
men of Israel were distressed that day; for Saul had adiured the
people, saying, Cursed bee the man that eateth any foode vntill
euening, that I may be auenged on mine enemies: so none of the
people tasted any food.</ab>
<ab n="25">And all they of
the land came to a wood, and there was honie vpon the
ground.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when the
people were come into the wood, behold, the honie dropped, but no
man put his hand to his mouth: for the people feared the
oath.</ab>
<ab n="27">But Ionathan
heard not when his father charged the people with the oath;
wherefore he put foorth the ende of the rodde that was in his hand,
and dipt it in an hony combe, and put his hand to his mouth, and
his eyes were enlightened.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then answered
one of the people, and said, Thy father straitly charged the people
with an oath, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth any food this
day. And the people were faint.<note> Or, wearie.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Then said
Ionathan, My father hath troubled the land: see, I pray you, how
mine eyes haue beene enlightened, because I tasted a little of this
honie:</ab>

<fw>Casting of lots.</fw>
<ab n="30">How much more,
if haply the people had eaten freely to day of the spoile of their
enemies which they found? for had there not beene now a much
greater slaughter among the Philistines?</ab>
<ab n="31">And they smote
the Philistines that day from Michmash to Aiialon: and the people
were very faint.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the people
flewe vpon the spoile, and tooke sheepe, and oxen, and calues, and
slew them on the ground, and the people did eate them with the
blood.<note> Leuit.7. 26. and 19. 26. deut. 12.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Then
they tolde Saul, saying, Behold, the people sinne against the Lord,
in that they eate with the blood. And he said, Yee haue
transgressed: roule a great stone vnto mee this day.<note> Or, dealt treacherously.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And Saul said,
Disperse your selues among the people, and say vnto them, Bring me
hither euery man his oxe, and euery man his sheepe, and slay them
here, and eat, and sinne not against the Lord in eating with the
blood. And all the people brought euery man his oxe with him that
night, and slew them there.<note> Heb. in his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And Saul built
an altar vnto the Lord: the same was the first altar that he built
vnto the Lord.<note> Hebr. that Altar he beganne to build vnto the LORD.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And Saul
saide, Let vs goe downe after the Philistines by night, and spoile
them vntil the morning light, and let vs not leaue a man of them.
And they said, Do whatsoeuer seemeth good vnto thee. Then said the
priest, Let vs draw neere hither vnto God.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Saul asked
counsell of God, Shall I goe downe after the Philistines? Wilt thou
deliuer them into the hand of Israel? But he answered him not that
day.</ab>
<ab n="38">And Saul said,
Draw yee neere hither all the chiefe of the people: and know and
see, wherein this sinne hath beene this day.<note> Iudg.20.2 , Heb. corners.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">For as the Lord
liueth, which saueth Israel, though it bee in Ionathan my sonne, he
shall surely die: But there was not a man among all the people that
answered him.</ab>
<ab n="40">Then said he
vnto all Israel, Be ye on one side, and I, and Ionathan my sonne
will be on the other side. And the people said vnto Saul, Doe what
seemeth good vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="41">Therefore Saul
saide vnto the Lord God of Israel, Giue a perfect lot. And Saul and
Ionathan were taken: but the people escaped.<note> Or, shew the innocent , Heb. went forth.</note></ab>

<fw>Ionathan is rescued.</fw>
<ab n="42">And Saul said,
Cast lots betweene me and Ionathan my sonne. And Ionathan was
taken.</ab>
<ab n="43">Then Saul said
to Ionathan, Tell me what thou hast done. And Ionathan tolde him,
and said, I did but taste a litle hony with the end of the rodde
that was in mine hand, and loe, I must die.</ab>
<ab n="44">And Saul
answered, God do so, and more also: for thou shalt surely die,
Ionathan.</ab>
<ab n="45">And the people
said vnto Saul, Shall Ionathan die, who hath wrought this great
saluation in Israel? God forbid: as the Lord liueth, there shal not
one haire of his head fall to the ground: for hee hath wrought with
God this day. So the people rescued Ionathan, that hee died
not.</ab>
<ab n="46">Then Saul went
vp from following the Philistines: and the Philistines went to
their owne place.</ab>
<ab n="47">¶ So Saul
tooke the kingdom ouer Israel, and fought against all his enemies
on euery side, against Moab, and against the children of Ammon, and
against Edom, and against the kings of Zobah, and against the
Philistines: and whithersoeuer hee turned himselfe, he vexed
them.</ab>
<ab n="48">And he gathered
an hoste, and smote the Amalekites, and deliuered Israel out of the
handes of them that spoiled them.<note> Or, wroght mightily.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">Now the sonnes
of Saul, were Ionathan, and Ishui, and Melchishua: and the names of
his two daughters were these: the name of the first borne Merab,
and the name of the yonger Michal:</ab>
<ab n="50">And the name of
Sauls wife was Ahinoam, the daughter of Ahimaaz, and the name of
the captaine of his host was Abner, the sonne of Ner, Sauls
vncle.</ab>
<ab n="51">And Kish was
the father of Saul, and Ner the father of Abner was the sonne of
Abiel.</ab>
<ab n="52">And there was
sore warre against the Philistines, all the dayes of Saul: and when
Saul saw any strong man, or any valiant man, he tooke him vnto
him.</ab>



</div>