<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Nahash offereth them of Iabesh
Gilead a reprochfull condition. 4 They send messengers and are
deliuered by Saul. 12 Saul thereby is confirmed, and his kingdome
renewed.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Nahash the
Ammonite came vp, and encamped against Iabesh Gilead: and all the
men of Iabesh sayde vnto Nahash, Make a couenant with vs, and we
will serue thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Nahash the
Ammonite answered them, On this condition will I make a couenant
with you, that I may thrust out all your right eyes, and lay it for
a reproch vpon all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the Elders
of Iabesh sayd vnto him, Giue vs seuen daies respite, that we may
send messengers vnto all the coasts of Israel: and then, if there
be no man to saue vs, we will come out to thee.<note> Hebr. forbeare vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then came
the messengers to Gibeah of Saul, and told the tidings in the eares
of the people: and all the people lift vp their voyces, and
wept.</ab>
<ab n="5">And behold, Saul
came after the herd out of the field, and Saul sayd, What aileth
the people that they weep? and they told him the tidings of the men
of Iabesh.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Spirit
of God came vpon Saul, when he heard those tydings, and his anger
was kindled greatly.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he tooke a
yoke of oxen, and hewed them in pieces, and sent them throughout
all the coasts of Israel by the hands of messengers, saying,
Whosoeuer commeth not foorth after Saul and after Samuel, so shall
it bee done vnto his oxen: and the feare of the Lord fell on the
people, and they came out with one consent.<note> Heb. as one man.</note></ab>

<fw>The Ammonites are discomfited.</fw>
<ab n="8">And when he
numbred them in Bezek, the children of Israel were three hundred
thousand, and the men of Iudah thirty thousand.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they said
vnto the messengers that came, Thus shall yee say vnto the men of
Iabesh Gilead, To morrow by that time the sunne be hote, ye shal
haue helpe. And the messengers came, and shewed it to the men of
Iabesh, and they were glad.<note> Or, deliuerance.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Therfore the
men of Iabesh said, To morrow wee will come out vnto you, and ye
shall doe with vs all that seemeth good vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it was so
on the morrow, that Saul put the people in three cōpanies, and
they came into the midst of the host in the morning watch, and
slewe the Ammonites, vntill the heat of the day: and it came to
passe, that they which remained were scattered, so that two of them
were not left together.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
people said vnto Samuel, Who is he that said, Shall Saul reigne
ouer vs? bring the men, that we may put them to death.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Saul said,
There shall not a man be put to death this day: for to day the Lord
hath wrought saluation in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then said
Samuel to the people, Come, and let vs goe to Gilgal, and renew the
kingdome there.</ab>
<ab n="15">And all the
people went to Gilgal, and there they made Saul King before the
Lord in Gilgal: and there they sacrificed sacrifices of peace
offerings before the Lord: and there Saul and all the men of Israel
reioyced greatly.</ab>



</div>