<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 They of Kiriath-iearim bring the
Arke into the house of Abinadab, and sanctifie Eleazar his sonne to
keepe it. 2 After twentie yeeres 3 The Israelites, by Samuels
meanes, solemnly repent at Mizpeh. 7 While Samuel prayeth and
sacrificeth, the Lord discomfiteth the Philistines by thunder, at
Eben-ezer. 13 The Philistines are subdued. 15 Samuel peaceably and
religiously iudgeth Israel.</head>


<fw>Israel repenteth.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the men of
Kiriath-iearim came, and fetcht vp the Arke of the Lord, and
brought it into the house of Abinadab in the hill, and sanctified
Eleazar his sonne, to keepe the Arke of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="2">And it came to
passe while the Arke abode in Kiriath-iearim, that the time was
long: for it was twentie yeeres: and all the house of Israel
lamented after the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And Samuel
spake vnto all the house of Israel, saying, If ye doe returne vnto
the Lord with all your hearts, then put away the strange gods, and
Ashtaroth from among you, and prepare your hearts vnto the Lord,
and serue him onely: &amp; he will deliuer you out of the hand of
the Philistines.<note> Iosh. 14. 15,23. , Iudg.2. 13. , Deut.6.4. matt.4. 10. luke 4.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then the children
of Israel did put away Baalim, and Ashtaroth, and serued the Lord
onely.<note> Iudg. 2. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Samuel said,
Gather all Israel to Mizpeh, and I will pray for you vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they gathered
together to Mizpeh, and drew water, and powred it out before the
Lord, and fasted on that day, and said there, We haue sinned
against the Lord. And Samuel iudged the children of Israel in
Mizpeh.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when the
Philistines heard that the children of Israel were gathered
together to Mizpeh, the lords of the Philistines went vp against
Israel: and when the children of Israel heard it, they were afraid
of the Philistines.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the children
of Israel said to Samuel, Cease not to crie vnto the Lord our God
for vs, that he will saue vs out of the hand of the
Philistines.<note> Heb. be not silent from vs from crying.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Samuel
tooke a sucking lambe, and offered it for a burnt offering wholly
vnto the Lord; and Samuel cried vnto the Lord for Israel, and the
Lord heard him.<note> Or, answered.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And as Samuel
was offering vp the burnt offering, the Philistines drewe neere to
battell against Israel: but the Lord thundred with a great thunder
on that day vpon the Philistines, and discomfited them, and they
were smitten before Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the men of
Israel went out of Mizpeh, and pursued the Philistines, and smote
them, vntill they came vnder Bethcar.</ab>

<fw>Samuels sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="12">Then Samuel
tooke a stone, and set it betweene Mizpeh and Shen, and called the
name of it Eben-Ezer, saying, Hitherto hath the Lord helped
vs.<note> That is, the stone of helpe.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ So the
Philistines were subdued, and they came no more into the coast of
Israel: and the hand of the Lord was against the Philistines, all
the dayes of Samuel.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the cities
which the Philistines had taken from Israel, were restored to
Israel, from Ekron euen vnto Gath, and the coasts thereof did
Israel deliuer out of the hands of the Philistines: and there was
peace betweene Israel and the Amorites.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Samuel
iudged Israel all the dayes of his life.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he went from
yeere to yeere in circuit to Bethel, and Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and
iudged Israel in all those places.<note> Heb. and he circuited.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And his returne
was to Ramah: for there was his house: and there hee iudged Israel,
and there hee built an altar vnto the Lord.</ab>



</div>