<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid marching with the
Philistines, 3 is disalowed by their Princes. 6 Achish dismisseth
him with commendations of his fidelity.</head>

<ab n="1">Now the
Philistines gathered together all their armies to Aphek: and the
Israelites pitched by a fountaine which is in Iezreel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the lords of
the Philistines passed on by hundreds, and by thousands: but Dauid
and his men passed on in the rere-ward with Achish.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then said the
princes of the Philistines, What doe these Hebrewes here? And
Achish said vnto the princes of the Philistines, Is not this Dauid
the seruant of Saul the king of Israel, which hath bene with me
these dayes, or these yeeres, and I haue found no fault in him
since he fell vnto me, vnto this day?</ab>
<ab n="4">And the princes
of the Philistines were wroth with him, and the princes of the
Philistines said vnto him, Make this fellow returne, that he may
goe againe to his place which thou hast appointed him, and let him
not go downe with vs to battel, lest in the battell he be an
aduersary to vs: for wherewith should hee reconcile himselfe vnto
his master? should it not be with the heads of these
men?<note> 1. Chron. 12.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Is not this
Dauid, of whom they sang one to another in daunces, saying, Saul
slew his thousands, and Dauid his ten thousands?<note> Chap. 18. 7. and 21. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then
Achish called Dauid, and said vnto him, Surely, as the Lord liueth,
thou hast bene vpright, and thy going out and thy comming in with
me in the hoste is good in my sight: for I haue not found euil in
thee, since the day of thy comming vnto me vnto this day:
neuertheles, the lords fauour thee not.<note> Hebr. thou art not good in the eyes of the lords.</note></ab>

<fw>Ziklag burnt. Dauid pursueth
them.</fw>
<ab n="7">Wherefore now
returne and goe in peace, that thou displease not the lords of the
Philistines.<note> Hebr. doe not euill in the eyes of the lords.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And Dauid
said vnto Achish, But what haue I done? and what hast thou found in
thy seruant so long as I haue bene with thee vnto this day, that I
may not goe fight against the enemies of my lord the
king?<note> Hebr. before thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Achish
answered, and said to Dauid, I know that thou art good in my sight,
as an Angel of God: notwithstanding the Princes of the Philistines
haue said, Hee shall not goe vp with vs to the battell.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wherfore now
rise vp early in the morning, with thy masters seruants that are
come with thee: and assoone as yee be vp early in the morning, and
haue light, depart.</ab>
<ab n="11">So Dauid and
his men rose vp early to depart in the morning, to returne into the
land of the Philistines; and the Philistines went vp to
Iezreel.</ab>



</div>