<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-25-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Samuel dieth. 2 Dauid in Paran
sendeth to Nabal. 10 Prouoked by Nabals churlishnesse, hee mindeth
to destroy him. 14 Abigail vnderstanding thereof, 18 taketh a
present, 23 and by her wisedome 32 pacifieth Dauid. 36 Nabal
hearing thereof, dieth. 39 Dauid taketh Abigail and Ahinoam to be
his wiues. 44 Michal is giuen to Phalti.</head>

<ab n="1">And Samuel died,
and all the Israelites were gathered together, and lamented him,
and buried him in his house at Ramah. And Dauid arose, &amp; went
downe to the wildernesse of Paran.<note> Chap. 28. 3. ecclus. 46.13, 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And there was a
man in Maon, whose possessions were in Carmel, and the man was very
great, and hee had three thousand sheepe, and a thousand goates:
and he was shearing his sheepe in Carmel.<note> Or, busines.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now the name of
the man was Nabal, and the name of his wife, Abigail: and shee was
a woman of good vnderstanding, and of a beautifull countenance: but
the man was churlish and euill in his doings, and hee was of the
house of Caleb.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And Dauid
heard in the wildernesse, that Nabal did sheare his sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Dauid sent
out ten yong men, and Dauid said vnto the young men, Get you vp to
Carmel, and goe to Nabal, and greete him in my name;<note> Heb. aske him in my name, of peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And thus shall
ye say to him that liueth in prosperitie, Peace be both to thee,
and peace be to thine house, and peace be vnto all that thou
hast.</ab>
<ab n="7">And now, I haue
heard that thou hast shearers: now thy shepheards which were with
vs, wee hurt them not, neither was there ought missing vnto them,
all the while they were in Carmel.<note> Heb. shamed.</note></ab>

<fw>Nabals churlishnes.</fw>
<ab n="8">Aske thy yong
men, and they will shew thee: wherefore let the yong men finde
fauour in thine eyes: (for we come in a good day) giue, I pray
thee, whatsoeuer commeth to thine hand, vnto thy seruants, and to
thy sonne Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when Dauids
yong men came, they spake to Nabal according to all those words in
the name of Dauid, and ceased.<note> Heb. rested.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
Nabal answered Dauids seruants, and said, Who is Dauid? and who is
the sonne of Iesse? There bee many seruants now a daies that breake
away euery man from his master.</ab>
<ab n="11">Shall I then
take my bread and my water, and my flesh that I haue killed for my
shearers, and giue it vnto men, whom I know not whence they
bee?<note> Hebr. slaughter.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So Dauids yong
men turned their way, and went againe, and came and told him all
those sayings.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Dauid said
vnto his men, Gird you on euery man his sword. And they girded on
euery man his sword, and Dauid also girded on his sword: and there
went vp after Dauid about foure hundred men, and two hundred abode
by the stuffe.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ But one
of the yong men told Abigail Nabals wife, saying, Behold, Dauid
sent messengers out of the wildernesse to salute our master: and he
railed on them.<note> Hebr. flew vpon them.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But the men
were very good vnto vs, and we were not hurt, neither missed we any
thing as long as wee were conuersant with them, when we were in the
fields.<note> Heb. shamed.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">They were a
wall vnto vs both by night and day, all the while we were with them
keeping sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now therefore
know and consider what thou wilt doe: for euill is determined
against our master, and against all his houshold: for he is such a
sonne of Belial, that a man cannot speake to him.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then
Abigail made haste, and tooke two hundred loaues, and two bottles
of wine, and fiue sheepe readie dressed, and fiue measures of
parched corne, and an hundred clusters of raisins, and two hundred
cakes of figges, and laid them on asses.<note> Or, lumps.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And she said
vnto her seruants, Goe on before me, behold, I come after you: but
she told not her husband Nabal.</ab>

<fw>Abigails wisdome.</fw>
<ab n="20">And it was so
as she rode on the asse, that she came downe by the couert of the
hill, and behold, Dauid and his men came downe against her, and she
met them.</ab>
<ab n="21">(Now Dauid had
said, Surely in vaine haue I kept all that this fellow hath in the
wildernesse, so that nothing was missed of all that pertained vnto
him: and he hath requited me euil for good.</ab>
<ab n="22">So and more
also doe God vnto the enemies of Dauid, if I leaue of all that
pertaine to him by the morning light, any that pisseth against the
wall.)</ab>
<ab n="23">And when
Abigail saw Dauid, she hasted, and lighted off the asse, and fell
before Dauid on her face, and bowed her selfe to the
ground,</ab>
<ab n="24">And fell at his
feet, and said, Upon me, my lord, vpon me let this iniquitie be,
and let thine handmaid, I pray thee, speake in thine audience, and
heare the words of thine handmaid.<note> Heb. eares</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Let not my
lord, I pray thee, regard this man of Belial, euen Nabal: for as
his name is, so is he: Nabal is his name, and folly is with him:
But I thine handmaid saw not the yong men of my lord, whom thou
didst send.<note> Heb. lay it to his heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Now therefore,
my lord, as the Lord liueth, and as thy soule liueth, seeing the
Lord hath withholden thee from comming to shed blood, and from
auenging thy selfe with thine owne hand: now let thine enemies and
they that secke euill to my lord, bee as Nabal.<note> Hebr. sauing thy selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And now this
blessing which thine handmaid hath brought vnto my lord, let it
euen be giuen vnto the yong men that follow my lord.<note> Or, present , Heb. walke at the feet of &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">I pray thee,
forgiue the trespasse of thine handmaide: for the Lord will
certainely make my lord a sure house, because my lord fighteth the
battels of the Lord, and euill hath not bene found in thee all thy
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="29">Yet a man is
risen to pursue thee, and to seeke thy soule: but the soule of my
lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with the Lord thy God,
and the soules of thine enemies, them shall he sling out, as out of
the middle of a sling.<note> Heb. in the midst of the bought of a sling.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And it shall
come to passe when the Lord shal haue done to my lord, according to
all the good that hee hath spoken concerning thee, and shall haue
appointed thee ruler ouer Israel;</ab>

<fw>Nabal dieth. Dauid marieth
Abigail.</fw>
<ab n="31">That this shall
bee no griefe vnto thee, nor offence of heart vnto my lord, either
that thou hast shed blood causelesse, or that my lord hath auenged
himselfe: But when the Lord shall haue dealt well with my lord,
then remember thine handmayd.<note> Hebr. no staggering: or, stumbling.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And
Dauid sayd to Abigail, Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, which
sent thee this day to meet me.</ab>
<ab n="33">And blessed bee
thy aduice, and blessed be thou, which hast kept me this day from
comming to shed blood, and from auenging my selfe with mine owne
hand.</ab>
<ab n="34">For in very
deed, as the Lord God of Israel liueth, which hath kept mee backe
from hurting thee, except thou hadst hasted and come to meet me,
surely there had not bene left vnto Nabal, by the morning light,
any that pisseth against the wall.</ab>
<ab n="35">So Dauid
receiued of her hand that which shee had brought him, and sayd vnto
her, Goe vp in peace to thine house; See, I haue hearkened to thy
voyce, and haue accepted thy person.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And
Abigail came to Nabal, and behold, he held a feast in his house
like the feast of a king; &amp; Nabals heart was merry within him,
for hee was very drunken: wherefore shee tolde him nothing, lesse
or more, vntill the morning light.</ab>
<ab n="37">But it came to
passe in the morning, when the wine was gone out of Nabal, and his
wife had told him these things, that his heart died within him, and
he became as a stone.</ab>
<ab n="38">And it came to
passe about ten dayes after, that the Lord smote Nabal, that he
died.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And when
Dauid heard that Nabal was dead, he said, Blessed be the Lord, that
hath pleaded the cause of my reproch from the hand of Nabal, and
hath kept his seruant from euil: for the Lord hath returned the
wickednesse of Nabal vpon his owne head. And Dauid sent, and
communed with Abigail, to take her to him to wife.</ab>
<ab n="40">And when the
seruants of Dauid were come to Abigail to Carmel, they spake vnto
her, saying, Dauid sent vs vnto thee, to take thee to him to
wife.</ab>

<fw>Dauid marieth Abigail.</fw>
<ab n="41">And shee arose,
and bowed her selfe on her face to the earth, and sayd, Beholde,
let thine handmayd bee a seruant to wash the feet of the seruants
of my lord.</ab>
<ab n="42">And Abigail
hasted, and rose, and rode vpon an asse, with fiue damosels of hers
that went after her; and she went after the messengers of Dauid,
and became his wife.<note> Hebr. at her feet.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Dauid also
tooke Ahinoam of Iezreel, and they were also both of them his
wiues.<note> Iosh.15. 56.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ But Saul
had giuen Michal his daughter, Dauids wife, to Phalti the sonne of
Laish, which was of Gallim.<note> 2.Sam. 3. 14,15.</note></ab>



</div>