<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ruth-Chapter-4-4-1-Samuel.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Elkanah a Leuite hauing two wiues,
worshippeth yeerely at Shiloh. 4 Hee cherisheth Hannah, though
barren, and prouoked by Peninnah. 9 Hannah in griefe, prayeth for a
childe. 12 Eli first rebuking her, afterwards blesseth her. 19
Hannah hauing borne Samuel, stayeth at home till he be weaned. 24
She presenteth him, according to her vow, to the Lord.</head>

<ab n="1">Now there was a
certaine man of Ramathaim Zophim, of mount Ephraim, &amp; his name
was Elkanah, the sonne of Ieroham, the sonne of Elihu, the sonne of
Tohu, the sonne of Zuph, an Ephrathite;</ab>
<ab n="2">And he had two
wiues, the name of the one was Hannah, and the name of the other
Peninnah: and Peninnah had children, but Hannah had no
children.</ab>
<ab n="3">And this man went
vp out of his citie yeerely, to worship and to sacrifice vnto the
Lord of hostes in Shiloh; and the two sonnes of Eli, Hophni, and
Phinehas, the Priests of the Lord, were there.<note> Deut.16. 16. , Hebr. from yeere to yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And when
the time was, that Elkanah offered, he gaue to Peninnah his wife,
and to all her sonnes, and her daughters, portions.</ab>
<ab n="5">But vnto Hannah
he gaue a worthy portion: (for he loued Hannah, but the Lord had
shut vp her wombe.<note> Or, a double portion.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And her aduersary
also prouoked her sore, for to make her fret, because the Lord had
shut vp her wombe.)<note> Hebr. angred her.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And as he did so
yeere by yeere, when she went vp to the house of the Lord, so she
prouoked her; therefore she wept, and did not eat.<note> Or, from the time that she &amp;c. Hebr. from her going vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then said Elkanah
her husband to her, Hannah, why weepest thou? and why eatest thou
not? and why is thy heart grieued? Am not I better to thee, then
ten sonnes?</ab>

<fw>Hannahs prayer, and
thanksgiuing.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ So Hannah
rose vp after they had eaten in Shiloh, and after they had drunke;
(now Eli the Priest sate vpon a seat by a poste of the Temple of
the Lord. )</ab>
<ab n="10">And shee was in
bitternesse of soule, and prayed vnto the Lord, and wept
sore.<note> Hebr. bitter of soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And she vowed a
vow, and said, O Lord of hostes, if thou wilt indeed looke on the
affliction of thine handmayd, and remember me, and not forget thine
handmayd, but wilt giue vnto thine handmayd a man childe, then I
will giue him vnto the Lord all the dayes of his life, and there
shall no rasor come vpon his head.<note> Hebr. seed of men. , Num.6.5. iudg.13.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And it came to
passe as she continued praying before the Lord, that Eli marked her
mouth.<note> Hebr. multiplied to pray.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Now Hannah, shee
spake in her heart; onely her lippes mooued, but her voice was not
heard: therefore Eli thought she had beene drunken.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Eli said
vnto her, How long wilt thou be drunken? put away thy wine from
thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Hannah
answered, and said, No, my lord, I am a woman of a sorrowfull
spirit: I haue drunke neither wine nor strong drinke, but haue
powred out my soule before the Lord.<note> Hebr. hard of spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Count not thine
handmaid for a daughter of Belial: for out of the abundance of my
complaint and griefe, haue I spoken hitherto.<note> Or, meditation.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Then Eli
answered, and said, Goe in peace: and the God of Israel grant thee
thy petition, that thou hast asked of him.</ab>
<ab n="18">And she said,
Let thine handmaid finde grace in thy sight. So the woman went her
way, and did eate, and her countenance was no more sad.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And they
rose vp in the morning early, and worshipped before the Lord, and
returned, and came to their house to Ramah: and Elkanah knewe
Hannah his wife, and the Lord remembred her.</ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore it
came to passe when the time was come about, after Hannah had
conceiued, that shee bare a sonne, and called his name Samuel,
saying; Because I haue asked him of the Lord.<note> Hebr. reuelation of dayes. , That is, asked of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the man
Elkanah, and all his house, went vp to offer vnto the Lord the
yeerely sacrifice, and his vowe.</ab>

<fw>Hannahs prayer, and
thanksgiuing.</fw>
<ab n="22">But Hannah went
not vp; for shee said vnto her husband, I will not goe vp vntill
the childe be weaned, and then I will bring him, that he may
appeare before the Lord, and there abide for euer.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Elkanah her
husband said vnto her, Do what seemeth thee good, tary vntill thou
haue weaned him, only the Lord establish his word: so the woman
abode, and gaue her sonne sucke vntill she weaned him.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And when
shee had weaned him, shee tooke him vp with her, with three
bullocks, and one Ephah of floure, and a bottle of wine, and
brought him vnto the house of the Lord in Shiloh: and the childe
was young.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they slew a
bullocke, and brought the childe to Eli.</ab>
<ab n="26">And she said, Oh
my lord, as thy soule liueth, my lord, I am the woman, that stood
by thee heere, praying vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="27">For this childe
I prayed, and the Lord hath giuen me my petition, which I asked of
him:</ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore also I
haue lent him to the Lord as long as hee liueth, he shall be lent
to the Lord. And he worshipped the Lord there.<note> Or, returned him, whom I have obtained by petition to the LORD. , Or, hee whom I haue obteined by petition, shalbe returned.</note></ab>



</div>