<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid enquiring of the Lord by
Abiathar, rescueth Keilah. 7 God shewing him the comming of Saul
and the trecherie of the Keilites, he escapeth from Keilah. 14 In
Ziph Ionathan commeth and comforteth him. 19 The Ziphites discouer
him to Saul. 25 At Maon he is rescued from Saul by the inuasion of
the Philistines. 29 He dwelleth at En-gedi.</head>

<ab n="1">Then they told
Dauid, saying, Beholde, the Philistines fight against Keilah, and
they rob the threshing floores.</ab>

<fw>Dauid in Keilah.</fw>
<ab n="2">Therefore Dauid
enquired of the Lord, saying, Shall I go and smite these
Philistines? And the Lord said vnto Dauid, Goe, and smite the
Philistines, and saue Keilah.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Dauids men
said vnto him, Behold, we be afraid here in Iudah: how much more
then if wee come to Keilah against the armies of the
Philistines?</ab>
<ab n="4">Then Dauid
enquired of the Lord yet againe: And the Lord answered him, and
said, Arise, go down to Keilah: for I will deliuer the Philistines
into thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="5">So Dauid and his
men went to Keilah, and fought with the Philistins, and brought
away their cattell, and smote them with a great slaughter: so Dauid
saued the inhabitants of Keilah.</ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe when Abiathar the sonne of Ahimelech fled to Dauid to Keilah,
that hee came downe with an Ephod in his hand.<note> Chap. 22. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And it
was told Saul that Dauid was come to Keilah: and Saul said, God
hath deliuered him into mine hand: for he is shut in, by entring
into a towne that hath gates and barres.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Saul called
all the people together to warre, to goe downe to Keilah, to
besiege Dauid, and his men.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Dauid
knewe that Saul secretly practised mischiefe against him, and hee
said to Abiathar the Priest, Bring hither the Ephod.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then saide
Dauid, O Lord God of Israel, thy seruant hath certainly heard that
Saul seeketh to come to Keilah, to destroy the citie for my
sake.</ab>
<ab n="11">Will the men of
Keilah deliuer me vp into his hande? will Saul come downe, as thy
seruant hath heard, O Lord God of Israel? I beseech thee tell thy
seruant. And the Lord said, He will come downe.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then said
Dauid, Will the men of Keilah deliuer me, and my men, into the hand
of Saul? And the Lord said, They will deliuer thee vp.<note> Hebr. shut vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then
Dauid and his men, which were about sixe hundred, arose, and
departed out of Keilah, and went whithersoeuer they could goe: and
it was told Saul that Dauid was escaped from Keilah, and hee
forbare to goe foorth.</ab>

<fw>Dauid deliuered, spareth Saul.</fw>
<ab n="14">And Dauid abode
in the wildernesse in strong holds, and remained in a mountaine in
the wildernes of Ziph: and Saul sought him euery day, but God
deliuered him not into his hand.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Dauid saw
that Saul was come out to seeke his life: and Dauid was in the
wildernes of Ziph in a wood.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
Ionathan Sauls sonne arose, &amp; went to Dauid into the wood, and
strengthened his hand in God.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said
vnto him, Feare not; for the hand of Saul my father shall not finde
thee, and thou shalt be king ouer Israel, and I shall be next vnto
thee: and that also Saul my father knoweth.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they two
made a couenant before the Lord: and Dauid abode in the wood, and
Ionathan went to his house.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then
came vp the Ziphites to Saul to Gibeah, saying, Doth not Dauid hide
himselfe with vs in strong holds in the wood, in the hill of
Hachilah, which is on the South of Ieshimon?<note> Hebr. on the right hand. , Or, the wildernesse?</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Now therefore,
O king, come downe according to all the desire of thy soule to come
downe, and our part shall be to deliuer him into the kings
hand.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Saul said,
Blessed be yee of the Lord, for yee haue compassion on me.</ab>
<ab n="22">Goe, I pray
you, prepare yet, and know, and see his place where his haunt is,
and who hath seene him there: for it is told mee that he dealeth
very subtilly.<note> Heb. foote shalbe.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">See therefore,
and take knowledge of all the lurking places where he hideth
himselfe, and come ye againe to me with the certainty, and I will
goe with you: and it shall come to passe, if he be in the land,
that I will search him out throughout all the thousands of
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they arose,
&amp; went to Ziph before Saul: but Dauid and his men were in the
wildernesse of Maon, in the plaine on the South of
Ieshimon.</ab>
<ab n="25">Saul also and
his men went to seeke him, and they told Dauid: wherefore he came
downe into a rocke, and abode in the wildernesse of Maon: and when
Saul heard that, he pursued after Dauid in the wildernes of
Maon.</ab>

<fw>Dauid deliuered, spareth Saul.</fw>
<ab n="26">And Saul went
on this side of the mountaine, and Dauid and his men on that side
of the mountaine: and Dauid made haste to get away for feare of
Saul: for Saul and his men compassed Dauid and his men round about
to take them.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ But
there came a messenger vnto Saul, saying, Haste thee, and come: for
the Philistines haue inuaded the land.<note> Hebr. spread themselues vpon &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Wherefore Saul
returned from pursuing after Dauid, &amp; went against the
Philistines; therefore they called that place
Sela-Hammahlekoth.<note> That is, the rocke of diuisions.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And
Dauid went vp from thence, and dwelt in strong holds at
En-gedi.</ab>



</div>