<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 By occasion of the ill gouernment
of Samuels sonnes, the Israelites aske a King. 6 Samuel praying in
griefe is comforted by God. 10 Hee telleth the manner of a King. 19
God willeth Samuel to yeeld vnto the importunitie of the
people.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when Samuel was old, that he made his sonnes Iudges ouer
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">Now the name of
his first borne was Ioel, and the name of his second, Abiah: they
were Iudges in Beer-sheba.</ab>
<ab n="3">And his sonnes
walked not in his wayes, but turned aside after lucre, and tooke
bribes, &amp; peruerted iudgement.<note> Deut.16. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then all the
Elders of Israel gathered themselues together, and came to Samuel
vnto Ramah,</ab>
<ab n="5">And said vnto
him, Behold, thou art olde, and thy sonnes walke not in thy wayes:
now make vs a King to iudge vs, like all the nations.<note> Ose. 13.10 acts 13.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ But the
thing displeased Samuel, when they said, Giue vs a King to iudge
vs: and Samuel prayed vnto the Lord.<note> Heb. was euill in the eyes of Samuel.</note></ab>

<fw>A king described.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the Lord said
vnto Samuel, Hearken vnto the voyce of the people in all that they
say vnto thee: for they haue not reiected thee, but they haue
reiected mee, that I should not reigne ouer them.</ab>
<ab n="8">According to all
the works which they haue done since the day that I brought them vp
out of Egypt euen vnto this day, wherewith they haue forsaken me,
and serued other gods: so doe they also vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">Nowe therefore
hearken vnto their voyce: howbeit, yet protest solemnly vnto them,
and shew them the maner of the King that shall reigne ouer
them.<note> Or, obey. , Or, notwithstanding, when thou hast solemnly protested against them, then thou shalt shew, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
Samuel told all the words of the Lord vnto the people, that asked
of him a King.</ab>
<ab n="11">And hee sayd,
This will be the maner of the king that shall reigne ouer you: Hee
will take your sonnes, and appoint them for himselfe for his
charets, and to bee his horsemen, and some shall runne before his
charets.</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee will
appoint him Captaines ouer thousands, and captaines ouer fifties,
and will set them to eare his ground, and to reape his haruest, and
to make his instruments of warre, and instruments of his
charets.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he will take
your daughters to be confectionaries, and to be cookes, and to be
bakers.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he will take
your fields, and your vineyards, and your oliue-yards, euen the
best of them, and giue them to his seruants.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he will take
the tenth of your seed, and of your vineyards, and giue to his
officers, and to his seruants.<note> Heb. Eunuches.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And hee will
take your men seruants, and your mayd seruants, and your goodliest
young men, and your asses, and put them to his worke.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hee will take
the tenth of your sheepe, and ye shall be his seruants.</ab>
<ab n="18">And ye shall cry
out in that day, because of your king which ye shall haue chosen
you; and the Lord will not heare you in that day.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶
Neuerthelesse, the people refused to obey the voyce of Samuel; and
they said, Nay, but we will haue a King ouer vs:</ab>
<ab n="20">That we also may
be like all the nations, and that our King may iudge vs, and goe
out before vs, and fight our battels.</ab>

<fw>Saul seeking asses, is by Samuel anointed
king.</fw>
<ab n="21">And Samuel heard
all the words of the people, and he rehearsed them in the eares of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Lord
said to Samuel, Hearken vnto their voyce, and make them a King. And
Samuel said vnto the men of Israel, Goe yee euery man vnto his
citie.</ab>



</div>