<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 After seuen moneths the
Philistines take counsell, how to send backe the Arke. 10 They
bring it on a new cart with an offering vnto Bethshemesh. 19 The
people are smitten for looking into the Arke. 21 They send to them
of Kiriath-iearim to fetch it.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Arke of
the Lord was in the countrey of the Philistines seuen
moneths.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the
Philistines called for the priests and the diuiners, saying, What
shall we doe to the Arke of the Lord ? Tell vs wherewith we shall
send it to his place?</ab>

<fw>The Arke is sent to
Bethshemesh.</fw>
<ab n="3">And they said, If
yee send away the Arke of the God of Israel, send it not empty: but
in any wise returne him a trespasse offring: then ye shall be
healed, and it shall be knowen to you, why his hand is not remooued
from you.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then said they,
What shall be the trespasse offering, which wee shall returne to
him? They answered, Fiue golden Emerods, and fiue golden mice,
according to the number of the lordes of the Philistines: for one
plague was on you all, and on your lords.<note> Heb. them.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Wherefore ye
shall make images of your Emerodes, and images of your Mice, that
marre the land, and ye shall giue glory vnto the God of Israel:
peraduenture hee will lighten his hand from off you, and from off
your gods, and from off your land.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore then
doe yee harden your hearts, as the Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened
their hearts? when he had wrought wonderfully among them, did they
not let the people goe, and they departed?<note> Or, reprochfully. , Exod. 12. 31. , Heb. them.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
make a new cart, and take two milch-kine, on which there hath come
no yoke, and tie the kine to the cart, and bring the calues home
from them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And take the Arke
of the Lord, and lay it vpon the cart, and put the iewels of golde,
which ye returne him for a trespasse offering, in a coffer by the
side thereof, and send it away, that it may goe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And see, if it
goeth vp by the way of his owne coast to Bethshemesh, then he hath
done vs this great euill: but if not, then wee shall know that it
is not his hand that smote vs; it was a chance that happened to
vs.<note> Or, it.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
men did so: and tooke two milch-kine, and tied them to the cart,
and shut vp their calues at home.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they layde
the Arke of the Lord vpon the cart, and the coffer, with the mice
of golde, and the images of their Emerods.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the kine
tooke the straight way to the way of Bethshemesh, and went along
the high way, lowing as they went, and turned not aside to the
right hand, or to the left: and the lords of the Philistines went
after them, vnto the border of Bethshemesh.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they of
Bethshemesh were reaping their wheat haruest in the valley: and
they lifted vp their eyes, and saw the Arke, and reioyced to see
it.</ab>

<fw>The Arke is sent to
Bethshemesh.</fw>
<ab n="14">And the cart
came into the field of Ioshua a Bethshemite, &amp; stood there,
where there was a great stone: and they claue the wood of the cart,
and offered the kine, a burnt offering vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Leuites
tooke downe the Arke of the Lord, and the coffer that was with it,
wherein the iewels of golde were, and put them on the great stone:
And the men of Bethshemesh offered burnt offrings, and sacrificed
sacrifices the same day vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when the
fiue lordes of the Philistines had seene it, they returned to Ekron
the same day.</ab>
<ab n="17">And these are
the golden Emerods which the Philistines returned for a trespasse
offering vnto the Lord; for Ashdod one, for Gaza one, for Askelon
one, for Gath one, for Ekron one.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the golden
Mice according to the number of all the cities of the Philistines,
belonging to the fiue lordes, both of fenced cities, and of
countrey villages, euen vnto the great stone of Abel, whereon they
set downe the Arke of the Lord; which stone remaineth vnto this
day, in the field of Ioshua the Bethshemite.<note> Or, great stone.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And he
smote the men of Bethshemesh, because they had looked into the Arke
of the Lord, euen he smote of the people fiftie thousand, and
threescore and tenne men: and the people lamented, because the Lord
had smitten many of the people with a great slaughter.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the men of
Bethshemesh said, Who is able to stand before this holy Lord God?
and to whom shal he goe vp from vs?</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And they
sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kiriath-iearim, saying, The
Philistines haue brought againe the Arke of the Lord; come ye
downe, and fetch it vp to you.</ab>



</div>