<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid at Nob, obtaineth of
Ahimelech hallowed bread. 7 Doeg was present. 8 Dauid taketh
Goliaths sword. 10 Dauid at Gath faineth himselfe
madde.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came Dauid
to Nob, to Ahimelech the Priest, and Ahimelech was afraide at the
meeting of Dauid, and said vnto him, Why art thou alone, and no man
with thee?</ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid said
vnto Ahimelech the Priest, The king hath commanded me a businesse,
and hath said vnto me, Let no man know any thing of the businesse
whereabout I send thee, and what I haue commanded thee: and I haue
appointed my seruants to such and such a place.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now therefore
what is vnder thine hand? giue me fiue loaues of bread in mine
hand, or what there is present.<note> Heb. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the Priest
answered Dauid, and said, There is no common bread vnder mine hand,
but there is hallowed bread: if the young men haue kept themselues
at least from women.<note> Exod. 25. 30. leuit. 24.5. matt. 12.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Dauid
answered the Priest, and said vnto him, Of a trueth women haue
beene kept from vs about these three dayes, since I came out, and
the vessels of the young men are holy, and the bread is in a manner
common, yea, though it were sanctified this day in the
vessell.<note> Or, especially wh this day there is other sanctified in the vessell.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">So the Priest
gaue him hallowed bread; for there was no bread there, but the
Shewbread that was taken from before the Lord, to put hote bread in
the day when it was taken away.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now a certaine
man of the seruants of Saul was there that day, detained before the
Lord, and his name was Doeg an Edomite, the chiefest of the
heardmen that belonged to Saul.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And Dauid
said vnto Ahimelech, And is there not here vnder thine hand speare
or sword? for I haue neither brought my sword nor my weapons with
mee, because the kings businesse required haste.</ab>

<fw>Dauid seemeth mad.</fw>
<ab n="9">And the Priest
said, The sword of Goliath the Philistine, whome thou slewest in
the valley of Elah, behold, it is heere wrapt in a cloth behinde
the Ephod: if thou wilt take that, take it; for there is no other
saue that, here. And Dauid saide, There is none like that, giue it
me.<note> Chap. 17.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
Dauid arose, and fled that day, for feare of Saul, and went to
Achish, the king of Gath.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the
seruants of Achish sayd vnto him, Is not this Dauid the king of the
land? Did they not sing one to another of him in daunces, saying,
Saul hath slaine his thousands, and Dauid his ten
thousands?<note> Chap. 18. 7. and 29.5. ecclus.47. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And Dauid layd
vp these wordes in his heart, and was sore afraid of Achish the
king of Gath.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he changed
his behauiour before them, and fained himselfe mad in their hands,
and scrabled on the doores of the gate, and let his spittle fall
downe vpon his beard.<note> Or, made markes.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Then saide
Achish vnto his seruants, Loe, you see the man is mad: wherefore
then haue yee brought him to mee?<note> Or, playeth the madman.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Haue I need of
mad-men, that ye haue brought this fellow to play the mad-man in my
presence? Shall this fellow come into my house?</ab>



</div>