<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Ionathan loueth Dauid. 5 Saul
enuieth his praise, 10 Seeketh to kill him in his furie, 12 Feareth
him for his good successe, 17 Offereth him his daughters for a
snare. 22 Dauid perswaded to be the Kings sonne in law, giueth two
hundred foreskinnes of the Philistines for Michals dowrie. 28 Sauls
hatred, and Dauids glory increaseth.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe when hee made an ende of speaking vnto Saul, that the soule
of Ionathan was knit with the soule of Dauid, and Ionathan loued
him as his owne soule.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Saul tooke
him that day, and would let him go no more home to his fathers
house.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then Ionathan
and Dauid made a couenant, because he loued him as his owne
soule.</ab>

<fw>Ionathans loue to Dauid. Sauls
enuie.</fw>
<ab n="4">And Ionathan
stript himselfe of the robe that was vpon him, and gaue it to
Dauid, and his garments, euen to his sword, and to his bow, and to
his girdle.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And Dauid
went out, whither soeuer Saul sent him, and behaued himselfe
wisely: and Saul set him ouer the men of warre, and he was accepted
in the sight of all the people, and also in the sight of Sauls
seruants.<note> Or, prospered.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe as they came when Dauid was returned from the slaughter of
the Philistine, that the women came out of all cities of Israel,
singing and dancing, to meete king Saul, with tabrets, with ioy,
and with instruments of musicke.<note> Or, Philistines. , Heb. three stringed instruments.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the women
answered one another as they played, and said, Saul hath slaine his
thousands, and Dauid his ten thousands.<note> Chap. 21. 11. and 29. 5. ecclus. 47.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Saul was
very wroth, and the saying displeased him, and he sayd, They haue
ascribed vnto Dauid tenne thousands, and to me they haue ascribed
but thousands: and what can he haue more, but the
kingdome?<note> Hebr. was euill in his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Saul eyed
Dauid from that day, and forward.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And it
came to passe on the morrow, that the euill spirit from God came
vpon Saul, and he prophecied in the midst of the house: and Dauid
played with his hand, as at other times: and there was a iauelin in
Sauls hand.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Saul cast
the iauelin; for hee said, I will smite Dauid euen to the wall with
it: and Dauid auoided out of his presence twice.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Saul
was afraid of Dauid, because the Lord was with him, and was
departed from Saul.</ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore Saul
remooued him from him, and made him his captaine ouer a thousand,
and hee went out and came in before the people.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Dauid
behaued himselfe wisely in all his wayes; &amp; the Lord was with
him.<note> Or, prospered.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Wherefore when
Saul saw that hee behaued himselfe very wisely, hee was afraid of
him.</ab>
<ab n="16">But all Israel
and Iudah loued Dauid, because hee went out and came in before
them.</ab>

<fw>Michal Dauids wife.</fw>
<ab n="17">¶ And Saul
said to Dauid, Behold, my elder daughter Merab, her will I giue
thee to wife: onely be thou valiant for me, and fight the Lords
battels: for Saul said, Let not mine hand be vpon him, but let the
hand of the Philistines be vpon him.<note> Hebr. a sonne of valour.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Dauid said
vnto Saul, Who am I? and what is my life, or my fathers family in
Israel, that I should be sonne in law to the king?</ab>
<ab n="19">But it came to
passe at the time when Merab Sauls daughter should haue beene giuen
to Dauid, that shee was giuen vnto Adriel the Meholathite to
wife.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Michal
Sauls daughter loued Dauid: and they tolde Saul, and the thing
pleased him.<note> Hebr. was right in his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Saul said,
I will giue him her, that she may be a snare to him, and that the
hand of the Philistines may be against him. Wherefore Saul said to
Dauid, Thou shalt this day be my sonne in law, in the one of the
twaine.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And Saul
commanded his seruants, saying, Commune with Dauid secretly, and
say, Behold, the king hath delight in thee, and all his seruants
loue thee: now therefore be the kings sonne in law.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Sauls
seruants spake those wordes in the eares of Dauid: And Dauid said,
Seemeth it to you a light thing to be a kings sonne in law, seeing
that I am a poore man, and lightly esteemed?</ab>
<ab n="24">And the
seruants of Saul tolde him, saying; On this manner spake
Dauid.<note> Hebr. according to these words.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Saul said,
Thus shall yee say to Dauid, The King desireth not any dowrie, but
an hundred foreskinnes of the Philistines, to be auenged of the
kings enemies. But Saul thought to make Dauid fal by the hand of
the Philistines.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when his
seruants told Dauid these wordes, it pleased Dauid well to be the
kings sonne in lawe: and the dayes were not expired.<note> Hebr. fulfilled.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore Dauid
arose, hee and his men, and slew of the Philistines two hundred
men, and Dauid brought their foreskinnes, and they gaue them in
full tale to the king, that hee might be the kings sonne in law:
and Saul gaue him Michal his daughter to wife.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And Saul
saw and knew that the Lord was with Dauid, and that Michal Sauls
daughter loued him.</ab>

<fw>Ionathans loue.</fw>
<ab n="29">And Saul was
yet the more afraid of Dauid; and Saul became Dauids enemie
continually.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then the
Princes of the Philistines went foorth: and it came to passe after
they went foorth, that Dauid behaued himselfe more wisely then all
the seruants of Saul, so that his name was much set by.<note> Hebr. precious.</note></ab>



</div>