<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-31-31-2-Samuel.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 Saul hauing lost his armie, and
his sonnes slaine, he and his armour bearer kill themselues. 7 The
Philistines possesse the forsaken townes of the Israelites. 8 They
triumph ouer the dead carkeises. 11 They of Iabesh Gilead,
recouering the bodies by night, burne them at Iabesh, and
mournfully burie their bones.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe the
Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from
before the Philistines, and fell downe slaine in mount
Gilboa.<note> 1. Chron. 10.1. , Or, wounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the
Philistines followed hard vpon Saul, and vpon his sonnes, and the
Philistines slewe Ionathan, and Abinadab, and Malchishua, Sauls
sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the battell
went sore against Saul, and the archers hit him, and he was sore
wounded of the archers.<note> Heb. shooters, men with bowes. , Heb. found him.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then said Saul
vnto his armour bearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through
therewith, lest these vncircumcised come and thrust me through, and
abuse mee. But his armour bearer would not, for he was sore afraid:
therfore Saul tooke a sword, &amp; fell vpon it.<note> Or, mocke me.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And when his
armour bearer saw that Saul was dead, he fell likewise vpon his
sword, and died with him.</ab>
<ab n="6">So Saul died,
and his three sons, and his armour bearer, and all his men that
same day together.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And when
the men of Israel that were on the other side of the valley, and
they that were on the other side Iordane, saw that the men of
Israel fled, and that Saul and his sonnes were dead, they forsooke
the cities and fled, and the Philistines came and dwelt in
them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came to
passe on the morrow when the Philistines came to strip the slaine,
that they found Saul, and his three sons fallen in mount
Gilboa.</ab>

<fw>Dauid heareth of Sauls death.</fw>
<ab n="9">And they cut off
his head, and stripped off his armour, and sent into the land of
the Philistines round about to publish it in the house of their
idoles, and among the people.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they put
his armour in the house of Ashtaroth: and they fastened his body to
the wall of Bethshan.</ab>

<fw>Dauid heareth of Sauls death.</fw>
<ab n="11">¶ And when
the inhabitants of Iabesh Gilead heard of that which the
Philistines had done to Saul:<note> Or, concerning him.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">All the valiant
men arose, and went all night, and tooke the body of Saul, and the
bodies of his sonnes from the wall of Bethshan, and came to Iabesh,
and burnt them there.<note> Iere. 34. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And they tooke
their bones, and buried them vnder a tree at Iabesh, and fasted
seuen dayes.<note> 2. Sam. 2. 4.</note></ab>



</div>