<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-20-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid consulteth with Ionathan for
his safetie. 11 Ionathan and Dauid renew their couenant by oath. 18
Ionathans token to Dauid. 24 Saul missing Dauid, seeketh to kill
Ionathan. 35 Ionathan louingly taketh his leaue of
Dauid.</head>

<ab n="1">And Dauid fled
from Naioth in Ramah, and came and said before Ionathan, What haue
I done? what is mine iniquity? and what is my sinne before thy
father, that he seeketh my life?</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said vnto
him, God forbid, thou shalt not die; beholde, my father will doe
nothing, either great or small, but that he will shew it me: and
why should my father hide this thing from me? it is not
so.<note> Heb. vncouer mine eare.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Dauid sware
moreouer, and said, Thy father certeinly knoweth that I haue found
grace in thine eyes, and he sayth, Let not Ionathan know this, lest
he be grieued: but truely, as the Lord liueth, and as thy soule
liueth, there is but a step betweene me &amp; death.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then said
Ionathan vnto Dauid, Whatsoeuer thy soule desireth, I will euen doe
it for thee.<note> Or, Say, what is thy mind, and I will doe, &amp;c. , Heb. speaketh, or thinketh.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Dauid said
vnto Ionathan, Behold, to morrow is the new moone, and I should not
faile to sit with the king at meate: but let me goe, that I may
hide my selfe in the fields vnto the third day at euen.</ab>

<fw>Ionathans couenant with Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="6">If thy father at
all misse me, then say, Dauid earnestly asked leaue of me that he
might runne to Bethlehem his citie: for there is a yeerely
sacrifice there for all the family.<note> Or, feast.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">If he say thus,
It is well, thy seruant shall haue peace: but if he be very wroth,
then be sure that euill is determined by him.</ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore thou
shalt deale kindly with thy seruant, for thou hast brought thy
seruant into a couenant of the Lord with thee: notwithstanding, if
there be in me iniquitie, slay me thy selfe: for why shouldest thou
bring me to thy father?<note> Chap. 18. 3. and 23. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Ionathan
said, Farre be it from thee: for if I knew certainely that euill
were determined by my father to come vpon thee, then would not I
tell it thee?</ab>
<ab n="10">Then said Dauid
to Ionathan, Who shall tell me? or what if thy father answere thee
roughly?</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
Ionathan said vnto Dauid, Come, and let vs goe out into the field.
And they went out both of them into the field.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Ionathan
said vnto Dauid, O Lord God of Israel, when I haue sounded my
father, about to morrow any time, or the third day, and behold, if
there be good toward Dauid, and I then send not vnto thee, and shew
it thee;<note> Heb. searched. , Heb. vncouer thine eare.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The Lord doe so
and much more to Ionathan: but if it please my father to doe thee
euill, then I wil shew it thee, and send thee away, that thou
mayest goe in peace, and the Lord be with thee, as hee hath beene
with my father.</ab>
<ab n="14">And thou shalt
not onely while yet I liue, shew me the kindnesse of the Lord, that
I die not:</ab>
<ab n="15">But also thou
shalt not cut off thy kindnesse from my house for euer: no not when
the Lord hath cut off the enemies of Dauid, euery one from the face
of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">So Ionathan
made a couenant with the house of Dauid, saying, Let the Lord euen
require it at the hande of Dauids enemies.<note> Heb. cut.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Ionathan
caused Dauid to sweare againe, because he loued him: for he loued
him as he loued his owne soule.<note> Or, by his loue towards him.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Then Ionathan
said to Dauid, To morrow is the newe moone: and thou shalt be
missed, because thy seat wil be emptie.<note> Heb. missed</note></ab>

<fw>Ionathans couenant with Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="19">And when thou
hast stayed three dayes, then thou shalt goe downe quickly, and
come to the place where thou diddest hide thy selfe, when the
businesse was in hand, and shalt remaine by the stone
Ezel.<note> Or, diligently. Heb. greatly. , Heb. in the day of the businesse. , Or, that sheweth the way.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And I will
shoot three arrowes on the side thereof, as though I shot at a
marke.</ab>
<ab n="21">And behold, I
will send a ladde, saying, Goe, find out the arrowes. If I expresly
say vnto the lad, Behold, the arrowes are on this side of thee,
take them: then come thou, for there is peace to thee, and no hurt,
as the Lord liueth.<note> Heb. not any thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But if I say
thus vnto the yong man, Behold, the arrowes are beyond thee: goe
thy way, for the Lord hath sent thee away.</ab>
<ab n="23">And as touching
the matter which thou and I haue spoken of, behold, the Lord be
betweene thee and mee for euer.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ So Dauid
hid himselfe in the field: and when the newe moone was come, the
king sate him downe to eate meate.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the king
sate vpon his seate, as at other times, euen vpon a seate by the
wall: and Ionathan arose, and Abner sate by Sauls side, and Dauids
place was emptie.</ab>
<ab n="26">Neuerthelesse,
Saul spake not any thing that day: for hee thought, Some thing hath
befallen him, hee is not cleane; surely he is not cleane.</ab>
<ab n="27">And it came to
passe on the morrow which was the second day of the moneth, that
Dauids place was emptie: and Saul said vnto Ionathan his sonne,
Wherefore commeth not the sonne of Iesse to meat, neither yesterday
nor to day?</ab>
<ab n="28">And Ionathan
answered Saul, Dauid earnestly asked leaue of me, to goe to
Bethlehem.</ab>
<ab n="29">And he said,
Let me goe, I pray thee, for our familie hath a sacrifice in the
citie, and my brother, hee hath commanded mee to be there: and now
if I haue found fauour in thine eyes, let me get away, I pray thee,
and see my brethren: Therefore he commeth not vnto the kings
table.</ab>

<fw>Ionathans kindnesse.</fw>
<ab n="30">Then Sauls
anger was kindled against Ionathan, and hee said vnto him, Thou
sonne of the peruerse rebellious woman, doe not I know that thou
hast chosen the sonne of Iesse to thine owne confusion, and vnto
the confusion of thy mothers nakednesse?<note> Or, thou peruerse rebell. Heb. sonne of peruerse rebellion.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For as long as
the sonne of Iesse liueth vpon the ground, thou shalt not be
stablished, nor thy kingdome: wherefore now send and fetch him vnto
mee, for he shall surely die.<note> Heb. is the sonne of death.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And Ionathan
answered Saul his father, and said vnto him, Wherefore shall hee be
slaine? what hath hee done?</ab>
<ab n="33">And Saul cast a
iauelin at him to smite him, whereby Ionathan knewe that it was
determined of his father to slay Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="34">So Ionathan
arose from the table in fierce anger, and did eate no meat the
second day of the moneth: for hee was grieued for Dauid, because
his father had done him shame.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And it
came to passe in the morning, that Ionathan went out into the
field, at the time appointed with Dauid, and a little ladde with
him.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he said
vnto his lad, Runne, finde out now the arrowes which I shoote. And
as the ladde ranne, he shot an arrow beyond him.<note> Hebr. to passe ouer him.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And when the
ladde was come to the place of the arrow, which Ionathan had shot,
Ionathan cryed after the ladde, and said, Is not the arrow beyond
thee?</ab>
<ab n="38">And Ionathan
cryed after the ladde, Make speed, haste, stay not. And Ionathans
ladde gathered vp the arrowes, and came to his master.</ab>
<ab n="39">But the lad
knew not any thing: onely Ionathan and Dauid knew the
matter.</ab>
<ab n="40">And Ionathan
gaue his artillery vnto his ladde, and said vnto him, Goe, cary
them to the citie.<note> Heb. instruments. , Hebr. that was his.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
assoone as the ladde was gone, Dauid arose out of a place toward
the South, and fell on his face to the ground, and bowed himselfe
three times: and they kissed one another, and wept one with
another, vntill Dauid exceeded.</ab>
<ab n="42">And Ionathan
said to Dauid, Goe in peace, forasmuch as wee haue sworne both of
vs in the Name of the Lord, saying; The Lord be betweene me and
thee, and betweene my seede and thy seede for euer. And hee arose,
and departed: and Ionathan went into the citie.<note> Or, The Lord be witnesse of that which, &amp;c.</note></ab>



</div>