<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Samuel_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Companies resort vnto Dauid at
Adullam. 3 At Mizpeh he commendeth his parents vnto the King of
Moab. 5 Admonished by Gad, hee commeth to Hareth. 6 Saul going to
pursue him, complaineth of his seruants vnfaithfulnesse. 9 Doeg
accuseth Ahimelech. 11 Saul cōmandeth to kil the Priests. 17
The footmen refusing, Doeg executeth it. 20 Abiathar escaping,
bringeth Dauid the newes.</head>

<ab n="1">Dauid therefore
departed thence, and escaped to the caue Adullam: and when his
brethren, and all his fathers house heard it, they went downe
thither to him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And euery one
that was in distresse, and euery one that was in debt, and euery
one that was discontented, gathered themselues vnto him, and he
became a captaine ouer them: and there were with him about foure
hundred men.<note> Hebr. had a creditour. , Hebr. bitter of soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And Dauid
went thence to Mizpeh of Moab; and he said vnto the king of Moab,
Let my father, and my mother, I pray thee, come foorth, and be with
you, till I know what God will doe for me.</ab>

<fw>Doegs villenie.</fw>
<ab n="4">And he brought
them before the king of Moab: and they dwelt with him all the while
that Dauid was in the hold.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
Prophet Gad said vnto Dauid, Abide not in the hold; depart, and get
thee into the land of Iudah. Then Dauid departed, and came into the
forrest of Hareth.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ When Saul
heard that Dauid was discouered, and the men that were with him:
(now Saul abode in Gibeah vnder a tree in Ramah, hauing his speare
in his hand, and all his seruants were standing about
him.)<note> Or, groue in a hie place.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then Saul saide
vnto his seruants that stood about him, Heare now, ye Beniamites:
Will the sonne of Iesse giue euery one of you fields, and
Uineyards, and make you all captaines of thousands, and captaines
of hundreds:</ab>
<ab n="8">That all of you
haue conspired against me, and there is none that sheweth mee, that
my sonne hath made a league with the sonne of Iesse, and there is
none of you that is sory for me, or sheweth vnto me that my sonne
hath stirred vp my seruant against me, to lye in wait, as at this
day?<note> Hebr. vncouereth mine eare.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then
answered Doeg the Edomite, (which was set ouer the seruants of
Saul) and saide, I saw the sonne of Iesse comming to Nob, to
Ahimelech the sonne of Ahitub.</ab>
<ab n="10">And hee
enquired of the Lord for him, and gaue him victuals, and gaue him
the sword of Goliath the Philistine.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then the king
sent to call Ahimelech the Priest, the sonne of Ahitub, and all his
fathers house, the Priests that were in Nob: and they came all of
them to the king.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Saul said,
Heare now thou sonne of Ahitub: and hee answered, Here I am, my
lord.<note> Hebr. behold me.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Saul saide
vnto him, Why haue ye conspired against me, thou and the sonne of
Iesse, in that thou hast giuen him bread, and a sword, and hast
enquired of God for him, that he should rise against mee, to lye in
waite, as at this day?</ab>
<ab n="14">Then Ahimelech
answered the king, and said, And who is so faithfull among all thy
seruants, as Dauid, which is the kings sonne in law, and goeth at
thy bidding, and is honourable in thine house?</ab>

<fw>Sauls crueltie.</fw>
<ab n="15">Did I then
beginne to enquire of God for him? be it farre from mee: let not
the king impute any thing vnto his seruant, nor to all the house of
my father: for thy seruant knew nothing of all this, lesse or
more.<note> Hebr. litle or great.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the king
saide, Thou shalt surely die, Ahimelech, thou, and all thy fathers
house.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
king said vnto the footmen that stood about him, Turne and slay the
Priests of the Lord, because their hand also is with Dauid, and
because they knew when he fled, and did not shew it to mee. But the
seruants of the king would not put foorth their hand to fall vpon
the Priestes of the Lord.<note> Or, guard. Heb. the runners.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And the king
said to Doeg, Turne thou and fall vpon the Priests. And Doeg the
Edomite turned, and hee fell vpon the Priests, and slew on that day
foure score and fiue persons that did weare a linnen Ephod.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Nob the
citie of the Priests smote he with the edge of the sword, both men
and women, children and sucklings, and oxen and asses, and sheepe,
with the edge of the sword.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And one
of the sonnes of Ahimelech, the sonne of Ahitub, named Abiathar,
escaped and fled after Dauid:</ab>
<ab n="21">And Abiathar
shewed Dauid that Saul had slaine the Lords Priests.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Dauid said
vnto Abiathar, I knew it that day, when Doeg the Edomite was there,
that he would surely tell Saul: I haue occasioned the death of all
the persons of thy fathers house.</ab>
<ab n="23">Abide thou with
me, feare not: for he that seeketh my life, seeketh thy life: but
with me thou shalt bee in safegard.</ab>



</div>