<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Thessalonians_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Colossians-Chapter-4-4-1-Thessalonians.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Thessalonians-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The Thessalonians are giuen to
vnderstand both how mindfull of them S. Paul was at all times in
thanks-giuing, &amp; prayer: 5 and also how well he was perswaded
of the truth, and sinceritie of their faith, &amp; conuersion to
God.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul and
Siluanus, and Timotheus, vnto the Church of the Thessalonians,
which is in God the Father, and in the Lord Iesus Christ: grace be
vnto you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>

<fw>Effectual faith.</fw>
<ab n="2">We giue
thankes to God alwaies for you all, making mention of you in our
prayers,</ab>
<ab n="3">Remembring
without ceasing your worke of faith, and labour of loue, and
patience of hope in our Lord Iesus Christ, in the sight of God and
our Father:</ab>
<ab n="4">Knowing,
brethren beloued, your election of God.<note> Or, beloued of God: your election.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For our
Gospel came not vnto you in word onely: but also in power, and in
the holy Ghost, and in much assurance, as yee know what maner of
men we were among you for your sake.</ab>
<ab n="6">And yee
became followers of vs, and of the Lord, hauing receiued the word
in much affliction, with ioy of the holy Ghost:</ab>
<ab n="7">So that ye
were ensamples to all that beleeue in Macedonia and Achaia.</ab>

<fw>Men pleasers.</fw>
<ab n="8">For from
you sounded out the Word of the Lord, not onely in Macedonia &amp;
Achaia, but also in euery place your faith to Godward is spred
abroad, so that we need not to speak any thing.</ab>
<ab n="9">For they
themselues shew of vs, what maner of entring in we had vnto you,
and how yee turned to God from idols, to serue the liuing, and true
God,</ab>
<ab n="10">And to
waite for his sonne from heauen whom he raised from the dead, euen
Iesus which deliuered vs from the wrath to come.</ab>



</div>