<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Thessalonians_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Thessalonians-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>In what manner the Gospel was
brought and preached to the Thessalonians, and in what sort also
they receiued it. 18 A reason is rendred both why Saint Paul was so
long absent from them, and also why hee was so desirous to see
them.</head>

<ab n="1">For your
selues, brethren, knowe our entrance in vnto you, that it was not
in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="2">But euen
after that wee had suffered before, and were shamefully entreated,
as ye know, at Philippi, wee were bold in our God, to speake vnto
you the Gospel of God with much contention.</ab>
<ab n="3">For our
exhortation was not of deceite, nor of vncleannesse, nor in
guile:</ab>
<ab n="4">But as we
were allowed of God to bee put in trust with the Gospel, euen so
wee speake, not as pleasing men, but God, which trieth our
hearts.</ab>
<ab n="5">For
neither at any time vsed wee flattering wordes, as yee knowe, nor a
cloke of couetousnesse, God is witnesse:</ab>
<ab n="6">Nor of men
sought we glorie, neither of you, nor yet of others, when we might
haue beene burdensome, as the Apostles of Christ.<note> Or, vsed authority.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But wee
were gentle among you, euen as a nurse cherisheth her
children:</ab>
<ab n="8">So being
affectionately desirous of you, we were willing to haue imparted
vnto you, not the Gospel of God only, but also our owne soules,
because ye were deare vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="9">For yee
remember, brethren, our labour and trauaile: for labourng night and
day, because wee would not bee chargeable vnto any of you, wee
preached vnto you the Gospel of God.</ab>

<fw>Pauls ioy.</fw>
<ab n="10">Yee are
witnesses, and God also, how holily, and iustly, and vnblameably
wee behaued our selues among you that beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="11">As you
know, how wee exhorted and comforted, and charged euery one of you,
(as a father doeth his children,)</ab>
<ab n="12">That ye
would walke worthy of God, who hath called you vnto his kingdome
and glory.</ab>
<ab n="13">For this
cause also thanke wee God without ceasing, because when yee
receiued the word of God, which yee heard of vs, yee receiued it
not as the word of men, but (as it is in trueth) the word of God,
which effectually worketh also in you that beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="14">For yee,
brethren, became followers of the Churches of God, which in Iudea
are in Christ Iesus: for ye also haue suffered like things of your
owne countreymen, euen as they haue of the Iewes:</ab>
<ab n="15">Who both
killed the Lord Iesus, and their owne Prophets, and haue persecuted
vs: and they please not God, and are contrary to all
men:<note> Or, chased vs out.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Forbidding
vs to speake to the Gentiles, that they might bee saued, to fill vp
their sinnes alway: for the wrath is come vpon them to the
vttermost.</ab>
<ab n="17">But wee,
brethren, beeing taken from you for a short time, in presence, not
in heart, endeuored the more abundantly to see your face with great
desire.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wherefore
we would haue come vnto you (euen I Paul) once &amp; againe: but
Satan hindered vs.</ab>
<ab n="19">For what
is our hope, or ioy, or crowne of reioycing? Are not euen ye in the
presence of our Lord Iesus Christ at his comming?<note> Or, glorying</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For, ye
are our glory and ioy.</ab>



</div>