<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Thessalonians_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Thessalonians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Hee proceedeth in the former
description of Christs comming to iudgement, 16 and giueth diuers
precepts, 23 and so concludeth the Epistle.</head>

<ab n="1">But of the
times and the seasons, brethren, yee haue no need that I write vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="2">For your
selues knowe perfectly that the day of the Lord so commeth as a
thiefe in the night.</ab>
<ab n="3">For when
they shal say, Peace and safety: then sudden destructiō
commeth vpon them, as trauaile vpon a woman with childe, and they
shall not escape.</ab>
<ab n="4">But ye,
brethren, are not in darkenesse, that that day should ouertake you
as a thiefe.</ab>
<ab n="5">Yee are
all the children of light, and the children of the day: we are not
of the night, nor of darkenesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore
let vs not sleepe, as doe others: but let vs watch and be
sober.</ab>
<ab n="7">For they
that sleepe, sleepe in the night, and they that bee drunken, are
drunken in the night.</ab>
<ab n="8">But let vs
who are of the day, bee sober, putting on the brestplate of faith
and loue, and for an helmet, the hope of saluation.</ab>
<ab n="9">For God
hath not appointed vs to wrath: but to obtaine saluation by our
Lord Iesus Christ,</ab>
<ab n="10">Who died
for vs, that whether we wake or sleepe, we should liue together
with him.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore,
comfort your selues together, and edifie one another, euen as also
ye doe.<note> Or, exhort.</note></ab>

<fw>Be at peace.</fw>
<ab n="12">And we
beseech you, brethren, to know them which labour among you, and are
ouer you in the Lord, and admonish you:</ab>
<ab n="13">And to
esteeme them very highly in loue for their workes sake, and be at
peace among your selues.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now we
exhort you, brethren, warne them that are vnruly, comfort the
feeble minded, support the weake, be patient toward all
men.<note> Or, beseech , Or, disorderly.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">See that
none render euill for euill vnto any man: but euer follow that
which is good, both among your selues and to all men.</ab>
<ab n="16">Reioyce
euermore:</ab>
<ab n="17">Pray
without ceasing:</ab>
<ab n="18">In euery
thing giue thankes: for this is the will of God in Christ Iesus
concerning you.</ab>
<ab n="19">Quench
not the spirit:</ab>
<ab n="20">Despise
not prophecyings:</ab>
<ab n="21">Proue all
things: hold fast that which is good.</ab>
<ab n="22">Abstaine
from all appearance of euill.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
very God of peace sanctifie you wholly: and I pray God your whole
spirit, and soule, and body be preserued blamelesse vnto the
comming of our Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="24">Faithfull
is hee that calleth you, who also will doe it.</ab>
<ab n="25">Brethren,
pray for vs.</ab>
<ab n="26">Greete
all the brethren with an holy kisse.</ab>
<ab n="27">I charge
you by the Lord, that this Epistle bee read vnto all the holy
brethren.<note> Or, adiure.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">The grace
of our Lord Iesus Christ be with you, Amen. The first Epistle vnto
the Thessalonians, was written from Athens.</ab>



</div>