<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Thessalonians_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Thessalonians-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Thessalonians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>Hee exhorteth them to goe on forward
in all manner of godlinesse, 6 to liue holily and iustly, 9 to loue
one another, 11 and quietly to followe their owne businesse: 13 and
last of all to sorrow moderately for the dead. 17 And vnto this
last exhortation is annexed a briefe description of the
resurrection, and second comming of Christ to
iudgement.</head>


<fw>The resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="1">Furthermore
then we beseech you, brethren, and exhort you by the Lord Iesus,
that as yee haue receiued of vs, how ye ought to walke, and to
please God, so yee would abound more and more.<note> Or, request , Or, beseech</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For yee
know what commandements wee gaue you, by the Lord Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="3">For this
is the will of God, euen your sanctification, that yee should
absteine from fornication:</ab>
<ab n="4">That euery
one of you should know how to possesse his vessell in
sanctification and honour:</ab>
<ab n="5">Not in the
lust of concupiscence, euen as the Gentiles which know not
God:</ab>
<ab n="6">That no
man goe beyond and defraud his brother in any matter, because that
the Lord is the auenger of all such; as we also haue forewarned
you, and testified:<note> Or, oppresse, or, ouerreach. , Or, in the matter.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For God
hath not called vs vnto vncleannesse, but vnto holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">He
therefore that despiseth, despiseth not man, but God, who hath also
giuen vnto vs his holy Spirit.<note> Or, reiecteth.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But as
touching brotherly loue, ye need not that I write vnto you: for yee
your selues are taught of God to loue one an other.</ab>
<ab n="10">And in
deed ye doe it towards all the brethren, which are in all
Macedonia: but we beseech you, brethren, that ye increase more and
more:</ab>
<ab n="11">And that
ye studie to be quiet, and to doe your owne businesse, and to worke
with your owne hands, (as wee commanded you:)</ab>
<ab n="12">That ye
may walke honestly toward them that are without, and that ye may
haue lacke of nothing.<note> Or, of no man.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But I
would not haue you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them which
are asleepe, that ye sorrow not, euen as others which haue no
hope.</ab>
<ab n="14">For if we
beleeue that Iesus died, and rose againe: euen so them also which
sleepe in Iesus, will God bring with him.</ab>
<ab n="15">For this
we say vnto you by the word of the Lord, That we which are aliue
and remaine vnto the comming of the Lord, shall not preuent them
which are asleepe.</ab>
<ab n="16">For the
Lord himselfe shall descend from heauen with a shout, with the
voyce of the Archangel, and with the trumpe of God: and the dead in
Christ shall rise first.</ab>

<fw>Day of the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="17">Then we
which are aliue, and remaine, shalbe caught vp together with them
in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the aire: and so shall wee euer
bee with the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wherefore,
comfort one an other with these words.<note> Or, exhort.</note></ab>



</div>