<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Timothy_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Rules to be obserued in
reproouing. 3 Of widowes. 17 Of Elders. 23 A precept for Timothies
health. 24 Some mens sinnes goe before vnto iudgement, and some
mens doe follow after.</head>


<fw>Of widowes.</fw>
<ab n="1">Rebuke not an
Elder, but intreate him as a father, and the yonger men as
brethren:</ab>
<ab n="2">The elder women
as mothers, the yonger as sisters with all puritie.</ab>
<ab n="3">Honour widowes
that are widowes indeed.</ab>
<ab n="4">But if any widow
haue children or nephewes, let them learne first to shew pietie at
home, and to requite their parents: for that is good and acceptable
before God.<note> Or, kindenesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Now she that is
a widow in deed, and desolate, trusteth in God, and continueth in
supplications and prayers night and day.</ab>
<ab n="6">But she that
liueth in pleasure, is dead while she liueth.<note> Or, delicately.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And these things
giue in charge, that they may be blamelesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">But if any
prouide not for his owne, &amp; specially for those of his owne
house, hee hath denied the faith, and is worse then an
infidel.<note> Or, kindred.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Let not a widow
bee taken into the number, vnder threescore yeeres old, hauing bene
the wife of one man,<note> Or, chosen.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Well reported
of for good works, if shee haue brought vp children, if shee haue
lodged strangers, if she haue washed the Saints feet, if shee haue
releeued the afflicted, if shee haue diligently followed euery good
worke.</ab>
<ab n="11">But the yonger
widowes refuse: for when they haue begunne to waxe wanton against
Christ, they will marry,</ab>
<ab n="12">Hauing
damnation, because they haue cast off their first faith.</ab>
<ab n="13">And withall
they learne to bee idle, wandering about from house to house; and
not onely idle, but tatlers also, and busibodies, speaking things
which they ought not.</ab>
<ab n="14">I will
therefore that the yonger women marry, beare children, guid the
house, giue none occasion to the aduersary to speake
reprochfully.<note> Gr. for their railing.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For some are
already turned aside after Satan.</ab>

<fw>Of Elders.</fw>
<ab n="16">If any man or
woman that beleeueth haue widowes, let them relieue them, and let
not the Church be charged, that it may relieue them that are
widowes indeed.</ab>
<ab n="17">Let the Elders
that rule well, be counted worthy of double honour, especially they
who labour in the word and doctrine.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the
Scripture saith, Thou shalt not mousell the oxe that treadeth out
the corne: and, The labourer is worthy of his reward.<note> Deut. 25. 4. , Matth. 10. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Against an
Elder receiue not an accusation, but before two or three
witnesses.<note> Or, vnder.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Them that sinne
rebuke before all, that others also may feare.</ab>
<ab n="21">I charge thee
before God, and the Lord Iesus Christ, and the elect Angels, that
thou obserue these things without preferring one before another,
doing nothing by partialitie.<note> Or, without preiudice.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Lay hands
suddenly on no man, neither bee partaker of other mens sinnes.
Keepe thy selfe pure.</ab>
<ab n="23">Drinke no
longer water, but vse a little wine for thy stomackes sake, and
thine often infirmities.</ab>
<ab n="24">Some mens
sinnes are open before hand, going before to iudgement: and some
men they follow after.</ab>
<ab n="25">Likewise also
the good works of some are manifest before hand, and they that are
otherwise, cannot be hid.</ab>



</div>