<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Timothy_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 That it is meete to pray and giue
thanks for all men, and the reason why. 9 How women should be
attired. 12 They are not permitted to teach. 15 They shalbe saued,
notwithstanding the testimonies of Gods wrath, in childbirth, if
they continue in faith.</head>


<fw>Prayers for all men.</fw>
<ab n="1">I exhort
therefore, that first of all, supplications, prayers,
intercessions, and giuing of thanks be made for all
men:<note> Or, desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For Kings, and
for all that are in authoritie, that we may leade a quiet and
peaceable life in all godlinesse and honestie.<note> Or, eminent place.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For this is good
and acceptable in the sight of God our Sauiour,</ab>
<ab n="4">Who will haue
all men to bee saued, and to come vnto the knowledge of the
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="5">For there is one
God, and one Mediatour betweene God and men, the man Christ
Iesus,</ab>
<ab n="6">Who gaue
himselfe a ransome for all, to be testified in due
time.<note> Or, a testimony.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Whereunto I am
ordained a preacher, and an Apostle (I speake the trueth in Christ,
and lie not) a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and
veritie.</ab>
<ab n="8">I will therefore
that men pray euery where, lifting vp holy handes without wrath,
and doubting.</ab>
<ab n="9">In like maner
also, that women adorne themselues in modest apparell, with
shamefastnesse and sobrietie, not with broided haire, or gold, or
pearles, or costly aray,<note> Or, plaited.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But (which
becommeth women professing godlines) with good works.</ab>
<ab n="11">Let the woman
learne in silence with all subiection:</ab>
<ab n="12">But I suffer
not a woman to teach, nor to vsurpe authoritie ouer the man, but to
be in silence.</ab>
<ab n="13">For Adam was
first formed, then Eue:</ab>
<ab n="14">And Adam was
not deceiued, but the woman being deceiued was in the
transgression:</ab>
<ab n="15">Notwithstanding
she shall be saued in child-bearing, if they continue in faith and
charitie, and holinesse, with sobrietie.</ab>



</div>