<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Timothy_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Timothie is put in mind of the
charge which was giuen vnto him by Paul at his going to Macedonia.
5 Of the right vse and end of the Law. 11 Of Saint Pauls calling to
be an Apostle, 20 and of Hymeneus &amp; Alexander.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul an Apostle
of Iesus Christ by the commaundement of God our Sauiour, &amp; Lord
Iesus Christ which is our hope,</ab>
<ab n="2">Unto Timothie my
own sonne in the Faith: Grace, mercie, and peace from God our
Father, and Iesus Christ our Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">As I besought
thee to abide still at Ephesus when I went into Macedonia, that
thou mightest charge some that they teach no other
doctrine,</ab>
<ab n="4">Neither giue
heed to fables, and endlesse genealogies, which minister questions,
rather then edifying which is in faith: so doe.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now the end of
the commandement is charity, out of a pure heart, and of a good
conscience, and of faith vnfained.</ab>
<ab n="6">From which some
hauing swarued, haue turned aside vnto vaine iangling,<note> Or, not aiming at.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Desiring to bee
teachers of the Law, vnderstāding neither what they say, nor
whereof they affirme.</ab>
<ab n="8">But we know that
the Law is good, if a man vse it lawfully.</ab>
<ab n="9">Knowing this,
that the Law is not made for a righteous man, but for the lawlesse
and disobedient, for the vngodly, and for sinners, for vnholy, and
profane, for murderers of fathers, and murderers of mothers, for
manslayers,</ab>

<fw>Why Christ came.</fw>
<ab n="10">For
whoremongers, for them that defile themselues with mankinde, for
men-stealers, for liars, for periured persons, and if there be any
other thing that is contrary to sound doctrine,</ab>
<ab n="11">According to
the glorious Gospel of the blessed God, which was committed to my
trust.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I thanke
Christ Iesus our Lord, who hath enabled mee: for that he counted me
faithfull, putting me into the Ministerie,</ab>
<ab n="13">Who was before
a blasphemer, and a persecuter, and iniurious. But I obtained
mercie, because I did it ignorantly, in vnbeliefe.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the grace
of our Lord was exceeding abundant, with faith, &amp; loue, which
is in Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="15">This is a
faithfull saying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Iesus
came into the world to saue sinners, of whom I am chiefe.</ab>
<ab n="16">Howbeit, for
this cause I obtained mercy, that in me first, Iesus Christ might
shew foorth all long suffering, for a paterne to them which should
hereafter beleeue on him to life euerlasting.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now vnto
þe king eternal, immortall, inuisible, the onely
wise God, be honour and glory for euer &amp; euer. Amen.</ab>
<ab n="18">This charge I
commit vnto thee, sonne Timothie, according to the prophesies which
went before on thee, that thou by them mightest warre a good
warfare,</ab>
<ab n="19">Holding faith,
and a good conscience, which some hauing put away, concerning
faith, haue made shipwracke.</ab>
<ab n="20">Of whom is
Hymeneus and Alexander, whome I haue deliuered vnto Satan, that
they may learne not to blaspheme.</ab>



</div>