<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Timothy_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>He foretelleth that in the latter
times there shall be a departure from the faith. 6 And to the end
that Timothie might not faile in doing his duetie, he furnisheth
him with diuers precepts belonging thereto.</head>


<fw>Seducing spirits.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now the Spirit
speaketh expresly, that in the latter times some shall depart from
the faith, giuing heed to seducing spirits, and doctrines of
deuils:</ab>
<ab n="2">Speaking lies in
hypocrisie, hauing their conscience seared with a hote
iron,</ab>
<ab n="3">Forbidding to
marry, and commanding to absteine from meates, which God hath
created to bee receiued with thankesgiuing of them which beleeue,
and know the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="4">For euery
creature of God is good, and nothing to be refused, if it be
receiued with thankesgiuing:</ab>
<ab n="5">For it is
sanctified by the word of God, and prayer.</ab>
<ab n="6">If thou put the
brethren in remembrance of these things, thou shalt be a good
minister of Iesus Christ, nourished vp in the wordes of faith, and
of good doctrine, whereunto thou hast attained.</ab>
<ab n="7">But refuse
prophane and olde wiues fables, and exercise thy selfe rather vnto
godlinesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">For bodily
exercise profiteth litle, but godlinesse is profitable vnto all
things, hauing promise of the life that now is, and of that which
is to come.<note> Or, for a little time.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">This is a
faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptation:</ab>
<ab n="10">For therfore we
both labour, and suffer reproch, because we trust in the liuing
God, who is the Sauiour of all men, specially of those that
beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="11">These things
command &amp; teach.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let no man
despise thy youth, but be thou an example of the beleeuers, in
word, in conuersation, in charitie, in spirit, in faith, in
puritie.</ab>
<ab n="13">Till I come,
giue attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine.</ab>
<ab n="14">Neglect not the
gift that is in thee, which was giuen thee by prophesie, with the
laying on of the hands of the Presbyterie.</ab>
<ab n="15">Meditate vpon
these things, giue thy selfe wholly to them, that thy profiting may
appeare to all.<note> Or, in all things.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Take heed vnto
thy selfe, and vnto the doctrine: continue in them: for in doing
this, thou shalt both saue thy selfe, and them that heare
thee.</ab>



</div>