<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Timothy_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-6-6-2-Timothy.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Of the duetie of seruants. 3 Not
to haue fellowship with newfangled teachers. 6 Godlinesse is great
gaine, 10 and loue of money the roote of all euill. 11 What
Timothie is to flie, and what to follow, 17 and whereof to admonish
the rich. 20 To keepe the puritie of true doctrine, and to auoyd
prophane ianglings.</head>

<ab n="1">Let as many
seruants as are vnder the yoke, count their owne masters worthy of
all honour, that the Name of God, and his doctrine be not
blasphemed.</ab>
<ab n="2">And they that
haue beleeuing masters, let them not despise them because they are
brethren: but rather doe them seruice, because they are faithfull
and beloued, partakers of the benefite: These things teach and
exhort.<note> Or, beleeuing.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">If any man teach
otherwise, and consent not to wholesome words, euen the wordes of
our Lord Iesus Christ, and to the doctrine which is according to
godlinesse:</ab>

<fw>Godlinesse, gaine.</fw>
<ab n="4">Hee is proud,
knowing nothing, but doting about questions, and strifes of wordes,
whereof commeth enuie, strife, railings, euill
surmisings,<note> Or, a foole. , Or, sicke.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Peruerse
disputings of men of corrupt mindes, and destitute of the trueth,
supposing that gaine is godlinesse: From such withdraw thy
selfe.<note> Or.gallings one of another.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But godlinesse
with contentment is great gaine.</ab>
<ab n="7">For we brought
nothing into this world, and it is certaine we can cary nothing
out.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hauing food
and raiment let vs be therewith content.</ab>
<ab n="9">But they that
will be rich, fall into temptation and a snare, and into many
foolish &amp; hurtfull lusts, which drowne men in destruction and
perdition.</ab>
<ab n="10">For the loue of
money is the root of all euill, which while some coueted after,
they haue erred from the faith, and pierced themselues through with
many sorrowes.<note> Or, bene seduced.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But thou, O man
of God, flie these things; and follow after righteousnesse,
godlinesse, faith, loue, patience, meekenesse.</ab>
<ab n="12">Fight the good
fight of faith, lay hold on eternall life, whereunto thou art also
called, and hast professed a good profession before many
witnesses.</ab>
<ab n="13">I giue thee
charge in the sight of God, who quickneth all things, and before
Christ Iesus, who before Pontius Pilate witnessed a good
Confession,<note> Or, profession.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">That thou keepe
this commandement without spot, vnrebukeable, vntill the appearing
of our Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="15">Which in his
times he shall shew, who is the blessed, and onely Potentate, the
King of kings, and Lord of lords:</ab>
<ab n="16">Who onely hath
immortalitie, dwelling in the light, which no man can approch vnto,
whom no man hath seene, nor can see: to whom be honour and power
euerlasting. Amen.</ab>
<ab n="17">Charge them
that are rich in this world, that they bee not high minded, nor
trust in vncertaine riches, but in the liuing God, who giueth vs
richly all things to enioy,<note> Gr. vncertaintie of riches.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">That they doe
good, that they be rich in good works, ready to distribute, willing
to communicate,<note> Or, sociable.</note></ab>

<fw>Vnfained faith.</fw>
<ab n="19">Laying vp in
store for themselues a good foundation against the time to come,
that they may lay holde on eternall life.</ab>
<ab n="20">O Timothie,
keepe that which is committed to thy trust, auoyding prophane and
vaine bablings, and oppositions of science, fasly so
called:</ab>
<ab n="21">Which some
professing, haue erred concerning the faith. Grace be with thee.
Amen. The first to Timothie was written from Laodicea, which is the
chiefest citie of Phrygia Pacaciana.</ab>



</div>