<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C1-Timothy_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>How Bishops, and Deacons, and their
wiues should be qualified, 14 and to what end S. Paul wrote to
Timothie of these things. 15 Of the Church, and the blessed trueth
therein taught and professed.</head>

<ab n="1">This is a true
saying: If a man desire the office of a Bishop, he desireth a good
worke.</ab>

<fw>Of Bishops.</fw>
<ab n="2">A Bishop then
must be blamelesse, the husband of one wife, vigilant, sober, of
good behauiour, giuen to hospitalitie, apt to teach;<note> Or, modest.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Not giuen to
wine, no striker, not greedy of filthy lucre, but patient, not a
brawler, not couetous;<note> Or, not ready to quarell and offer wrong, as one in wine.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">One that ruleth
well his owne house, hauing his children in subiection with all
grauitie.</ab>
<ab n="5">(For if a man
know not how to rule his owne house, how shall he take care of the
Church of God?)</ab>
<ab n="6">Not a nouice,
lest being lifted vp with pride, hee fall into the condemnation of
the deuill.<note> Or, one newly come to the faith.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Moreouer, hee
must haue a good report of them which are without, lest he fall
into reproch, and the snare of the deuill.</ab>
<ab n="8">Likewise must
the Deacons bee graue, not double tongued, not giuen to much wine,
not greedy of filthy lucre,</ab>
<ab n="9">Holding the
mysterie of the faith in a pure conscience.</ab>
<ab n="10">And let these
also first be proued; then let them vse the office of a Deacon,
being found blamelesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">Euen so must
their wiues be graue; not slanderers, sober, faithfull in all
things.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let the Deacons
be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children, and their owne
houses well.</ab>
<ab n="13">For they that
haue vsed the office of a Deacon well, purchase to themselues a
good degree, and great boldnesse in the faith, which is in Christ
Iesus.<note> Or, ministred.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">These things
write I vnto thee, hoping to come vnto thee shortly.</ab>
<ab n="15">But if I tary
long, that thou mayest know how thou oughtest to behaue thy selfe
in the House of God, which is the Church of the liuing God, the
pillar and ground of the trueth.<note> Or, stay.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And without
controuersie, great is the mysterie of godlinesse: God was manifest
in the flesh, iustified in the Spirit, seene of Angels, preached
vnto the Gentiles, beleeued on in the world, receiued vp into
glory.</ab>



</div>