<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The dedicated treasures. 2 The
solemne induction of the Arke into the oracle. 11 God being
praised, giueth a visible signe of his fauour.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus al the
worke that Solomon made for the house of the Lord, was finished:
&amp; Solomon brought in all the things that Dauid his father had
dedicated; and the siluer, and the gold, and all the instruments,
put he among the treasures of the house of God.<note> 1.King.7. 51.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomon sacrificeth, and praiseth
God.</fw>
<ab n="2">¶ Then
Solomon assembled the Elders of Israel, and all the heads of the
Tribes, the chiefe of the fathers of the children of Israel vnto
Ierusalem, to bring vp the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord, out of
the citie of Dauid, which is Zion.<note> 1.King.8. 1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore all
the men of Israel assembled themselues vnto the king in the feast,
which was in the seuenth moneth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And all the
Elders of Israel came, and the Leuites tooke vp the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they
brought vp the Arke, and the tabernacle of the Congregation, and
all the holy vessels that were in the tabernacle, these did the
Priests and the Leuites bring vp.</ab>
<ab n="6">Also king
Solomon and all the congregation of Israel that were assembled vnto
him before the Arke, sacrificed sheepe and oxen, which could not be
told nor numbred for multitude.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the
priests brought in the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord vnto his
place, to the Oracle of the house, into the most holy place, euen
vnder the wings of the Cherubims:</ab>
<ab n="8">For the
Cherubims spread foorth their wings ouer the place of the Arke, and
the Cherubims couered the Arke and the staues thereof,
aboue.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they drew
out the staues of the Arke, that the ends of the staues were seene
from the Arke before the Oracle, but they were not seene without.
And there it is vnto this day.<note> Or, they are there, as 1.king.8.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">There was
nothing in the Arke saue the two tables which Moses put therein at
Horeb, when the Lord made a couenant with the children of Israel,
when they came out of Egypt.<note> Deut.10. 2.5. , Or, where.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
it came to passe when the Priests were come out of the holy place
(for all the priests that were present were sanctified, and did not
then wait by course:<note> Heb. found</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Also the
Leuites which were the singers, all of them of Asaph, of Heman, of
Ieduthun, with their sonnes and their brethren, being arayed in
white linnen hauing cymbals, and psalteries, and harpes, stood at
the East end of the altar, and with them an hundred and twentie
Priests, sounding with trumpets:)<note> 1.Chron. 24.5.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomon sacrificeth, and praiseth
God.</fw>
<ab n="13">It came euen
to passe, as the trumpetters and singers were as one, to make one
sound to be heard in praising and thanking the Lord: and when they
lift vp their voyce with the trumpets, and cymbals, and instruments
of musicke, and praised the Lord, saying, For he is good, for his
mercie endureth for euer: that then the house was filled with a
cloude, euen the house of the Lord.<note> Psal.136.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">So that the
Priests could not stand to minister, by reason of the cloud: for
the glory of the Lord had filled the house of God.</ab>



</div>