<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-24-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Ioash reigneth well, all the dayes
of Iehoiada. 4 Hee giueth order for the repaire of the Temple. 15
Iehoiada, his death and honourable buriall. 17 Ioash falling to
idolatrie, slaieth Zechariah the sonne of Iehoiada. 23 Ioash is
spoiled by the Syrians, and slaine by Zabad and Iehozabad. 27
Amaziah succeedeth him.</head>


<fw>Ioash his zeale.</fw>
<ab n="1">Ioash was
seuen yeeres old when he beganne to reigne; and he reigned fortie
yeeres in Ierusalem: his mothers name also was Zibiah, of
Beer-sheba.<note> 2.Kin. 12. 1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Ioash
did that which was right in the sight of the Lord, all the dayes of
Iehoiada the Priest.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Iehoiada
tooke for him two wiues, and he begat sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
it came to passe after this that Ioash was minded to repaire the
house of the Lord.<note> Heb. to renew.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And hee
gathered together the priests and the Leuites, and saide to them,
Go out vnto the cities of Iudah, and gather of all Israel money to
repaire the house of your God from yeere to yere, and see that ye
haste the matter: howbeit the Leuites hastened it not.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the king
called for Iehoiada the chiefe, and saide vnto him, Why hast thou
not required of the Leuites to bring in out of Iudah and out of
Ierusalem, the collection, according to the commandement of Moses
the seruant of the Lord, and of the Congregation of Israel, for the
tabernacle of Witnesse?<note> Exod. 30. 12,13,14.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For the
sonnes of Athaliah that wicked woman, had broken vp the house of
God, and also all the dedicate things of the house of the Lord, did
they bestow vpon Baalim.</ab>
<ab n="8">And at the
kings commandement they made a chest, and set it without, at the
gate of the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they
made a proclamation through Iudah &amp; Ierusalem, to bring in to
the Lord, the collection that Moses the seruant of God laid vpon
Israel in the wildernesse.<note> Hebr. a voice.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And all the
Princes and all the people reioyced, and brought in, and cast into
the chest, vntill they had made an ende.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now it came
to passe that at what time the chest was brought vnto the kings
office, by the hand of the Leuites: and when they sawe that there
was much money: the kings Scribe, and the high priests officer,
came and emptied the chest, and tooke it, and caried it to his
place againe. Thus they did day by day, and gathered money in
abundance.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the
king and Iehoiada gaue it to such as did the worke of the seruice
of the house of the Lord, and hired Masons and carpenters to
repaire the house of the Lord, and also such as wrought yron and
brasse to mend the house of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Iehoiada dieth.</fw>
<ab n="13">So the
workemen wrought, and the worke was perfected by them: and they set
the house of God in his state, and strengthened it.<note> Hebr. the healing went vp vpon the worke.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And when
they had finished it, they brought the rest of the money before the
king and Iehoiada, whereof were made vessels for the house of the
Lord, euen vessels to minister and to offer withall, and spoones,
and vessels of golde and siluer: and they offered burnt offerings
in the house of the Lord continually, all the dayes of
Iehoiada.<note> Or, pestils.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ But
Iehoiada waxed old, and was full of dayes when hee died: an hundred
and thirtie yeeres olde was hee when hee died.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they
buried him in the citie of Dauid among the kings, because he had
done good in Israel, both towards God, and towards his
house.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now after
the death of Iehoiada, came the Princes of Iudah, and made
obeysance to the king: then the king hearkened vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they
left the house of the Lord God of their fathers, and serued groues
and idols: and wrath came vpon Iudah and Ierusalem for this their
trespasse.</ab>
<ab n="19">Yet hee
sent prophets to them to bring them againe vnto the Lord, and they
testified against them: but they would not giue eare.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the
spirit of God came vpon Zechariah the sonne of Iehoiada the priest,
which stood aboue the people, and said vnto them: Thus saith God,
Why transgresse yee the commandements of the Lord, that yee cannot
prosper? Because yee haue forsaken the Lord, he hath also forsaken
you.<note> Heb. clothed.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And they
conspired against him, and stoned him with stones at the
commandement of the king, in the court of the house of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">Thus Ioash
the king remembred not the kindnesse which Iehoiada his father had
done to him, but slew his sonne: and when he died, he said, The
Lord looke vpon it, and require it.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
it came to passe at the end of the yeere, that the hoste of Syria
came vp against him: and they came to Iudah and Ierusalem, and
destroyed all the Princes of the people from among the people, and
sent all the spoile of them vnto the king of Damascus.<note> Heb. in the reuolution of the yeere. , Heb. Darmesek.</note></ab>

<fw>Ioash slaine.</fw>
<ab n="24">For the
armie of the Syrians came with a small companie of men, and the
Lord deliuered a very great hoste into their hand, because they had
forsaken the Lord God of their fathers: so they executed iudgement
against Ioash.</ab>
<ab n="25">And when
they were departed from him (for they left him in great diseases)
his owne seruants conspired against him, for the blood of the
sonnes of Iehoiada the Priest, and slewe him on his bed, and he
died: and they buried him in the citie of Dauid, but they buried
him not in the sepulchres of the Kings.</ab>
<ab n="26">And these
are they that conspired against him; Zabad the sonne of Shimeah an
Ammonitesse, and Iehozabad the sonne of Shimrith a
Moabitesse.<note> Or, Iozachar, 2 king 12.21. , Or, Shomer.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Now
concerning his sonnes, and the greatnesse of the burdens laide vpon
him, and the repairing of the house of God, behold, they are
written in the story of the booke of the Kings. And Amaziah his
sonne reigned in his stead.<note> Heb. founding. , Or, Commentarie.</note></ab>



</div>