<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-21-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Ahaziah succeeding, reigneth
wickedly. 5 In his confederacie with Ioram the sonne of Ahab, he is
slaine by Iehu. 10 Athaliah destroying all the seed royall, saue
Ioash, whō Iehoshabeath his aunt hid, vsurpeth the
kingdom.</head>

<ab n="1">And the
inhabitants of Ierusalem made Ahaziah his yongest sonne, king in
his stead: for the band of men that came with the Arabians to the
campe, had slaine all the eldest. So Ahaziah the sonne of Iehoram
king of Iudah reigned.<note> 2.King.8. 24,&amp;c. , Chap. 21. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Fourtie and
two yeeres old was Ahaziah, when he began to reigne, and he reigned
one yeere in Ierusalem: his mothers name also was Athaliah the
daughter of Omri.<note> Chap.21.6</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Hee also
walked in the wayes of the house of Ahab: for his mother was his
counseller to doe wickedly.</ab>
<ab n="4">Wherefore he
did euill in the sight of the Lord, like the house of Ahab: for
they were his counsellers after the death of his father, to his
destruction.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ He
walked also after their counsell, and went with Iehoram the sonne
of Ahab king of Israel, to warre against Hazael king of Syria at
Ramoth Gilead: and the Syrians smote Ioram.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
returned to bee healed in Iezreel, because of the wounds which were
giuen him at Ramah when hee fought with Hazael king of Syria. And
Azariah the sonne of Iehoram king of Iudah, went downe to see
Iehoram the sonne of Ahab at Iezreel, because he was
sicke.<note> Heb. wherwith they wounded him. , Otherwise called Ahaziah, ver. 1. &amp; Iehoahaz chap.21.17.</note></ab>

<fw>Ahaziah wicked: He is slaine.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the
destruction of Ahaziah was of God by comming to Ioram: For when he
was come, hee went out with Iehoram against Iehu the sonne of
Nimshi, whome the Lord had anointed to cut off the house of
Ahab.<note> Hebr. treading downe. , 2.King. 9.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And it came
to passe, that when Iehu was executing iudgement vpon the house of
Ahab, and found the princes of Iudah, and the sonnes of the
brethren of Ahaziah, that ministred to Ahaziah, he slew
them.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he
sought Ahaziah: and they caught him (for he was hid in Samaria) and
brought him to Iehu: and when they had slaine him, they buried him:
because, said they, hee is the sonne of Iehoshaphat, who sought the
Lord with all his heart. So the house of Ahaziah had no power to
keepe still the kingdome.<note> 2.Kings 9.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ But
when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah, sawe that her sonne was dead,
shee arose, and destroyed all the seed royall of the house of
Iudah.<note> 2.Kings 11.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But
Iehoshabeath the daughter of the king, tooke Ioash the sonne of
Ahaziah, and stole him from among the kings sonnes, that were
slaine, and put him and his nurse in a bed chamber. So Iehoshabeath
the daughter of king Iehoram, the wife of Iehoiada the priest (for
she was the sister of Ahaziah) hid him from Athaliah, so that she
slew him not.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he was
with them hid in the house of God sixe yeeres, and Athaliah reigned
ouer the land.</ab>



</div>