<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The Queene of Sheba admireth the
wisedome of Solomon. 13 Solomons golde, 15 His Targets. 17 The
throne of Iuory. 20 His vessels. 23 His presents. 25 His chariots
and horse. 26 His tributes. 29 His reigne and death.</head>

<ab n="1">And when the
Queene of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, shee came to prooue
Solomon with hard questions at Ierusalem, with a very great
companie, and camels that bare spices, and golde in abundance, and
precious stones: and when she was come to Solomon, shee communed
with him of all that was in her heart.<note> 1.King. 10.1,&amp;c. mat.12.42. luke 11.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Solomon
tolde her all her questions: and there was nothing hid from
Solomon, which he told her not.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when the
Queene of Sheba had seene the wisedome of Solomon, and the house
that he had built,</ab>
<ab n="4">And the meate
of his table, and the sitting of his seruants, and the attendance
of his ministers, and their apparell, his cup-bearers also, and
their apparell, and his ascent, by which hee went vp into the house
of the Lord; there was no more spirit in her.<note> Or, butlers</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And she said
to the King, It was a true report which I heard in mine owne land,
of thine actes, and of thy wisedome:<note> Heb. word. , Or, sayings</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Howbeit, I
beleeued not their wordes, vntill I came, and mine eyes had seene
it: and behold, the one halfe of the greatnesse of thy wisedome was
not tolde mee: for thou exceedest the fame that I heard.</ab>
<ab n="7">Happy are thy
men, and happy are these thy seruants, which stand continually
before thee, and heare thy wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="8">Blessed be
the Lord thy God, which delighted in thee to set thee on his
throne, to be King for the Lord thy God: because thy God loued
Israel, to establish them for euer, therefore made hee thee King
ouer them, to doe iudgement and iustice.</ab>

<fw>Solomon riches: His death.</fw>
<ab n="9">And she gaue
the king an hundred and twentie talents of gold, and of spices
great abundance, &amp; precious stones: neither was there any such
spice as the Queene of Sheba gaue King Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
seruants also of Huram, and the seruants of Solomon, which brought
gold from Ophir, brought Algume trees and, precious stones.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the king
made of the Algume trees, terrises to the house of the Lord, and to
the kings palace, and harpes and psalteries for singers: and there
were none such seene before in the laud of Iudah.<note> Or, staires: Heb. high wayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And King
Solomon gaue to the Queene of Sheba, all her desire, whatsoeuer she
asked, besides that which she had brought vnto the king: So she
turned, and went away to her owne land, she, and her
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Now
the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one yeere, was sixe
hundred and threescore and sixe talents of gold:</ab>
<ab n="14">Besides that
which chapmen and merchants brought: and all the kings of Arabia,
and gouernours of the countrie, brought gold and siluer to
Solomon.<note> Or, captaines.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And
king Solomon made two hundred targets of beaten gold: sixe hundred
shekels of beaten gold went to one target.</ab>
<ab n="16">And three
hundred shields made he of beaten gold: three hundred shekels of
gold went to one shield: and the king put them in the house of the
forrest of Lebanon.</ab>
<ab n="17">Moreouer the
king made a great throne of yuorie, and ouerlaid it with pure
gold.</ab>
<ab n="18">And there
were sixe steps to the throne, with a footstoole of gold, which
were fastened to the throne, and stayes on each side of the sitting
place, and two lyons standing by the stayes.<note> Heb. hands</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And twelue
lyons stood there on the one side and on the other, vpon the sixe
steps. There was not the like made in any kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
all the drinking vessels of King Solomon were of gold, and all the
vessels of the house of the forrest of Lebanon were of pure gold:
none were of siluer; it was not any thing accounted of in the dayes
of Solomon.<note> Heb. shut vp. , Or, there was no siluer in them.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons riches: His death.</fw>
<ab n="21">For the
kings ships went to Tarshish with the seruants of Huram: euerie
three yeeres once came the ships of Tarshish bringing golde, and
siluer, yuorie, and apes, and peacocks.<note> Or, elephants teeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And king
Solomon passed all the kings of the earth in riches and
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
all the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to heare
his wisedome, that God had put in his heart.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they
brought euery man his present, vessels of siluer, and vessels of
gold, and raiment, harnesse, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate
yeere by yeere.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
Solomon had foure thousand stalles for horses, and charets, and
twelue thousand horsemen, whom hee bestowed in the charet cities,
and with the king at Ierusalem.<note> 1.King.4. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And
hee reigned ouer all the kings, from the riuer, euen vnto the land
of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt.<note> Gen.15. 18. , That is, Euphrates.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the king
made siluer in Ierusalem as stones, and cedar trees made he as the
Sycomore trees, that are in the low plaines, in
abundance.<note> Heb. gaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And they
brought vnto Solomon horses out of Egypt, and out of all
lands.<note> 1.King.10 28. and 2. chron.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Now
the rest of the actes of Solomon first and last, are they not
written in the booke of Nathan the Prophet, and in the prophesie of
Ahiiah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the Seer, against
Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat?<note> 1.King.11. 41. , Heb. words , Chap.12. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Solomon
reigned in Ierusalem ouer all Israel, fourtie yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Solomon
slept with his fathers, and hee was buried in the citie of Dauid
his father, and Rehoboam his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>



</div>