<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Iehoshaphat succeeding Asa,
reigneth well, and prospereth. 7 He sendeth Leuites with the
Princes to teach Iudah. 10 His enemies being terrified by God, some
of them bring him presents and tribute. 12 His greatnesse,
captaines and armies.</head>

<ab n="1">And
Iehoshaphat his sonne reigned in his stead, and strengthened
himselfe against Israel.<note> 1.King. 15.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he
placed forces in all the fenced cities of Iudah, and set garisons
in the land of Iudah, and in the cities of Ephraim, which Asa his
father had taken.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the Lord
was with Iehoshaphat, because hee walked in the first wayes of his
father Dauid, and sought not vnto Baalim:</ab>
<ab n="4">But sought
to the Lord God of his father, and walked in his commandements, and
not after the doings of Israel:</ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore
the Lord stablished the kingdome in his hand, and all Iudah brought
to Iehoshaphat presents, and he had riches and honour in
abundance.<note> Heb. gaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And his
heart was lift vp in the wayes of the Lord: moreouer hee tooke away
the high places and groues out of Iudah.<note> That is, was encouraged.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Also
in the third yeere of his reigne, hee sent to his princes, euen to
Benhail, and to Obadiah, and to Zechariah, and to Nethaneel, and to
Michaiah, to teach in the cities of Iudah:</ab>
<ab n="8">And with
them hee sent Leuites, euen Shemaiah, and Nethaniah, and Zebadiah,
and Asahel, and Shemiramoth, and Iehonathan, and Adoniiah, and
Tobiiah, and Tob-adoniiah, Leuites: and with them, Elishama and
Iehoram, Priests.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they
taught in Iudah, and had the book of the Law of the Lord with them,
and went about throughout all the cities of Iudah, and taught the
people.</ab>

<fw>His captaines.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ And
the feare of the Lord fell vpon all the kingdomes of the lands that
were round about Iudah, so that they made no warre against
Iehoshaphat.<note> Heb. was.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Also some
of the Philistines brought Iehoshaphat presents, and tribute
siluer, and the Arabians brought him flocks, seuen thousand and
seuen hundred rammes, and seuen thousand and seuen hundred he
goats.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
Iehoshaphat waxed great exceedingly, and he built in Iudah castles,
and cities of store.<note> Or, palaces</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he had
much businesse in the cities of Iudah: and the men of warre,
mightie men of valour, were in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="14">And these
are the numbers of them according to the house of their fathers: Of
Iudah, the captaines of thousands, Adnah the chiefe, and with him
mighty men of valour, three hundred thousand.</ab>
<ab n="15">And next to
him was Iehohanan the captaine, and with him two hundred and
fourescore thousand.<note> Heb. at his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And next
him was Amasiah the sonne of Zichri, who willingly offered himselfe
vnto the Lord, and with him two hundred thousand mightie men of
valour.</ab>
<ab n="17">And of
Beniamin, Eliada a mightie man of valour, and with him, armed men
with bow and shield two hundred thousand.</ab>
<ab n="18">And next
him was Iehoshabad, and with him an hundred and foure score
thousand, ready prepared for the warre.</ab>
<ab n="19">These
waited on the king, besides those whom the king put in the fenced
cities throughout all Iudah.</ab>



</div>