<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Iotham reigning well, prospereth.
5 He subdueth the Ammonites. 7 His reigne. 9 Ahaz succeedeth
him.</head>

<ab n="1">Iotham was
twenty and fiue yeeres olde, when hee began to reigne, and hee
reigned sixteene yeeres in Ierusalem: his mothers name also was
Ierushah, the daughter of Zadok.<note> 2.Kings 15.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he did
that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all
that his father Uzziah did: howbeit hee entred not into the temple
of the Lord. And the people did yet corruptly.</ab>
<ab n="3">He built the
high gate of the house of the Lord, and on the wall of Ophel, he
built much.<note> Or, the tower.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Moreouer hee
built cities in the mountaines of Iudah, and in the forrests he
built castles and towers.</ab>

<fw>Iotham. Ahaz.</fw>
<ab n="5">¶ He
fought also with the king of the Ammonites, and preuailed against
them. And the children of Ammon gaue him the same yeere an hundred
talents of siluer, and ten thousand measures of wheate, and tenne
thousand of barley. So much did the children of Ammon pay vnto him,
both the second yeere, and the third.<note> Heb. much.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">So Iotham
became mightie, because he prepared his wayes before the Lord his
God.<note> Or, established.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Now
the rest of the actes of Iotham and all his warres, and his wayes,
lo, they are written in the booke of the Kings of Israel and
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hee was fiue
and twentie yeeres olde when he began to reigne, and reigned
sixteene yeeres in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Iotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of
Dauid: and Ahaz his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>



</div>