<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 Iosiah keepeth a most solemne
Passeouer. 20 Hee prouoking Pharaoh Nechoh, is slaine at Megiddo.
25 Lamentations for Iosiah.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer
Iosiah kept a Passeouer vnto þe Lord in Ierusalem:
and they killed the Passeouer on the fourteenth day of the first
moneth.<note> 2.King. 23.21,22. , Exo.12.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee set
the Priestes in their charges, and encouraged them to the seruice
of the house of the Lord,</ab>
<ab n="3">And said
vnto the Leuites, that taught all Israel, which were holy vnto the
Lord, Put the holy Arke in the house, which Solomon the sonne of
Dauid king of Israel did build; it shall not be a burden vpon your
shoulders: serue now the Lord your God, and his people
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">And prepare
your selues by the houses of your fathers, after your courses,
according to the writing of Dauid king of Israel, and according to
the writing of Solomon his sonne.<note> 1.Chron. 9.10. and chap.23, 24.25, and 26. , 2. Chron. 8.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And stand in
the holy place according to the diuisions of the families of the
fathers of your brethren the people, and after the diuision of the
families of the Leuites.<note> Heb. the house of the fathers. , Heb. the sonnes of the people.</note></ab>

<fw>Iosiah keepeth the Passeouer.</fw>
<ab n="6">So kill the
Passeouer, and sanctifie your selues, and prepare your brethren,
that they may doe according to the word of the Lord, by the hand of
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Iosiah
gaue to the people, of the flocke, lambes and kiddes, all for the
Passeouer-offerings, for all that were present, to the number of
thirtie thousand, and three thousand bullocks: these were of the
kings substance.<note> Heb. offred</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And his
Princes gaue willingly vnto the people, to the Priests and to the
Leuites: Hilkiah, and Zachariah, and Iehiel, rulers of the house of
God, gaue vnto the Priests for the Passeouer-offerings, two
thousand and sixe hundred small cattell, and three hundred
oxen.<note> Heb. offred.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Conaniah
also, and Shemaiah, and Nethaneel, his brethren, &amp; Hashabiah,
and Iehiel, and Ioshabad chiefe of the Leuites, gaue vnto the
Leuites for Passeouer-offerings, fiue thousand small cattell, and
fiue hundred oxen.<note> Heb. offred.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So the
seruice was prepared, and the Priests stood in their place, and the
Leuites in their courses, according to the kings
commandement.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they
killed the Passeouer, and the Priestes sprinckled the blood from
their handes, and the Leuites flayed them.<note> See Chap. 29.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they
remooued the burnt offerings, that they might giue according to the
diuisions of the families of the people, to offer vnto the Lord, as
it is written in the booke of Moses: and so did they with the
oxen.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they
rosted the Passeouer with fire, according to the ordinance: but the
other holy offerings sod they in pots, and in cauldrons, and in
pannes, and diuided them speedily among all the people.<note> Exod. 12. 8,9. , Heb. made them runne.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And
afterward they made ready for themselues, and for the Priests:
because the Priests the sonnes of Aaron were busied in offring of
burnt offrings, and the fat vntill night: therefore the Leuites
prepared for themselues, and for the Priests the sonnes of
Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
singers the sonnes of Asaph, were in their place according to the
commandement of Dauid, and Asaph, and Heman, and Ieduthun the kings
Seer: and the Porters waited at euery gate: they might not depart
from their seruice; for their brethren the Leuites prepared for
them.<note> Heb. station , 1.Chron. 25.1,&amp;c. , 1.Chron. 9.17. and 26.14.</note></ab>

<fw>Iosiah slaine.</fw>
<ab n="16">So all the
seruice of the Lord was prepared the same day, to keepe the
Passeouer, and to offer burnt offerings vpon the altar of the Lord,
according to the commaundement of king Iosiah.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the
children of Israel that were present, kept the Passeouer at that
time, and the feast of vnleauened bread seuen dayes.<note> Heb. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And there
was no Passeouer like to that, kept in Israel, from the dayes of
Samuel the Prophet: neither did all the Kings of Israel keepe such
a Passeouer, as Iosiah kept, and the Priests and the Leuites, and
all Iudah and Israel that were present, and the inhabitants of
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="19">In the
eighteenth yeere of the reigne of Iosiah, was this Passeouer
kept.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶
After all this, when Iosiah had prepared the Temple, Necho king of
Egypt came vp to fight against Carchemish by Euphrates: and Iosiah
went out against him.<note> 2.King. 23.29. , Heb. house.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But hee
sent Embassadours to him, saying, What haue I to doe with thee,
thou king of Iudah? I come not against thee this day, but against
the house, wherewith I haue warre: for God commaunded mee to make
haste: forbeare thee from medling with God, who is with mee, that
hee destroy thee not.<note> Hebr. the house of my warre.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Neuerthelesse
Iosiah would not turne his face from him, but disguised himselfe
that he might fight with him, and hearkened not vnto the wordes of
Necho from the mouth of God, and came to fight in the valley of
Megiddo.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
archers shot at king Iosiah: and the King saide to his seruants,
Haue mee away, for I am sore wounded.<note> Hebr. made sicke.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">His
seruants therefore tooke him out of that charet, and put him in the
second charet that hee had: and they brought him to Ierusalem, and
hee died, and was buried in one of the Sepulchres of his fathers.
And all Iudah and Ierusalem mourned for Iosiah.<note> Or, among the sepulchres. , Zach.12. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
Ieremiah lamented for Iosiah, and all the singing men and the
singing women spake of Iosiah in their lamentations to this day,
and made them an ordinance in Israel; and beholde, they are written
in the Lamentations.</ab>

<fw>Iehoahaz king.</fw>
<ab n="26">Now the
rest of the acts of Iosiah, and his goodnes, according to that
which was written in the Law of the Lord,<note> Hebr. kindnesses.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And his
deedes first and last; behold, they are written in the booke of the
kings of Israel and Iudah.</ab>



</div>