<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 Manasseh his wicked reigne. 3 Hee
setteth vp idolatry, and would not be admonished. 11 He is caried
into Babylon. 12 Vpon his prayer to God hee is released, and
putteth downe idolatry. 18 His acts. 20 Hee dying, Amon succeedeth
him. 21 Amon reigning wickedly is slaine by his seruants. 25 The
murtherers beeing slaine, Iosiah succeedeth him.</head>

<ab n="1">Manasseh was
twelue yeeres old when he began to reigne, and he reigned fiftie
and fiue yeres in Ierusalem:<note> 2.King. 21.1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But did that
which was euil in the sight of the Lord, like vnto the abominations
of the heathen, whom the Lord had cast out before the children of
Israel.<note> Deut. 18. 9.</note></ab>

<fw>Manasseh wicked.</fw>
<ab n="3">¶ For
hee built againe the high places, which Hezekiah his father had
broken downe, and he reared vp altars for Baalim, and made groues,
and worshipped all the host of heauen, and serued them.<note> Hebr. hee returned and built. , 2.King. 18.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Also hee
built altars in the house of the Lord, whereof the Lord had saide,
In Ierusalem shall my Name be for euer.<note> Deut. 12. 11. 1.king. 8.29. and 9.3. 2.chro. 6.6. and 7. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And he built
altars for all the host of heauen, in the two Courts of the house
of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
caused his children to passe through the fire in the valley of the
son of Hinnom: also he obserued times, and vsed inchantments, and
vsed witchcraft, and dealt with a familiar spirit, and with
wizards: he wrought much euill in the sight of the Lord, to prouoke
him to anger.</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee set
a carued image (the idole which he had made) in the house of God,
of which God had said to Dauid, and to Solomon his sonne: In this
house, and in Ierusalem which I haue chosen before all the tribes
of Israel, will I put my Name for euer.<note> Psal.132. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Neither will
I any more remoue the foot of Israel from out of the land which I
haue appointed for your fathers; so that they will take heed to doe
all that I haue commanded them, according to the whole Law, and the
statutes, and the ordinances by the hand of Moses.<note> 2. Sam.7. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So Manasseh
made Iudah, and the inhabitants of Ierusalem to erre, and to doe
worse then the heathen, whom the Lord had destroyed before the
children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
Lord spake to Manasseh, and to his people: but they would not
hearken.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶
Wherfore the Lord brought vpon them the captaines of the host of
the king of Assyria, which took Manasseh among the thornes, &amp;
bound him with setters, &amp; caried him to Babylon.<note> Heb. which were the kings. , Or, chaines.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And when
hee was in affliction, he besought the Lord his God, and humbled
himselfe greatly before the God of his fathers,</ab>
<ab n="13">And prayed
vnto him, and he was intreated of him, and heard his supplication,
and brought him againe to Ierusalem into his kingdome. Then
Manasseh knew that the Lord hee was God.</ab>

<fw>Manasseh dieth.</fw>
<ab n="14">Now after
this, hee built a wall without the citie of Dauid, on the Westside
of Gihon, in the valley, euen to the entring in at the fish-gate,
and compassed about Ophel, and raised it vp a very great height,
and put captaines of warre in all the fenced cities of
Iudah.<note> Or, the tower.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And hee
tooke away the strange gods and the idol out of the house of the
Lord, and all the altars that he had built in the mount of the
house of the Lord, and in Ierusalem, and cast them out of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="16">And hee
repaired the altar of the Lord, and sacrificed thereon peace
offerings, and thanke offerings, and commaunded Iudah to serue the
Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="17">Neuerthelesse,
the people did sacrifice still in the high places, yet vnto the
Lord their God only.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Nowe
the rest of the actes of Manasseh, &amp; his prayer vnto his God,
and the words of the seers that spake to him in the name of the
Lord God of Israel, behold, they are written in the booke of the
kings of Israel:</ab>
<ab n="19">His prayer
also, and how God was intreated of him, and all his sinne, and his
trespasse, and the places wherein he built high places, and set vp
groues and grauen images before hee was humbled: behold, they are
written among the sayings of the Seers.<note> Or, Hosai.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ So
Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his owne
house: and Amon his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Amon
was two and twentie yeeres old, when he beganne to reigne, and
reigned two yeares in Ierusalem.<note> 2. Kin.21. 19. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But he did
that which was euill in the sight of the Lord, as did Manasseh his
father: for Amon sacrificed vnto all the carued images, which
Manasseh his father had made, and serued them;</ab>
<ab n="23">And humbled
not himselfe before the Lord, as Manasseh his father had humbled
himselfe: but Amon trespassed more and more.<note> Heb. multiplied trespasse.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And his
seruants conspired against him, and slew him in his owne
house.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ But
the people of the land slew all them that had conspired against
king Amon, and the people of the land made Iosiah his sonne, king
in his stead.</ab>



</div>