<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Ahaz reigning very wickedly, is
greatly afflicted by the Syrians. 6 Iudah being captiuated by the
Israelites, is sent home by the counsell of Oded the Prophet. 16
Ahaz sending for aide to Assyria, is not helped thereby. 22 In his
distresse, he groweth more idolatrous. 26 He dying, Hezekiah
succeedeth him.</head>

<ab n="1">Ahaz was
twentie yeeres olde when hee beganne to reigne, and he reigned
sixteene yeres in Ierusalem: but hee did not that which was right
in the sight of the Lord, like Dauid his father.<note> 2.King. 16.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For he
walked in the wayes of the Kings of Israel, and made also molten
images for Baalim.</ab>
<ab n="3">Moreouer, he
burnt incense in the valley of the sonne of Hinnom, &amp; burnt his
children in the fire, after the abominations of the heathen, whome
the Lord had cast out before the children of Israel.<note> Or, offered sacrifice. , Leuit. 18. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Hee
sacrificed also, and burnt incense in the high places, and on the
hils, and vnder euery greene tree.</ab>

<fw>Israels crueltie.</fw>
<ab n="5">Wherefore
the Lord his God deliuered him into the hand of the king of Syria,
and they smote him, and caried away a great multitude of them
captiues, and brought them to Damascus: And he was also deliuered
into the hand of the king of Israel, who smote him wich a great
slaughter.<note> Heb. Darmesek.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ For
Pekah the sonne of Remaliah slew in Iudah an hundred &amp; twentie
thousand in one day, which were all valiant men: because they had
forsaken the Lord God of their fathers.<note> Heb. sonnes of valour.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Zichri a
mightie man of Ephraim, slue Maaseiah the kings sonne, and Azrikam
the gouernour of the house, and Elkanah that was next to the
King.<note> Heb. the second to the King.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the
children of Israel caried away captiue of their brethren, two
hundred thousand, women, sonnes and daughters, and tooke also away
much spoile from them, and brought the spoile to Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="9">But a
Prophet of the Lord was there, whose name was Oded: and hee went
out before the hoste that came to Samaria, and said vnto them,
Behold, because the Lord God of your fathers was wroth with Iudah,
he hath deliuered them into your hand, and yee haue slaine them in
a rage that reacheth vp vnto heauen.</ab>
<ab n="10">And now ye
purpose to keepe vnder the children of Iudah and Ierusalem for
bondmen, and bondwomen vnto you: But are there not with you, euen
with you, sinnes against the Lord your God?</ab>
<ab n="11">Now heare
me therefore, and deliuer the captiues againe, which ye haue taken
captiue of your brethren: for the fierce wrath of God is vpon
you.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then
certeine of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the sonne
of Iohanan, Berechiah the sonne of Meshillemoth, and Iehizkiah the
son of Shallum, and Amasa the sonne of Hadlai, stood vp against
them that came from the warre,</ab>
<ab n="13">And said
vnto them, Ye shall not bring in the captiues hither: for whereas
wee haue offended against the Lord already, ye intend to adde more
to our sinnes and to our trespasse: for our trespasse is great, and
there is fierce wrath against Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">So the
armed men left the captiues, and the spoile before the Princes, and
all the congregation.</ab>

<fw>Ahaz an idolater.</fw>
<ab n="15">And the men
which were expressed by name, rose vp and tooke the captiues, and
with the spoile clothed all that were naked among them, and arayed
them, and shod them, and gaue them to eate and to drinke, and
anointed them, and caried all the feeble of them vpon asses, and
brought them to Iericho, the city of palme-trees, to their
brethren: then they returned to Samaria.<note> Deut.34. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ At
that time did king Ahaz send vnto the kings of Assyria to helpe
him.</ab>
<ab n="17">For againe
the Edomites had come and smitten Iudah, and caried away
captiues.<note> Hebr. a captivitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The
Philistines also had inuaded the cities of the low-countrey, and of
the South of Iudah, and had taken Beth-shemesh, and Aialon, and
Gedetoth, and Shocho with the villages thereof, and Timnah with the
villages thereof, Gimzo also, and the villages thereof: and they
dwelt there.</ab>
<ab n="19">For the
Lord brought Iudah low, because of Ahaz king of Israel; for he made
Iudah naked, and transgressed sore against the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">And
Tilgath-Pilneser king of Assyria came vnto him, and distressed him,
but strengthened him not.</ab>
<ab n="21">For Ahaz
tooke away a portion out of the house of the Lord, and out of the
house of the King, and of the Princes, and gaue it vnto the King of
Assyria: but he helped him not.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
in the time of this distresse did hee trespasse yet more against
the Lord: This is that king Ahaz.</ab>
<ab n="23">For he
sacrificed vnto the gods of Damascus, which smote him: and he said,
Because the gods of the kings of Syria helpe them, therefore will I
sacrifice to them, that they may helpe me: but they were the ruine
of him, and of all Israel.<note> Heb. Darmesek.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Ahaz
gathered together the vessels of the house of God, and cut in
pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shut vp the doores of
the house of the Lord, and hee made him altars in euery corner of
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="25">And in
euery seuerall city of Iudah hee made high places to burne incense
vnto other gods, and prouoked to anger the Lord God of his
fathers.<note> Or, to offer.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Now
the rest of his acts, and of all his wayes, first and last, behold,
they are written in the booke of the kings of Iudah and
Israel.</ab>

<fw>Hezekiah king.</fw>
<ab n="27">And Ahaz
slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the citie, euen in
Ierusalem: but they brought him not into the sepulchres of the
kings of Israel: and Hezekiah his sonne reigned in his
stead.</ab>



</div>