<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-21-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Iehoram succeeding Iehoshaphat,
slayeth his brethren. 5 His wicked reigne. 8 Edom and Libnah
reuolt. 12 The prophecie of Eliiah against him in writing. 16
Philistines and Arabians oppresse him. 18 His incurable disease,
infamous death, and buriall.</head>

<ab n="1">Now
Iehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers
in the citie of Dauid: and Iehoram his sonne reigned in his
stead.<note> 1.King. 22.50.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he had
brethren the sonnes of Iehoshaphat, Azariah, and Iehiel, and
Zechariah, and Azariah, and Michael, and Shephatiah: All these were
the sonnes of Iehoshaphat king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">And their
father gaue them great giftes of siluer and of golde, and of
precious things, with fenced cities in Iudah: but the kingdome gaue
hee to Iehoram, because he was the first borne.</ab>
<ab n="4">Now when
Iehoram was risen vp to the kingdome of his father, he strengthened
himselfe, and slew all his brethren with the sword, and diuers also
of the Princes of Israel.<note> 2.King.8. 16,17.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶
Iehoram was thirtie and two yeeres olde when hee began to reigne,
and hee reigned eight yeeres in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
walked in the way of the kings of Israel, like as did the house of
Ahab: for hee had the daughter of Ahab to wife: and he wrought that
which was euill in the eyes of the Lord.<note> Cha.22.2.</note></ab>

<fw>Iehorams crueltie: His great
plague.</fw>
<ab n="7">Howbeit the
Lord would not destroy the house of Dauid, because of the couenant
that hee had made with Dauid, and as hee promised, to giue a light
to him and to his sons for euer.<note> Heb. lamp, or candle. , 2.Sam. 8. 1.king.11. 36. 2.king. 8.19. psal. 132.11,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ In
his dayes the Edomites reuolted from vnder the dominion of Iudah,
and made themselues a king.<note> Heb. hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then Iehoram
went forth with his Princes, and all his charets with him: and he
rose vp by night, and smote the Edomites which compassed him in,
and the captaines of the charets.<note> 2.King. 8.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So the
Edomites reuolted from vnder the hand of Iudah vnto this day. The
same time also did Libnah reuolt from vnder his hand, because he
had forsaken the Lord God of his fathers.</ab>
<ab n="11">Moreouer,
he made high places in the mountaines of Iudah, and caused the
inhabitants of Ierusalem to commit fornication, and compelled Iudah
thereto.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
there came a writing to him from Eliiah the Prophet, saying, Thus
saith the Lord God of Dauid thy father, Because thou hast not
walked in the wayes of Iehoshaphat thy father, nor in the wayes of
Asa king of Iudah:</ab>
<ab n="13">But hast
walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and hast made Iudah and
the inhabitants of Ierusalem to goe a whoring, like to the
whoredomes of the house of Ahab, and also hast slaine thy brethren
of thy fathers house, which were better then thy selfe:</ab>
<ab n="14">Behold,
with a great plague wil the Lord smite thy people, and thy
children, and thy wiues, and all thy goods.<note> Heb. a great stroke.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And thou
shalt haue great sicknesse by disease of thy bowels, vntil thy
bowels fall out, by reason of the sickenesse day by day.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶
Moreouer, the Lord stirred vp against Iehoram the spirit of the
Philistines, and of the Arabians, that were neere the
Ethiopians.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they
came vp into Iudah, and brake into it, and caried away all the
substance that was found in the kings house, and his sonnes also
and his wiues; so that there was neuer a sonne left him, saue
Iehoahaz, the yongest of his sonnes.<note> Heb. caried captiue. , Or, Ahaziah, chap. 22.1. or, Azariah, ver. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And
after all this, the Lord smote him in his bowels, with an incurable
disease.</ab>

<fw>Ahaziah wicked: He is slaine.</fw>
<ab n="19">And it came
to passe, that in processe of time, after the end of two yeres, his
bowels fell out by reason of his sickenesse: so hee dyed of sore
diseases. And his people made no burning for him, like the burning
of his fathers.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thirtie and
two yeeres old was he when he began to reigne, and he reigned in
Ierusalem eight yeeres, and departed without being desired:
howbeit, they buried him in the citie of Dauid, but not in the
sepulchres of the kings.<note> Heb. without desire.</note></ab>



</div>