<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 God hauing giuen testimonie to
Solomons prayer by fire from heauen, and glory in the Temple, the
people worship him. 4 Solomons solemne sacrifice. 8 Solomon hauing
kept the feast of Tabernacles and the feast of the Dedication of
the Altar, dismisseth the people. 12 God appearing to Solomon,
giueth him promises vpon condition.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when
Solomon had made an ende of praying, the fire came downe from
heauen, and consumed the burnt offering, and the sacrifices, and
the glory of the Lord filled the house.<note> 1.King.8. 54,&amp;c. leuit.9.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the
Priests could not enter into the house of the Lord, because the
glory of the Lord had filled the Lords house.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when all
the children of Israel saw how the fire came downe, and the glory
of the Lord vpon the house, they bowed themselues with their faces
to the ground vpon the pauement, and worshipped, and praised the
Lord, saying, For hee is good, for his mercy endureth for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then
the King and all the people, offered sacrifices before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">And King
Solomon offered a sacrifice of twentie and two thousand oxen, and
an hundred and twentie thousand sheepe. So the King and all the
people, dedicated the house of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the
Priests waited on their offices: the Leuites also with instruments
of musicke of the Lord, which Dauid the King had made to praise the
Lord, because his mercy endureth for euer, when Dauid praised by
their ministerie: and the Priests sounded trumpets before them, and
all Israel stood.<note> 1.Chron. 15.16. , Heb. by their hand.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods promises.</fw>
<ab n="7">Moreouer,
Solomon hallowed the middle of the Court, that was before the house
of the Lord: for there hee offered burnt offerings, and the fat of
the peace offerings, because the brasen Altar which Solomon had
made, was not able to receiue the burnt offerings, and the meat
offerings, and the fat.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Also
at the same time Solomon kept the feast seuen dayes, and all Israel
with him, a very great Congregation, from the entring in of Hamath,
vnto the Riuer of Egypt.<note> Iosh.13.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And in the
eight day they made a solemne assembly: for they kept the
dedication of the Altar seuen dayes, and the feast seuen
dayes.<note> Hebr. a restraint.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And on the
three and twentieth day of the seuenth moneth, he sent the people
away into their tents, glad and merry in heart for the goodnesse
that the Lord had shewed vnto Dauid, and to Solomon, and to Israel
his people.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus Solomon
finished the house of the Lord, and the Kings house: and all that
came into Solomons heart to make in the house of the Lord, and in
his owne house, hee prosperously effected.<note> 1.King.9. 1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
the Lord appeared to Solomon by night, and said vnto him, I haue
heard thy prayer, and haue chosen this place to my selfe for an
house of sacrifice.<note> Deut.12. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">If I shut vp
heauen that there bee no raine, or if I command the locusts to
deuoure the land, or if I send pestilence among my people:</ab>
<ab n="14">If my people
which are called by my Name, shall humble themselues and pray, and
seeke my face, and turne from their wicked wayes: then will I heare
from heauen, and will forgiue their sinne, and will heale their
land.<note> Hebr. vpon whom my Name is called.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Now mine
eyes shalbe open, and mine eares attent vnto the prayer that is
made in this place.<note> Chap.6. 40. , Heb. to the prayer of this place.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For now haue
I chosen, &amp; sanctified this house, that my Name may be there
for euer: and mine eyes and mine heart shalbe there
perpetually.<note> Chap.6.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And as for
thee, if thou wilt walke before me, as Dauid thy father walked, and
doe according to all that I haue commanded thee, and shalt obserue
my Statutes, and my Iudgements:</ab>
<ab n="18">Then wil I
stablish the throne of thy kingdome, according as I haue couenanted
with Dauid thy father, saying, There shall not faile thee a man to
be ruler in Israel.<note> Chap.6. 16. , Hebr. there shall not be cut off to thee.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons buildings.</fw>
<ab n="19">But if yee
turne away and forsake my Statutes and my Commandements which I
haue set before you, and shall goe and serue other gods, and
worship them:<note> Leuit. 26. 14. deut.28. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then will I
plucke them vp by the roots out of my land which I haue giuen them,
and this house which I haue sanctified for my Name, wil I cast out
of my sight, and will make it to be a prouerbe, and a by-word among
all nations.</ab>
<ab n="21">And this
house which is high, shall be an astonishment to euery one that
passeth by it; so that hee shall say; Why hath the Lord done thus
vnto this land, and vnto this house?<note> Deut. 29. 24, iere. 22. 8,9.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And it
shalbe answered, Because they forsooke the Lord God of their
fathers, which brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, and
layd hold on others gods, and worshipped them, aud serued them:
Therefore hath hee brought all this euil vpon them.</ab>



</div>