<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Iehoshaphat ioyned in affinitie
with Ahab, is perswaded to goe with him against Ramoth Gilead. 4
Ahab seduced by false prophets, according to the worde of Micaiah
is slaine there.</head>

<ab n="1">Now
Iehoshaphat had riches and honour in abundance, and ioyned
affinitie with Ahab.</ab>

<fw>Ahabs prophets.</fw>
<ab n="2">And after
certaine yeeres, he went downe to Ahab to Samaria: and Ahab killed
sheepe and oxen for him in abundance, and for the people that he
had with him, and perswaded him to goe vp with him to Ramoth
Gilead.<note> 1.King.22 2. , Heb. at the end of yeeres.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Ahab
king of Israel said vnto Iehoshaphat king of Iudah, Wilt thou goe
with me to Ramoth Gilead? And he answered him, I am as thou art,
and my people as thy people, and we will be with thee in the
warre.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
Iehoshaphat saide vnto the king of Israel, Enquire, I pray thee, at
the word of the Lord to day.</ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore
the king of Israel gathered together of prophets foure hundred men,
and said vnto them, Shal we goe to Ramoth Gilead to battel, or shal
I forbeare? And they said, Goe vp, for God will deliuer it into the
kings hand.</ab>
<ab n="6">But
Iehoshaphat saide, Is there not here a Prophet of the Lord besides,
that we might enquire of him?<note> Heb. yet or more.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the king
of Israel said vnto Iehoshaphat, There is yet one man, by whom we
may enquire of the Lord: but I hate him, for he neuer prophesied
good vnto me, but alwayes euill: the same is Micaiah the sonne of
Iimla. And Iehoshaphat saide, Let not the king say so.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the king
of Israel called for one of his officers, and saide, Fetch quickly
Micaiah the sonne of Iimla.<note> Or, Eunuches. , Heb. hasten</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the king
of Israel and Iehoshaphat king of Iudah sate, either of them on his
throne, clothed in their robes, and they sate in a voide place at
the entring in of the gate of Samaria, and all the prophets
prophesied before them.<note> Or, floore.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And
Zedekiah the sonne of Chenaanah, had made him hornes of yron, and
said, Thus saith the Lord, With these thou shalt push Syria, vntil
they be consumed.<note> Hebr. thou consume them.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And all the
prophets prophesied so, saying, Goe vp to Ramoth Gilead, and
prosper: for the Lord shall deliuer it into the hand of the
king.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the
messenger that went to call Micaiah, spake to him, saying, Behold,
the words of the prophets declare good to the king with one assent:
let thy word therefore, I pray thee be like one of theirs, and
speake thou good.<note> Heb. with one mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Micaiah
said, As the Lord liueth, euen what my God saith, that will I
speake.</ab>

<fw>Micaiahs prophecie.</fw>
<ab n="14">And when
hee was come to the king, the king sayd vnto him, Micaiah, shall we
goe to Ramoth Gilead to battell, or shall I fobreare? and he sayd,
Goe yee vp, and prosper, and they shall be deliuered into your
hand.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
king sayd to him, Howe many times shall I adiure thee, that thou
say nothing but the truth to me, in the name of the Lord?</ab>
<ab n="16">Then he
sayd, I did see all Israel scattered vpon the mountaines, as sheepe
that haue no shepheard: and the Lord sayd, These haue no master,
let them returne therefore, euery man to his house in
peace.</ab>
<ab n="17">(And the
king of Israel sayd to Iehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee, that hee
would not prophesie good vnto mee, but euill?)<note> Or, but for euill.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Againe he
sayd; Therefore heare the word of the Lord: I sawe the Lord sitting
vpon his throne, and all the hoste of heauen standing on his right
hand, and on his left.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
Lord sayd, Who shall entise Ahab king of Israel, that hee may goe
vp and fall at Ramoth Gilead? And one spake, saying after this
maner, and another saying after that maner.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then there
came out a spirit, and stood before the Lord, and sayd, I will
entise him. And the Lord sayd vnto him, Wherewith?<note> Iob.1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And hee
sayd, I will goe out, and be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his
prophets. And the Lord sayd, Thou shalt entise him, and thou shalt
also preuaile: goe out, and doe euen so.</ab>
<ab n="22">Nowe
therefore behold, the Lord hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of
these thy prophets, and the Lord hath spoken euill against
thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then
Zedekiah the sonne of Chenaanah, came neere, and smote Micaiah vpon
the cheeke, and sayd, Which way went the spirit of the Lord from
mee, to speake vnto thee?</ab>
<ab n="24">And Micaiah
sayd, Behold, thou shalt see on that day, when thou shalt goe into
an inner chamber to hide thy selfe.<note> Or, from chamber to chamber: Heb. chamber in a chamber.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then the
king of Israel sayd, Take yee Micaiah, and carie him backe to Amon
the gouernour of the citie, and to Ioash the kings sonne:</ab>
<ab n="26">And say,
Thus saith the king, Put this fellow in the prison, and feede him
with bread of affliction, and with water of affliction, vntill I
returne in peace.</ab>

<fw>Ahab slaine.</fw>
<ab n="27">And Micaiah
sayd, If thou certainly returne in peace, then hath not the Lord
spoken by mee. And hee sayd, Hearken all yee people.</ab>
<ab n="28">So the king
of Israel, and Iehoshaphat the king of Iudah, went vp to Ramoth
Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="29">And the
king of Israel sayd vnto Iehoshaphat, I will disguise my selfe, and
will goe to the battell, but put thou on thy robes. So the king of
Israel disguised himselfe, and they went to the battell.</ab>
<ab n="30">Now the
king of Syria had commaunded the captaines of the charets that were
with him, saying, Fight ye not with small or great, saue onely with
the king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="31">And it came
to passe when the captaines of the charets saw Iehoshaphat, that
they sayd, It is the king of Israel: therefore they compassed about
him to fight. But Iehoshaphat cryed out, and the Lord helped him,
and God moued them to depart from him.</ab>
<ab n="32">For it came
to passe, that when the captaines of the charets perceiued that it
was not the king of Israel, they turned backe againe from pursuing
him.<note> Heb. from after him.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And a
certaine man drew a bowe at a venture, and smote the king of Israel
betweene the ioints of the harnesse: therefore hee sayd to his
charetman, Turne thine hand, that thou mayest carie me out of the
hoste, for I am wounded.<note> Heb. in his simplicitie. , Heb. betweene the ioints and betweene the brestplate. , Heb. made sicke.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And the
battell increased that day: howbeit the king of Israel stayed
himselfe vp in his charet against the Syrians, vntill the Euen: and
about the time of the sunne going downe, hee dyed.</ab>



</div>