<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The place, and time of building
the Temple. 3 The measure and ornaments of the house. 11 The
Cherubims. 14 The vaile and pillars.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Solomon
began to build the house of the Lord at Ierusalem in Mount Moriah,
where the Lord appeared vnto Dauid his father, in the place that
Dauid had prepared in the threshing floore of Ornan the
Iebusite.<note> 1.Kin.6.1, &amp;c. , Or, which was seene of Dauid his father. , Or, Araunah, 2.Sam. 24.18. 1.chr. 21.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he began
to build in the second day of the second moneth, in the fourth
yeere of his reigne.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Now
these are the things wherein Solomon was instructed for the
building of the house of God. The length by cubites after the first
measure was threescore cubits, and the breadth twentie
cubites.<note> 1.King.6. 2. , Heb. founded.</note></ab>

<fw>The building of the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="4">And the porch
that was in the front of the house, the length of it was atcording
to the breadth of the house, twentie cubites, and the height was an
hundred and twenty: and he ouerlaid it within, with pure
gold.<note> 1.King.6. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the
greater house hee sieled with firre tree, which he ouerlaid with
fine gold, and set thereon palme trees and chaines.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
garnished the house with precious stones for beautie, and the gold
was gold of Paruaim.<note> Heb. couered.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Hee ouerlaid
also the house, the beames, the postes and the wals thereof, and
the doores thereof with gold, and graued Cherubims on the
walles.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he made
the most holy house, the length whereof was, according to the
breadth of the house, twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof
twentie cubits: and he ouerlaid it with fine gold amounting to sixe
hundred talents.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the
weight of the nailes was fiftie shekels of gold: and he ouerlaide
the vpper chambers with gold.</ab>
<ab n="10">And in the
most holy place hee made two Cherubims of image work, and ouerlaid
them with gold.<note> Or, (as some thinke) of mooueable worke.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
the wings of the Cherubims were twentie cubites long: one wing of
the one Cherub was fiue cubites, reaching to the wall of the house:
and the other wing was likewise fiue cubites, reaching to the wing
of the other Cherub:</ab>
<ab n="12">And one wing
of the other Cherub was fiue cubites, reaching to the wall of the
house: and the other wing was fiue cubites also, ioyning to the
wing of the other Cherub.</ab>
<ab n="13">The wings of
these Cherubims spread themselues forth twentie cubits: and they
stood on their feet, and their faces were inward.<note> Or, toward the house.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
he made the vaile of blue and purple, and crimson, and fine linen,
and wrought Cherubims thereon.<note> Mat.27.51 , Heb. caused to ascend</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Also hee
made before the house, two pillars of thirtie and fiue cubites
high, and the chapiter that was on the top of each of them, was
fiue cubites.<note> Ier.52. 21 1.king.7.15 , Hebr. long.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And he made
chaines, as in the Oracle, and put them on the heads of the
pillars, and made an hundred pomegranates, and put them on the
chaines.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he
reared vp the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand, and
the other on the left, and called the name of that on the right
hand, Iachin, and the name of that on the left, Boaz.<note> 1.King.7. 21. , That is, he shal establish , That is, in it is strength</note></ab>



</div>