<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 Vzziah succeeding, and reigning
well in the dayes of Zechariah, prospereth. 16 Waxing proud, he
inuadeth the Priests office, and is smitten with leprosie. 22 Hee
dieth, and Iotham succeedeth him.</head>

<ab n="1">Then all the
people of Iudah tooke Uzziah, who was sixteene yeeres old, and made
him King in the roome of his father Amaziah.<note> 2.King. 14.21. and 15.1. , Or, Azariah.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He built
Eloth, and restored it to Iudah: after that the King slept with his
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="3">Sixteene
yeeres old was Uzziah, when he began to reigne, and he reigned
fiftie and two yeeres in Ierusalem: his mothers name also was
Iecoliah of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee did
that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all
that his father Amaziah did.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee
sought God in the dayes of Zechariah, who had vnderstanding in the
visions of God: and as long as he sought the Lord, God made him to
prosper.<note> Hebr. in the seeing of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And hee went
foorth and warred against the Philistines, &amp; brake downe the
wall of Gath, and the wall of Iabneh, and the wall of Ashdod, and
built cities about Ashdod, and among the Philistines.<note> Or, in the countrey of Ashdod.</note></ab>

<fw>Vzziahs strength: He is
leprous.</fw>
<ab n="7">And God
helped him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians, that
dwelt in Gur-baal, and the Mehunims.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the
Ammonites gaue gifts to Uzziah, and his name spread abroad euen to
the entring in of Egypt: for hee strengthened himselfe
exceedingly.<note> Heb. went.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Moreouer
Uzziah built towers in Ierusalem at the corner gate, and at the
valley gate, and at the turning of the wall, and fortified
them.<note> Or, repaired.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Also he
built towers in the desert, and digged many welles, for hee had
much cattell, both in the low countrey, and in the plaines:
husbandmen also, and vine dressers in the mountaines, and in
Carmel: for hee loued husbandrie.<note> Or, cut out many cisterues. , Or, fruitfull fields. , Hebr. ground.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Moreouer,
Uzziah had an host of fighting men, that went out to warre by
bands, according to the number of their account, by the hand of
Ieiel the Scribe, and Maasiah the ruler, vnder the hand of
Hananiah, one of the kings captaines.</ab>
<ab n="12">The whole
number of the chiefe of the fathers of the mightie men of valour,
were two thousand and sixe hundred.</ab>
<ab n="13">And vnder
their hand was an armie, three hundred thousand, and seuen
thousand, and fiue hundred, that made warre with mightie power, to
helpe the king against the enemie.<note> Hebr. the power of an armie.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Uzziah
prepared for them throughout all the hoste, shields, and speares,
and helmets, and habergions, and bowes, and slings to cast
stones.<note> Heb. stones of slings.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And hee
made in Ierusalem engines inuented by cunning men, to bee on the
towers, &amp; vpon the bulwarks, to shoote arrowes and great stones
withall: and his name spread farre abroad, for he was marueilously
helped, till he was strong.<note> Heb. went foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ But
when he was strong, his heart was lifted vp to his destruction: for
he transgressed against the Lord his God, and went into the temple
of the Lord, to burne incense vpon the altar of incense.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Azariah
the priest went in after him, and with him fourescore priests of
the Lord, that were valiant men.</ab>

<fw>Vzziahs strength: He is
leprous.</fw>
<ab n="18">And they
withstood Uzziah the king, and said vnto him, It perteineth not
vnto thee, Uzziah, to burne incense vnto the Lord, but to the
priestes the sonnes of Aaron, that are consecrated to burne
incense. Goe out of the Sanctuarie; for thou hast trespassed,
neither shall it be for thine honour from the Lord God.<note> Num.18.7 , Exo.30.7</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Then Uzziah
was wroth, and had a censer in his hand, to burne incense, and
while he was wroth with the priests, the leprosie euen rose vp in
his forehead, before the priests, in the house of the Lord, from
beside the incense altar.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Azariah
the chiefe priest, and all the priests looked vpon him, and behold,
he was leprous in his forehead, and they thrust him out from
thence, yea himselfe hasted also to goe out, because the Lord had
smitten him.<note> As Ester 6 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Uzziah
the king was a leper vnto the day of his death, and dwelt in a
seuerall house being a leper, for he was cut off from the house of
the Lord: and Iotham his sonne was ouer the kings house, iudging
the people of the land.<note> 2.Kings 15.5. , Leuit.13. 46. , Heb. free.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Now
the rest of the actes of Uzziah first and last, did Isaiah the
prophet the sonne of Amoz write.</ab>
<ab n="23">So Uzziah
slept with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the
field of the buriall which belonged to the kings: for they saide,
He is a leper: And Iotham his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>



</div>