<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Asa, by the aide of the Syrians,
diuerteth Baasha from building of Ramah. 7 Being reproued thereof
by Hanani, he putteth him in prison. 11 Among his other actes in
his disease he seeketh not to God, but to the Physitians. 13 His
death and buriall.</head>

<ab n="1">In the sixe
and thirtieth yeere of the reigne of Asa, Baasha king of Israel
came vp against Iudah, and built Ramah, to the intent that hee
might let none goe out or come in to Asa king of Iudah.<note> 1.Kings 15.17.</note></ab>

<fw>Asa his death, and buriall.</fw>
<ab n="2">Then Asa
brought out siluer and golde out of the treasures of the house of
the Lord, and of the kings house, and sent to Benhadad King of
Syria that dwelt at Damascus, saying;<note> Heb. Darmesek.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">There is a
league betweene me and thee, as there was betweene my father and
thy father: beholde, I haue sent thee siluer and golde, goe, breake
thy league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from
me.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Benhadad
hearkened vnto king Asa, and sent the captaines of his armies
against the cities of Israel; and they smote Iion, and Dan, and
Abelmaim, &amp; all the store-cities of Naphtali.<note> Heb. which were his.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And it came
to passe, when Baasha heard it, that hee left off building of
Ramah, and let his worke cease.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Asa the
king tooke all Iudah, and they caried away the stones of Ramah, and
the timber thereof, wherewith Baasha was a building, and hee built
there with Geba and Mizpah.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
at that time Hanani the Seer came to Asa king of Iudah, and said
vnto him, Because thou hast relyed on the king of Syria, and not
relyed on the Lord thy God, therefore is the hoste of the king of
Syria escaped out of thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="8">Were not the
Ethiopians and the Lubims a huge hoste, with very many charets and
horsemen? Yet because thou diddest relie on the Lord, he deliuered
them into thine hand.<note> Cha. 14.9. , Heb. in abundance.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For the eyes
of the Lord run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to shewe
himselfe strong in the behalfe of them, whose heart is perfite
towards him. Herein thou hast done foolishly; therefore, from
hencefoorth thou shalt haue warres.<note> Or, strongly to holde with them, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then Asa
was wroth with the Seer, and put him in a prison-house; for he was
in a rage with him because of this thing. And Asa oppressed some of
the people the same time.<note> Heb. crushed.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
behold, the actes of Asa first and last, lo, they are written in
the booke of the Kings of Iudah and Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Asa in
the thirtie and ninth yeere of his reigne, was diseased in his
feete, vntill his disease was exceeding great: yet in his disease
hee sought not to the Lord, but to the Physicians.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
Asa slept with his fathers, and died in the one and fourtieth yeere
of his reigne.</ab>

<fw>Asa his death, and buriall.
Iehoshaphat.</fw>
<ab n="14">And they
buried him in his owne sepulchres which he had made for himselfe in
the citie of Dauid, and laide him in the bed, which was filled with
sweet odours, and diuers kindes of spices prepared by the
Apothecaries arte: &amp; they made a very great burning for
him.<note> Heb. digged.</note></ab>




</div>