<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Solomon hauing blessed the people,
blesseth God. 12 Solomons prayer in the consecration of the Temple,
vpon the brasen scaffold.</head>

<ab n="1">Then said
Solomon, The Lord hath said that he would dwell in the thicke
darkenesse.<note> 1.King.8. 12,&amp;c. , Leuit.16. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But I haue
built an house of habitation for thee, and a place for thy dwelling
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the King
turned his face and blessed the whole Congregation of Israel, (and
all the Congregation of Israel stood)</ab>
<ab n="4">And he said,
Blessed be the Lord God of Israel, who hath with his handes
fulfilled that which he spake with his mouth to my father Dauid,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Since the day
that I brought foorth my people out of the land of Egypt, I chose
no citie among all the tribes of Israel to builde an house in, that
my Name might be there, neither chose I any man to be a ruler ouer
my people Israel:</ab>
<ab n="6">But I haue
chosen Ierusalem, that my name might be there, and haue chosen
Dauid to be ouer my people Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now it was in
the heart of Dauid my father to build an house for the Name of the
Lord God of Israel.<note> 2.Sam.7. 2. 1.chro. 28.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But the Lord
said to Dauid my father: Forasmuch as it was in thine heart to
builde an house for my Name, thou diddest well in that it was in
thine heart.</ab>
<ab n="9">Notwithstanding
thou shalt not build the house, but thy sonne which shall come
foorth out of thy loynes, he shall build the house for my
Name.</ab>

<fw>The prayer of Solomon.</fw>
<ab n="10">The Lord
therefore hath performed his word that he hath spoken: for I am
risen vp in the roome of Dauid my father, and am set on the throne
of Israel, as the Lord promised, and haue built the house for the
Name of the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">And in it
haue I put the Arke, wherein is the Couenant of the Lord, that hee
made with the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
he stood before the Altar of the Lord, in the presence of all the
Congregation of Israel, and spread foorth his hands:</ab>
<ab n="13">(For Solomon
had made a brasen scaffold of fiue cubites long, and fiue cubites
broad, and three cubites high, and had set it in the midst of the
Court, and vpon it hee stood, and kneeled downe vpon his knees
before all the Congregation of Israel, and spread foorth his hands
towards heauen.)<note> Hebr. the length thereof, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And said, O
Lord God of Israel, there is no God like thee in the heauen, nor in
the earth, which keepest couenant, and shewest mercy vnto thy
seruants, that walke before thee with all their hearts,<note> Exod.15. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thou which
hast kept with thy seruant Dauid my father, that which thou hast
promised him: and spakest with thy mouth, and hast fulfilled it
with thine hand, as it is this day.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now
therefore, O Lord God of Israel, keepe with thy seruant Dauid my
father, that which thou hast promised him, saying, There shall not
faile thee a man in my sight, to sit vpon the throne of Israel: yet
so, that thy children take heede to their way, to walke in my Law,
as thou hast walked before me.<note> 2.Sam.7. 12. 1.king. 2.4. and 6. 12. , Heb. there shall not a man be cut off. , Psal.132. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Now then, O
Lord God of Israel, let thy word be verified, which thou hast
spoken vnto thy seruant Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="18">(But wil God
in very deed dwell with men on the earth? Behold, heauen, and the
heauen of heauens cannot conteine thee: how much lesse this house
which I haue built?)<note> Chap.2. 6. esay 66. 1 acts.7. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Haue respect
therfore to the prayer of thy seruant, and to his supplication, O
Lord my God, to hearken vnto the cry, and the prayer which thy
seruant prayeth before thee:</ab>

<fw>The prayer of Solomon.</fw>
<ab n="20">That thine
eyes may bee open vpon this house day and night, vpon the place
whereof thou hast saide, that thou wouldest put thy Name there, to
hearken vnto the prayer, which thy seruant prayeth towards this
place.<note> Or, in this place.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Hearken
therefore vnto the supplications of thy seruant, and of thy people
Israel, which they shall make towards this place: heare thou from
thy dwelling place, euen from heauen; and when thou hearest,
forgiue.<note> Heb. pray.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ If a
man sinne against his neighbour, and an oath be layd vpon him, to
make him sweare, and the oath come before thine Altar in this
house:<note> Hebr. and he require an oath of him.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then heare
thou from heauen, and doe, and iudge thy seruants by requiting the
wicked, by recompensing his way vpon his owne head, and by
iustifying the righteous, by giuing him according to his
righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And
if thy people Israel be put to the worse before the enemy, because
they haue sinned against thee, and shall returne and confesse thy
Name, and pray and make supplication before thee in this
house:<note> Or, bee smitten. , Or, towards.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then heare
thou from the heauens, and forgiue the sinne of thy people Israel,
and bring them againe vnto the land which thou gauest to them, and
to their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ When
the heauen is shut vp, and there is no raine, because they haue
sinned against thee: yet if they pray towards this place, and
confesse thy Name, and turne from their sinne, when thou doest
afflict them:<note> 1.King. 17.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Then heare
thou from heauen, and forgiue the sinne of thy seruants, and of thy
people Israel; when thou hast taught them the good way, wherein
they should walke, and send raine vpon the land, which thou hast
giuen vnto thy people for an inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ If
there be dearth in the land, if there be pestilence, if there be
blasting, or mil-dew, locusts or caterpillers; if their enemies
besiege them in the cities of their land: whatsoeuer sore, or
whatsoeuer sicknesse there be:<note> Chap. 20. 9. , Hebr. in the land of their gates.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Then what
prayer, or what supplication soeuer shall bee made of any man, or
of all thy people Israel, when euery one shal know his owne sore
and his owne griefe, and shall spread foorth his hands in this
house:<note> Or, toward this house.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomon prayeth, and offreth
sacrifices.</fw>
<ab n="30">Then heare
thou from heauen thy dwelling place, and forgiue, and render vnto
euery man according vnto all his wayes, whose heart thou knowest
(for thou onely knowest the hearts of the children of
men:)<note> 1.Chron. 28.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">That they
may feare thee, to walke in thy waies so long as they liue in the
land which thou gauest vnto our fathers.<note> Hebr. all the dayes which. , Hebr. vpon the face of the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶
Moreouer concerning the stranger which is not of thy people Israel,
but is come from a farre countrey for thy great Names sake, &amp;
thy mightie hand, and thy stretched out arme: if they come and pray
in this house:<note> Iohn 12. 20. acts.8. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Then heare
thou from the heauens, euen from thy dwelling place, and doe
according to all that the stranger calleth to thee for; that all
people of the earth may know thy Name, and feare thee, as doeth thy
people Israel, and may know that this house which I haue built, is
called by thy Name.<note> Heb. thy Name is called vpon this house.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">If thy
people goe out to warre against their enemies by the way that thou
shalt send them, and they pray vnto thee toward this citie which
thou hast chosen, and the house which I haue built for thy
Name:</ab>
<ab n="35">Then heare
thou from the heauens their prayer and their supplication, and
maintaine their cause.<note> Or, right.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">If they
sinne against thee (for there is no man which sinneth not) and thou
be angry with them, and deliuer them ouer before their enemies, and
they cary them away captiues vnto a land far off or
neere:<note> Prou.20.9. eccles.7.21. iames 3.2. 1.iohn 1.8. , Heb. they that take them captiues cary them away.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Yet if they
bethinke themselues in the land whither they are caried captiue,
and turne and pray vnto thee in the land of their captiuitie,
saying, Wee haue sinned, we haue done amisse, and haue dealt
wickedly:<note> Heb. bring back to their heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">If they
returne to thee with all their heart, and with all their soule, in
the land of their captiuitie, whither they haue caried them
captiues, and pray toward their land which thou gauest vnto their
fathers, and toward the citie which thou hast chosen, and toward
the house which I haue built for thy Name:</ab>
<ab n="39">Then heare
thou from the heauens, euen from thy dwelling place, their prayer
and their supplications, and maintaine their cause, and forgiue thy
people, which haue sinned against thee.<note> Or, right.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Now, my God,
let (I beseech thee) thine eyes bee open, and let thine eares be
attent vnto the prayer that is made in this place.<note> Heb. to the prayer of this place.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomon prayeth, and offreth
sacrifices.</fw>
<ab n="41">Now
therefore arise, O Lord God, into thy resting place, thou, and the
Arke of thy strength: Let thy Priests, O Lord God, be clothed with
saluation, and let thy Saints reioyce in goodnesse.<note> Psal.132.9</note></ab>
<ab n="42">O Lord God,
turne not away the face of thine anointed: remember the mercies of
Dauid thy seruant.</ab>



</div>