<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Abiiah succeeding, maketh warre
against Ieroboam. 4 Hee declareth the right of his cause. 13
Trusting in God, hee ouercommeth Ieroboam. 21 The wiues and
children of Abiiah.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe in the
eighteenth yeere of king Ieroboam, began Abiiah to reigne ouer
Iudah.<note> 1.King. 15.1,&amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>His death, and successour.</fw>
<ab n="2">He reigned
three yeres in Ierusalem: (his mothers name also was Michaiah the
daughter of Uriel of Gibea:) and there was warre between Abiiah and
Ieroboam.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Abiiah
set the battel in aray with an army of valiant men of warre, euen
foure hundred thousand chosen men: Ieroboam also set the battell in
aray against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, being
mightie men of valour.<note> Heb. bound together.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
Abiiah stood vp vpon mount Zemaraim, which is in mount Ephraim, and
sayde, Heare mee thou Ieroboam, and all Israel:</ab>
<ab n="5">Ought you
not to know, that the Lord God of Israel gaue the kingdome ouer
Israel to Dauid for euer, euen to him and to his sonnes by a
couenant of salt?</ab>
<ab n="6">Yet Ieroboam
the sonne of Nebat, the seruant of Solomon the sonne of Dauid, is
risen vp, and hath rebelled against his Lord.<note> 1.King. 11.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And there
are gathered vnto him vaine men the children of Belial, and haue
strengthened themselues against Rehoboam the sonne of Solomon, when
Rehoboam was young, &amp; tender hearted, and could not withstand
them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And now ye
thinke to withstand the kingdome of the Lord, in the hand of the
sonnes of Dauid, and ye be a great multitude, and there are with
you golden calues, which Ieroboam made you for gods.<note> 1.King. 12.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Haue yee not
cast out the Priests of the Lord the sonnes of Aaron, and the
Leuites, and haue made you priests after the maner of the nations
of other lands? so that whosoeuer commeth to consecrate himselfe
with a young bullocke and seuen rammes, the same may be a priest of
them that are no gods.<note> Chap.11. 14. , Heb. to fill his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But as for
vs, the Lord is our God, and wee haue not forsaken him, and the
Priests which minister vnto the Lord, are the sonnes of Aaron, and
the Leuites waite vpon their businesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they
burne vnto the Lord euery morning, and euery euening, burnt
sacrifices and sweete incense: the shew-bread also set they in
order vpon the pure table, and the Candlesticke of golde with the
lampes therof, to burne euery euening: for we keepe the charge of
the Lord our God, but yee haue forsaken him.<note> Chap.2.4. , Leu.24.6.</note></ab>

<fw>Ieroboam dieth.</fw>
<ab n="12">And behold,
God himselfe is with vs for our captaine, and his Priests with
sounding trumpets to cry alarme against you: O children of Israel,
fight ye not against the Lord God of your fathers, for you shall
not prosper.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ But
Ieroboam caused an ambushment to come about behinde them: so they
were before Iudah, and the ambushment was behind them.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when
Iudah looked backe, behold, the battel was before and behind; and
they cried vnto the Lord, and the Priests sounded with the
trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then the
men of Iudah gaue a shout: and as the men of Iudah shouted, it came
to passe that God smote Ieroboam and all Israel, before Abiiah and
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the
children of Israel fled before Iudah: and God deliuered them into
their hand.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Abiiah
and his people slew them with a great slaughter: so there fel downe
slaine of Israel, fiue hundred thousand chosen men.</ab>
<ab n="18">Thus the
children of Israel were brought vnder at that time, and the
children of Iudah preuailed, because they relied vpon the Lord God
of their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Abiiah
pursued after Ieroboam, &amp; tooke cities from him, Beth-el with
the townes thereof, and Ieshanah with the townes thereof, and
Ephrain with the townes thereof.</ab>
<ab n="20">Neither did
Ieroboam recouer strength againe in the dayes of Abiiah: and the
Lord strooke him, &amp; he died.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ But
Abiiah waxed mighty, and married fourteene wiues, and begate
twentie and two sonnes, and sixteene daughters.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the
rest of the acts of Abiiah, and his waies, and his sayings, are
written in the story of the Prophet Iddo.<note> Or, commentary. , Chap. 12. 15.</note></ab>



</div>