<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah proclaimeth a solemne
Passeouer on the second moneth, for Iudah and Israel. 13 The
assembly hauing destroyed the altars of idolatry, keepe the feast
fourteene dayes. 27 The Priests and Leuites blesse the
people.</head>

<ab n="1">And Hezekiah
sent to all Israel and Iudah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and
Manasseh, that they should come to the house of the Lord at
Ierusalem, to keepe the Passeouer vnto the Lord God of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">For the king
had taken counsell, and his Princes, and all the congregation in
Ierusalem, to keepe the Passeouer in the second moneth.<note> Num.19. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For they
could not keepe it at that time, because the Priests had not
sanctified themselues sufficiently, neither had the people gathered
themselues together to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the
thing pleased the king, and all the Congregation.<note> Heb. was right in the eyes of the King.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So they
established a decree, to make proclamation throughout all Israel,
from Beersheba euen to Dan, that they should come to keep the
Passeouer vnto the Lord God of Israel at Ierusalem: for they had
not done it of a long time in such sort, as it was written.</ab>

<fw>The Passeouer is proclaimed.</fw>
<ab n="6">So the
Postes went with the letters from the King and his Princes,
throughout all Israel and Iudah, and according to the commandement
of the king, saying; Yee children of Israel, turne againe vnto the
Lord God of Abraham, Isaac and Israel, and hee wil returne to the
remnant of you, that are escaped out of the hand of the kings of
Assyria.<note> Heb. from the hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And be not
ye like your fathers, and like your brethren, which trespassed
against the Lord God of their fathers, who therefore gaue them vp
to desolation, as ye see.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now be yee
not stiffe-necked as your fathers were, but yeeld your selues vnto
the Lord, and enter into his Sanctuarie, which he hath sanctified
for euer: and serue the Lord your God, that the fiercenesse of his
wrath may turne away from you.<note> Harden not your neckes. , Heb. giue the hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For if yee
turne againe vnto the Lord, your brethren and your children shall
finde compassion before them that leade them captiue, so that they
shall come againe into this land: for the Lord your God is gracious
and mercifull, and will not turne away his face from you, if ye
returne vnto him.<note> Exo.34.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So the
Posts passed from citie to citie, through the countrey of Ephraim
and Manasseh, euen vnto Zebulun: but they laughed them to scorne,
and mocked them.</ab>
<ab n="11">Neuerthelesse,
diuers of Asher, and Manasseh, and of Zebulun, humbled themselues,
and came to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="12">Also in
Iudah, the hand of God was to giue them one heart to doe the
commandement of the king and of the Princes, by the word of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
there assembled at Ierusalem much people, to keepe the feast of
vnleauened bread in the second moneth, a very great
congregation.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they
arose and tooke away the altars that were in Ierusalem, and all the
altars for incense tooke they away, and cast them into the brooke
Kidron.<note> Chap.28. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then they
killed the Passeouer on the fourteenth day of the second moneth:
and the Priests and the Leuites were ashamed, and sanctified
themselues, and brought in the burnt offerings into the house of
the Lord.</ab>

<fw>The Passeouer.</fw>
<ab n="16">And they
stood in their place after their maner, according to the Law of
Moses the man of God: The priests sprinckled the blood, which they
receiued of the hand of the Leuites.<note> Heb. their standing.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For there
were many in the Congregation that were not sanctified: therefore
the Leuites had the charge of the killing of the Passeouers for
euery one that was not cleane, to sanctifie them vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">For a
multitude of the people, euen many of Ephraim and Manasseh,
Issachar and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselues: yet did they
eate the Passeouer otherwise then it was written. But Hezekiah
prayed for them, saying; The good Lord pardon euery one,</ab>
<ab n="19">That
prepareth his heart to seeke God, the Lord God of his fathers,
though hee be not cleansed according to the purification of the
Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the
Lord hearkened to Hezekiah, and healed the people.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
children of Israel that were present at Ierusalem, kept the feast
of vnleauened bread seuen dayes with great gladnesse: and the
Leuites and the Priests praised the Lord day by day, singing with
lowd instruments vnto the Lord.<note> Heb. found. , Hebr. instruments of strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And
Hezekiah spake comfortably vnto all the Leuites, that taught the
good knowledge of the Lord: and they did eate throughout the feast,
seuen dayes, offering peace-offerings, and making confession to the
Lord God of their fathers.<note> Hebr. to the heart of all &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the
whole assembly tooke counsel to keepe other seuen dayes: and they
kept other seuen dayes with gladnesse.</ab>
<ab n="24">For
Hezekiah king of Iudah did giue to the Congregation, a thousand
bullockes, and seuen thousand sheep: and the Princes gaue to the
Congregation a thousand bullocks, and ten thousand sheepe, and a
great number of Priests sanctified themselues.<note> Heb. lifted vp or offred.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And all the
Congregation of Iudah, with the Priests and the Leuites, and all
the Congregation that came out of Israel, and the strangers that
came out of the land of Israel, and that dwelt in Iudah,
reioyced.</ab>
<ab n="26">So there
was great ioy in Ierusalem: for since the time of Solomon the sonne
of Dauid King of Israel, there was not the like in
Ierusalem.</ab>

<fw>Idolatry destroyed.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ Then
the Priests the Leuites arose, and blessed the people: and their
voice was heard, and their prayer came vp to his holy dwelling
place, euen vnto heauen.<note> Hebr. the habitation of his holinesse.</note></ab>



</div>