<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Solomons buildings. 7 The Gentiles
which were left, Solomon made tributaries, but the Israelites,
rulers. 11 Pharaohs daughter remoueth to her house. 12 Solomons
yeerely solemne sacrifices. 14 Hee appointeth the Priests and
Leuites to their places. 17 The Nauie fetcheth gold from
Ophir.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came
to passe (at the end of twentie yeeres, wherein Solomon had built
the house of the Lord, &amp; his own house)<note> 1.King.9. 10,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">That the
cities which Huram had restored to Solomon, Solomon built them, and
caused the children of Israel to dwell there.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Solomon
went to Hamath Zobah, and preuailed against it.</ab>
<ab n="4">And he built
Tadmor in the wildernesse, and all the store-cities, which he built
in Hamath.</ab>
<ab n="5">Also he built
Beth-horon the vpper, and Beth-horon the nether, fensed cities with
walles, gates and barres:</ab>
<ab n="6">And Baalath,
and all the store-cities that Solomon had, and all the
charet-cities, and the cities of the horsemen, and all that Solomon
desired to build in Ierusalem, and in Lebanon, and throughout all
the land of his dominion.<note> Hebr. all the desire of Solomon, which he desired to build.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons offrings: His
wisedome.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ As for
all the people that were left of the Hittites, and the Amorites,
and the Perizzites, and the Hiuites, and the Iebusites, which were
not of Israel:</ab>
<ab n="8">But of their
children, who were left after them in the land, whom the children
of Israel consumed not; them did Solomon make to pay tribute,
vntill this day.</ab>
<ab n="9">But of the
children of Israel did Solomon make no seruants for his worke: but
they were men of warre, and chiefe of his captains, and captains of
his charets and horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="10">And these
were the chiefe of king Solomons officers, euen two hundred and
fifty, that bare rule ouer the people.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
Solomon brought vp the daughter of Pharaoh out of the citie of
Dauid, vnto the house that he had built for her: for hee said, My
wife shall not dwell in the house of Dauid king of Israel, because
the places are holy, whereunto the Arke of the Lord hath
come.<note> 1.King. 3.1. &amp; 7.8. , Heb. holinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then
Solomon offered burnt offerings vnto the Lord on the Altar of the
Lord, which he had built before the porch:</ab>
<ab n="13">Euen after a
certaine rate euery day, offering according to the commandement of
Moses, on the Sabbaths, and on the new Moones, and on the solemne
Feasts three times in the yeere, euen in the feast of Unleauened
bread, and in the feast of Weekes, and in the feast of
Tabernacles.<note> Exod. 29. 23. , Exod. 23. 14. deut. 16.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
he appointed, according to the order of Dauid his father, the
courses of the Priests to their seruice, and the Leuites to their
charges, to praise and minister before the Priests, as the duety of
euery day required: the porters also by their courses, at euery
gate: for so had Dauid the man of God commanded.<note> 1.Chron. 24.1. , 1.Chron. 9.17. , Heb. so was the commandement of Dauid the man of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And they
departed not from the commandement of the King vnto the Priests and
Leuites, concerning any matter, or concerning the
treasures.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now all the
worke of Solomon was prepared vnto the day of the foundation of the
house of the Lord, and vntill it was finished: so the house of God
was perfected.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Then
went Solomon to Ezion Geber, and to Eloth, at the sea side in the
land of Edom.<note> Or, Elath, deut.2.8.</note></ab>

<fw>Solomons offrings: His
wisedome.</fw>
<ab n="18">And Huram
sent him by the hands of his seruants, shippes, and seruants that
had knowledge of the sea; and they went with the seruants of
Solomon to Ophir, and tooke thence foure hundred and fiftie talents
of golde, and brought them to king Solomon.</ab>



</div>