<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-29-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah his good reigne. 3 He
restoreth Religion. 5 He exhorteth the Leuites. 12 They sanctifie
themselues, and cleanse the house of God. 20 Hezekiah offereth
solemne sacrifices, wherein the Leuites were more forward then the
Priests.</head>

<ab n="1">Hezekiah
began to reigne when hee was fiue and twentie yeeres old, and he
reigned nine and twentie yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name
was Abiiah the daughter of Zechariah.<note> 2.King. 18.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee did
that which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all
that Dauid his father had done.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ He,
in the first yere of his reigne, in the first moneth, opened the
doores of the house of the Lord, and repaired them.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee
brought in the Priests, and the Leuites, and gathered them together
into the East street,</ab>
<ab n="5">And said
vnto them, Heare me, ye Leuites, sanctifie now your selues, and
sanctifie the house of the Lord God of your fathers, and cary
foorth the filthinesse out of the holy place.</ab>
<ab n="6">For our
fathers haue trespassed, and done that which was euill in the eyes
of the Lord our God, and haue forsaken him, and haue turned away
their faces from the habitation of the Lord, and turned their
backs.<note> Hebr. giuen the necke.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Also they
haue shut vp the doores of the Porch, and put out the lampes, and
haue not burnt incense, nor offered burnt offerings in the holy
place, vnto the God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">Wherfore the
wrath of the Lord was vpon Iudah and Ierusalem, and he hath
deliuered them to trouble, to astonishment, and to hissing, as yee
see with your eyes.<note> Hebr. commotion.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For loe, our
fathers haue fallen by the sword, and our sonnes and our daughters,
and our wiues, are in captiuitie for this.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now it is
in mine heart to make a couenant with the Lord God of Israel, that
his fierce wrath may turne away from vs.</ab>

<fw>The clensing of the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="11">My sonnes,
bee not now negligent: for the Lord hath chosen you to stand before
him, to serue him, and that you should minister vnto him, and burne
incense.<note> Or, be not now deceiued. , Num.8.14 and 18.2,6. , Or, offer sacrifice.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then
the Leuites arose, Mahath the sonne of Amashai, and Ioel the sonne
of Azariah, of the sonnes of the Kohathites: and of the sonnes of
Merari, Kish the sonne of Abdi, and Azariah the sonne of Iahalelel:
and of the Gershonites Ioah, the sonne of Zimmah, and Eden the
sonne of Ioah:</ab>
<ab n="13">And of the
sonnes of Elizaphan, Shimri, and Iehiel: and of the sonnes of
Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah:</ab>
<ab n="14">And of the
sonnes of Heman, Iehiel, and Shimei: and of the sonnes of Ieduthun,
Shemaiah and Uzziel.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they
gathered their brethren, and sanctified themselues, and came
according to the commandement of the king, by the words of the
Lord, to cleanse the house of the Lord.<note> Or, in the busines of the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the
priests went into the inner part of the house of the Lord, to
cleanse it, and brought out all the vncleannes that they found in
the temple of the Lord, into the court of the house of the Lord.
And the Leuites tooke it, to carie it out abroad into the brooke
Kidron.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now they
began on the first day of the first moneth to sanctifie, and on the
eight day of the moneth, came they to the porch of the Lord. So
they sanctified the house of the Lord in eight dayes, and in the
sixteenth day of the first moneth, they made an end.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then they
went in to Hezekiah the king, and said, We haue cleansed all the
house of the Lord, and the altar of burnt offering, with all the
vessels thereof, and the shew-bread table, with all the vessels
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="19">Moreouer
all the vessels which king Ahaz in his reigne did cast away in his
transgression, haue we prepared and sanctified, and behold, they
are before the altar of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Then
Hezekiah the king rose earely, and gathered the rulers of the
citie, and went vp to the house of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>The clensing of the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="21">And they
brought seuen bullocks and seuen rammes, and seuen lambes, and
seuen hee goats for a sinne offring for the kingdome, and for the
Sanctuarie, and for Iudah: and he commaunded the priests the sonnes
of Aaron to offer them on the Altar of the Lord.<note> Leuit.4. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">So they
killed the bullockes, and the priestes receiued the blood, and
sprinkled it on the altar: like wise when they had killed the rams,
they sprinkled the blood vpon the altar: they killed also the
lambes, and they sprinkled the blood vpon the altar.<note> Leuit. 8. 14,15. heb. 9.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And they
brought foorth the hee goats for the sinne offering, before the
king and the congregation, and laide their hands vpon
them:<note> Heb. neere. , Leuit.4. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the
priests killed them, and they made reconciliation with their blood
vpon the altar, to make an atonement for all Israel: for the king
commanded that the burnt offring and the sin offering should be
made for all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="25">And hee set
the Leuites in the house of the Lord with cymbals, with psalteries,
and with harpes, according to the commandement of Dauid, and of Gad
the kings Seer, and Nathan the prophet: for so was the commandement
of the Lord by his prophets.<note> 1.Chro.16 4. and 25.6. , Heb. by the hand of the Lord. , Heb. by the hand of.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And the
Leuites stood with the instruments of Dauid, and the priestes with
the trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="27">And
Hezekiah commaunded to offer the burnt offering vpon the altar: and
when the burnt offering began, the song of the Lord began also with
the trumpets, and with the instruments ordeined by Dauid king of
Israel.<note> Heb. in the time. , Heb. hands of instruments.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And all the
congregation worshipped, and the singers sang, and the trumpetters
sounded: and all this continued vntill the burnt offering was
finished.<note> Heb. song.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And when
they had made an end of offering, the king and all that were
present with him, bowed themselues and worshipped.<note> Heb. found</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Moreouer
Hezekiah the king and the Princes, commanded the Leuites to sing
praise vnto the Lord, with the words of Dauid, and of Asaph the
Seer: and they sang praises with gladnes, and they bowed their
heads and worshipped.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then
Hezekiah answered and said, Now ye haue consecrated your selues
vnto the Lord: come neere and bring sacrifices, and
thanke-offerings into the house of the Lord. And the congregation
brought in sacrifices, and thank-offrings, and as many as were of a
free heart, burnt offerings.<note> Or, filled your hand.</note></ab>

<fw>The Passeouer is proclaimed.</fw>
<ab n="32">And the
number of the burnt offerings which the congregation brought, was
threescore and ten bullockes, an hundred rammes, and two hundred
lambs: all these were for a burnt offring to the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the
consecrated things were, sixe hundred oxen, and three thousand
sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="34">But the
Priests were too few, so that they could not flay all the burnt
offerings: wherefore their brethren the Leuites did helpe them,
till the worke was ended, and vntill the other Priestes had
sanctified themselues: for the Leuites were more vpright in heart,
to sanctifie themselues, then the Priests.<note> Heb. strengthened them</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And also
the burnt offerings were in abundance, with the fat of the peace
offerings, &amp; the drinke offrings, for euery burnt offering. So
the seruice of the house of the Lord was set in order.</ab>
<ab n="36">And
Hezekiah reioyced, and all the people, that God had prepared the
people: for the thing was done suddenly.</ab>



</div>