<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Asa with Iudah and many of Israel,
moued by the prophesie of Azariah the sonne of Oded, make a solemne
couenant with God. 16 He putteth downe Maachah his mother, for her
idolatry. 18 He bringeth dedicate things into the house of God, and
enioyeth a long peace.</head>

<ab n="1">And the
Spirit of God came vpon Azariah the sonne of Oded.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he went
out to meet Asa, and said vnto him, Heare ye me, Asa, and all
Iudah, and Beniamin, The Lord is with you, while yee be with him:
and if yee seeke him, he will be found of you: but if ye forsake
him, he will forsake you.<note> Heb. before Asa.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now for a
long season Israel hath bene without the true God, and without a
teaching priest, and without law.</ab>
<ab n="4">But when
they in their trouble did turne vnto the Lord God of Israel, and
sought him, hee was found of them.</ab>
<ab n="5">And in those
times there was no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came
in, but great vexations were vpon all the inhabitants of the
countreys.</ab>
<ab n="6">And nation
was destroyed of nation, and citie of citie: for God did vexe them
with all aduersitie.<note> Hebr. beaten in pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Be ye strong
therefore, and let not your hands bee weake: for your worke shall
be rewarded.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when Asa
heard these words, and the prophesie of Oded the prophet, he tooke
courage, and put away the abominable idoles out of all the lande of
Iudah and Beniamin, and out of the cities which hee had taken from
mount Ephraim, and renewed the Altar of the Lord, that was before
the porch of the Lord.<note> Heb. abominations.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels couenant with God.</fw>
<ab n="9">And he
gathered all Iudah and Beniamin, and the strangers with them out of
Ephraim and Manasseh, and out of Simeon: (for they fell to him out
of Israel in abundance when they saw that the Lord his God was with
him.)</ab>
<ab n="10">So they
gathered themselues together at Ierusalem, in the third moneth, in
the fifteenth yeere of the reigne of Asa.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they
offered vnto the Lord the same time, of the spoile which they had
brought, seuen hundred oxen, and seuen thousand sheepe.<note> Heb. in that day.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they
entred into a couenant to seeke the Lord God of their fathers, with
all their heart and with all their soule:</ab>
<ab n="13">That
whosoeuer would not seeke the Lord God of Israel, should be put to
death, whether small or great, whether man or woman.<note> Deut.13.9</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And they
sware vnto the Lord with a loud voice, and with shouting, and with
trumpets, and with cornets.</ab>
<ab n="15">And all
Iudah reioyced at the oath: for they had sworne with all their
heart, &amp; sought him with their whole desire, and he was found
of them: and the Lord gaue them rest round about.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
also concerning Maachah the mother of Asa the king, he remooued her
from beeing Queene, because she had made an idole in a groue: and
Asa cut downe her idole, and stamped it, and burnt it at the brooke
Kidron.<note> 1.King. 15.13. , Heb. horror</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But the
high places were not taken away out of Israel: neuerthelesse the
heart of Asa was perfect all his dayes.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And
he brought into the house of God the things that his father had
dedicated, and that he himselfe had dedicated, siluer, and gold,
and vessels.</ab>
<ab n="19">And there
was no more warre vnto the fiue and thirtieth yeere of the reigne
of Asa.</ab>



</div>