<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The Altar of brasse. 2 The molten
Sea vpon twelue oxen. 6 The ten lauers, canstlesticks, and tables.
9 The Courts &amp; the instruments of brasse. 19 The instruments of
gold.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer he
made an Altar of brasse, twentie cubites the length thereof, and
twentie cubites the breadth thereof, and ten cubites the height
therof.</ab>
<ab n="2">¶ Also
he made a molten Sea of ten cubites, from brim to brim, round in
compasse, and fiue cubites the height thereof, and a line of
thirtie cubites did compasse it round about.<note> 1.King.7. 23. &amp;c. , Hebr. from his brim, to his brim.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And vnder it
was the similitude of oxen, which did compasse it round about:
tenne in a cubite compassing the Sea round about. Two rowes of oxen
were cast, when it was cast.<note> 1.King. 7. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">It stood vpon
twelue oxen: three looking toward the North, and three looking
toward the West, and three looking toward the South, and three
looking toward the East: and the Sea was set aboue vpon them, and
all their hinder parts were inward.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the
thicknes of it was an hand breadth, &amp; the brim of it like the
worke of the brim of a cup, with flowers of Lillies: and it
receiued and held three thousand baths.<note> Or, like a Lillie flower.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ He
made also ten Lauers, and put fiue on the right hand, and fiue on
the left, to wash in them: such things as they offered for the
burnt offring, they washed in them, but the Sea was for the Priests
to wash in.<note> Hebr. the worke of burnt offering.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And hee made
ten candlesticks of gold according to their forme, and set them in
the Temple, fiue on the right hand, and fiue on the left.</ab>
<ab n="8">He made also
ten tables, and placed them in the Temple, fiue on the right side,
and fiue on the left: and hee made an hundred basens of
gold.<note> Or, bowles.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶
Furthermore, hee made the court of the Priests, and the great
court, and doores for the court, and ouerlayd the doores of them
with brasse.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he set
the Sea on the rightside of the East end, ouer against the
South.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Huram
made the pots, and the shouels, and the basens, and Huram finished
the worke that he was to make for King Solomon for the house of
God:<note> Or, bowles. , Hebr. finished to make.</note></ab>

<fw>Diuers vessels for the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="12">To wit, the
two pillars, and the pommels, and the chapiters, which were on the
top of the two pillars, and the two wreathes to couer the two
pommels of the chapiters, which were on the top of the
pillars:</ab>
<ab n="13">And foure
hundred Pomegranats on the two wreathes: two rowes of Pomegranats
on each wreath, to couer the two pommels of the chapiters, which
were vpon the pillars.<note> Hebr. vpon the face.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">He made also
bases; and lauers made he vpon the bases.<note> Or, caldrons.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">One Sea,
&amp; twelue oxen vnder it.</ab>
<ab n="16">The pots
also, and the shouels, and the fleshhookes, and all their
instruments, did Huram his father make to King Solomon for the
house of the Lord, of bright brasse.<note> Heb. made bright, or scoured.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">In the
plaine of Iordan did the King cast them, in the clay-ground,
betweene Succoth and Zeredathah.<note> Heb. thicknesses of the ground.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Thus Solomon
made all these vessels in great abundance: for the weight of the
brasse could not be found out.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And
Solomon made all the vessels, that were for the house of God, the
golden Altar also, and the tables whereon the Shew-bread was
set.</ab>
<ab n="20">Moreouer the
candlesticks with their lampes, that they should burne after the
maner, before the Oracle, of pure gold:</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs made he of golde, and that
perfect gold.<note> Hebr. perfections of gold.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And the
snuffers, and the basens, and the spoones, and the censers, of pure
gold. And the entry of the house, the inner doores thereof for the
most Holy place, and the doores of the house of the Temple, were of
gold.<note> Or, bowles.</note></ab>



</div>