<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Amaziah beginneth to reigne well.
3 Hee executeth iustice on the traitours. 5 Hauing hired an armie
of Israelites against the Edomites, at the word of a Prophet, he
loseth the hundred talents, and dismisseth them. 11 He ouerthroweth
the Edomites. 10. 13 The Israelites discontented with their
dismission, spoile as they returne home. 14 Amaziah proud of his
victory, serueth the gods of Edom, and despiseth the admonitions of
the Prophet. 17 Hee prouoketh Ioash to his ouerthrow. 25 His
reigne. 27 Hee is slaine by conspiracie.</head>

<ab n="1">Amaziah was
twentie and fiue yeeres olde when hee began to reigne, and hee
reigned twentie and nine yeeres in Ierusalem, and his mothers name
was Iehoadan of Ierusalem.<note> 2.King. 14.1,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee did
that which was right in the sight of the Lord, but not with a
perfite heart.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Now
it came to passe when the kingdome was established to him, that he
slew his seruants, that had killed the king his father.<note> Heb. confirmed vpon him.</note></ab>

<fw>Amaziah king.</fw>
<ab n="4">But hee
slewe not their children, but did as it is written in the Law in
the booke of Moses, where the Lord commanded, saying, The fathers
shall not die for the children, neither shall the children die for
the fathers; but euery man shall die for his owne
sinne.<note> Deut. 24. 16. 2 king. 14.6. iere. 31.30. ezek. 18.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶
Moreouer, Amaziah gathered Iudah together, and made them Captaines
ouer thousands, and captaines ouer hundreds, according to the
houses of their fathers, throughout all Iudah and Beniamin: And he
numbred them from twentie yeeres olde and aboue, and found them
three hundred thousand choice men, able to goe foorth to warre,
that could handle speare and shield.</ab>
<ab n="6">Hee hired
also an hundred thousand mightie men of valour, out of Israel, for
an hundred talents of siluer.</ab>
<ab n="7">But there
came a man of God to him, saying, O king, let not the armie of
Israel goe with thee: for the Lord is not with Israel, to wit, with
all the children of Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="8">But if thou
wilt goe, doe it, bee strong for the battell: God shall make thee
fall before the enemy: for God hath power to helpe, and to cast
downe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Amaziah
said to the man of God, But what shall wee doe for the hundred
talents which I haue giuen to the armie of Israel? And the man of
God answered, The Lord is able to giue thee much more then
this.<note> Heb. band.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then
Amaziah separated them, to wit, the armie that was come to him out
of Ephraim, to goe home againe. Wherfore their anger was greatly
kindled against Iudah, and they returned home in great
anger.<note> Heb. to their place. , Heb. in heat of anger.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
Amaziah strengthened himselfe, and ledde foorth his people, and
went to the valley of salt, and smote of the children of Seir, ten
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="12">And other
ten thousand left aliue, did the children of Iudah cary away
captiue, and brought them vnto the top of the rocke, and cast them
downe from the top of the rocke, that they all were broken in
pieces.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ But
the souldiers of the army which Amaziah sent backe, that they
should not goe with him to battell, fell vpon the cities of Iudah,
from Samaria euen vnto Beth-horon, and smote three thousand of
them, and took much spoile.<note> Heb. the sonnes of the band.</note></ab>

<fw>Amaziah taken.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ Now
it came to passe, after that Amaziah was come from the slaughter of
the Edomites, that hee brought the gods of the children of Seir,
and set them vp to be his gods, and bowed down himselfe before
them, and burned incense vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wherfore
the anger of the Lord was kindled against Amaziah, and hee sent
vnto him a Prophet, which said vnto him, Why hast thou sought after
the gods of the people, which could not deliuer their owne people
out of thine hand?</ab>
<ab n="16">And it came
to passe as hee talked with him, that the king said vnto him, Art
thou made of the Kings counsell? forbeare; why shouldest thou be
smitten? Then the Prophet forbare, and said, I know that God hath
determined to destroy thee, because thou hast done this, and hast
not hearkened vnto my counsell.<note> Heb. counselled.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Then
Amaziah king of Iudah tooke aduice, and sent to Ioash the sonne of
Iehoahaz the sonne of Iehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let vs
see one another in the face.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Ioash
king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Iudah, saying, The thistle
that was in Lebanon, sent to the Cedar that was in Lebanon, saying,
Giue thy daughter to my sonne to wife: and there passed by a wild
beast that was in Lebanon, and trode downe the thistle.<note> 2.King.14. 8,9. , Or, furre bush, or thorne. , Hebr. a beast of the field.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Thou
sayest, Loe, thou hast smitten the Edomites, and thine heart
lifteth thee vp to boast. Abide now at home, why shouldest thou
meddle to thine hurt, that thou shouldest fall, euen thou, and
Iudah with thee?</ab>
<ab n="20">But Amaziah
would not heare: for it came of God, that he might deliuer them
into the hand of their enemies, because they sought after the gods
of Edom.</ab>
<ab n="21">So Ioash
the King of Israel went vp, and they saw one another in the face,
both hee and Amaziah King of Iudah at Beth-shemesh, which belongeth
to Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Iudah
was put to the worse before Israel, and they fled euery man to his
tent.<note> Hebr. smitten.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Ioash
the king of Israel tooke Amaziah king of Iudah the son of Ioash,
the son of Ioahaz, at Bethshemesh, and brought him to Ierusalem,
and brake downe the wall of Ierusalem, from the gate of Ephraim to
the corner gate, foure hundred cubits.<note> Hebr. the gate of it that looketh.</note></ab>

<fw>He is slaine.</fw>
<ab n="24">And hee
tooke all the gold and the siluer, and all the vessels that were
found in the house of God with Obed-Edom, and the treasures of the
kings house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
Amaziah the sonne of Ioash King of Iudah liued after the death of
Ioash sonne of Iehoahaz king of Israel, fifteene yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="26">Now the
rest of the acts of Amaziah, first and last, behold, are they not
written in the booke of the Kings of Iudah and Israel?</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Now
after the time that Amaziah did turne away from following the Lord,
they made a conspiracie against him in Ierusalem, and he fled to
Lachish: but they sent to Lachish after him, and slew him
there.<note> Heb. from after. , Hebr. conspired a conspiracie.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And they
brought him vpon horses, and buried him with his fathers in the
citie of Iudah.<note> That is, the citie of Dauid, as it is 2.king.14. 20.</note></ab>



</div>