<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Rehoboam raising an armie to
subdue Israel, is forbidden by Shemaiah. 5 He strengtheneth his
kingdome with forts and prouision. 13 The Priests and Leuites, and
such as feared God, forsaken by Ieroboam, strengthen the kingdome
of Iudah. 18 The wiues and children of Rehoboam.</head>

<ab n="1">And when
Rehoboam was come to Ierusalem, he gathered of the house of Iudah
and Beniamin, an hundred and fourescore thousand chosen men, which
were warriers, to fight against Israel, that hee might bring the
kingdome againe to Rehoboam.<note> 1.King.12 21,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But the
worde of the Lord came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Speake vnto
Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Iudah, and to all Israel in
Iudah &amp; Beniamin, saying,</ab>
<ab n="4">Thus saith
the Lord; Ye shall not goe vp, nor fight against your brethren:
returne euery man to his house, for this thing is done of me. And
they obeyed the words of the Lord, and returned from going against
Ieroboam.</ab>

<fw>Rehoboams wiues:</fw>
<ab n="5">¶ And
Rehoboam dwelt in Ierusalem, and built cities for defence in
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="6">He built
euen Bethlehem, and Etam, and Tekoa,</ab>
<ab n="7">And Bethzur,
and Shoco, and Adullam,</ab>
<ab n="8">And Gath,
and Maresha, and Ziph,</ab>
<ab n="9">And Adoraim,
and Lachish, and Azekah,</ab>
<ab n="10">And Zorah,
and Aialon, and Hebron, which are in Iudah and in Beniamin, fenced
cities.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he
fortified the strong holds, and put captaines in them, and store of
vitaile, and of oyle and wine.</ab>
<ab n="12">And in
euery seuerall citie he put shields and speares, and made them
exceeding strong, hauing Iudah and Beniamin on his side.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
the Priests and the Leuites that were in all Israel, resorted to
him out of all their coasts.<note> Hebr. presented themselues to him.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the
Leuites left their suburbs, and their possession, and came to Iudah
and Ierusalem: for Ieroboam and his sonnes had cast them off from
executing the Priests office vnto the Lord.<note> Chap. 13. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And hee
ordeined him priests for the high places, and for the deuils, and
for the calues which he had made.</ab>
<ab n="16">And after
them out of all the tribes of Israel, such as set their hearts to
seeke the Lord God of Israel, came to Ierusalem, to sacrifice vnto
the Lord God of their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="17">So they
strengthened the kingdome of Iudah, and made Rehoboam the sonne of
Solomon strong, three yeeres: for three yeeres they walked in the
way of Dauid and Solomon.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And
Rehoboam tooke him Mahalath the daughter of Ierimoth the sonne of
Dauid to wife, and Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of
Iesse:</ab>
<ab n="19">Which bare
him children, Ieush, and Shamariah, and Zaham.</ab>
<ab n="20">And after
her, hee tooke Maacah the daughter of Absalom, which bare him
Abiiah, and Atthai, and Ziza, and Shelomith.<note> 1.King. 15.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And
Rehoboam loued Maacah the daughter of Absalom, aboue all his wiues
and his concubines: for he tooke eighteene wiues, and threescore
concubines, and begate twentie and eight sonnes, and threescore
daughters.</ab>

<fw>Rehoboams wiues: His sinne,</fw>
<ab n="22">And
Rehoboam made Abiiah the sonne of Maacah the chiefe, to be ruler
among his brethren: for he thought to make him king.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he
dealt wisely, and dispersed of all his children throughout all the
countries of Iudah and Beniamin, vnto euery fenced citie: and he
gaue them vitaile in abundance: and hee desired many
wiues.<note> Hebr. a multitude of wiues.</note></ab>



</div>