<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Asa succeeding destroieth
idolatry. 6 Hauing peace, he strengtheneth his kingdome with forts
and armies. 9 Calling on God, he ouerthroweth Zerah, and spoileth
the Ethiopians.</head>

<ab n="1">So Abiiah
slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the citie of Dauid,
and Asa his sonne reigned in his stead: in his dayes the land was
quiet ten yeeres.<note> 1.King. 15.8. &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Asa his victory.</fw>
<ab n="2">And Asa did
that which was good and right in the eyes of the Lord his
God.</ab>
<ab n="3">For hee
tooke away the altars of the strange gods, and the high places, and
brake downe the images, and cut downe the groues:<note> Hebr. statues.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And
commanded Iudah to seeke the Lord God of their fathers, and to do
the Law, and the Commandement.</ab>
<ab n="5">Also he
tooke away out of all the cities of Iudah, the high places and the
images: and the kingdome was quiet before him.<note> Heb. Sun-images.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
hee built fenced cities in Iudah; for the land had rest, and hee
had no warre in those yeeres; because the Lord had giuen him
rest.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore
hee said vnto Iudah, Let vs build these cities, &amp; make about
them walles, and towers, gates and barres, while the land is yet
before vs: because wee haue sought the Lord our God, wee haue
sought him, and hee hath giuen vs rest on euery side: so they
built, and prospered.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Asa had
an armie of men that bare targets and speares, out of Iudah three
hundred thousand, and out of Beniamin, that bare shields and drew
bowes, two hundred and fourescore thousand: all these were mighty
men of valour.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
there came out against them Zerah the Ethiopian, with an host of a
thousand thousand, and three hundred charets, and came vnto
Mareshah.<note> Chap. 16. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then Asa
went out against him, and they set the battel in aray in the valley
of Zephathah at Mareshah.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Asa
cried vnto the Lord his God, and said, Lord, it is nothing with
thee to helpe, whether with many, or with them that haue no power.
Helpe vs, O Lord our God, for we rest on thee, and in thy Name wee
goe against this multitude: O Lord thou art our God, let not man
preuaile against thee.<note> 11.Sam.14. 6. , Or, mortall man.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So the Lord
smote the Ethiopians before Asa, and before Iudah, and the
Ethiopians fled.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Asa and
the people that were with him, pursued them vnto Gerar: and the
Ethiopians were ouerthrown, that they could not recouer themselues,
for they were destroyed before the Lord, and before his hoste, and
they caried away very much spoile.<note> Hebr. broken.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels couenant with God.</fw>
<ab n="14">And they
smote all the cities round about Gerar, for the feare of the Lord
came vpon them: and they spoiled all the cities, for there was
exceeding much spoile in them.</ab>
<ab n="15">They smote
also the tents of cattell, and caried away sheepe and camels
inabundance, and returned to Ierusalem.</ab>



</div>