<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Chronicles_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Chronicles-Chapter-29-29b-2-Chronicles.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Chronicles-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The solemne offering of Solomon at
Gibeon. 7 Solomons choise of wisdome is blessed by God. 13 Solomons
strength and wealth.</head>

<ab n="1">And Solomon
the sonne of Dauid was strengthned in his kingdome, and the Lord
his God was with him, &amp; magnified him exceedingly.<note> 1.King. 2. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then Solomon
spake vnto all Israel, to the captaines of thousands, and of
hundreds, and to the Iudges, and to euery gouernour in all Israel,
the chiefe of the fathers.</ab>
<ab n="3">So Solomon
and all the Congregation with him, went to the high place that was
at Gibeon, for there was the Tabernacle of the Congregation of God,
which Moses the seruant of the Lord had made in the
wildernesse.<note> 1.King. 3. 4. 1.Chro. 16.39. and 21. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But the Arke
of God had Dauid brought vp from Kiriath-iearim, to the place which
Dauid had prepared for it: for he had pitched a tent for it at
Ierusalem.<note> 2.Sam 6. 2,17.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer the
brasen Altar that Bezaleel the sonne of Uri, the sonne of Hur, had
made, hee put before the Tabernacle of the Lord: and Solomon and
the Congregation sought vnto it.<note> Exod. 38. 1. , Or, was there.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Solomon
went vp thither to the brasen Altar before the Lord, which was at
the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and offered a thousand burnt
offerings vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ In
that night did God appeare vnto Solomon, and saide vnto him; Aske
what I shall giue thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Solomon
saide vnto God, Thou hast shewed great mercy vnto Dauid my father,
and hast made me to reigne in his stead:<note> 1.Chro. 28.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Now, O Lord
God, let thy promise vnto Dauid my father be established: for thou
hast made mee King ouer a people, like the dust of the earth in
multitude.<note> 1.King.3. 9. , Heb. much as the dust of the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Giue mee now
wisedome and knowledge, that I may goe out and come in before this
people. For who can iudge this thy people, that is so
great?<note> 1.King.3. 11,12. num.27. 17.</note></ab>

<fw>Preparation for the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="11">And God said
to Solomon, Because this was in thine heart, and thou hast not
asked riches, wealth, or honour, nor the life of thine enemies,
neither yet hast asked long life; but hast asked wisedome and
knowledge for thy selfe, that thou mayest iudge my people, ouer
whom I haue made thee King:</ab>
<ab n="12">Wisedome and
knowledge is granted vnto thee, and I will giue thee riches, and
wealth, and honour, such as none of the kings haue had, that haue
beene before thee, neither shall there any after thee haue the
like.<note> 1.Chron. 29.25. eccles.2.9. 2.chro. 9.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then
Solomon came from his iourney to the high place that was at Gibeon,
to Ierusalem, from before the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and
reigned ouer Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Solomon
gathered charets and horsemen: and hee had a thousand and foure
hundred charets, and twelue thousand horsemen, which he placed in
the charet-cities, and with the King at Ierusalem.<note> 1.King.10 26. &amp;c. and 4.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the King
made siluer and gold at Ierusalem as plenteous as stones, and Cedar
trees made hee as the Sycomore trees, that are in the vale for
abundance.<note> 1.King. 10 26. 2.chro. 9.27,28. , Heb. gaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Solomon
had horses brought out of Egypt, and linen yarne: the Kings
merchants receiued the linnen yarne at a price.<note> 1.King.10 28. 2.chro. 9.28. , Heb. the going foorth of the horses which was Solomons.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And they
fetcht vp and brought foorth out of Egypt, a charet for sixe
hundred shekels of siluer, and an horse for an hundred and fiftie:
and so brought they out horses for all the kings of the Hittites,
and for the kings of Syria, by their meanes.<note> Heb. by their hand.</note></ab>



</div>