<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>That hee hath approued himselfe a
faithfull minister of Christ, both by his exhortations, 3 and by
integritie of life, 4 and by patient enduring all kinds of
affliction and disgraces for the Gospel. 10 Of which hee speaketh
the more boldly amongst them, because his heart is open to them, 13
And he expecteth the like affection from them againe, 14 Exhorting
to flee the societie and pollutions of Idolaters, as being
themselues Temples of the liuing God.</head>


<fw>True Ministers.</fw>
<ab n="1">Wee then, as
workers together with him, beseech you also, that ye receiue not
the grace of God in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="2">(For he
saith, I haue heard thee in a time accepted, and in the day of
saluation haue I succoured thee: beholde, now is the accepted time,
behold, now is the day of saluation)<note> Esa.49.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Giuing no
offence in any thing, that the ministery be not blamed:</ab>
<ab n="4">But in all
things approuing our selues, as the Ministers of God, in much
patience, in afflictions, in necessities, in
distresses,<note> Gr. commending.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">In stripes,
in imprisonments, in tumults, in labours, in watchings, in
fastings,<note> Or, in tossings to and fro.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">By
purenesse, by knowledge, by long suffering, by kindnesse, by the
holy Ghost, by loue vnfained,</ab>
<ab n="7">By the worde
of trueth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteousnesse, on
the right hand, and on the left,</ab>
<ab n="8">By honour
and dishonour, by euil report and good report, as deceiuers and yet
true:</ab>
<ab n="9">As vnknowen,
&amp; yet wel knowen: as dying, and behold, we liue: as chastened,
and not killed:</ab>
<ab n="10">As
sorrowfull, yet alway reioycing: as poore, yet making many rich: as
hauing nothing, and yet possessing all things.</ab>
<ab n="11">O yee
Corinthians, our mouth is open vnto you, our heart is
enlarged.</ab>
<ab n="12">Yee are not
straitened in vs, but yee are straitned in your owne
bowels.</ab>
<ab n="13">Nowe for a
recompense in the same, (I speake as vnto my children) be ye also
inlarged.</ab>
<ab n="14">Be ye not
vnequally yoked together with vnbeleeuers: for what fellowship hath
righteousnesse with vnrighteousnesse? and what communion hath light
with darknesse?</ab>
<ab n="15">And what
concord hath Christ with Belial? or what part hath he that
beleeueth, with an infidel?</ab>

<fw>Of godly, and worldly sorow.</fw>
<ab n="16">And what
agreement hath the Temple of God with idoles? for ye are the Temple
of the liuing God, as God hath saide, I will dwell in them, and
walke in them, and I will be their God, and they shall be my
people.<note> Leuit.26 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Wherefore
come out from among them, and bee yee separate, saieth the Lord,
and touch not the vncleane thing, and I will receiue
you,<note> Esa.52.11</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And will
bee a Father vnto you, and ye shall bee my sonnes and daughters,
saith the Lord Almightie.<note> Iere.31.1</note></ab>



</div>