<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Lest their false teachers should
charge him with vaineglory, hee sheweth the faith and graces of the
Corinthians, to bee a sufficient commendation of his ministerie. 6
Whereupon entring a comparison betweene the ministers of the Law
&amp; of the Gospel, 12 he proueth that his ministerie is so far
the more excellent, as the Gospel of life and libertie is more
glorious then the law of condemnation.</head>

<ab n="1">Doe wee
begin againe to commend our selues? or need wee, as some others,
Epistles of commendation to you, or letters of commendation from
you?</ab>
<ab n="2">Ye are our
Epistle written in our hearts, knowen and read of all men.</ab>

<fw>Letter and spirit.</fw>
<ab n="3">Forasmuch as
yee are manifestly declared to be the Epistle of Christ ministred
by vs, written not with inke, but with the spirit of the liuing
God, not in tables of stone, but in fleshy tables of the
heart.</ab>
<ab n="4">And such
trust haue wee through Christ to Godward:</ab>
<ab n="5">Not that wee
are sufficient of our selues to thinke any thing as of our selues:
but our sufficiencie is of God:</ab>
<ab n="6">Who also
hath made vs able ministers of the New Testament, not of the
letter, but of the spirit: for the letter killeth, but the spirit
giueth life.<note> Or, quickneth.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But if the
ministration of death written, and ingrauen in stones, was
glorious, so that the children of Israel could not stedfastly
beholde the face of Moses, for the glory of his countenance, which
glorie was to be done away:</ab>
<ab n="8">How shall
not the ministration of the spirit, be rather glorious?</ab>
<ab n="9">For if the
ministration of condemnation bee glory, much more doth the
ministration of righteousnesse exceed in glorie.</ab>
<ab n="10">For euen
that which was made glorious, had no glorie in this respect by
reason of the glorie that excelleth.</ab>
<ab n="11">For if that
which is done away, was glorious, much more that which remaineth is
glorious.</ab>
<ab n="12">Seeing then
that wee haue such hope, we vse great plainnesse of
speech.<note> Or, boldnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And not as
Moses, which put a vaile ouer his face, that the children of Israel
could not stedfastly looke to the end of that which is
abolished;</ab>
<ab n="14">But their
mindes were blinded: for vntill this day remaineth the same vaile
vntaken away, in the reading of the old testament: which vaile is
done away in Christ.</ab>
<ab n="15">But euen
vnto this day, when Moses is read, the vaile is vpon their
heart.</ab>
<ab n="16">Neuerthelesse,
when it shall turne to the Lord, the vaile shall be taken
away.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now the
Lord is that spirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is
libertie.</ab>
<ab n="18">But we all,
with open face beholding as in a glasse the glory of the Lord, are
changed into the same image, from glorie to glorie, euen as by the
spirit of the Lord.<note> Or, of the Lord the spirit.</note></ab>



</div>