<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 He stirreth them vp to a liberall
contribution for the poore Saints at Ierusalem, by the example of
the Macedonians, 7 by commendation of their former forwardnesse, 9
by the example of Christ, 14 and by the spirituall profit that
shall redound to themselues thereby: 16 Commending to them the
integritie and willingnesse of Titus, and those other brethren, who
vpon his request, exhortation and commendation, were purposely come
to them for this businesse.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer,
brethren, wee do you to wit of the grace of God bestowed on the
Churches of Macedonia,</ab>
<ab n="2">How that in
a great trial of affliction, the abundance of their ioy, and their
deepe pouertie, abounded vnto the riches of their
liberalitie.</ab>

<fw>Christs pouertie.</fw>
<ab n="3">For to their
power (I beare record) yea, and beyond their power they were
willing of themselues:</ab>
<ab n="4">Praying vs
with much entreatie, that we would receiue the gift, and take vpon
vs the fellowship of the ministring to the Saints.</ab>
<ab n="5">And this
they did, not as we hoped, but first gaue their owne selues to the
Lord, and vnto vs, by the will of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">In so much
that wee desired Titus, that as he had begun, so hee would also
finish in you, the same grace also.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore
(as ye abound in euery thing, in faith, and vtterance, &amp;
knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your loue to vs) see that
yee abound in this grace also.</ab>
<ab n="8">I speake not
by commandement, but by occasion of the forwardnesse of others, and
to prooue the sinceritie of your loue.</ab>
<ab n="9">For yee know
the grace of our Lord Iesus Christ, that though he was rich, yet
for your sakes he became poore, that yee through his pouertie might
be rich.</ab>
<ab n="10">And herein
I giue my aduice, for this is expedient for you, who haue begun
before, not onely to doe, but also to be forward a yeere
agoe.<note> Gr. willing.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Now
therefore performe the doing of it, that as there was a readinesse
to will, so there may be a performance also out of that which you
haue.</ab>
<ab n="12">For if
there bee first a willing minde, it is accepted according to that a
man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</ab>
<ab n="13">For I meane
not that other men bee eased, and you burthened:</ab>
<ab n="14">But by an
equalitie: that now at this time your abundance may be a supply for
their want, that their abundance also may be a supply for your
want, that there may be equalitie,</ab>
<ab n="15">As it is
written, Hee that had gathered much, had nothing ouer, and hee that
had gathered little, had no lacke.<note> Exod. 16. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But thankes
bee to God which put the same earnest care into the heart of Titus
for you.</ab>
<ab n="17">For indeed
he accepted the exhortation, but being more forward, of his owne
accord he went vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="18">And wee
haue sent with him the brother, whose praise is in the Gospel,
throughout all the Churches.</ab>

<fw>Bountie towards the Saints.</fw>
<ab n="19">And not
that onely, but who was also chosen of the Churches to trauaile
with vs with this grace which is administred by vs to the glorie of
the same Lord, and declaration of your readie minde.<note> Or, gift.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Auoyding
this, that no man should blame vs in this aboundance which is
administred by vs.</ab>
<ab n="21">Prouiding
for honest things, not onely in the sight of the Lord, but in the
sight of men.</ab>
<ab n="22">And we haue
sent with them our brother, whom wee haue often times proued
diligent in many things, but now much more diligent, vpon the great
confidence which I haue in you.<note> Or, hee hath.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Whether any
doe enquire of Titus; he is my partner and fellow helper concerning
you: or our brethren bee enquired of, they are the messengers of
the Churches, and the glorie of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore
shew ye to them, and before the Churches, the proofe of your loue,
&amp; of our boasting on your behalfe.</ab>



</div>