<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Hee proceedeth in exhorting them
to puritie of life, 2 and to beare him like affection as hee doeth
to them. 3 Whereof, lest hee might seeme to doubt, hee declareth
what comfort he tooke in his afflictions, by the report which Titus
gaue of their godly sorrow, which his former Epistle had wrought in
them, 13 and of their louing kindnes and obedience towards Titus,
answerable to his former boastings of them.</head>

<ab n="1">Hauing
therefore these promises (dearely beloued) let vs cleanse our
selues from all filthines of the flesh and spirit, perfecting
holinesse in the feare of God.</ab>
<ab n="2">Receiue vs,
we haue wronged no man, wee haue corrupted no man, wee haue
defrauded no man.</ab>
<ab n="3">I speake not
this to condemne you: for I haue said before, that you are in our
hearts to die and liue with you.</ab>
<ab n="4">Great is my
boldnesse of speach toward you, great is my glorying of you, I am
filled with comfort, I am exceeding ioyfull in all our
tribulation.</ab>
<ab n="5">For when wee
were come into Macedonia, our flesh had no rest, but we were
troubled on euery side; without were fightings, within were
feares.</ab>
<ab n="6">Neuerthelesse,
God that comforteth those that are cast downe, comforted vs by the
comming of Titus.</ab>
<ab n="7">And not by
his comming onely, but by the consolation wherewith hee was
comforted in you, when he told vs your earnest desire, your
mourning, your feruent minde toward me, so that I reioyced the
more.</ab>
<ab n="8">For though I
made you sory with a letter, I doe not repent, though I did repent:
For I perceiue that the same Epistle hath made you sory, thogh it
were but for a season.</ab>

<fw>Of godly, and worldly sorow.</fw>
<ab n="9">Now I
reioyce, not that ye were made sorie, but that ye sorrowed to
repentance: for ye were made sorie after a godly maner, that ye
might receiue damage by vs in nothing.<note> Or, according to God.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For godly
sorrow worketh repentance to saluation not to be repented of, but
the sorrow of the world worketh death.</ab>
<ab n="11">For behold
this selfe same thing that yee sorrowed after a godly sort, what
carefulnesse it wrought in you, yea, what clearing of your selues,
yea, what indignation, yea what feare, yea what vehement desire,
yea what zeale, yea what reuenge; In all things yee haue approued
your selues to be cleare in this matter.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore
though I wrote vnto you, I did it not for his cause that had done
the wrong, nor for his cause that suffered wrong, but that our care
for you in the sight of God might appeare vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore
we were comforted in your comfort, yea and exceedingly the more
ioyed wee for the ioy of Titus, because his spirit was refreshed by
you all.</ab>
<ab n="14">For if I
haue boasted any thing to him of you, I am not ashamed; but as we
spake all things to you in trueth, euen so our boasting which I
made before Titus, is found a trueth.</ab>
<ab n="15">And his
inward affection is more aboundant toward you, whilest he
remembreth the obedience of you all, how with feare and trembling
you receiued him.<note> Gr. bowels.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I reioyce
therefore that I haue confidence in you in all things.</ab>



</div>