<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Hee yeeldeth the reason why,
though hee knewe their forwardnesse, yet hee sent Titus and his
brethren before hand. 6 And hee proceedeth in stirring them vp to a
bountifull almes, as being but a kind of sowing of seed, 10 which
shall returne a great increase to them, 13 and occasion a great
sacrifice of thanksgiuings vnto God.</head>

<ab n="1">For as
touching the ministring to the Saints, it is superfluous for mee to
write to you.</ab>
<ab n="2">For I know
the forwardnesse of your mind, for which I boast of you to them of
Macedonia, that Achaia was ready a yeere agoe, and your zeale hath
prouoked very many.</ab>
<ab n="3">Yet haue I
sent the brethren, least our boasting of you should bee in vaine in
this behalfe, that as I saide, yee may be readie.</ab>
<ab n="4">Lest happily
if they of Macedonia come with mee, &amp; find you vnprepared, wee
(that wee say not, you) should bee ashamed in this same confident
boasting.</ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore I
thought it necessary to exhort the brethren, that they would go
before vnto you, and make vp before hand your bountie, whereof yee
had notice before, that the same might bee readie, as a matter of
bountie, not of couetousnesse.<note> Gr. blessing , Or, which hath bene so much spoken of before.</note></ab>

<fw>Bountie towards the Saints.</fw>
<ab n="6">But this I
say, Hee which soweth sparingly, shall reape sparingly: and he
which soweth bountifully, shall reape bountifully.</ab>
<ab n="7">Euerie man
according as he purposeth in his heart, so let him giue; not
grudgingly, or of necessitie: for God loueth a cheerefull
giuer.<note> Pro.11.25 rom.12.8. ecclu.35.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And God is
able to make all grace abound towards you, that ye alwayes hauing
all sufficiencie in all things, may abound to euery good
worke,</ab>
<ab n="9">(As it is
written: Hee hath dispersed abroad: Hee hath giuen to the poore:
his righteousnesse remaineth for euer.<note> Psa.112.9</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Now he that
ministreth seede to the sower, both minister bread for your foode,
and multiply your seede sowen, and encrease the fruites of your
righteousnesse)<note> Esa.55.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Being
enriched in euery thing to al bountifulnes, which causeth through
vs thankesgiuing to God.</ab>
<ab n="12">For the
administration of this seruice, not onely supplieth the want of the
Saints, but is abundant also by many thanksgiuings vnto
God,</ab>
<ab n="13">Whiles by
the experiment of this ministration, they glorifie God for your
professed subiection vnto the Gospel of Christ, and for your
liberall distribution vnto them, and vnto all men:</ab>
<ab n="14">And by
their prayer for you, which long after you for the exceeding grace
of God in you.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thanks be
vnto God for his vnspeakeable gift.</ab>



</div>