<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 That in his assured hope of
immortall glorie, 9 and in expectance of it, and of the generall
iudgement, hee laboureth to keepe a good conscience, 12 not that he
may herein boast of himselfe, 14 but as one that hauing receiued
life from Christ, indeuoureth to liue as a new creature to Christ
onely, 18 and by his ministery of reconciliation to reconcile
others also in Christ to God.</head>

<ab n="1">For we know,
that if our earthly house of this Tabernacle were dissolued, wee
haue a building of God, an house not made with hand, eternall in
the heauens.</ab>
<ab n="2">For in this
we grone earnestly, desiring to be clothed vpō with our house,
which is from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="3">If so be
that being clothed we shal not be found naked.</ab>
<ab n="4">For, we that
are in this tabernacle, doe grone, being burdened, not for that wee
would bee vnclothed, but clothed vpon, that mortalitie might bee
swallowed vp of life.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now he
þe hath wrought vs for the selfe same thing, is
God, who also hath giuen vnto vs the earnest of the spirit.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore we
are alwayes confident, knowing that whilest wee are at home in the
body, wee are absent from the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">(For we
walke by faith, not by sight.)</ab>
<ab n="8">We are
confident, I say, and willing rather to be absent from the body,
and to be present with the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore we
labour, that whether present or absent, we may be accepted of
him.<note> Or, indeuour.</note></ab>

<fw>New creatures.</fw>
<ab n="10">For we must
all appeare before the iudgement seat of Christ, that euery one may
receiue the things done in his body, according to that hee hath
done, whether it be good or bad.</ab>
<ab n="11">Knowing
therefore the terrour of the Lord, we perswade men; but we are made
manifest vnto God, &amp; I trust also, are made manifest in your
consciences.</ab>
<ab n="12">For we
commend not our selues againe vnto you, but giue you occasion to
glory on our behalfe, that you may haue somewhat to answere them,
which glory in appearance, and not in heart.<note> Gr. in the face.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For whether
wee bee besides our selues, it is to God: or whether we bee sober,
it is for your cause.</ab>
<ab n="14">For the
loue of Christ constreineth vs, because wee thus iudge: that if one
died for all, then were all dead:</ab>
<ab n="15">And that he
died for all, that they which liue, should not hencefoorth liue
vnto themselues, but vnto him which died for them, and rose
againe.</ab>
<ab n="16">Wherefore
hencefoorth know we no man, after the flesh: yea, though we haue
knowen Christ after the flesh, yet now hencefoorth knowe wee him no
more.</ab>
<ab n="17">Therfore if
any man be in Christ, hee is a new creature: old things are past
away, behold, al things are become new.<note> Or, let him be. , Esa.43.19 reuel.21.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And all
things are of God, who hath reconciled vs to himselfe by Iesus
Christ, and hath giuen to vs the ministery of
reconciliation,</ab>
<ab n="19">To wit,
that God was in Christ, reconciling the world vnto himselfe, not
imputing their trespasses vnto them, and hath committed vnto vs the
word of reconciliation.<note> Gr. put in vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Now then we
are Ambassadors for Christ, as though God did beseech you by vs; we
pray you in Christs stead, that be ye reconciled to God.</ab>
<ab n="21">For he hath
made him to be sinne for vs, who knewe no sinne, that wee might bee
made the righteousnesse of God in him.</ab>



</div>