<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 He declareth how hee hath vsed all
synceritie and faithfull diligence in preaching the Gospel, 7 and
how the troubles and persecutions which he dayly indured for the
same, did redound to the praise of Gods power, 12 to the benefit of
the Church, 16 and to the Apostles owne eternall
glory.</head>

<ab n="1">Therefore,
seeing we haue this ministery, as we haue receiued mercie wee faint
not:</ab>
<ab n="2">But haue
renounced the hidden things of dishonesty, not walking in
craftines, nor handling the word of God deceitfully, but by
manifestation of the trueth, commending our selues to euery mans
conscience, in the sight of God.<note> Gr. shame.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But if our
Gospel be hid, it is hid to them that are lost:</ab>
<ab n="4">In whom the
God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which beleeue not,
lest the light of the glorious Gospel of Christ, who is the image
of God, should shine vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="5">For we
preach not our selues, but Christ Iesus the Lord, and our selues
your seruants for Iesus sake.</ab>
<ab n="6">For God who
commaunded the light to shine out of darkenes, hath shined in our
hearts, to giue the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in
the face of Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="7">But we haue
this treasure in earthen vessels, that the excellencie of the power
may be of God, and not of vs.</ab>
<ab n="8">Wee are
troubled on euery side, yet not distressed; we are perplexed, but
not in despaire,<note> Or, not altogether without help or meanes.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Persecuted,
but not forsaken; cast downe, but not destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="10">Alwayes
bearing about in the body, the dying of the Lord Iesus, that the
life also of Iesus might bee made manifest in our body.</ab>
<ab n="11">For we
which liue, are always deliuered vnto death for Iesus sake, that
the life also of Iesus might bee made manifest in our mortall
flesh.</ab>
<ab n="12">So then
death worketh in vs, but life in you.</ab>
<ab n="13">We hauing
the same spirit of faith, according as it is written, I beleeued,
and therefore haue I spoken: wee also beleeue, and therefore
speake.<note> Ps.116.10</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Knowing
that hee which raised vp the Lord Iesus, shall raise vp vs also by
Iesus, and shall present vs with you.</ab>

<fw>The inward man.</fw>
<ab n="15">For all
things are for your sakes, that the abundāt grace might,
through the thankesgiuing of many, redound to the glory of
God.</ab>
<ab n="16">For which
cause we faint not, but though our outward man perish, yet the
inward man is renewed day by day.</ab>
<ab n="17">For our
light affliction, which is but for a momēt, worketh for vs a
farre more exceeding and eternall waight of glory,</ab>
<ab n="18">While we
looke not at the things which are seene, but at þ<note/>
things which are not seene: for the things which are seene, are
temporall, but the things which are not seene, are
eternall.</ab>



</div>