<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>3 The Apostle incourageth them
against troubles, by the comforts and deliuerances which God had
giuen him, as in all his afflictions, 8 so particularly in his late
danger in Asia. 12 And calling both his owne conscience, and theirs
to witnesse, of his sincere maner of preaching the immutable trueth
of the Gospel, 15 Hee excuseth his not comming to them, as
proceeding not of lightnesse, but of his lenitie towards
them.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul an
Apostle of Iesus Christ by the will of God, and Timothie our
brother, vnto the Church of God, which is at Corinth, with all the
Saints, which are in all Achaia:</ab>
<ab n="2">Grace bee to
you and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="3">Blessed be
God, euen the Father of our Lord Iesus Christ, the Father of
mercies, and the God of all comfort,</ab>
<ab n="4">Who
comforteth vs in all our tribulation, that we may be able to
comfort them which are in any trouble, by the comfort, wherewith we
our selues are comforted of God.</ab>
<ab n="5">For as the
sufferings of Christ abound in vs, so our consolation also
aboundeth by Christ.</ab>
<ab n="6">And whether
we be afflicted, it is for your consolation and saluation, which is
effectuall in the enduring of the same sufferings, which wee also
suffer: or whether we be comforted, it is for your consolation, and
saluation.<note> Or, is wrought.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And our hope
of you is stedfast, knowing, that as you are partakers of the
sufferings, so shall yee be also of the consolatiou.</ab>

<fw>The profit of afflictions.</fw>
<ab n="8">For we would
not, brethren, haue you ignorant of our trouble which came to vs in
Asia, that we were pressed out of measure, aboue strength, in so
much that we dispaired euen of life.</ab>
<ab n="9">But we had
the sentence of death in our selues, that we should not trust in
our selues, but in God which raiseth the dead.<note> Or, answere.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Who
deliuered vs from so great a death, and doeth deliuer: in whom we
trust that he will yet deliuer vs:</ab>
<ab n="11">You also
helping together by prayer for vs, that for the gift bestowed vpon
vs by the meanes of many persons, thankes may bee giuen by many on
our behalfe.</ab>
<ab n="12">For our
reioycing is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in
simplicitie and godly sinceritie, not with fleshly wisedome, but by
the grace of God, wee haue had our conuersation in the world, and
more aboundantly to youwards.</ab>
<ab n="13">For we
write none other things vnto you, then what you reade or
acknowledge, and I trust you shall acknowledge euen to the
end.</ab>
<ab n="14">As also you
haue acknowledged vs in part, that we are your reioycing, euen as
ye also are ours, in the day of the Lord Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="15">And in this
confidence I was minded to come vnto you before, that you might
haue a second benefit:<note> Or, grace.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And to
passe by you into Macedonia, and to come againe out of Macedonia
vnto you, and of you to bee brought on my way toward Iudea.</ab>
<ab n="17">When I
therefore was thus minded, did I vse lightnesse? or the things that
I purpose, doe I purpose according to the flesh, that with mee
there should be yea yea, and nay nay?</ab>
<ab n="18">But as God
is true, our word toward you, was not yea and nay.<note> Or, preaching.</note></ab>

<fw>Not yea and nay.</fw>
<ab n="19">For the
Sonne of God Iesus Christ, who was preached among you by vs, euen
by me, and Syluanus and Timotheus, was not Yea, and Nay, but in
him, was yea.</ab>
<ab n="20">For all the
promises of God in him are Yea, and in him Amen, vnto the glory of
God by vs.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now hee
which stablisheth vs with you, in Christ, and hath anoynted vs, is
God,</ab>
<ab n="22">Who hath
also sealed vs, and giuen the earnest of the Spirit in our
hearts.</ab>
<ab n="23">Moreouer, I
call God for a record vpō my soule, that to spare you I came
not as yet vnto Corinth.</ab>
<ab n="24">Not for
that we haue dominion ouer your faith, but are helpers of your ioy:
for by faith ye stand.</ab>



</div>