<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>Against the false Apostles, who
disgraced the weaknesse of his person and bodily presence, he
setteth out the spirituall might and authoritie, with which hee is
armed against all aduersary powers, 7 assuring them that at his
comming hee will bee found as mightie in word, as hee is now in
writing beeing absent, 12 And withall taxing them for reaching out
themselues beyond their compasse, and vanting thēselues into
other mens labors.</head>

<ab n="1">Now I Paul
my selfe beseech you, by the meekenes and gentlenesse of Christ,
who in presence am base among you, but being absent, am bold toward
you:<note> Or, in outward appearance.</note></ab>

<fw>Pauls weapons,</fw>
<ab n="2">But I
beseech you, that I may not bee bold when I am present, with that
confidence wherewith I thinke to be bold against some, which thinke
of vs as if wee walked according to the flesh.<note> Or, reckon.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For though
we walke in the flesh, we doe not warre after the flesh:</ab>
<ab n="4">(For the
weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty through God to
the pulling downe of strong holds.)<note> Or, to God.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Casting
down imaginations, and euery high thing that exalteth it selfe
against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captiuitie euery
thought to the obedience of Christ:<note> Or, reasonings.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And hauing
in a readinesse to reuenge all disobedience, when your obedience is
fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="7">Doe ye
looke on things after the outward appearance? if any man trust to
himselfe, that he is Christs, let him of himselfe thinke this
againe, that as he is Christs, euen so are we Christs.</ab>
<ab n="8">For though
I should boast somewhat more of our authority (which the Lord hath
giuen vs for edification, and not for your destruction) I should
not be ashamed:</ab>
<ab n="9">That I may
not seeme as if I would terrifie you by letters.</ab>
<ab n="10">For his
letters (say they) are waighty and powerfull, but his bodily
presence is weake, and his speach contemptible.</ab>
<ab n="11">Let such a
one thinke this: that such as we are in word by letters, when we
are absent, such will we be also in deede when we are
present.</ab>
<ab n="12">For we
dare not make our selues of the number, or compare our selues with
some that commend themselues: but they measuring themselues by
themselues, and comparing themselues amongst themselues, are not
wise.<note> Or, vnderstand it not.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But we
will not boast of things without our measure, but according to the
measure of the rule, which God hath distributed to vs, a measure to
reach euen vnto you.<note> Or, line.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For we
stretch not our selues beyond our measure as though wee reached not
vnto you, for wee are come as farre as to you also, in preaching
the Gospel of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="15">Not
boasting of things without our measure, that is, of other mens
labours, but hauing hope, when your faith is increased, that wee
shall bee enlarged by you, according to our rule
abundantly.<note> Or, magnified in you.</note></ab>

<fw>His godly ielousie.</fw>
<ab n="16">To preach
the Gospel in the regions beyond you, and not to boast in another
mans line of things made ready to our hand.<note> Or, rule.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But he
that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.<note> Iere.9.24. 1.cor. 1.31</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For, not
he that commendeth himselfe is approued, but whom the Lord
commendeth.</ab>



</div>