<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 For commending of his Apostleship,
though he might glory of his wonderfull reuelations, 9 Yet hee
rather chuseth to glory of his infirmities, 11 blaming them for
forcing him to this vaine boasting. 14 Hee promiseth to come to
them againe: but yet altogether in the affection of a father, 10
although hee feareth he shall to his griefe finde many offenders,
and publike disorders there.</head>

<ab n="1">It is not
expedient for me, doubtlesse, to glory, I wil come to visions and
reuelations of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="2">I knewe a
man in Christ aboue foureteene yeeres agoe, whether in the body, I
cannot tell, or whether out of the body, I cannot tell, God
knoweth: such a one, caught vp to the third heauen.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I knew
such a man (whether in the body, or out of the body, I cannot tell,
God knoweth.)</ab>
<ab n="4">How that he
was caught vp into Paradise, and heard vnspeakeable wordes, which
it is not lawfull for a man to vtter.<note> Or, possible.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Of such a
one will I glory, yet of my selfe I will not glory, but in mine
infirmities.</ab>

<fw>Pauls zeale.</fw>
<ab n="6">For though
I would desire to glory, I shall not be a foole: for I will say the
trueth. But now I forbeare, lest any man should thinke of me aboue
that which hee seeth me to bee, or that hee heareth of me:</ab>
<ab n="7">And least I
should bee exalted aboue measure through the abundance of the
reuelations, there was giuen to me a thorne in the flesh, the
messenger of Sathan to buffet me, lest I should be exalted aboue
measure.<note> See Ezek. 18.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For this
thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from
mee.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he said
vnto me, My grace is sufficient for thee: for my strength is made
perfect in weaknes. Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my
infirmities, that the power of Christ may rest vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore
I take pleasure in infirmities, in reproches, in necessities, in
persecutions, in distresses for Christes sake: for when I am weake,
then am I strong.</ab>
<ab n="11">I am
become a foole in glorying, ye haue compelled me. For I ought to
haue beene commended of you: for in nothing am I behinde the very
chiefest Apostles, though I be nothing.</ab>
<ab n="12">Truely the
signes of an Apostle were wrought among you in all patience, in
signes and wonders, and mightie deeds.</ab>
<ab n="13">For what
is it wherein yee were inferior to other Churches, except it bee
that I my selfe was not burthensome to you? forgiue me this
wrong.</ab>
<ab n="14">Behold,
the third time I am readie to come to you, and I will not bee
burthensome to you; for I seeke not yours, but you: for the
children ought not to lay vp for the parents, but the parents for
the children.</ab>
<ab n="15">And I wil
very gladly spend and bee spent for you, though the more abundantly
I loue you, the lesse I bee loued.<note> Gr. your soules.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But be it
so: I did not burthen you: neuerthelesse beeing craftie, I caught
you with guile.</ab>
<ab n="17">Did I make
a gaine of you by any of them, whom I sent vnto you?</ab>
<ab n="18">I desired
Titus, and with him I sent a brother: did Titus make a gaine of
you? Walked wee not in the same spirit? walked wee not in the same
steps?</ab>

<fw>Trie your faith.</fw>
<ab n="19">Againe,
thinke you that we excuse our selues vnto you? wee speake before
God in Christ: but wee doe all things, dearely beloued, for your
edifying.</ab>
<ab n="20">For I
feare lest when I come, I shall not find you such as I would, and
that I shall bee found vnto you such as ye would not, lest there
bee debates, enuyings, wraths, strifes, backebitings, whisperings,
swellings, tumults,</ab>
<ab n="21">And least
when I come againe, my God will humble mee among you, and that I
shall bewaile many which haue sinned alreadie, and haue not
repented of the vncleannesse, and fornication, and lasciuiousnesse
which they haue committed.</ab>



</div>