<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Corinthians_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Corinthians-Chapter-13-13-Galatians.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 He threatneth seueritie, and the
power of his Apostleship against obstinate sinners. 5 And aduising
them to a triall of their faith, 7 and to a reformation of their
sinnes before his comming, 11 He concludeth his Epistle with a
generall exhortation and a prayer.</head>

<ab n="1">This is the
third time I am comming to you: in the mouth of two or three
witnesses shal euery word be established.</ab>
<ab n="2">I told you
before, and foretell you as if I were present the second time, and
being absent, now I write to them which heretofore haue sinned, and
to all other, that if I come againe I will not spare:</ab>
<ab n="3">Since ye
seeke a proofe of Christ, speaking in me, which to you-ward is not
weake, but is mightie in you.</ab>
<ab n="4">For though
hee was crucified through weaknesse, yet he liueth by the power of
God: for wee also are weake in him, but wee shall liue with him by
the power of God toward you.<note> Or, with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Examine
your selues, whether ye be in the faith: proue your owne selues.
Know yee not your owne selues, how that Iesus Christ is in you,
except ye be reprobates?</ab>
<ab n="6">But I trust
that yee shall knowe that we are not reprobates.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now I pray
to God, that ye doe no euill, not that we should appeare approued,
but that ye should doe þe which is honest, though
we be as reprobates.</ab>
<ab n="8">For wee can
doe nothing against the trueth, but for the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="9">For wee are
glad when wee are weake, and ye are strong: and this also we wish,
euen your perfection.</ab>

<fw>Inconstancie.</fw>
<ab n="10">Therefore
I write these things being absent, lest being present I should vse
sharpnesse, according to the power which the Lord hath giuen me to
edification, and not to destruction.</ab>
<ab n="11">Finally,
brethren, farewell: Bee perfect, bee of good comfort, bee of one
minde, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace shalbe with
you.</ab>
<ab n="12">Greet one
another with an holy kisse.</ab>
<ab n="13">All the
Saints salute you.</ab>
<ab n="14">The grace
of the Lord Iesus Christ, and the loue of God, and the communion of
the holy Ghost, be with you all. Amen. The second Epistle to the
Corinthians, was written from Philippos a citie of Macedonia, by
Titus and Lucas.</ab>



</div>