<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-16-16b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-16-16c-Tobit.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Babylon and other places are
threatned with plagues that cannot be auoided: 23 and with
desolation. 40 The seruants of the Lorde must looke for troubles:
51 and not hide their sinnes, 74 but leaue them, and they shall be
deliuered.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe be vnto
thee, Babylon and Asia, woe be vnto thee Egypt and Syria.</ab>
<ab n="2">Gird vp your
selues with clothes of sacke and haire, bewaile your children, and
be sory, for your destruction is at hand.</ab>
<ab n="3">A sword is sent
vpon you, and who may turne it backe?</ab>
<ab n="4">A fire is sent
among you, and who may quench it?</ab>
<ab n="5">Plagues are sent
vnto you, and what is he that may driue them away?</ab>
<ab n="6">May any man
driue away a hungry Lion in the wood? or may any one quench the
fire in stubble, when it hath begun to burne?</ab>
<ab n="7">May one turne
againe the arrow that is shot of a strong archer?</ab>
<ab n="8">The mightie Lord
sendeth the plagues, and who is hee that can driue them
away?</ab>
<ab n="9">A fire shall goe
foorth from his wrath: &amp; who is he that may quench it?</ab>
<ab n="10">He shall cast
lightnings, and who shall not feare? he shall thunder, and who
shall not be afraid?</ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord shall
threaten, and who shall not be vtterly beaten to powder at his
presence?</ab>
<ab n="12">The earth
quaketh and the foundations thereof, the sea ariseth vp with waues
from the deepe, and the waues of it are troubled, and the fishes
thereof also before the Lord, and before the glorie of his
power.</ab>
<ab n="13">For strong is
his right hand that bendeth the bow, his arrowes that hee shooteth
are sharpe, and shall not misse when they begin to bee shot into
the ends of the world.</ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, the
plagues are sent, and shall not returne againe, vntill they come
vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="15">The fire is
kindled, and shall not be put out, till it consume the foundation
of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">Like as an
arrow which is shot of a mightie archer returneth not backward:
euen so the plagues that shall be sent vpon earth, shall not
returne againe.</ab>
<ab n="17">Woe is me, woe
is me, who will deliuer me in those dayes?</ab>
<ab n="18">The beginning
of sorrowes, and great mournings, the beginning of famine, and
great death: the beginning of warres, and the powers shall stand in
feare, the beginning of euils, what shall I doe when these euils
shal come?</ab>
<ab n="19">Behold, famine,
and plague, tribulation and anguish, are sent as scourges for
amendment.</ab>
<ab n="20">But for all
these things they shall not turne from their wickednes, nor be
alway mindfull of the scourges.</ab>
<ab n="21">Behold,
victuals shall be so good cheape vpon earth, that they shal think
themselues to be in good case, and euen then shall euils growe vpon
earth, sword, famine, and great confusion.<note> Or plagues</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For many of
them that dwell vpon earth, shall perish of famine, and the other
that escape the hunger, shall the sword destroy.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the dead
shall be cast out as doung, and there shalbe no man to comfort
them, for the earth shall be wasted, and the cities shall be cast
downe.</ab>
<ab n="24">There shall be
no man left to till the earth, and to sow it.</ab>
<ab n="25">The trees shall
giue fruite, and who shall gather them?</ab>
<ab n="26">The grapes
shall ripe, and who shall treade them? for all places shall be
desolate of men.</ab>
<ab n="27">So that one man
shall desire to see another, and to heare his voyce.</ab>
<ab n="28">For of a citie
there shalbe ten left, and two of the field which shall hide
themselues in the thicke groues, and in the clefts of
rockes.</ab>
<ab n="29">As in an
orchard of oliues, vpon euery tree there are left three or foure
oliues:</ab>
<ab n="30">Or, when as a
vineyard is gathered, there are left some clusters of them that
diligently seek through þe vineyard:</ab>
<ab n="31">Euen so in
those dayes there shalbe three or foure left by them that search
their houses with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the earth
shall be laid waste, and the fields therof shal waxe old, and her
wayes and all her paths shall grow full of thornes, because no man
shal trauaile therethrough.</ab>
<ab n="33">The virgins
shall mourne hauing no bridegromes, þe women shal
mourne hauing no husbands, their daughters shall mourne hauing no
helpers.</ab>
<ab n="34">In the warres
shall their bridegromes bee destroyed, and their husbands shall
perish of famine.</ab>
<ab n="35">Heare now these
things, and vnderstand them, ye seruants of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="36">Behold the word
of the Lord, receiue it, beleeue not the gods of whom the Lord
spake.</ab>
<ab n="37">Behold, the
plagues draw nigh, and are not slacke.</ab>
<ab n="38">As when a woman
with childe in the ninth month bringeth forth her son, within two
or three houres of her birth great paines compasse her wombe, which
paines, when the child commeth forth, they slacke not a
moment,</ab>
<ab n="39">Euen so shall
not the plagues bee slacke to come vpon the earth, and the world
shall mourne, and sorrowes shal come vpon it on euery side.</ab>
<ab n="40">O my people,
Heare my word: make you ready to the battell, and in those euils,
be euen as pilgrimes vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="41">He that selleth
let him be as hee that fleeth away: and he that buyeth, as one that
will loose.</ab>
<ab n="42">He that
occupieth merchandize, as he that had no profit by it: and he that
buildeth, as hee that shall not dwell therein.</ab>
<ab n="43">He that soweth,
as if he should not reape: so also he that planteth the vineyard,
as he that shal not gather the grapes.</ab>
<ab n="44">They that
marry, as they that shall get no children: and they that marrie
not, as the widowers.</ab>
<ab n="45">And therefore
they that labour, labour in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="46">For strangers
shall reape their fruits, and spoile their goods, ouerthrowe their
houses; and take their children captiues, for in captiuity and
famine shall they get children.</ab>
<ab n="47">And they that
occupy their merchandize with robbery, the more they decke their
citties, their houses, their possessions and their owne
persons:</ab>
<ab n="48">The more will I
be angry with them for their sinne, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="49">Like as an
whore enuieth a right honest and vertuous woman:</ab>
<ab n="50">So shall
righteousnesse haue iniquity, when she decketh herselfe, and shall
accuse her, to her face, when he commeth that shall defend him that
diligently searcheth out euery sinne vpon earth.</ab>
<ab n="51">And therfore be
yee not like therunto, nor to the workes thereof.</ab>
<ab n="52">For yet a
little iniquitie shall be taken away out of the earth, and
righteousnesse shall reigne among you.</ab>
<ab n="53">Let not the
sinner say that he hath not sinned: for God shall burne coales of
fire vpon his head, which saith before the Lord God and his glory,
I haue not sinned.</ab>
<ab n="54">Behold, the
Lord knoweth all the workes of men, their imaginations, their
thoughts, and their hearts:<note> Luke 16. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">Which spake but
the word, let the earth be made, and it was made: let the heauen be
made, and it was created.<note> Gene.1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">In his word
were the starres made, and he knoweth the number of
them.<note> Psal.146. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="57">He searcheth
the deepe, and the treasures thereof, he hath measured the Sea, and
what it containeth.</ab>
<ab n="58">He hath shut
the Sea in the midst of the waters, and with his word hath he
hanged the earth vpon the waters.</ab>
<ab n="59">He spreadeth
out the heauens like a vault, vpon the waters hath he founded
it.</ab>
<ab n="60">In the desart
hath hee made springs of water, and pooles vpon the tops of the
mountaines, that the floods might powre downe from the high rockes
to water the earth.</ab>
<ab n="61">He made man,
and put his heart in the midst of the body, and gaue him breath,
life, and vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="62">Yea and the
spirit of Almighty God, which made all things, and searcheth out
all hidden things in the secrets of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="63">Surely he
knoweth your inuentions, and what you thinke in your hearts, euen
them that sinne, and would hide their sinne.</ab>
<ab n="64">Therefore hath
the Lord exactly searched out all your workes, and he will put you
all to shame.</ab>
<ab n="65">And when your
sinnes are brought foorth yee shalbe ashamed before men, and your
owne sinnes shall be your accusers in that day.</ab>
<ab n="66">What will yee
doe? or how will yee hide your sinnes before God and his
Angels?</ab>
<ab n="67">Behold, God
himselfe is the iudge, feare him: leaue off from your sinnes, and
forget your iniquities to medle no more with them for euer, so
shall God lead you forth, and deliuer you from all trouble.</ab>
<ab n="68">For behold, the
burning wrath of a great multitude is kindled ouer you, and they
shall take away certaine of you, and feede you being idle with
things offered vnto idoles.<note> Or, being vnable to resist.</note></ab>
<ab n="69">And they that
consent vnto them shall be had in derision, and in reproch, and
troden vnder foote.</ab>
<ab n="70">For there shall
be in euery place, and in the next cities a great insurrection vpon
those that feare the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="71">They shall be
like mad men, sparing none, but still spoiling and destroying those
that feare the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="72">For they shal
waste and take away their goods, and cast them out of their
houses.</ab>
<ab n="73">Then shall they
be knowen who are my chosen, and they shall be tried, as the gold
in the fire:</ab>
<ab n="74">Heare, O yee my
beloued, saith the Lord: behold, the dayes of trouble are at hand,
but I will deliuer you from the same.</ab>
<ab n="75">Be yee not
afraid, neither doubt, for God is your guide,</ab>
<ab n="76">And the guide
of them who keepe my commaundements, and precepts, saith the Lord
God; Let not your sinnes weigh you downe, and let not your
iniquities lift vp themselues.</ab>
<ab n="77">Woe bee vnto
them that are bound with their sinnes, and couered with their
iniquities: like as a field is couered ouer with bushes, and the
path thereof couered with thornes, that no man may trauell
through.</ab>
<ab n="78">It is left
vndressed, and is cast into the fire, to bee consumed
therewith.<note> Or, shut out.</note></ab>



</div>