<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 God complaineth of his people: 10
Yet Esdras is willed to comfort them. 34 Because they refused, the
Gentiles are called. 43 Esdras seeth the Sonne of God, and those
that are crowned by him.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord, I brought this people out of bondage, and I gaue them my
Commaundements by my seruants the prophets, whom they would not
heare, but despised my counsailes.</ab>
<ab n="2">The mother that
bare them, saith vnto them, Goe your way ye children, for I am a
widow, and forsaken.</ab>
<ab n="3">I brought you vp
with gladnesse, but with sorrow and heauinesse haue I lost you: for
yee haue sinned before the Lord your God, and done that thing that
is euil before him.</ab>
<ab n="4">But what shall I
now doe vnto you? I am a widow and forsaken: goe your way, O my
children, and aske mercy of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">As for mee, O
father, I call vpon thee for a witnesse ouer the mother of these
children, which would not keepe my Couenant,</ab>
<ab n="6">That thou bring
them to confusion, and their mother to a spoile, that there may be
no off spring of them.</ab>
<ab n="7">Let them bee
scattered abroad among the heathen, let their names bee put out of
the earth: for they haue despised my Couenant.<note> Sacrament or oath.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Woe be vnto thee
Assur, thou that hidest the vnrighteous in thee, O thou wicked
people, remember what I did vnto Sodome and Gomorrhe.<note> Gene. 19. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Whose land lieth
in clods of pitch and heapes of ashes: euen so also wil I doe vnto
them that heare me not, saith the Almightie Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thus saith the
Lord vnto Esdras, Tell my people that I will giue them the kingdome
of Hierusalem, which I would haue giuen vnto Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">Their glory also
wil I take vnto mee, and giue these the euerlasting Tabernacles,
which I had prepared for them.</ab>
<ab n="12">They shall haue
the tree of Life for an oyntment of sweet sauour, they shall nether
labour, nor be weary.</ab>
<ab n="13">Goe and yee
shall receiue: pray for few dayes vnto you, that they may be
shortned: the kingdome is already prepared for you: Watch.</ab>
<ab n="14">Take heauen and
earth to witnesse; for I haue broken the euill in pieces, and
created the good; for I liue, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">Mother, embrace
thy children, and bring them vp with gladnesse, make their feet as
fast as a pillar: for I haue chosen thee, saith the
Lord.<note> Or, bring them vp with gladnesse as a done: make their feet fast. For, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And those that
be dead wil I raise vp againe from their places, and bring them out
of the graues: for I haue knowen my Name in Israel.<note> Or, thy name, O Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Feare not thou
mother of the children: for I haue chosen thee, saith the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">For thy helpe I
will send my seruants Esay and Ieremie, after whose counsaile I
haue sanctified and prepared for thee twelue trees, laden with
diuers fruits;</ab>
<ab n="19">And as many
fountaines flowing with milke and hony: and seuen mightie
mountaines, whereupon there grow roses and lillies, whereby I will
fill thy children with ioy.</ab>
<ab n="20">Doe right to the
widow, iudge for the fatherlesse, giue to the poore, defend the
orphane, clothe the naked,</ab>
<ab n="21">Heale the broken
and the weake, laugh not a lame man to scorne, defend the maimed,
and let the blind man come into the sight of my
clearenesse.</ab>
<ab n="22">Keepe the olde
and yong within thy walles.</ab>
<ab n="23">Wheresouer thou
findest the dead, take them and bury them, and I will giue thee the
first place in my resurrection.<note> Tob.17. 18. , Signing bury them.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Abide still, O
my people, and take thy rest, for thy quietnesse shall
come.</ab>
<ab n="25">Nourish thy
children, O thou good nource, stablish their feete.</ab>
<ab n="26">As for the
seruants whom I haue giuen thee, there shall not one of them
perish; for I will require them from among thy number.</ab>
<ab n="27">Be not weary,
for when the day of trouble and heauinesse commeth, others shal
weepe and be sorrowfull, but thou shalt be merry, and haue
abundance.</ab>
<ab n="28">The heathen
shall enuie thee, but they shall be able to doe nothing against
thee, sayth the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">My hands shal
couer thee, so that thy children shall not see hell.</ab>
<ab n="30">Be ioyfull, O
thou mother, with thy children, for I will deliuer thee, sayth the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="31">Remember thy
children that sleep, for I shall bring them out of the sides of the
earth, and shew mercy vnto them: for I am mercifull, sayth the Lord
Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="32">Embrace thy
children vntill I come and shew mercy vnto them: for my welles
runne ouer, and my grace shall not faile.<note> Or, preach.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">I Esdras
receiued a charge of the Lord vpon the mount Oreb, that I should
goe vnto Israel; but when I came vnto them, they set me at nought,
and despised the commandement of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="34">And therefore I
say vnto you, O yee heathen, that heare and vnderstand, Looke for
your shepheard, hee shall giue you euerlasting rest; for he is nigh
at hand, that shall come in the end of the world.</ab>
<ab n="35">Be ready to the
reward of the kingdome, for the euerlasting light shal shine vpon
you for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="36">Flee the shadow
of this world, receiue the ioyfulnesse of your glory: I testifie my
Sauiour openly.</ab>
<ab n="37">O receiue the
gift that is giuen you, and be glad, giuing thankes vnto him that
hath called you to the heauenly kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="38">Arise vp and
stand, behold the number of those that be sealed in the feast of
the Lord:<note> Or, for.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Which are
departed from the shadow of the world, and haue receiued glorious
garments of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="40">Take thy number,
O Sion, and shut vp those of thine that are clothed in white, which
haue fulfilled the Law of the Lord.<note> Lat. conclude.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">The number of
thy children whom thou longedst for, is fulfilled: beseech the
power of the Lord, that thy people which haue been called from the
beginning, may be hallowed.</ab>
<ab n="42">I Esdras saw
vpon the mount Sion a great people, whom I could not number, and
they all praised the Lord with songs.<note> Reu.7.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And in the
middest of them there was a young man of a high stature, taller
then all the rest, and vpon euery one of their heads he set
crownes, and was more exalted, which I marueiled at
greatly.</ab>
<ab n="44">So I asked the
Angel, and said, Sir, what are these?<note> Or, Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Hee answered,
and said vnto me, These be they that haue put off the mortall
clothing, and put on the immortall, and haue confessed the Name of
God: now are they crowned, and receiue palmes.</ab>
<ab n="46">Then sayd I vnto
the Angel, What yong person is it that crowneth them, and giueth
them palmes in their handes?</ab>
<ab n="47">So hee answered,
and said vnto me, It is the sonne of God, whom they haue confessed
in the world. Then began I greatly to commend them, that stood so
stiffely for the Name of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="48">Then the Angel
sayd vnto me, Goe thy way, and tell my people what maner of things,
and how great wonders of the Lord thy God thou hast seene.</ab>



</div>