<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>A voice out of a bush calleth
Esdras, 10 and telleth him that the world waxeth old. 22 He
desireth, because the Law was burnt, to write all againe, 24 and is
bid to get swift writers. 39 Hee and they are filled with
vnderstanding: 45 but hee is charged not to publish all that is
written.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, vpon the third day I sate vnder an oke, and behold, there
came a voyce out of a bush ouer against me, and said, Esdras,
Esdras.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I said, Here
am I Lord, and I stood vp vpon my feet.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then said he
vnto me, In the bush I did manifestly reueale my selfe vnto Moses,
and talked with him, when my people serued in Egypt.<note> Exod.3. 2,8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I sent him,
and led my people out of Egypt, and brought him vp to the mount of
Sinai, where I held him by me, a long season,</ab>
<ab n="5">And told him
many wonderous things, and shewed him the secrets of the times, and
the end, and commanded him, saying,</ab>
<ab n="6">These wordes
shalt thou declare, and these shalt thou hide.</ab>
<ab n="7">And now I say
vnto thee,</ab>
<ab n="8">That thou lay vp
in thy heart the signes that I haue shewed, and the dreames that
thou hast seene, and the interpretations which thou hast
heard:</ab>
<ab n="9">For thou shalt
be taken away from all, and from henceforth thou shalt remaine with
my sonne, and with such as be like thee, vntill the times be
ended.</ab>
<ab n="10">For the world
hath lost his youth, and the times begin to waxe old.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the world
is diuided into twelue parts, and the ten parts of it are gone
already, and halfe of a tenth part.</ab>
<ab n="12">And there
remaineth that which is after the halfe of the tenth part.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now therefore
set thine house in order, and reproue thy people, comfort such of
them as be in trouble, and now renounce corruption.</ab>
<ab n="14">Let go frō
thee mortall thoughts, cast away the burdens of man, put off now
the weake nature,</ab>
<ab n="15">And set aside
the thoughts that are most heauy vnto thee, and haste thee to flie
from these times.</ab>
<ab n="16">For yet greater
euils then those which thou hast seene happen, shall bee done
hereafter.<note> Mat.24.7</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For looke how
much the world shall be weaker through age: so much the more shall
euils increase vpon them that dwell therein.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the trueth
is fled farre away, and leasing is hard at hand: For now hasteth
the vision to come, which thou hast seene.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then answered I
before thee, and said,</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, Lord, I
will go as thou hast commanded me, and reprooue the people which
are present, but they that shall be borne afterward, who shall
admonish them? thus the world is set in darkenes, and they that
dwell therein, are without light.</ab>
<ab n="21">For thy law is
burnt, therefore no man knoweth the things that are done of thee,
or the works that shal begin.</ab>
<ab n="22">But if I haue
found grace before thee, send the holy Ghost into me, and I shall
write all that hath bene done in the world, since the beginning,
which were written in thy Lawe, that men may find thy path, and
that they which will liue in the latter dayes, may liue.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he answered
me, saying, Goe thy way, gather the people together, and say vnto
them, that they seeke thee not for fourtie dayes.</ab>
<ab n="24">But looke thou
prepare thee many boxe trees, and take with thee Sarea, Dabria,
Selemia, Eranus and Asiel, these fiue which are ready to write
swiftly.<note> Or, boxe tables to write on, See ver.44. , Or, Banus.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And come
hither, and I shall light a candle of vnderstanding in thine heart,
which shall not be put out, till the things be performed which thou
shalt beginne to write.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when thou
hast done, some things shalt thou publish, and some things shalt
thou shew secretly to the wise: to morrowe this houre shalt thou
beginne to write.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then went I
foorth as he commanded, and gathered all the people together, and
said,</ab>
<ab n="28">Heare these
words, O Israel.</ab>
<ab n="29">Our fathers at
the beginning were strangers in Egypt, from whence they were
deliuered:<note> Gene. 47.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And receiued
the law of life which they kept not, which ye also haue
transgressed after them.<note> Act.7. 53.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Then was the
land, euen the land of Sion, parted among you by lot, but your
fathers, and yee your selues haue done vnrighteousnesse, and haue
not kept the wayes which the Highest commanded you.</ab>
<ab n="32">And for as much
as he is a righteous iudge, hee tooke from you in time, the thing
that he had giuen you.</ab>
<ab n="33">And now are you
heere, and your brethren amongst you.</ab>
<ab n="34">Therefore if so
be that you will subdue your owne vnderstanding, and reforme your
hearts, yee shall be kept aliue, and after death yee shall obtaine
mercy.</ab>
<ab n="35">For after
death, shall the iudgement come, when we shall liue againe: and
then shall the names of the righteous be manifest, and the workes
of the vngodly shall be declared.</ab>
<ab n="36">Let no man
therefore come vnto me now, nor seeke after me these fourty
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="37">So I tooke the
fiue men as hee commanded me, and we went into the field, and
remained there.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the next
day behold a voyce called mee saying, Esdras, open thy mouth and
drinke that I giue thee to drinke.<note> Ezek.3.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Then opened I
my mouth, and behold, he reached me a full cup, which was full as
it were with water, but the colour of it was like fire.</ab>
<ab n="40">And I tooke it,
and dranke: and when I had drunke of it, my heart vttered
vnderstanding: and wisedome grew in my brest, for my spirit
strengthened my memory.</ab>
<ab n="41">And my mouth
was opened and shut no more.</ab>
<ab n="42">The highest
gaue vnderstanding vnto the fiue men, and they wrote the wonderfull
visions of the night, that were told, which they knew not: And they
sate fourty dayes, and they wrote in the day, and at night they ate
bread.</ab>
<ab n="43">As for me I
spake in the day, and held not my tongue by night:</ab>
<ab n="44">In fourty dayes
they wrote two hundred and foure bookes.<note> Or, 904.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And it came to
passe when the fourty dayes were fulfilled, that the Highest spake,
saying, The first that thou hast written, publish openly, that the
worthy and vnworthy may read it.</ab>
<ab n="46">But keepe the
seuenty last, that thou mayest deliuer them onely to such as be
wise, among the people.</ab>
<ab n="47">For in them is
the spring of vnderstanding, the fountains of wisedome, and the
streame of knowledge.<note> Or, the light of knowledge.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And I did
so.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>