<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Esdras-Chapter-9-9b-2-Esdras.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Esdras is commanded to reproue the
people. 24 God threatneth to cast them off, 35 and to giue their
houses to a people of more grace then they.</head>

<ab n="1">The second booke
of the Prophet Esdras the sonne of Saraias, the sonne of Azarias,
the sonne of Helchias, the sonne of Sadamias, the sonne of Sadoc,
the sonne of Achitob,<note> Ezra 7.1. , Or, Shallum.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The sonne of
Achias, the sonne of Phinees, the sonne of Heli, the sonne of
Amarias, the sonne of Aziei, the sonne of Marimoth, the sonne of
Arna, the sonne of Ozias, the sonne of Borith, the sonne of Abisei,
the sonne of Phinees, the sonne of Eleazar,</ab>
<ab n="3">The sonne of
Aaron, of the Tribe of Leui, which was captiue in the land of the
Medes, in the reigne of Artaxerxes king of the Persians.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the word of
the Lord came vnto me, saying,<note> Isa.58.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Goe thy way, and
shew my people their sinfull deeds, and their children their
wickednes which they haue done against me, that they may tell their
childrens children,</ab>
<ab n="6">Because the
sinnes of their fathers are increased in them: for they haue
forgotten me, &amp; haue offered vnto strange gods.</ab>
<ab n="7">Am not I euen hee
that brought them out of the land of Egypt, from the house of
bondage? but they haue prouoked me vnto wrath, and despised my
counsels.</ab>
<ab n="8">Pull thou off
then the haire of thy head, and cast all euill vpon them, for they
haue not beene obedient vnto my law, but it is a rebellious
people.</ab>
<ab n="9">How long shall I
forbeare them vnto whō I haue done so much good?</ab>
<ab n="10">Many kings haue
I destroyed for their sakes, Pharao with his seruants, and all his
power haue I smitten downe.<note> Exod.14. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">All the nations
haue I destroyed before them, &amp; in the East I haue scattered
the people of two prouinces, euen of Tyrus and Sidon, and haue
slaine all their enemies.<note> Num. 21. 24. iosh.8. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Speake thou
therefore vnto them saying, Thus saith the Lord,</ab>
<ab n="13">I led you
through the Sea, and in the beginning gaue you a large and safe
passage, I gaue you Moyses for a leader, and Aaron for a
priest,<note> Exod.14. 29. , Or, street. , Exo. 3.10. and 4.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I gaue you light
in a pillar of fire, and great wonders haue I done among you, yet
haue you forgotten me, saith the Lord.<note> Exod.13. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thus saith the
Almightie Lord, The quailes were as a token for you, I gaue you
tents for your safegard, neuerthelesse you murmured
there,<note> Exod.16. 13. psal.104 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And triumphed
not in my name for the destruction of your enemies, but euer to
this day doe ye yet murmure.</ab>
<ab n="17">Where are the
benefits that I haue done for you? when you were hungry and
thirstie in the wildernesse, did you not crie vnto me?<note> Num. 14.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Saying, Why hast
thou brought vs into this wildernesse to kill vs? It had bin better
for vs to haue serued the Egyptians, then to die in this
wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then had I pity
vpon your mournings, and gaue you Manna to eat, so ye did eate
Angels bread.<note> Wisd.16. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">When ye were
thirstie, did I not cleaue the rocke, and waters flowed out to your
fill? for the heate I couered you with the leaues of the
trees.<note> Numb. 20 11. wisd. 11 4. , Or, abundantly.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">I diuided
amongst you a fruitfull land, I cast out the Canaanites, the
Pherezites, and the Philistines before you: what shall I yet doe
more for you: saith the Lord?<note> Isa. 5.4. &amp; exod. 15.23</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Thus saith the
Almighty Lord, when you were in the wildernes in the riuer of the
Amorites, being athirst, and blaspheming my Name,<note> Or, at the bitter waters, or waters of Marah.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">I gaue you not
fire for your blasphemies, but cast a tree in the water, and made
the riuer sweet.</ab>
<ab n="24">What shall I doe
vnto thee, O Iacob? thou Iuda wouldest not obey me: I will turne me
to other nations, and vnto those will I giue my Name, that they may
keepe my Statutes.<note> Exo.32.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Seeing yee haue
forsaken mee, I will forsake you also: when yee desire me to be
gracious vnto you, I shall haue no mercy vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="26">Whensoeuer you
shall call vpon me, I will not heare you: for yee haue defiled your
hands with blood, and your feete are swift to commit
manslaughter.<note> Isa.1.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Yee haue not as
it were forsaken me, but your owne selues, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="28">Thus saith the
Almighty Lord, Haue I not prayed you as a father his sonnes, as a
mother her daughters, and a nurse her young babes,</ab>
<ab n="29">That yee would
be my people, and I shoud be your God, that ye would be my
children, and I should be your father?<note> Or, as I am your God</note></ab>
<ab n="30">I gathered you
together, as a henne gathereth her chickens vnder her wings: but
now, what shall I doe vnto you? I will cast you out from my
face.<note> Mat.23. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">When you offer
vnto me, I will turne my face from you: for your solemne feast
dayes, your newe Moone, and your circumcisions haue I
forsaken.<note> Isa.1.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">I sent vnto you
my seruants the Prophets, whom yee haue taken and slaine, and torne
their bodies in pieces, whose blood I will require of your hands,
saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="33">Thus saith the
Almighty Lord, Your house is desolate, I will cast you out, as the
wind doth stubble.</ab>
<ab n="34">And your
children shall not bee fruitful: for they haue despised my
Commandement, and done the thing that is euill before me.</ab>
<ab n="35">Your houses wil
I giue to a people that shall come, which not hauing heard of mee,
yet shall beleeue mee, to whom I haue shewed no signes, yet they
shall doe that I haue commaunded them.</ab>
<ab n="36">They haue seene
no Prophets, yet they shall call their sinnes to remembrance, and
acknowledge them.</ab>
<ab n="37">I take to
witnesse the grace of the people to come, whose little ones reioyce
in gladnesse: and though they haue not seene me with bodily eyes,
yet in spirit they beleeue the thing that I say.</ab>
<ab n="38">And now brother,
behold what glory: and see the people that commeth from the
East.</ab>
<ab n="39">Unto whom I will
giue for leaders, Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, Oseas, Amos, and
Micheas, Ioel, Abdias, and Ionas,</ab>
<ab n="40">Nahum, and
Abacuc, Sophonias, Aggeus, Zacharie, and Malachie, which is called
also an Angel of the Lord.<note> Mala. 3.1.</note></ab>



</div>