<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Hee seeth in his dreame a man
comming out of the sea. 25 The declaration of his dreame. 54 He is
praised, and promised to see more.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after seuen dayes, I dreamed a dreame by night.</ab>
<ab n="2">And loe, there
arose a winde from the sea that it mooued all the waues
thereof.<note> A certaine man as the winde. Iunius.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And I beheld,
and loe, that man waxed strong with the thousands of heauen: and
when he turned his countenance to looke, all the things trembled
that were seene vnder him.<note> Clouds.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And whensoeuer
the voyce went out of his mouth, all they burnt, that heard his
voyce, like as the earth faileth when it feeleth the fire.</ab>
<ab n="5">And after this I
beheld, and loe, there was gathered together a multitude of men out
of number, from the foure windes of the heauen, to subdue the man
that came out of the sea.</ab>
<ab n="6">But I beheld,
and loe, hee had graued himselfe a great mountaine, and flew vp
vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="7">But I would haue
seene the region, or place, whereout the hill was grauen, and I
could not.</ab>
<ab n="8">And after this I
beheld, and loe, all they which were gathered together to subdue
him, were sore afraid, and yet durst fight.</ab>
<ab n="9">And loe, as hee
saw the violence of the multitude that came, hee neither lift vp
his hand, nor held sword, nor any instrument of warre.</ab>
<ab n="10">But onely I saw
that he sent out of his mouth, as it had bene a blast of fire, and
out of his lippes a flaming breath, and out of his tongue he cast
out sparkes and tempests,</ab>
<ab n="11">And they were
all mixt together; the blast of fire, the flaming breath, and the
great tempest, and fel with violence vpon the multitude, which was
prepared to fight, and burnt them vp euery one, so that vpon a
sudden, of an innumerable multitude, nothing was to be perceiued,
but onely dust and smell of smoke: whē I saw this, I was
afraid.</ab>
<ab n="12">Afterward saw I
the same man come downe from the mountaine, and call vnto him an
other peaceable multitude.</ab>
<ab n="13">And there came
much people vnto him, whereof some were glad, some were sory, some
of them were bound, and other some brought of them that were
offred: then was I sicke through great feare, and I awaked and
said,<note> Iunius. Of the things that were offered.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thou hast
shewed thy seruant wonders from the beginning, and hast counted me
worthy that thou shouldest receiue my prayer:</ab>
<ab n="15">Shew mee now
yet the interpretation of this dreame.</ab>
<ab n="16">For as I
conceiue in mine vnderstanding, woe vnto them that shall be left in
those dayes; and much more woe vnto them that are not left
behinde.</ab>
<ab n="17">For they that
were not left, were in heauinesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now vnderstand
I the things that are layde vp in the latter dayes, which shall
happen vnto them, and to those that are left behinde.</ab>
<ab n="19">Therefore are
they come into great perils, and many necessities, like as these
dreames declare.</ab>
<ab n="20">Yet is it
easier for him that is in danger, to come into these things, then
to passe away as a cloud out of the world, and not to see the
things that happen in the last dayes. And he answered vnto me, and
said,<note> Or, this day.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The
interpretation of the vision shal I shew thee, and I wil open vnto
thee, the thing that thou hast required.</ab>
<ab n="22">Wheras thou
hast spoken of them that are left behinde, this is the
interpretation.</ab>
<ab n="23">He that shall
endure the perill in that time, hath kept himselfe: they that be
fallen into danger, are such as haue workes, and faith towards the
Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="24">Know this
therefore, that they which be left behinde, are more blessed then
they that be dead.</ab>
<ab n="25">This is the
meaning of the vision: Whereas thou sawest a man comming vp from
the middest of the Sea:</ab>
<ab n="26">The same is hee
whom God the highest hath kept a great season, which by his owne
selfe shall deliuer his creature: and hee shall order them that are
left behinde.</ab>
<ab n="27">And whereas
thou sawest, that out of his mouth there came as a blast of winde,
and fire, and storme:</ab>
<ab n="28">And that he
helde neither sword, nor any instrument of warre, but that the
rushing in of him destroyed the whole multitude that came to subdue
him, this is the interpretation.</ab>
<ab n="29">Behold, the
dayes come, when the most high wil begin to deliuer them that are
vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="30">And he shall
come to the astonishment of them that dwell on the earth.</ab>
<ab n="31">And one shall
vndertake to fight against another, one city against another, one
place against another, one people against another, and one realme
against another.<note> Mat.24.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And the time
shalbe, when these things shall come to passe, and the signes shall
happen which I shewed thee before, and then shall my sonne be
declared, whom thou sawest as a man ascending.</ab>
<ab n="33">And when all
the people heare his voice, euery man shall in their owne land,
leaue the battaile they haue one against another.</ab>
<ab n="34">And an
innumerable multitude shalbe gathered together, as thou sawest them
willing to come, and to ouercome him by fighting.</ab>
<ab n="35">But hee shall
stand vpon the top of the mount Sion.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Sion shall
come and shall be shewed to all men, being prepared and builded,
like as thou sawest the hill grauen without hands.</ab>
<ab n="37">And this my
sonne shall rebuke the wicked inuentions of those nations, which
for their wicked life are fallen into the tempest,</ab>
<ab n="38">And shall lay
before them their euill thoughts, and the torments wherwith they
shall begin to be tormented, which are like vnto a flame: and hee
shall destroy them without labour, by the law which is like vnto
fire.</ab>
<ab n="39">And whereas
thou sawest that hee gathered another peaceable multitude vnto
him;</ab>
<ab n="40">Those are the
ten tribes, which were caried away prisoners out of their owne
land, in the time of Osea the king, whom Salmanasar the king of
Assyria ledde away captiue, and hee caried them ouer the waters,
and so came they into another land.<note> 2.Kings 17.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">But they tooke
this counsaile amongst themselues, that they would leaue the
multitude of the heathen, and goe foorth into a further countrey,
where neuer mankind dwelt,</ab>
<ab n="42">That they might
there keepe their statutes, which they neuer kept in their owne
land.</ab>
<ab n="43">And they entred
into Euphrates by the narrow passages of the Riuer.</ab>
<ab n="44">For the most
high then shewed signes for them, and held still the flood, till
they were passed ouer.<note> Exod.14. 21. iosh.3. 15, 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">For through
that countrey there was a great way to goe; namely, of a yeere and
a halfe: and the same region is called Arsareth.<note> Or, Ararath.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">Then dwelt they
there vntill the latter time; and now when they shall begin to
come,</ab>
<ab n="47">The highest
shall stay the springs of the streame againe, that they may go
through: therefore sawest thou the multitude with peace.</ab>
<ab n="48">But those that
be left behinde of thy people, are they that are found within my
borders.</ab>
<ab n="49">Now when hee
destroyeth the multitude of the nations that are gathered together,
he shal defend his people that remaine.</ab>
<ab n="50">And then shall
hee shewe them great wonders.</ab>
<ab n="51">Then said I, O
Lord, that bearest rule, shew me this: Wherefore haue I seene the
man comming vp from the midst of the Sea?</ab>
<ab n="52">And he said
vnto me, Like as thou canst neither seeke out, nor know the things
that are in the deepe of the sea: euen so can no man vpon earth see
my sonne, or those that be with him, but in the day time.</ab>
<ab n="53">This is the
interpretation of the dreame which thou sawest, and whereby thou
onely art here lightened.</ab>
<ab n="54">For thou hast
forsaken thine owne way, and applied thy diligence vnto my law, and
sought it.</ab>
<ab n="55">Thy life hast
thou ordered in wisdome, and hast called vnderstanding thy
mother.</ab>
<ab n="56">And therefore
haue I shewed thee the treasures of the Highest: After other three
dayes, I will speake other things vnto thee, and declare vnto thee
mightie and wonderous things.</ab>
<ab n="57">Then went I
forth into the field giuing praise and thanks greatly vnto the most
High, because of his wonders which he did in time,</ab>
<ab n="58">And because hee
gouerneth the same, and such things as fall in their seasons, and
there I sate three dayes.</ab>



</div>