<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>4 The way is narrow. 12 When it was
made narrow. 28 All shall die and rise againe. 33 Christ shall sit
in iudgement. 46 God hath not made Paradise in vaine, 62 &amp; is
merciful.</head>

<ab n="1">And when I had
made an ende of speaking these words, there was sent vnto mee the
Angel which had beene sent vnto mee the nights afore.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said vnto
me, Up Esdras, and heare the wordes that I am come to tell
thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I said,
Speake on, my God. Then said he vnto me, The Sea is set in a wide
place, that it might be deepe and great.</ab>
<ab n="4">But put the case
the entrance were narrow, and like a riuer,</ab>
<ab n="5">Who then could
goe into the Sea to looke vpon it, and to rule it? If hee went not
through the narrow, how could he come into the broad?</ab>
<ab n="6">There is also
another thing. A city is builded, and set vpon a broad field, and
is full of all good things.</ab>
<ab n="7">The entrance
thereof is narrow, and is set in a dangerous place to fall, like as
if there were a fire on the right hand, and on the left a deepe
water.<note> Or, steepe place.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And one only path
between them both, euen betweene the fire and the water, so small
that there could but one man goe there at once.</ab>
<ab n="9">If this city now
were giuen vnto a man for an inheritance, if he neuer shall passe
the danger set before it, how shall he receiue this
inheritance?</ab>
<ab n="10">And I said, It
is so, Lord. Then said he vnto me, Euen so also is Israels
portion:</ab>
<ab n="11">Because for
their sakes I made the world: and when Adam transgressed my
Statutes, then was decreed that now is done.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then were the
entrances of this world made narrow, full of sorrow and trauaile:
they are but few and euill, full of perils, and very
painefull.</ab>
<ab n="13">For the
entrances of the elder world were wide and sure, and brought
immortall fruit.<note> Or, greater</note></ab>
<ab n="14">If then they
that liue, labour not to enter these strait and vaine things, they
can neuer receiue those that are laide vp for them.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now therefore
why disquietest thou thy selfe, seeing thou art but a corruptible
man? and why art thou mooued, whereas thou art but mortall?</ab>
<ab n="16">Why hast thou
not considered in thy minde this thing that is to come, rather then
that which is present?</ab>
<ab n="17">Then answered I,
and sayd, O Lord, that bearest rule, thou hast ordained in thy Law,
that the righteous should inherite these things, but that the
vngodly should perish:<note> Deut.8.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Neuerthelesse,
the righteous shal suffer strait things, and hope for wide: for
they that haue done wickedly, haue suffered the strait things, and
yet shall not see the wide.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he said vnto
me, There is no iudge aboue God, and none that hath vnderstanding
aboue the highest.</ab>
<ab n="20">For there be
many that perish in this life, because they despise the Lawe of God
that is set before them.</ab>
<ab n="21">For God hath
giuen strait commandement to such as came, what they should doe to
liue, euen as they came, and what they should obserue to auoid
punishment.</ab>
<ab n="22">Neuerthelesse
they were not obedient vnto him, but spake against him, and
imagined vaine things:</ab>
<ab n="23">And deceiued
themselues by their wicked deeds, and sayd of the most Hie, that he
is not, and knew not his waies.</ab>
<ab n="24">But his Law haue
they despised, and denied his couenants in his statutes haue they
not beene faithfull, and haue not performed his workes.</ab>
<ab n="25">And therfore
Esdras, for the emptie, are emptie things, and for the ful, are the
full things.</ab>
<ab n="26">Behold, the time
shall come, that these tokens which I haue told thee, shall come to
passe, and the bride shall appeare, and she comming forth shall be
seene, that now is withdrawen from the earth.</ab>
<ab n="27">And whosoeuer is
deliuered from the foresaid euils, shall see my wonders.</ab>
<ab n="28">For my sonne
Iesus shall be reuealed with those that be with him, and they that
remaine shall reioyce within foure hundred yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="29">After these
yeeres shall my sonne Christ die, and all men that haue
life.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the world
shall be turned into the old silence seuen dayes, like as in the
former iudgements: so that no man shall remaine.<note> Or, first beginning.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And after seuen
dayes, the world that yet awaketh not shall be raised vp, and that
shall die, that is corrupt.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the earth
shall restore those that are asleepe in her, and so shall the dust
those that dwell in silence, and the secret places shall deliuer
those soules that were committed vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the most
high shall appeare vpon the seate of iudgement, and miserie shall
passe away, and the long suffering shall haue an end.</ab>
<ab n="34">But iudgement
onely shall remaine, trueth shall stand, and faith shall waxe
strong.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the worke
shall follow, and the reward shall be shewed, and the good deeds
shall be of force, and wicked deeds shall beare no rule.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then said I,
Abraham prayed first for the Sodomites, and Moses for the fathers
that sinned in the wildernesse:<note> Gen.18. 13. , Exod.32. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And Iesus after
him for Israel in the time of Achan,<note> Or, Archer.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And Samuel; and
Dauid for the destruction: and Solomon for them that should come to
the sanctuary.<note> 2.Sam.24. 17. 2.chro. 6.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And Helias for
those that receiued raine, &amp; for the dead that hee might
liue.<note> 1.King.17 21. and 18. 42.45.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">And Ezechias for
the people in the time of Sennacherib: and many for
many.<note> 2.King. 19.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">Euen so now
seeing corruption is growen vp, and wickednesse increased, and the
righteous haue prayed for the vngodly: wherefore shall it not be so
now also?</ab>
<ab n="42">He answered me
and said, This present life is not the end where much glory doth
abide; therefore haue they prayed for the weake.</ab>
<ab n="43">But the day of
doome shall be the end of this time, and the beginning of the
immortality for to come, wherein corruption is past.</ab>
<ab n="44">Intemperancie is
at an end, infidelity is cut off, righteousnesse is growen, and
trueth is sprung vp.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then shall no
man be able to saue him that is destroyed, nor to oppresse him that
hath gotten the victory.</ab>
<ab n="46">I answered then
and said, This is my first and last saying; that it had beene
better not to haue giuen the earth vnto Adam: or else when it was
giuen him, to haue restrained him from sinning.</ab>
<ab n="47">For what profit
is it for men now in this present time to liue in heauinesse, and
after death to looke for punishment?</ab>
<ab n="48">O thou Adam,
what hast thou done? for though it was thou that sinned, thou art
not fallen alone, but we all that come of thee.<note> Rom.5. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">For what profit
is it vnto vs, if there be promised vs an immortall time, wheras we
haue done the works that bring death?</ab>
<ab n="50">And that their
is promised vs an euerlasting hope, whereas our selues being most
wicked are made vaine?</ab>
<ab n="51">And that there
are layd vp for vs dwellings of health and safety, whereas we haue
liued wickedly?</ab>
<ab n="52">And that the
glory of the most high is kept to defend them which haue led a wary
life, whereas we haue walked in the most wicked wayes of
all?<note> Or, a chast life.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">And that there
should be shewed a paradise whose fruite endureth for euer, wherein
is securitie and medicine, sith we shall not enter into
it?<note> Or, fulnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">For we haue
walked in vnpleasant places.</ab>
<ab n="55">And that the
faces of them which haue vsed abstinence, shall shine aboue the
starres, whereas our faces shall bee blacker then
darkenesse?</ab>
<ab n="56">For while we
liued and committed iniquitie, we considered not that we should
begin to suffer for it after death.</ab>
<ab n="57">Then answered he
me and saide, This is the condition of the battell, which man that
is borne vpon the earth shall fight,<note> Or, intent.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">That if he be
ouercome, he shall suffer as thou hast said, but if he get the
victorie, he shall receiue the thing that I say.</ab>
<ab n="59">For this is the
life whereof Moses spake vnto the people while hee liued, saying,
Choose thee life that thou mayest liue.<note> Deut.30. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">Neuerthelesse
they beleeued not him, nor yet the prophets after him, no nor me
which haue spoken vnto them,</ab>
<ab n="61">That there
should not be such heauinesse in their destruction, as shall bee
ioy ouer them that are perswaded to saluation.</ab>
<ab n="62">I answered then
and saide, I know, Lord, that the most Hie is called mercifull, in
that he hath mercy vpon them, which are not yet come into the
world,</ab>
<ab n="63">And vpon those
also that turne to his Law,</ab>
<ab n="64">And that he is
patient, and long suffereth those that haue sinned, as his
creatures,<note> Rom.2.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="65">And that he is
bountifull, for hee is ready to giue where it needeth,</ab>
<ab n="66">And that is of
great mercie, for he multiplieth more and more mercies to them that
are present, and that are past, &amp; also to them which are to
come.</ab>
<ab n="67">For if he shall
not multiplie his mercies, the world would not continue with them
that inherit therein.</ab>
<ab n="68">And he
pardoneth; for if hee did not so of his goodnesse, that they which
haue committed iniquities might be eased of them, the ten thousand
part of men should not remaine liuing.</ab>
<ab n="69">And being Iudge,
if he should not forgiue them that are cured with his word, and put
out the multitude of contentions,<note> Or, created. , Or, contempts.</note></ab>
<ab n="70">There should bee
very fewe left peraduenture in an innumerable multitude.</ab>



</div>