<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Gods purpose is eternall. 8 The
next world shall follow this immediatly. 13 What shall fall out at
the last. 31 Hee is promised more knowledge, 38 and reckoneth vp
the workes of the creation, 57 and complaineth that they haue no
part in the world for whome it was made.</head>

<ab n="1">And he said vnto
me, in the beginning when þe earth was made, before
the borders of the world stood, or euer the windes
blew,<note> Or, circle of the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Before it
thundred and lightned, or euer the foundations of Paradise were
laide,</ab>
<ab n="3">Before the faire
flowers were seene, or euer the moueable powers were established,
before þe innumerable multitude of Angels were
gathered together,</ab>
<ab n="4">Or euer the
heights of the aire were lifted vp, before the measures of the
firmament were named, or euer the chimnies in Sion were
hot,</ab>
<ab n="5">And ere the
present yeeres were sought out, and or euer the inuentions of them
that now sinne were turned, before they were sealed that haue
gathered faith for a treasure:</ab>
<ab n="6">Then did I
consider these things, and they all were made through mee alone,
and through none other: by mee also they shall be ended, &amp; by
none other.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then answered I
and said, What shall bee the parting asunder of the times? or when
shall be the ende of the first, and the beginning of it that
followeth?</ab>
<ab n="8">And he said vnto
me, From Abraham vnto Isaac, when Iacob and Esau were borne of him,
Iacobs hand held first the heele of Esau.<note> Gen.25. 26. , Or, from the beginning.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For Esau is the
end of the world, and Iacob is the beginning of it that
followeth.</ab>
<ab n="10">The hand of man
is betwixt the heele and the hand: other question, Esdras, aske
thou not.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ I
answered then and said, O Lord that bearest rule, if I haue found
fauour in thy sight,</ab>
<ab n="12">I beseech thee,
shew thy seruant the end of thy tokens, whereof thou shewedst me
part the last night.</ab>
<ab n="13">So he answered
and said vnto me, Stand vp vpon thy feete, and heare a mightie
sounding voyce.</ab>
<ab n="14">And it shall be
as it were a great motion, but the place where thou standest, shall
not be moued.<note> Or, earthquake.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And therefore
when it speaketh be not afraid: for the word is of the end, and the
foundation of the earth is vnderstood.</ab>
<ab n="16">And why? because
the speech of these things trembleth and is mooued: for it knoweth
that the ende of these things must be changed.</ab>
<ab n="17">And it happened
that when I had heard it, I stood vp vpon my feet, and hearkened,
&amp; behold, there was a voice that spake, and the sound of it was
like the sound of many waters.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it said,
Behold, the dayes come, that I will begin to draw nigh, and to
visit them that dwell vpon the earth,</ab>
<ab n="19">And will begin
to make inquisition of them, what they be that haue hurt vniustly
with their vnrighteousnesse, and when the affliction of Sion shalbe
fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when the
world that shal begin to vanish away shall bee finished: then will
I shew these tokens, the books shalbe opened before the firmament,
and they shall see all together.<note> Or, sealed.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the children
of a yeere olde shall speake with their voyces, the women with
childe shall bring foorth vntimely children, of three or foure
moneths old: and they shall liue, and bee raised vp.</ab>
<ab n="22">And suddenly
shal the sowen places appeare vnsowen, the full storehouses shall
suddenly be found empty.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the trumpet
shall giue a sound, which when euery man heareth they shalbe
suddenly afraid.</ab>
<ab n="24">At that time
shall friendes fight one against another like enemies, and the
earth shall stand in feare with those that dwell therein, the
springs of the fountaines shall stand still, and in three houres
they shall not runne.</ab>
<ab n="25">Whosoeuer
remaineth from all these that I haue told thee, shall escape, and
see my saluation, and the ende of your world.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the men that
are receiued, shall see it, who haue not tasted death from their
birth: and the heart of the inhabitants shalbe changed, and turned
into another meaning.</ab>
<ab n="27">For euil shalbe
put out, and deceit shalbe quenched.</ab>
<ab n="28">As for faith, it
shall flourish, corruption shalbe ouercome, &amp; the trueth which
hath bene so long without fruit, shalbe declared.</ab>
<ab n="29">And when hee
talked with mee, behold, I looked by little and little vpon him
before whom I stood.</ab>
<ab n="30">And these words
said he vnto me, I am come to shew thee the time of the night to
come.</ab>
<ab n="31">If thou wilt
pray yet more, &amp; fast seuen daies againe, I shal tel thee
greater things by day, then I haue heard.<note> See cap. 13. vers. 52.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For thy voice is
heard before the most High: for the mighty hath seene thy righteous
dealing, he hath seene also thy chastitie, which thou hast had euer
since thy youth.</ab>
<ab n="33">And therefore
hath he sent mee to shew thee al these things, and to say vnto
thee, Be of good comfort, &amp; feare not.</ab>
<ab n="34">And hasten not
with the times that are past, to thinke vaine things, that thou
mayest not hasten from the latter times.</ab>
<ab n="35">And it came to
passe after this, that I wept againe, and fasted seuen dayes in
like maner, that I might fulfill the three weekes which he told
me.</ab>
<ab n="36">And in the eight
night was my heart vexed within mee againe, and I began to speake
before the most High.</ab>
<ab n="37">For my spirit
was greatly set on fire, and my soule was in distresse.</ab>
<ab n="38">And I said, O
Lord, thou spakest from the beginning of the creation, euen the
first day, &amp; saidest thus, Let heauen and earth bee made: and
thy word was a perfect worke.<note> Gen. 1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And then was the
spirit, and darkenesse, and silence were on euery side; the sound
of mans voice was not yet formed.</ab>
<ab n="40">Then commandedst
thou a faire light to come foorth of thy treasures, that thy worke
might appeare.</ab>
<ab n="41">Upon the second
day thou madest the spirit of the firmament, and commandedst it to
part asunder, and to make a diuision betwixt the waters, that the
one part might goe vp, and the other remaine beneath.</ab>
<ab n="42">Upon the thirde
day thou didst commaund that the waters should bee gathered in the
seuenth part of the earth: sixe parts hast thou dried vp and kept
them, to the intent that of these some being planted of God and
tilled, might serue thee.</ab>
<ab n="43">For as soone as
thy word went foorth, the worke was made.</ab>
<ab n="44">For immediatly
there was great and innumerable fruit, and many and diuers
pleasures for the taste, &amp; flowers of vnchangeable colour, and
odours of wonderfull smell: and this was done the third
day.</ab>
<ab n="45">Upon the fourth
day thou commandedst that the Sunne should shine, and the Moone
giue her light, and the starres should be in order,<note> Gen. 1. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And gauest them
a charge to do seruice vnto man, that was to be made.<note> Gen. 1. 15. deut.4.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Upon the fift
day, thou saydst vnto the seuenth part, where the waters were
gathered, that it should bring foorth liuing creatures, foules and
fishes: and so it came to passe.<note> Gene.1.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">For the dumbe
water, and without life, brought foorth liuing things at the
commandement of God, that al people might praise thy wondrous
works.</ab>
<ab n="49">Then didst thou
ordeine two liuing creatures, the one thou calledst Enoch, and the
other Leuiathan,<note> Behemoth.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">And didst
separate the one from the other: for the seuenth part (namely where
the water was gathered together) might not hold them both.</ab>
<ab n="51">Unto Enoch thou
gauest one part which was dried vp the third day, that he should
dwel in the same part, wherein are a thousand hilles.</ab>
<ab n="52">But vnto
Leuiathan thou gauest the seuenth part, namely the moist, and hast
kept him to be deuoured of whom thou wilt, and when.</ab>
<ab n="53">Upon the sixt
day thou gauest commaundement vnto the earth, that before thee it
should bring foorth beasts, cattell, and creeping things:</ab>
<ab n="54">And after these,
Adam also whom thou madest lord of all thy creatures, of him come
wee all, and the people also whom thou hast chosen.</ab>
<ab n="55">All this haue I
spoken before thee, O Lord, because thou madest the world for our
sakes.</ab>
<ab n="56">As for the other
people which also come of Adam, thou hast said that they are
nothing, but be like vnto spittle, and hast likened the abundance
of them vnto a drop that falleth from a vessell.</ab>
<ab n="57">And now, O Lord,
behold, these heathen, which haue euer been reputed as nothing,
haue begun to be lordes ouer vs, and to deuoure vs:</ab>
<ab n="58">But wee thy
people (whom thou hast called thy first borne, thy onely begotten,
and thy feruent louer) are giuen into their hands.</ab>
<ab n="59">If the world now
be made for our sakes, why doe we not possesse an inheritance with
the world? how long shall this endure?</ab>



</div>