<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Many created, but few saued. 6 Hee
asketh why God destroyeth his owne worke, 26 and prayeth God to
looke vpon the people which onely serue him. 41 God answereth that
all seed commeth not to God, 52 and that glory is prepared for him
and such like.</head>

<ab n="1">And he answered
me, saying, The most High hath made this world for many, but the
world to come for fewe.</ab>
<ab n="2">I will tell thee
a similitude, Esdras, As when thou askest the earth, it shall say
vnto thee, that it giueth much mold wherof earthen vessels are
made, but litle dust that golde commeth of: euen so is
þ<note/> course of this present world.</ab>
<ab n="3">There be many
created, but few shall be saued.<note> Mat.20. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">So answered I and
said, Swallow then downe O my soule, vnderstanding, and deuoure
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="5">For thou hast
agreed to giue eare, and art willing to prophesie: for thou hast no
longer space then onely to liue.</ab>
<ab n="6">O Lord, if thou
suffer not thy seruant that we may pray before thee, and thou giue
vs seed vnto our heart, and culture to our vnderstanding, that
there may come fruit of it, howe shall each man liue that is
corrupt, who beareth the place of a man?<note> Or, to giue vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For thou art
alone, and we all one workemanship of thine hands, like as thou
hast said.</ab>
<ab n="8">For when the body
is fashioned now in the mothers wombe, and thou giuest it members,
thy creature is preserued in fire &amp; water, and nine months
doeth thy workemanship endure thy creature which is created in
her.<note> Or, how is the body fashioned.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But that which
keepeth, and is kept, shall both be preserued: and when the time
commeth, the wombe preserued, deliuereth vp the things that grew in
it.</ab>
<ab n="10">For thou hast
commanded out of the parts of the body, that is to say, out of the
breasts milke to be giuen, which is the fruit of the
breasts,</ab>
<ab n="11">That the thing
which is fashioned, may bee nourished for a time, till thou
disposest it to thy mercy.</ab>
<ab n="12">Thou broughtest
it vp with thy righteousnesse, and nourturedst it in thy Law, and
reformedst it with thy iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="13">And thou shalt
mortifie it as thy creature, and quicken it as thy worke.</ab>
<ab n="14">If therefore
thou shalt destroy him which with so great labour was fashioned, it
is an easie thing to be ordeined by thy Commaundement, that the
thing which was made might be preserued.<note> Iob 10.8. psal.139. 14. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Now therefore,
Lord, I will speake (touchiug man in generall, thou knowest best)
but touching thy people, for whose sake I am sory,</ab>
<ab n="16">And for thine
inheritance, for whose cause I mourne, and for Israel, for whom I
am heauy, and for Iacob, for whose sake I am troubled:</ab>
<ab n="17">Therefore will I
begin to pray before thee, for my selfe, and for them: for I see
the falles of vs that dwell in the land.</ab>
<ab n="18">But I haue heard
the swiftnesse of the Iudge which is to come.</ab>
<ab n="19">Therefore heare
my voyce, and vnderstand my wordes, and I shall speake before thee:
this is the beginning of the words of Esdras, before he was taken
vp: and I said;</ab>
<ab n="20">O Lord, Thou
that dwellest in euerlastingnes, which beholdest from aboue, things
in the heauen, &amp; in the aire,</ab>
<ab n="21">Whose Throne is
inestimable, whose glory may not be comprehended, before whom the
hosts of Angels stand with trembling,</ab>
<ab n="22">(Whose seruice
is conuersant in wind and fire,) whose word is true, and sayings
constant, whose Commandement is strong, and ordinance
fearefull,</ab>
<ab n="23">Whose looke
drieth vp the depths, and indignation maketh the mountaines to melt
away, which the trueth witnesseth:</ab>
<ab n="24">O heare the
prayer of thy seruant, and giue eare to the petition of thy
creature.</ab>
<ab n="25">For while I
liue, I will speake, and so long as I haue vnderstanding, I wil
answere.</ab>
<ab n="26">O looke not vpon
the sinnes of thy people: but on them which serue thee in
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="27">Regard not the
wicked inuentions of the heathen: but the desire of those that
keepe thy Testimonies in afflictions.</ab>
<ab n="28">Thinke not vpon
those that haue walked fainedly before thee: but remember them,
which according to thy will haue knowen thy feare.</ab>
<ab n="29">Let it not bee
thy will to destroy them, which haue liued like beasts: but to
looke vpon them that haue clearely taught thy Law.</ab>
<ab n="30">Take thou no
indignation at them which are deemed worse then beasts: but loue
them that alway put their trust in thy righteousnesse, and
glory.</ab>
<ab n="31">For we and our
fathers doe languish of such diseases; but because of vs sinners,
thou shalt be called mercifull.<note> Are sicke.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For if thou hast
a desire to haue mercy vpon vs, thou shalt bee called mercifull, to
vs namely, that haue no workes of righteousnesse.<note> Be willing.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">For the iust
which haue many good workes layed vp with thee, shall out of their
owne deedes receiue reward.</ab>
<ab n="34">For what is man
that thou shouldest take displeasure at him? or what is a
corruptible generation, that thou shouldest be so bitter toward
it?</ab>
<ab n="35">For in trueth
there is no man among them that be borne, but he hath dealt
wickedly, and among the faithfull, there is none which hath not
done amisse.<note> 1.King.8. 46.and 2. chro.6.36.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">For in this, O
Lord, thy righteousnesse, and thy goodnesse shalbe declared, if
thou be mercifull vnto them which haue not the confidence of good
workes.<note> Or, substance.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Then answered he
mee, and said, Some things hast thou spoken aright, and according
vnto thy words it shalbe.</ab>
<ab n="38">For indeed I
will not thinke on the disposition of them which haue sinned before
death, before iudgement, before destruction.</ab>
<ab n="39">But I will
reioyce ouer the disposition of the righteous, and I wil remember
also their pilgrimage, and the saluation, and the reward that they
shall haue.<note> Gen.4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Like as I haue
spoken now, so shall it come to passe.</ab>
<ab n="41">For as the
husbandmau soweth much seed vpon the ground, and planteth many
trees, and yet the thing that is sowen good in his season, commeth
not vp, neither doeth all that is planted take root: euen so is it
of them that are sowen in the world, they shall not all be
saued.</ab>
<ab n="42">I answered then,
and said, If I haue found grace, let me speake.</ab>
<ab n="43">Like as the
husbandmans seede perisheth, if it come not vp, and receiue not the
raine in due season, or if there come too much raine and corrupt
it:</ab>
<ab n="44">Euen so
perisheth man also which is formed with thy hands, and is called
thine owne image, because thou art like vnto him, for whose sake
thou hast made all things, and likened him vnto the husbandmans
seede.</ab>
<ab n="45">Be not wroth
with vs, but spare thy people, and haue mercy vpon thine owne
inheritance: for thou art mercifull vnto thy creature.</ab>
<ab n="46">Then answered he
me, and said, Things present are for the present, and things to
come, for such as be to come.</ab>
<ab n="47">For thou commest
farre short, that thou shouldest be able to loue my creature more
then I: but I haue oft times drawen nigh vnto thee, and vnto it,
but neuer to the vnrighteous.</ab>
<ab n="48">In this also
thou art marueilous before the most high;</ab>
<ab n="49">In that thou
hast humbled thy selfe as it becommeth thee, and hast not iudged
thy selfe worthy to be much glorified among the righteous.</ab>
<ab n="50">For many great
miseries shall be done to them, that in the latter time shal dwell
in the world, because they haue walked in great pride.</ab>
<ab n="51">But vnderstand
thou for thy selfe, and seeke out the glory for such as be like
thee.</ab>
<ab n="52">For vnto you is
Paradise opened, the tree of life is planted, the time to come is
prepared, plenteousnesse is made ready, a citie is builded, and
rest is allowed, yea perfect goodnesse and wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="53">The root of euil
is sealed vp from you, weakenesse and the moth is hidde from you,
and corruption is fled into hell to be forgotten.<note> Or, graue.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">Sorrows are
passed, &amp; in the end is shewed the treasure of
immortalitie.</ab>
<ab n="55">And therefore
aske thou no more questions concerning the multitude of them that
perish.</ab>
<ab n="56">For when they
had taken liberty, they despised the most High, thought scorne of
his Lawe, and forsooke his wayes.</ab>
<ab n="57">Moreouer, they
haue troden downe his righteous,</ab>
<ab n="58">And said in
their heart, that there is no God, yea and that knowing they must
die.<note> Psal.14.1. and 53.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">For as the
things aforesaid shall receiue you, so thirst and paine are
prepared for them; for it was not his will that men should come to
nought.</ab>
<ab n="60">But they which
be created, haue defiled the Name of him that made them, and were
vnthankefull vnto him which prepared life for them.</ab>
<ab n="61">And therefore is
my iudgement now at hand.</ab>
<ab n="62">These things
haue I not shewed vnto all men, but vnto thee, and a fewe like
thee. Then answered I, and said,</ab>
<ab n="63">Behold, O Lord,
now hast thou shewed me the multitude of the wonders which thou
wilt begin to doe in the last times: but at what time, thou hast
not shewed me.</ab>



</div>