<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>7 Who shall be saued, and who not.
19 All the world is now corrupted: 22 Yet God doeth saue a few. 33
Hee complaineth that those perish which keepe Gods Law: 38 and
seeth a woman lamenting in a field.</head>

<ab n="1">Hee answered me
then, and sayde, Measure thou the time diligently in it selfe: and
when thou seest part of the signes past, which I haue tolde thee
before,</ab>
<ab n="2">Then shalt thou
vnderstand, that it is the very same time, wherein the highest will
begin to visite the world which he made.</ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore when
there shall bee seene earthquakes and vprores of the people in the
world:<note> Mat.24.7</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then shalt thou
wel vnderstand, that the most high spake of those things from the
dayes that were before thee, euen from the beginning.</ab>
<ab n="5">For like as all
that is made in the world hath a beginning, and an ende, and the
end is manifest:</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen so the times
also of the highest, haue plaine beginnings in wonders and
powerfull workes, and endings in effects and signes.</ab>
<ab n="7">And euery one
that shalbe saued, and shalbe able to escape by his works, and by
faith, whereby ye haue beleeued,</ab>
<ab n="8">Shall be
preserued from the sayd perils, and shall see my saluation, in my
land, and within my borders: for I haue sanctified them for me,
from the beginning.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then shall they
be in pitifull case which now haue abused my wayes: and they that
haue cast them away desspitefully, shall dwell in
torments.<note> Or, they shall maruell.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For such, as in
their life haue receiued benefits, &amp; haue not knowen
me:</ab>
<ab n="11">And they that
haue loathed my law, while they had yet liberty, and when as yet
place of repentance was open vnto them, vnderstood not, but
despised it:</ab>
<ab n="12">The same must
know it after death by paine.</ab>
<ab n="13">And therefore be
thou not curious, how the vngodly shalbe punished and when: but
enquire how the righteous shall be saued, whose the world is, and
for whom the world is created.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then answered I,
and said,</ab>
<ab n="15">I haue said
before, and now doe speake, and will speake it also heereafter:
that there be many moe of them which perish, then of them which
shall be saued,</ab>
<ab n="16">Like as a waue
is greater then a droppe.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he answered
me, saying: like as the field is, so is also the seed: as the
flowres be, such are the colours also: such as the workeman is,
such also is the worke: and as the husbandman is himselfe, so is
his husbandry also: for it was the time of the world.</ab>
<ab n="18">And now when I
prepared the world, which was not yet made, euen for them to dwell
in that now liue, no man spake against me.<note> And now because the time of the world was come, when I was preparing the world &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For then euery
one obeyed, but now the maners of them which are created in this
world that is made, are corrupted by a perpetuall seed, &amp; by a
law which is vnsearchable, rid themselues.<note> But when the world was made, both now and then, the maners of euery one created were corrupted by a neuer failing haruest, and a law vnsearchable.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">So I considered
the world, and behold there was perill, because of the deuices that
were come into it.</ab>
<ab n="21">And I saw and
spared it greatly, and haue kept me a grape of the cluster, and a
plant of a great people.<note> Or, graine.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Let the
multitude perish then, which was borne in vaine, and let my grape
be kept and my plant: for with great labour haue I made it
perfect.<note> Or, graine.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Neuerthelesse if
thou wilt cease yet seuen dayes moe (but thou shalt not fast in
them.)</ab>
<ab n="24">But goe into a
field of flowres, where no house is builded, and eate only the
flowres of the field, Tast no flesh, drinke no wine, but eate
flowres onely.</ab>
<ab n="25">And pray vnto
the Highest continually, then wil I come and talke with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="26">So I went my way
into the field which is called Ardath, like as he commanded me, and
there I sate amongst the flowres, and did eate of the herbes of the
field, and the meate of the same satisfied me.</ab>
<ab n="27">After seuen
dayes I sate vpon the grasse, and my heart was vexed within me,
like as before.</ab>
<ab n="28">And I opened my
mouth, and beganne to talke before the most High and said,</ab>
<ab n="29">O Lord, thou
that shewest thy selfe vnto vs, thou wast shewed vnto our fathers
in the wildernesse, in a place where no man treadeth, in a barren
place when they came out of Egypt.<note> Exod. 19. 9.and 24. 3. deut.4. 12. , Or, commeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And thou
spakest, saying, Heare me, O Israel, and marke my words, thou seed
of Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="31">For behold I sow
my law in you, and it shall bring fruite in you, and yee shall be
honoured in it for euer.</ab>
<ab n="32">But our fathers
which receiued the law, kept it not, and obserued not thy
ordinances, and though the fruite of thy law did not perish,
neither could it, for it was thine:</ab>
<ab n="33">Yet they that
receiued it, perished, because they kept not the thing that was
sowen in them.</ab>
<ab n="34">And loe, it is a
custome when the ground hath receiued seed, or the Sea a ship, or
any vessel, meate or drinke, that, that being perished wherein it
was sowen, or cast into,</ab>
<ab n="35">That thing also
which was sowen or cast therein, or receiued, doth perish, and
remaineth not with vs: but with vs it hath not happened so.</ab>
<ab n="36">For we that haue
receiued the law perish by sinne, and our heart also which receiued
it.</ab>
<ab n="37">Notwithstanding
the law perisheth not, but remaineth in his force.</ab>
<ab n="38">And when I spake
these things in my heart, I looked backe with mine eyes, &amp; vpon
the right side I saw a woman, and behold, she mourned, &amp; wept
with a loud voyce, and was much grieued in heart, and her clothes
were rent, and she had ashes vpon her head.</ab>
<ab n="39">Then let I my
thoughts goe that I was in, and turned me vnto her,</ab>
<ab n="40">And said vnto
her, Wherefore weepest thou? why art thou so grieued in thy
minde?</ab>
<ab n="41">And she said
vnto me, Sir, let me alone, that I may bewaile my selfe, and adde
vnto my sorow, for I am sore vexed in my minde, and brought very
low.</ab>
<ab n="42">And I said vnto
her, What aileth thee? Tell me.</ab>
<ab n="43">She said vnto
me, I thy seruant haue bene barren, and had no childe, though I had
an husband thirty yeres.</ab>
<ab n="44">And those
thirtie yeeres I did nothing else day and night, and euery houre,
but make my prayer to þ<note/> highest.</ab>
<ab n="45">After thirtie
yeeres, God heard me thine handmaid, looked vpon my misery,
considered my trouble, and gaue me a sonne: and I was very glad of
him, so was my husband also, and all my neighbours, and we gaue
great honour vnto the Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="46">And I nourished
him with great trauaile.</ab>
<ab n="47">So when he grew
vp, and came to the time that he should haue a wife, I made a
feast.</ab>



</div>