<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Esdras is troubled, 13 and
acknowledgeth the sinnes of the people: 28 yet complaineth that the
heathen were lords ouer them, being more wicked then
they.</head>

<ab n="1">In the thirtieth
yeere after the ruine of the citie, I was in Babylon, and lay
troubled vpon my bed, and my thoughts came vp ouer my
heart.</ab>
<ab n="2">For I saw the
desolation of Sion, and the wealth of them that dwelt at
Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="3">And my spirit was
sore moued, so that I began to speake words full of feare to the
most High, and said,</ab>
<ab n="4">O Lord, who
bearest rule, thou spakest at the beginning, when thou didst plant
the earth (and that thy selfe alone) and commandedst the
people,</ab>
<ab n="5">And gauest a body
vnto Adam without soule, which was the workemanship of thine hands,
&amp; didst breathe into him the breath of life, and he was made
liuing before thee.<note> Gen.2.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And thou leddest
him into paradise, which thy right hand had planted, before euer
the earth came forward.</ab>
<ab n="7">And vnto him thou
gauest commandement to loue thy way, which he transgressed, and
immediatly thou appointedst death in him, and in his generations,
of whom came nations, tribes, people, and kinreds out of
number.</ab>
<ab n="8">And euery people
walked after their owne will, and did wonderfull things before
thee, and despised thy commandements.<note> Gen.6. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And againe in
processe of time thou broughtest the flood vpon those that dwelt in
the world, and destroyedst them.<note> Gen.7.10</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe in euery of them, that as death was to Adam, so was the flood
to these.</ab>
<ab n="11">Neuerthelesse
one of them thou leftest, namely Noah with his household, of whom
came all righteous men.<note> 1.Pet.3. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And it happened,
that when they that dwelt vpō the earth began to multiply, and
had gotten them many children, and were a great people, they
beganne againe to be more vngodly then the first.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now when they
liued so wickedly before thee, thou diddest choose thee a man from
among them, whose name was Abraham.<note> Gen.12.1 , Gen.17.5</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Him thou
louedst, and vnto him onely thou shewedst thy will:</ab>
<ab n="15">And madest an
euerlasting couenant with him, promising him that thou wouldest
neuer forsake his seede.</ab>
<ab n="16">And vnto him,
thou gauest Isahac, and vnto Isahac also thou gauest Iacob and
Esau. As for Iacob thou didst choose him to thee, and put by Esau:
and so Iacob became a great multitude.<note> Gen.21. 2,3. , Gen.25. 25,26. , Mal.1.2,3</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And it came to
passe, that when thou leddest his seede out of Egypt, thou
broughtest them vp to the mount Sina.<note> Rom.9. 13. exod. 19.1. deut. 4.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And bowing the
heauens, thou didest set fast the earth, mouedst the whole world,
and madest the depth to tremble, and troubledst the men of that
age.</ab>
<ab n="19">And thy glory
went through foure gates, of fire, and of earthquake, and of wind,
and of cold, that thou mightest giue the law vnto the seed of
Iacob, and diligence vnto the generation of Israel.<note> And to all the generation of Israel, that they should keepe it with diligence.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And yet tookest
thou not away from them a wicked heart, that thy law might bring
forth fruite in them.</ab>
<ab n="21">For the first
Adam bearing a wicked heart transgressed, and was ouercome; and so
be all they that are borne of him.</ab>
<ab n="22">Thus infirmity
was made permanent; and the law (also) in the heart of the people
with the malignity of the roote, so that the good departed away,
and the euill abode still.</ab>
<ab n="23">So the times
passed away, and the yeeres were brought to an end: then diddest
thou raise thee vp a seruant, called Dauid,<note> 1.Sam. 16.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Whom thou
commandedst to build a citie vnto thy name, and to offer incense
and oblations vnto thee therein.<note> 2.Sam.5. 1. and 7.5. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">When this was
done many yeeres, then they that inhabited the citie forsooke
thee,</ab>
<ab n="26">And in all
things did euen as Adam, and all his generations had done, for they
also had a wicked heart.</ab>
<ab n="27">And so thou
gauest the citie ouer into the hands of thine enemies.</ab>
<ab n="28">Are their deeds
then any better that inhabite Babylon, that they should therefore
haue the dominion ouer Sion?</ab>
<ab n="29">For when I came
thither, and had seene impieties without number, then my soule saw
many euill doers in this thirtieth yeere, so that my heart failed
me.</ab>
<ab n="30">For I haue seene
how thou sufferest them sinning, and hast spared wicked doers: and
hast destroyed thy people, and hast preserued thine enemies, and
hast not signified it.</ab>
<ab n="31">I doe not
remember how this way may be left: Are they then of Babylon better
then they of Sion?<note> Or, I conceive.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Or is there any
other people that knoweth thee besides Israel? or what generation
hath so beleeued thy Couenants as Iacob?</ab>
<ab n="33">And yet their
reward appeareth not, and their labour hath no fruite: for I haue
gone here and there through the heathen, and I see that they flowe
in wealth, and think not vpon thy commandements.<note> Or, abound</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Weigh thou
therfore our wickednesse now in the ballance, and theirs also that
dwell in the world: and so shall thy Name no where be found, but in
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="35">Or when was it
that they which dwell vpon the earth, haue not sinned in thy sight?
or what people hath so kept thy commandements?</ab>
<ab n="36">Thou shalt find
that Israel by name hath kept thy precepts: but not the
heathen.</ab>



</div>