<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The Angel declareth the ignorance
of Esdras in Gods iudgments, 13 and aduiseth him not to meddle with
things aboue his reach. 23 Neuerthelesse Esdras asketh diuers
questions, and receiueth answeres to them.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Angel
that was sent vnto me, whose name was Uriel, gaue mee an
answere,</ab>
<ab n="2">And said, Thy
heart hath gone too farre in this world, and thinkest thou to
comprehend the way of the most High?</ab>
<ab n="3">Then said I, Yea
my Lord: and he answered me and said, I am sent to shew thee three
wayes, and to set forth three similitudes before thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Whereof if thou
canst declare me one, I will shew thee also the way that thou
desirest to see, &amp; I shall shew thee from whence the wicked
heart cōmeth.</ab>
<ab n="5">And I said, Tel
on my Lord. Then said he vnto me, Goe thy way, weigh me the weight
of the fire, or measure me the blast of the wind, or call me againe
the day that is past.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then answered I
and said, What man is able to doe that, that thou shouldest aske
such things of mee?</ab>
<ab n="7">And he said vnto
me, If I should aske thee how great dwellings are in the midst of
þ<note/> sea, or how many springs are in the beginning of
the deepe, or how many springs are aboue the firmament, or which
are the outgoings of Paradise:</ab>
<ab n="8">Peraduenture thou
wouldest say vnto me, I neuer went downe into the deepe, nor as yet
into hell, neither did I euer climbe vp into heauen.</ab>
<ab n="9">Neuerthelesse,
now haue I asked thee but onely of the fire and winde, and of the
day where through thou hast passed, and of things frō which
thou canst not be separated, and yet canst thou giue me uo answeere
of them.</ab>
<ab n="10">He said moreouer
vnto me, Thine owne things, and such as are growen vp with thee,
canst thou not know.</ab>
<ab n="11">How should thy
vessel then bee able to comprehend the way of the highest, and the
world being now outwardly corrupted, to vnderstand the corruption
that is euident in my sight?<note> Or, incorruption.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then said I vnto
him, It were better that we were not at all, then that we should
liue still in wickednesse, and to suffer, and not to know
wherefore.</ab>
<ab n="13">He answered me
and said, I went into a forest into a plaine, and the trees tooke
counsell,<note> Iudg. 9.8. 2.chron.25 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And said, Come,
let vs goe and make warre against the Sea, that it may depart away
before vs, and that we may make vs more woods.</ab>
<ab n="15">The floods of
the Sea also in like maner tooke counsell, and said, Come, let vs
goe vp and subdue the woods of the plaine, that there also we may
make vs another countrey.</ab>
<ab n="16">The thought of
the wood was in vaine, for the fire came and consumed it.</ab>
<ab n="17">The thought of
the floods of the Sea came likewise to nought, for the sand stood
vp and stopped them.</ab>
<ab n="18">If thou wert
iudge now betwixt these two, whom wouldest thou begin to iustifie,
or whom wouldest thou condemne?</ab>
<ab n="19">I answered and
said, Uerily it is a foolish thought that they both haue deuised:
for the ground is giuen vnto the wood, and the sea also hath his
place to beare his floods.<note> Or, the land. , Or, waues.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then answered he
me and said, Thou hast giuen a right iudgment, but why iudgest thou
not thy selfe also?</ab>
<ab n="21">For like as the
ground is giuen vnto the wood, &amp; the sea to his floods: euen so
they that dwell vpon the earth may vnderstand nothing, but that
which is vpon the earth: and hee that dwelleth aboue the heauens,
may onely vnderstand the things that are aboue the height of the
heauens.<note> The land. , Isay 55. 8,9 iohn 3. 31. 1.cor.2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then answered I,
and said, I beseech thee, O Lord, let me haue
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="23">For it was not
my minde to be curious of the high things, but of such as passe by
vs dayly, namely wherefore Israel is giuen vp as a reproch to the
heathen, and for what cause the people whom thou hast loued, is
giuen ouer vnto vngodly nations, and why the Lawe of our
forefathers is brought to nought, and the written Couenants come to
none effect.<note> Or, no where.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And wee passe
away out of the world as grassehoppers, and our life is
astonishment and feare, and we are not worthy to obtaine
mercie.</ab>
<ab n="25">What will he
then doe vnto his Name, whereby we are called? of these things haue
I asked.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then answered he
me, and said, The more thou searchest, the more thou shalt
marueile, for the world hasteth fast to passe away,</ab>
<ab n="27">And cannot
comprehend the things that are promised to the righteous in time to
come: for this world is ful of vnrighteousnesse and
infirmities.</ab>
<ab n="28">But as
concerning the things whereof thou askest me, I wil tell thee; for
the euil is sowen, but the destruction thereof is not yet
come.</ab>
<ab n="29">If therefore
that which is sowen, be not turned vpside downe; and if the place
where the euil is sowen passe not away, then cannot it come that is
sowen with good.</ab>
<ab n="30">For the graine
of euill seed hath bene sowen in the heart of Adam from the
beginning, and how much vngodlinesse hath it brought vp vnto this
time? and how much shall it yet bring foorth vntill the time of
threshing come.<note> Or, floore.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Ponder now by
thy selfe, how great fruit of wickednesse the graine of euil seed
hath brought forth.</ab>
<ab n="32">And when the
eares shall bee cut downe, which are without number, how great a
floore shall they fill?</ab>
<ab n="33">Then I answered
and said, How and when shall these things come to passe? wherefore
are our yeeres few and euill?</ab>
<ab n="34">And he answered
me, saying, Do not thou hasten aboue the most Highest: for thy
haste is in vaine to be aboue him, for thou hast much
exceeded.</ab>
<ab n="35">Did not the
soules also of the righteous aske question of these things in their
chambers, saying, How long shall I hope on this fashion? when
commeth the fruit of the floore of our reward?</ab>
<ab n="36">And vnto these
things Uriel the Archangel gaue them answere, and said, Euen when
the number of seedes is filled in you: for he hath weighed the
world in the ballance.<note> Ieremiel.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">By measure hath
hee measured the times, and by number hath he numbred the times;
and he doeth not mooue nor stirre them, vntill the said measure be
fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="38">Then answered I,
and said, O Lord that bearest rule, euen we all are full of
impietie.</ab>
<ab n="39">And for our
sakes peraduenture it is that the floores of the righteous are not
filled, because of the sinnes of them that dwell vpon the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="40">So he answered
me, and said, Go thy way to a wman with childe, and aske of her,
when she hath fulfilled her nine moneths, if her wombe may keepe
the birth any longer within her?</ab>
<ab n="41">Then said I, No
Lord, that can she not. And he said vnto mee, In the graue, the
chambers of soules are like the wombe of a woman:</ab>
<ab n="42">For like as a
woman that trauaileth, maketh haste to escape the necessitie of the
trauaile: euen so doe these places haste to deliuer those things
that are committed vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="43">From the
beginning looke what thou desirest to see, it shalbe shewed
thee.</ab>
<ab n="44">Then answered I,
and said, If I haue found fauour in thy sight, and if it be
possible, and if I be meet therefore,</ab>
<ab n="45">Shew me then
whether there be more to come then is past, or more past then is to
come.</ab>
<ab n="46">What is past I
know; but what is for to come I know not.</ab>
<ab n="47">And he said vnto
me, Stand vp vpon the right side, and I shal expound the similitude
vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="48">So I stood and
saw, and behold an hot burning ouen passed by before mee: and it
happened that when the flame was gone by, I looked, and behold, the
smoke remained still.</ab>
<ab n="49">After this there
passed by before me a watrie cloude, and sent downe much raine with
a storme, and when the stormie raine was past, the drops remained
still.</ab>
<ab n="50">Then said he
vnto me, Consider with thy selfe: as the raine is more then the
drops, and as the fire is greater then the smoke: but the drops and
the smoke remaine behind: so the quantity which is past, did more
exceede.<note> Or, measure.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">Then I prayed,
and sayd, May I liue, thinkest thou, vntill that time? or what
shall happen in those dayes?<note> Or, who shalbe manuscript?</note></ab>
<ab n="52">He answered me,
and sayd, As for the tokens whereof thou askest me, I may tell thee
of them in part; but as touching thy life, I am not sent to shew
thee, for I doe not know it.</ab>



</div>