<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>3 The Eagle which hee saw, is
destroyed. 10 The vision is interpreted. 37 He is bid to write his
visions, 39 and to fast, that he may see more. 46 He doth comfort
those, that were grieued for his absence.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe whiles the Lyon spake these words vnto the Eagle, I
saw:</ab>
<ab n="2">And behold, the
head that remained, and the foure wings appeared no more, and the
two went vnto it, and set themselues vp to raigne, and their
kingdome was small and full of vprore.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I saw, and
behold, they appeared no more, and the whole body of the Eagle was
burnt, so that the earth was in great feare: then awaked I out of
the trouble and traunce of my minde, and from great feare, and said
vnto my spirit,</ab>
<ab n="4">Loe, this hast
thou done vnto me, in that thou searchest out the wayes of the
Highest.</ab>
<ab n="5">Loe, yet am I
weary in my mind, and very weake in my spirit: and litle strength
is there in me; for the great feare, wherewith I was affrighted
this night.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore wil I
now beseech the Highest, that hee will comfort me vnto the
end.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I said,
Lord, that bearest rule, If I haue found grace before thy sight,
and if I am iustified with thee, before many others, and if my
prayer indeed be come vp before thy face,</ab>
<ab n="8">Comfort me then,
and shew me thy seruant the interpretation, and plaine difference
of this fearefull vision, that thou maist perfectly comfort my
soule.</ab>
<ab n="9">For thou hast
iudged me worthy, to shew me the last times.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said
vnto me, This is the interpretation of the vision.</ab>
<ab n="11">The Eagle whom
thou sawest come vp from the sea, is the kingdome which was seene,
in the vision of thy brother Daniel.<note> Daniel 7.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But it was not
expounded vnto him, therefore now I declare it vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">Behold, the
dayes will come, that there shall rise vp a kingdome vpon earth,
and it shall be feared aboue all the kingdomes that were before
it.</ab>
<ab n="14">In the same
shall twelue kings reigne, one after another.</ab>
<ab n="15">Whereof the
second shall begin to reigne, and shall haue more time then any of
the twelue.</ab>
<ab n="16">And this doe
the twelue wings signifie which thou sawest.</ab>
<ab n="17">As for the
voice which thou heardest speake, and that thou sawest not to goe
out from the heads, but from the mids of the body thereof, this is
the interpretation:</ab>
<ab n="18">That after the
time of that kingdome, there shall arise great striuings, and it
shall stand in perill of falling: neuerthelesse it shall not then
fall, but shal be restored againe to his beginning.</ab>
<ab n="19">And whereas
thou sawest the eight small vnder feathers sticking to her wings,
this is the interpretation:</ab>
<ab n="20">That in him
there shal arise eight kings, whose time shall bee but small, and
their yeeres swift.</ab>
<ab n="21">And two of them
shall perish: the middle time approching, foure shall bee kept
vntill their end begin to approch: but two shall be kept vnto the
end.</ab>
<ab n="22">And whereas
thou sawest three heads resting, this is the interpretation</ab>
<ab n="23">In his last
dayes shall the most High raise vp three kingdomes, and renew many
things therein, and they shal haue the dominion of the
earth,</ab>
<ab n="24">And of those
that dwell therein with much oppression, aboue all those that were
before them: therefore are they called the heads of the
Eagle.</ab>
<ab n="25">For these are
they that shal accomplish his wickednesse, and that shall finish
his last end.</ab>
<ab n="26">And whereas
thou sawest that the great head appeared no more, it signifieth
that one of them shall die vpon his bed, and yet with
paine.</ab>
<ab n="27">For the two
that remaine, shall be slaine with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="28">For the sword
of the one shall deuoure the other: but at the last shall he fall
through the sword himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="29">And whereas
thou sawest two feathers vnder the wings passing ouer the head,
that is on the right side:</ab>
<ab n="30">It signifieth
that these are they whom the Highest hath kept vnto their end: this
is the small kingdom and full of trouble, as thou sawest.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the Lyon
whom thou sawest rising vp out of the wood, and roaring, and
speaking to the Eagle, and rebuking her for her vnrighteousnesse,
with all the words which thou hast heard,</ab>
<ab n="32">This is the
Anointed which the Highest hath kept for them, and for their
wickednesse vnto the end: he shall reprooue them, and shall vpbraid
them with their crueltie.</ab>
<ab n="33">For hee shall
set them before him aliue in iudgement, and shall rebuke them and
correct them.</ab>
<ab n="34">For the rest of
my people shall he deliuer with mercie, those that haue bin
preserued vpon my borders, and he shal make them ioyfull vntill the
comming of the day of iudgement, whereof I haue spoken vnto thee
from the beginning.</ab>
<ab n="35">This is the
dreame that thou sawest, and these are the interpretations.</ab>
<ab n="36">Thou onely hast
bene meete to know this secret of the Highest.</ab>
<ab n="37">Therefore write
all these things that thou hast seene, in a booke, and hide
them.</ab>
<ab n="38">And teach them
to the wise of the people, whose hearts thou knowest may
comprehend, &amp; keepe these seerets.</ab>
<ab n="39">But wait thou
here thy selfe yet seuen dayes moe, that it may be shewed thee
whatsoeuer it pleaseth the Highest to declare vnto thee: And with
that he went his way.</ab>
<ab n="40">And it came to
passe when all the people saw that the seuen dayes were past, and I
not come againe into the citie, they gathered them all together,
from the least vnto the greatest, and came vnto me, and
said,</ab>
<ab n="41">What haue we
offended thee? and what euill haue we done against thee, that thou
forsakest vs, and sittest here in this place?</ab>
<ab n="42">For of all the
prophets thou only art left vs, as a cluster of the vintage, and as
a candle in a darke place, and as a hauen or ship preserued from
the tempest:<note> Or, people.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Are not the
euils which are come to vs, sufficient?</ab>
<ab n="44">If thou shalt
forsake vs, how much better had it bene for vs, if we also had bene
burnt in the midst of Sion.</ab>
<ab n="45">For we are not
better then they that died there. And they wept with a loud voice:
then answered I them, and said,</ab>
<ab n="46">Be of good
comfort, O Israel, and be not heauy thou house of Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="47">For the Highest
hath you in remembrance, and the mighty hath not forgotten you in
temptation.</ab>
<ab n="48">As for mee, I
haue not forsaken you, neither am I departed from you: but am come
into this place, to pray for the desolation of Sion, and that I
might seeke mercy for the low estate of your Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="49">And now goe
your way home euery man, and after these dayes will I come vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="50">So the people
went their way into the city, like as I commanded them:</ab>
<ab n="51">But I remained
still in the field seuen dayes, as the Angel commanded me, and did
eate onely in those dayes, of the flowers of the fielde, and had my
meat of the herbes.</ab>



</div>