<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-5-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The signes of the times to come.
23 He asketh why God choosing but one people, did cast them off. 30
Hee is taught, that Gods Iudgements are vnsearchable: 46 and that
God doeth not all at once.</head>

<ab n="1">Neuertheles as
concerning the tokens, beholde, the dayes shall come that they
which dwell vpon earth, shall bee taken in a great number, and the
way of trueth shall be hidden, and the land shall be barren of
faith.<note> Shalbe found with great wealth</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But iniquitie
shalbe increased aboue that which now thou seest, or that thou hast
heard long agoe.<note> Mat.24.12</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the land that
thou seest now to haue roote, shalt thou see wasted
suddenly.<note> Or, that thou treadest vpon and seest.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But if the most
high graunt thee to liue, thou shalt see after the third trumpet,
that the Sunne shall suddenly shine againe in the night, and the
Moone thrice in the day.</ab>
<ab n="5">And blood shal
drop out of wood, and the stone shall giue his voice, and the
people shalbe troubled.</ab>
<ab n="6">And enen he shal
rule whom they looke not for that dwel vpon the earth, and the
foules shall take their flight away together.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the
Sodomitish sea shall cast out fish, and make a noyse in the night,
which many haue not knowen: but they shall all heare the voice
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="8">There shall be a
confusion also in many places, and the fire shalbe oft sent out
againe, and the wilde beasts shall change their places, and
menstruous women shall bring foorth monsters.<note> Or, slaked.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And salt waters
shall be found in the sweete, and all friends shall destroy one
another: then shall wit hide it selfe, and vnderstanding withdraw
it selfe into his secret chamber,</ab>
<ab n="10">And shall be
sought of many, and yet not be found: then shall vnrighteousnesse
and incontinencie be multiplyed vpon earth.</ab>
<ab n="11">One land also
shall aske another, and say, Is righteousnes that maketh a man
righteous, gone through thee? And it shall say, No.</ab>
<ab n="12">At the same time
shall men hope, but nothing obtaine: they shall labour, but their
wayes shall not prosper.<note> Or, be reiected.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">To shew thee
such tokens I haue leaue: and if thou wilt pray againe, and weepe
as now, and fast seuen dayes, thou shalt heare yet greater
things.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then I awaked,
&amp; an extreme fearefulnesse went through all my body, and my
minde was troubled, so that it fainted.</ab>
<ab n="15">So the Angel
that was come to talke with me, helde me, comforted me, and set me
vp vpon my feete.</ab>
<ab n="16">And in the
second night it came to passe, that Salathiel the captaine of the
people came vnto mee, saying, Where hast thou beene? and why is thy
countenance so heauie?</ab>
<ab n="17">Knowest thou not
that Israel is committed vnto thee, in the land of their
captiuitie?</ab>
<ab n="18">Up then, and
eate bread, and forsake vs not as the shepheard that leaueth his
flocke in the handes of cruell wolues.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then sayd I vnto
him, Goe thy waies from me, and come not nigh me: And he heard what
I said, and went from me.</ab>
<ab n="20">And so I fasted
seuen dayes, monrning and weeping, like as Uriel the Angel
commanded me.</ab>
<ab n="21">And after seuen
dayes, so it was that the thoughts of my heart were very grieuous
vnto me againe.</ab>
<ab n="22">And my soule
recouered the spirit of vnderstanding, and I began to talke with
the most high againe,</ab>
<ab n="23">And said, O
Lord, that bearest rule of euery wood of the earth, and of all the
trees thereof, thou hast chosen thee one onely vine.</ab>
<ab n="24">And of all lands
of the whole world thou hast chosen thee one pit: and of all the
flowers thereof, one Lillie.</ab>
<ab n="25">And of all the
depths of the Sea, thou hast filled thee one riuer: and of all
builded cities, thou hast hallowed Sion vnto thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="26">And of all the
foules that are created, thou hast named thee one Doue: and of all
the cattell that are made, thou hast prouided thee one
sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="27">And among all
the multitudes of peoples, thou hast gotten thee one people: and
vnto this people whom thou louedst, thou gauest a law that is
approued of all.</ab>
<ab n="28">And now O Lord,
why hast thou giuen this one people ouer vnto many? and vpon the
one roote hast thou prepared others, and why hast thou scattered
thy onely one people among many?<note> Or, ouer.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And they which
did gainesay thy promises, and beleeued not thy couenants, haue
trodden them downe.</ab>
<ab n="30">If thou didst so
much hate thy people, yet shouldest thou punish them with thine
owne hands.</ab>
<ab n="31">Now when I had
spoken these words, the Angell that came to me the night afore, was
sent vnto me,</ab>
<ab n="32">And said vnto
me, Heare me, and I will instruct thee, hearken to the thing that I
say, &amp; I shal tell thee more.</ab>
<ab n="33">And I said,
Speake on, my Lord: then said he vnto me, thou art sore troubled in
minde for Israels sake: louest thou that people better then hee
that made them?</ab>
<ab n="34">And I said, No
Lord, but of very griefe haue I spoken: For my reines paine me
euery houre, while I labour to comprehend the way of the most High,
and to seeke out part of his iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="35">And he said vnto
me, Thou canst not: and I said, wherfore Lord? wherunto was I borne
then? or why was not my mothers wombe then my graue, that I might
not haue seene the trauell of Iacob, and the wearisome toyle of the
stocke of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="36">And he said vnto
me, Number me the things that are not yet come, gather me together
the droppes that are scattered abroad, make mee the flowres greene
againe that are withered.</ab>
<ab n="37">Open me the
places that are closed, and bring me forth the winds that in them
are shut vp, shew me the image of a voyce: and then I will declare
to thee the thing that thou labourest to knowe.</ab>
<ab n="38">And I said, O
Lord, that bearest rule, who may know these things, but hee that
hath not his dwelling with men?</ab>
<ab n="39">As for me, I am
vnwise: how may I then speake of these things whereof thou askest
me?</ab>
<ab n="40">Then said he
vnto me, Like as thou canst doe none of these things that I haue
spoken of, euen so canst thou not find out my iudgement, or in the
end the loue that I haue promised vnto my people.</ab>
<ab n="41">And I said,
behold, O Lord, yet art thou nigh vnto them that be reserued till
the end; and what shall they doe that haue beene before me, or we
(that be now) or they that shall come after vs?</ab>
<ab n="42">And he said vnto
me, I wil liken my iudgement vnto a ring: like as there is no
slacknesse of the last, euen so there is no swiftnesse of the
first.</ab>
<ab n="43">So I answered
and said, Couldst thou not make those that haue beene made, and be
now, and that are for to come, at once, that thou mightest shewe
thy iudgement the sooner?</ab>
<ab n="44">Then answered he
me, and said, The creature may not hast aboue the maker, neither
may the world hold them at once that shalbe created therin.</ab>
<ab n="45">And I said, As
thou hast said vnto thy seruant, that thou which giuest life to
all, hast giuen life at once to the creature that thou hast
created, and the creature bare it: euen so it might now also beare
them that now be present at once.</ab>
<ab n="46">And he said vnto
me, Aske the wombe of a woman, &amp; say vnto her, If thou bringest
forth children, why doest thou it not together, but one after
another? pray her therefore to bring forth tenne children at
once.</ab>
<ab n="47">And I said, She
cannot: but must doe it by distance of time.</ab>
<ab n="48">Then said he
vnto me, Euen so haue I giuen the wombe of the earth to those that
be sowen in it, in their times.</ab>
<ab n="49">For like as a
young child may not bring forth the things that belong to the aged,
euen so haue I disposed the world which I created.</ab>
<ab n="50">And I asked and
said, Seeing thou hast now giuen me the way, I will proceed to
speak before thee: for our mother of whom thou hast told me that
she is yong, draweth now nigh vnto age.</ab>
<ab n="51">He answered me
and said, Aske a woman that beareth children, and shee shall tell
thee.</ab>
<ab n="52">Say vnto her,
Wherefore are not they whome thou hast now brought forth, like
those that were before, but lesse of stature?</ab>
<ab n="53">And she shall
answere thee, They that be borne in the strength of youth, are of
one fashion, and they that are borne in the time of age (when the
wombe faileth) are otherwise.</ab>
<ab n="54">Consider thou
therfore also, how that yee are lesse of stature then those that
were before you.</ab>
<ab n="55">And so are they
that come after you lesse then ye, as the creatures which now begin
to be old, and haue passed ouer the strength of youth.</ab>
<ab n="56">Then saide I,
Lord, I beseech thee, if I haue found fauor in thy sight, shew thy
seruant by whom thou visitest thy creature.</ab>



</div>