<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Hee comforteth the woman in the
field. 17 She vanisheth away, and a citie appeareth in her place.
40 The Angel declareth these visions in the field.</head>

<ab n="1">And it so came
to passe, that when my sonne was entred into his wedding chamber,
he fell downe and died.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then we all
ouerthrew the lights, and all my neighbours rose vp to comfort me,
so I tooke my rest vnto the second day at night.<note> Or countrey men citizens.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And it came to
passe when they had all left off to comfort me, to the end I might
be quiet: then rose I vp by night and fled, and came hither into
this field, as thou seest.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I doe now
purpose not to returne into the citie, but here to stay, and
neither to eate nor drinke, but continually to mourne, &amp; to
fast vntil I die.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then left I the
meditations wherein I was, and spake to her in anger,
saying,<note> Or, speeches.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou foolish
woman aboue all other, seest thou not our mourning, and what
happeneth vnto vs?</ab>
<ab n="7">How that Sion
our mother is full of all heauinesse, and much humbled, mourning
very sore?</ab>
<ab n="8">And now seeing
we all mourne, and are sad, for we are all in heauinesse, art thou
grieued for one sonne?</ab>
<ab n="9">For aske the
earth, and she shall tell thee, that it is she, which ought to
mourne, for the fall of so many that grow vpon her.</ab>
<ab n="10">For out of her
came all at the first, and out of her shal all others come: and
behold they walke almost all into destruction, and a multitude of
them is vtterly rooted out.<note> Or, abolished.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Who then should
make more mourning, then she that hath lost so great a multitude,
and not thou which art sory but for one?</ab>
<ab n="12">But if thou
sayest vnto me, My lamentation is not like the earths, because I
haue lost the fruit of my womb, which I brought foorth with paines,
and bare with sorrowes.</ab>
<ab n="13">But the earth
not so: for the multitude present in it, according to the course of
the earth, is gone, as it came.<note> But the earth after the maner of the earth: whereinto the present multitude is gone againe, as it came out.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Then say I vnto
thee, Like as thou hast brought foorth with labour: euen so the
earth also hath giuen her fruit, namely man, euer sithence the
beginning, vnto him that made her.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now therefore
keepe thy sorrow to thy selfe, and beare with a good courage that
which hath befallen thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">For if thou
shalt acknowledge the determination of God to be iust, thou shalt
both receiue thy sonne in time, and shalt be commended amongst
women.</ab>
<ab n="17">Goe thy way
then into the citie, to thine husband.</ab>
<ab n="18">And she said
vnto me, That will I not doe: I will not goe into the city, but
here will I die.</ab>
<ab n="19">So I proceeded
to speake further vnto her, and said,</ab>
<ab n="20">Doe not so, but
bee counselled by me: for how many are the aduersities of Sion? Bee
comforted in regard of the sorow of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="21">For thou seest
that our Sanctuary is laid waste, our Altar broken downe, our
Temple destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="22">Our Psaltery is
laid on þe ground, our song is put to silence, our
reioycing is at an end, the light of our candlesticke is put out,
the Arke of our Couenant is spoiled, our holy things are defiled,
and the Name that is called vpon vs, is almost prophaned: our
children are put to shame, our priests are burnt, our Leuites are
gone into captiuitie, our virgines are defiled, and our wiues
rauished, our righteous men caried away, our litle ones destroyed,
our yong men are brought in bondage, and our strong men are become
weake.</ab>
<ab n="23">And which is
the greatest of all, the seale of Sion hath now lost her honour:
for she is deliuered into the hands of them that hate vs.</ab>
<ab n="24">And therefore
shake off thy great heauinesse, and put away the multitude of
sorrowes, that the mighty may be mercifull vnto thee againe, and
the highest shal giue thee rest, and ease from thy labour.</ab>
<ab n="25">And it came to
passe while I was talking with her, behold her face vpon a sudden
shined exceedingly, &amp; her countenance glistered, so that I was
afraid of her, and mused what it might be.</ab>
<ab n="26">And behold
suddenly, she made a great cry very fearful: so that the earth
shooke at the noise of the woman.</ab>
<ab n="27">And I looked,
and beholde, the woman appeared vnto me no more, but there was a
city builded, and a large place shewed it selfe from the
foundations: then was I afraid, and cried with a lowd voice, and
said,</ab>
<ab n="28">Where is Uriel
the Angel, who came vnto mee at the first? for hee hath caused me
to fall into many traunces, and mine end is turned into corruption,
and my prayer to rebuke.<note> Chap.4.1. , Or, into the multitude in a traunce.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And as I was
speaking these wordes, behold, he came vnto me, and looked vpon
me.</ab>
<ab n="30">And loe, I lay
as one that had bene dead, &amp; mine vnderstanding was taken from
me, and he tooke me by the right hand, and comforted mee, and set
me vpon my feet, and said vnto me,</ab>
<ab n="31">What aileth
thee? and why art thou so disquieted, and why is thine
vnderstanding troubled, &amp; the thoughts of thine heart?</ab>
<ab n="32">And I said,
because thou hast forsaken me, and yet I did according to thy
words, and I went into the field, and loe I haue seene, and yet
see, that I am not able to expresse.<note> Chap.5. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And hee said
vnto me, Stand vp manfully, and I wil aduise thee.</ab>
<ab n="34">Then said I,
Speake on, my lord in me, onely forsake me not, lest I die
frustrate of my hope.</ab>
<ab n="35">For I haue
seene, that I knew not, and heare that I do not know.</ab>
<ab n="36">Or, is my sense
deceiued, or my soule in a dreame?</ab>
<ab n="37">Now therfore, I
beseech thee, that thou wilt shew thy seruant of this
visiō.<note> Or, traunce.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">He answered me
then, &amp; said, Heare me, and I shall enforme thee, and tell thee
wherefore thou art afraid: for the highest will reueile many secret
things vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="39">Hee hath seene
that thy way is right: for that thou sorrowest continually for thy
people, and makest great lamentation for Sion.<note> Or, purpose.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">This therefore
is the meaning of the vision which thou lately sawest.</ab>
<ab n="41">Thou sawest a
woman mourning, and thou beganst to comfort her:</ab>
<ab n="42">But now seest
thou the likenesse of the woman no more, but there appeared vnto
thee a city builded.</ab>
<ab n="43">And whereas she
told thee of the death of her sonne, this is the
solution.<note> Or, Interpretation.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">This woman whom
thou sawest, is Sion: and whereas she said vnto thee (euen she whom
thou seest as a city builded.)</ab>
<ab n="45">Whereas I say,
she said vnto thee, that she hath bene thirty yeres barren: those
are the thirty yeeres wherein there was no offering made in
her.</ab>
<ab n="46">But after
thirtie yeeres, Solomon builded the city, &amp; offered offrings:
and then bare the barren a sonne.</ab>
<ab n="47">And whereas she
told thee that shee nourished him with labour: that was the
dwelling in Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="48">But whereas she
said vnto thee, That my sonne comming into his marriage chamber,
happened to haue a fall, and died, this was the destruction that
came to Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="49">And behold,
thou sawest her likenesse, and because she mourned for her sonne,
thou beganst to comfort her, and of these things which haue
chaunced, these are to be opened vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="50">For now the
most High seeth, that thou art grieued vnfainedly, &amp; sufferest
from thy whole heart for her, so hath he shewed thee the brightnes
of her glory, and the comelinesse of her beautie.</ab>
<ab n="51">And therfore I
bad thee remaine in þe field, where no house was
builded.</ab>
<ab n="52">For I knew that
the Highest would shew this vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="53">Therefore I
commanded thee to goe into the field, where no foundation of any
building was.</ab>
<ab n="54">For in the
place wherein the Highest beginneth to shew his city, ther can no
mans building be able to stand.</ab>
<ab n="55">And therfore
feare not, let not thy heart be afrighted, but goe thy way in, and
see the beautie and greatnesse of the building, as much as thine
eyes be able to see:</ab>
<ab n="56">And then shalt
thou heare as much as thine eares may comprehend.</ab>
<ab n="57">For thou art
blessed aboue many other, and art called with the highest, and so
are but few.<note> Or, art called to be with, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">But to morrow
at night thou shalt remaine here.</ab>
<ab n="59">And so shall
the highest shew thee visions of the high things, which the most
high will do vnto them, that dwel vpon earth in the last dayes. So
I slept that night and another, like as he commanded
me.<note> Or, last things.</note></ab>



</div>