<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Esdras_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Hee seeth in his dreame an Eagle
comming out of the Sea: 37 And a Lion out of a wood talking to the
Eagle.</head>

<ab n="1">Then saw I a
dreame, and beholde, there came vp from the Sea an Eagle, which had
twelue feathered wings, &amp; three heads.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I saw, and
behold, she spred her wings ouer all the earth, and all the windes
of the ayre blewe on her, and were gathered together.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I beheld,
and out of her feathers there grewe other contrary feathers, and
they became little feathers, and small.</ab>
<ab n="4">But her heads
were at rest: the head in the middest was greater then the other,
yet rested it with the residue.<note> Lat. shee.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer I
beheld, and loe, the Eagle flew with her feathers, and reigned vpon
earth, and ouer them that dwelt therein.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I saw that
all things vnder heauen were subiect vnto her, and no man spake
against her, no not one creature vpon earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I beheld,
and loe, the Eagle rose vpon her talents, and spake to her
feathers, saying,</ab>
<ab n="8">Watch not all at
once, sleepe euery one in his own place, &amp; watch by
course.</ab>
<ab n="9">But let the
heads be preserued for the last.</ab>
<ab n="10">And I beheld,
and loe, the voice went not out of her heads, but from the middest
of her body.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I numbred
her contrary feathers, and behold, there were eight of
them.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I looked,
and behold, on the right side there arose one feather, and reigned
ouer all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And so it was,
that when it reigned, the ende of it came, and the place thereof
appeared no more: so the next following stood vp and reigned, and
had a great time.</ab>
<ab n="14">And it
happened, that when it reigned, the end of it came also, like as
the first, so that it appeared no more.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then came there
a voice vnto it, and sayd,</ab>
<ab n="16">Heare, thou
that hast borne rule ouer the earth so long: this I say vnto thee,
before thou beginnest to appeare no more.</ab>
<ab n="17">There shall
none after thee attaine vnto thy time, neither vnto the halfe
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then arose the
third, and reigned as the other before: and appeared no more
also.</ab>
<ab n="19">So went it with
all the residue one after another, as that euery one reigned, and
then appeared no more.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then I beheld,
&amp; loe, in processe of time, the feathers that folowed, stood vp
vpon the right side, that they might rule also, and some of them
ruled, but within a while they appeared no more:</ab>
<ab n="21">For some of
them were set vp, but ruled not.</ab>
<ab n="22">After this I
looked, and behold, the twelue feathers appeared no more, nor the
two little feathers:</ab>
<ab n="23">And there was
no more vpon the Eagles body, but three heads that rested, and sixe
little wings.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then saw I also
that two little feathers diuided themselues from the sixe, and
remained vnder the head, that was vpon the right side: for the
foure continued in their place.</ab>
<ab n="25">And I beheld,
&amp; loe, the feathers that were vnder the wing, thought to set vp
themselues, and to haue the rule.</ab>
<ab n="26">And I beheld,
&amp; loe, there was one set vp, but shortly it appeared no
more.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the second
was sooner away then the first.</ab>
<ab n="28">And I beheld,
and loe, the two that remained, thought also in themselues to
reigne.</ab>
<ab n="29">And when they
so thought, behold, there awaked one of the heads that were at
rest, namely it that was in the middest, for that was greater then
the two other heads.</ab>
<ab n="30">And then I saw,
that the two other heads were ioyned with it.</ab>
<ab n="31">And behold, the
head was turned with them that were with it, and did eate vp the
two feathers vnder the wing that would haue reigned.</ab>
<ab n="32">But this head
put the whole earth in feare, and bare rule in it ouer all those
that dwelt vpon the earth, with much oppression, and it had the
gouernance of the world more then all the wings that had
beene.</ab>
<ab n="33">And after this
I beheld, and loe the head that was in the midst, suddenly appeared
no more, like as the wings.</ab>
<ab n="34">But there
remained the two heads, which also in like sort ruled vpon the
earth, and ouer those that dwelt therein.</ab>
<ab n="35">And I beheld,
and loe, the head vpon the right side, deuoured it, that was vpon
the left side.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then I heard a
voyce, which said vnto me, Looke before thee, and consider the
thing that thou seest.</ab>
<ab n="37">And I beheld,
and loe, as it were a roaring Lyon, chased out of the wood: and I
saw that hee sent out a mans voyce vnto the Eagle, and
said,</ab>
<ab n="38">Heare thou, I
will talke with thee, and the highest shall say vnto thee,</ab>
<ab n="39">Art not thou it
that remainest of the foure beasts, whom I made to raigne in my
world, that the end of their times might come through them?</ab>
<ab n="40">And the fourth
came and ouercame all the beasts that were past, and had power ouer
the world with great fearefulnesse, and ouer the whole compasse of
the earth with much wicked oppression, and so long time dwelt he
vpon the earth with deceit.</ab>
<ab n="41">For the earth
hast thou not iudged with trueth.</ab>
<ab n="42">For thou hast
afflicted the meeke, thou hast hurt the peaceable, thou hast loued
lyers, and destroyed the dwellings of them that brought forth
fruite, and hast cast downe the walles of such, as did thee no
harme.</ab>
<ab n="43">Therefore is
thy wrongfull dealing come vp vnto the Highest, and thy pride vnto
the Mighty.</ab>
<ab n="44">The Highest
also hath looked vpon the proud times, and behold, they are ended,
and his abominations are fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="45">And therefore
appeare no more thou Eagle, nor thy horrible wings, nor thy wicked
feathers, nor thy malitious heads, nor thy hurtfull clawes, nor all
thy vaine body:</ab>
<ab n="46">That all the
earth may be refreshed, and may returne, being deliuered from thy
violence, and that she may hope for the iudgement, and mercy of him
that made her.</ab>



</div>