<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-John_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-John-Chapter-5-5-2-John.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>Hee exhorteth a certaine honourable
matrone, with her children, to perseuere in Christian loue, and
beliefe, 8 lest they lose the reward of their former profession: 10
And to haue nothing to doe with those seducers that bring not the
true doctrine of Christ Iesus.</head>

<ab n="1">The Elder
vnto the elect Lady, and her children, whome I loue in the trueth:
and not I onely, but also all they that haue knowen
þe trueth:</ab>
<ab n="2">For the
trueths sake which dwelleth in vs, and shalbe with vs for
euer:</ab>
<ab n="3">Grace bee
with you, mercie, and peace from God the Father, and from the Lord
Iesus Christ, the Sonne of the Father in trueth and loue.</ab>
<ab n="4">I reioyced
greatly, that I found of thy children walking in trueth, as wee
haue receiued a commaundement from the Father.</ab>
<ab n="5">And now, I
beseech thee Lady, not as though I wrote a new commandement vnto
thee: but that which wee had from the beginning, that wee loue one
another.</ab>
<ab n="6">And this is
loue, that wee walke after his Commandements. This is the
Commandement, that as yee haue heard from the beginning, yee should
walke in it.</ab>
<ab n="7">For many
deceiuers are entred into the world, who confesse not that Iesus
Christ is come in the flesh. This is a deceiuer, and an
Antichrist.</ab>
<ab n="8">Looke to your
selues, that wee lose not those things which wee haue wrought, but
that we receiue a full reward.<note> Or, gained. Some copies reade, which yee haue gained, but that ye receiue, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Whosoeuer
transgresseth and abideth not in the doctrine of Christ, hath not
God: hee that abideth in the doctrine of Christ, he hath both the
Father and the Sonne.</ab>
<ab n="10">If there come any
vnto you, and bring not this doctrine, receiue him not into your
house, neither bid him, God speed.</ab>
<ab n="11">For hee that
biddeth him God speed, is partaker of his euill deeds.</ab>
<ab n="12">Hauing many things
to write vnto you, I would not write with paper and inke, but I
trust to come vnto you, and speake face to face, that our ioy may
be full.<note> Gr. mouth to mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The children of
thy elect sister greet thee. Amen.</ab>



</div>