<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Iehoahaz his wicked reigne. 3
Iehoahaz oppressed by Hazael, is relieued by prayer. 8 Ioash
succeedeth him. 10 His wicked reigne. 12 Ieroboam succeedeth him.
14 Elisha dying prophecieth to Ioash three victories ouer the
Syrians. 20 The Moabites inuading the land, Elishas bones raise vp
a dead man. 22 Hazael dying, Ioash getteth three victories ouer
Benhadad.</head>

<ab n="1">In the three and
twentieth yeere of Ioash the sonne of Ahaziah king of Iudah,
Iehoahaz the sonne of Iehu beganne to reigne ouer Israel in
Samaria, and reigned seuenteene yeeres.<note> Heb. in the twentieth yeere and third yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, and followed the sinnes
of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, which made Israel to sinne, he
departed not there from.<note> Heb. walked after.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And the
anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, and hee deliuered
them into the hand of Hazael king of Syria, and into the hand of
Benhadad the sonne of Hazael, all their dayes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iehoahaz
besought the Lord, and the Lord hearkened vnto him: for hee saw the
oppression of Israel, because the king of Syria oppressed
them.</ab>
<ab n="5">(And the Lord
gaue Israel a sauiour, so that they went out from vnder the hand of
the Syrians: and the children of Israel dwelt in their tents as
before-time.<note> Heb. as yesterday, and third day.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Neuerthelesse,
they departed not from the sinnes of the house of Ieroboam, who
made Israel sinne, but walked therein: and there remained the groue
also in Samaria.)<note> Heb. hee walked. , Heb. stood.</note></ab>

<fw>Elisha sick.</fw>
<ab n="7">Neither did he
leaue of the people to Iehoahaz, but fiftie horsemen, and tenne
charets, and tenne thousand footmen: for the king of Syria had
destroyed them, and had made them like the dust by
threshing.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Nowe the
rest of the actes of Iehoahaz, and all that he did, and his might,
are they not written in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of
Israel?</ab>
<ab n="9">And Iehoahaz
slept with his fathers, and they buried him in Samaria, and Ioash
his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ In the
thirty and seuenth yeere of Ioash king of Iudah, beganne Iehoash
the sonne of Iehoahaz to reigne ouer Israel in Samaria, and reigned
sixteene yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="11">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord; hee departed not from all
the sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who made Israel sinne:
but hee walked therein.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the rest of
the actes of Ioash, and all that hee did, and his might, wherewith
hee fought against Amaziah king of Iudah, are they not written in
the booke of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="13">And Ioash slept
with his fathers, and Ieroboam sate vpon his throne: and Ioash was
buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Nowe
Elisha was fallen sicke, of his sicknesse whereof he died, and
Ioash the king of Israel came downe vnto him, and wept ouer his
face, and said, O my father, my father, the charet of Israel, and
the horsemen thereof.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Elisha said
vnto him, Take bowe and arrowes. And he tooke vnto him bowe and
arrowes.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he said to
the king of Israel, Put thine hand vpon the bowe. And he put his
hand vpon it: and Elisha put his hands vpon the kings
hands.<note> Heb. make thine hand to ride.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And he sayd,
Open the window Eastward. And hee opened it. Then Elisha sayd,
Shoote. And he shot. And he said; The arrowe of the Lords
deliuerance, and the arrowe of deliuerance from Syria: for thou
shalt smite the Syrians in Aphek, till thou haue consumed
them.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he sayd,
Take the arrowes. And he tooke them. And hee said vnto the king of
Israel, Smite vpon the ground. And he smote thrise, and
stayed.</ab>

<fw>Elisha dieth.</fw>
<ab n="19">And the man of
God was wroth with him, and saide, Thou shouldest haue smitten fiue
or sixe times, then haddest thou smitten Syria till thou haddest
consumed it: whereas now thou shalt smite Syria but thrice.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
Elisha died, and they buried him: And the bands of the Moabites
inuaded the land at the comming in of the yeere.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it came to
passe as they were burying a man, that behold, they spyed a band of
men, and they cast the man into the sepulchre of Elisha: and when
the man was let downe, and touched the bones of Elisha, he reuiued,
and stood vp on his feete.<note> Heb. went downe. , Ecclus. 48.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ But
Hazael king of Syria, oppressed Israel all the dayes of
Iehoahaz.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the Lord was
gracious vnto them, and had compassion on them, and had respect
vnto them, because of his couenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob,
and would not destroy them, neither cast hee them from his presence
as yet.<note> Heb. face.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">So Hazael the
king of Syria dyed, and Benhadad his sonne reigned in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Iehoash the
sonne of Iehoahaz tooke againe out of the hand of Benhadad the
sonne of Hazael, the cities which he had taken out of the hand of
Iehoahaz his father, by warre: three times did Ioash beat him, and
recouered the cities of Israel.<note> Heb. returned and tooke.</note></ab>



</div>