<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-25-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-25-25b-1-Chronicles.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Ierusalem is besieged. 4 Zedekiah
taken, his sonnes slaine, his eyes put out. 8 Nabuzaradan defaceth
the city, carieth the remnant, except a few poore labourers, into
captiuitie, 13 Spoileth and carieth away the treasures. 18 The
Nobles are slaine at Riblah. 22 Gedaliah, who was set ouer them
that remained, being slaine, the rest flee into Egypt. 27
Euilmerodach aduanceth Iehoiachin in his court.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe in the ninth yeere of his reigne, in the tenth moneth, in the
tenth day of the moneth, that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came,
hee, and all his hoste, against Ierusalem, and pitched against it,
and they built fortes against it, round about.<note> Iere. 39.1. and 52.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the citie was
besieged vnto the eleuenth yeere of king Zedekiah.</ab>
<ab n="3">And on the ninth
day of the fourth moneth, the famine preuailed in the city, and
there was no bread for the people of the land.<note> Iere. 52.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And the
citie was broken vp, and all the men of warre fled by night, by the
way of the gate, betweene two walles, which is by the kings garden,
(now the Caldees were against the citie round about) and the King
went the way toward the plaine.</ab>

<fw>Zedekiah taken.</fw>
<ab n="5">And the army of
the Caldees pursued after the King, and ouertooke him in the
plaines of Iericho: and all his armie were scattered from
him.</ab>
<ab n="6">So they tooke the
King, and brought him vp to the King of Babylon, to Riblah, and
they gaue iudgement vpon him.<note> Hebr. spake iudgment with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they slew the
sonnes of Zedekiah before his eyes, and put out the eyes of
Zedekiah, and bound him with fetters of brasse, and carried him to
Babylon.<note> Heb. made blinde.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And in the
fifth moneth, on the seuenth day of the moneth (which is the
nineteenth yeere of King Nebuchadnezzar King of Babylon) came
Nebuzaradan captaine of the guard, a seruant of the king of
Babylon, vnto Ierusalem:<note> Or, chiefe Marshall.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And hee burnt the
house of the Lord, and the kings house, and all the houses of
Ierusalem, and euery great mans house burnt he with fire.</ab>
<ab n="10">And all the army
of the Caldees that were with the captaine of the guard, brake
downe the walles of Ierusalem round about.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now the rest of
the people that were left in the citie, and the fugitiues that fell
away to the king of Babylon, with the remnant of the multitude, did
Nebuzaradan the captaine of the guard cary away.<note> Hebr. fallen away.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But the captaine
of the guard left of the poore of the land, to be Uine-dressers,
and husbandmen.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the pillars
of brasse that were in the house of the Lord, and the bases, and
the brasen sea that was in the house of the Lord, did the Caldees
breake in pieces, and caried the brasse of them to
Babylon.<note> Chap, 20.17. iere. 27.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the pots,
and the shouels, and the snuffers, and the spoones, and all the
vessels of brasse wherewith they ministred, tooke they
away.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
fire-pans, and the bowles, &amp; such things as were of golde, in
golde, and of siluer, in siluer, the captaine of the guard tooke
away.</ab>
<ab n="16">The two pillars,
one sea, and the bases which Solomon had made for the house of the
Lord, the brasse of al these vessels was without
weight.<note> Hebr. the one sea.</note></ab>

<fw>Gedaliah slaine.</fw>
<ab n="17">The height of
the one pillar was eighteene cubits, and the chapiter vpon it was
brasse: and the height of the chapiter three cubites; and the
wreathen worke, and pomegranates vpon the chapiter round about, all
of brasse: and like vnto these had the second pillar with wreathen
worke.<note> 1 King. 7.15. iere. 52.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And the
captaine of the guard, tooke Seraiah the chiefe Priest, and
Zephaniah the second Priest, and the three keepers of the
doore.<note> Hebr. threshold.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And out of the
citie hee tooke an Officer, that was set ouer the men of warre, and
fiue men of them that were in the kings presence, which were found
in the citie, and the principall Scribe of the hoste, which
mustered the people of the land, and threescore men of the people
of the land that were found in the citie.<note> Or, Eunuch. , Hebr. saw the Kings face. , Or, scribe of the captaine of the hoste.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Nebuzaradan
captaine of the guard tooke these, and brought them to the king of
Babylon, to Riblah.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the King of
Babylon smote them, and slew them at Riblah in the land of Hamath:
so Iudah was caried away out of their land.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And as
for the people that remained in the land of Iudah, whom
Nebuchadnezzar King of Babylon had left, euen ouer them he made
Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam, the sonne of Shaphan,
ruler.<note> Iere. 40.5, 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And when all the
captaines of the armies, they, and their men, heard that the King
of Babylon had made Gedaliah gouernour, there came to Gedaliah to
Mispah, euen Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah, and Iohanan the sonne
of Careah, and Seraiah the sonne of Tanhumeth the Netophathite, and
Iaazaniah the sonne of a Maachathite, they, and their
men.<note> Iere. 40.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Gedaliah
sware to them and to their men, and said vnto them, Feare not to be
the seruants of the Caldees: dwell in the land, and serue the King
of Babylon; and it shall bee well with you.</ab>
<ab n="25">But it came to
passe in the seuenth moneth, that Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah,
the sonne of Elishama, of the seed royal, came, and ten men with
him, and smote Gedaliah, that he died, and the Iewes, and the
Caldees that were with him at Mizpah.<note> Hebr. of the kingdome. , Iere. 41.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And all the
people both small and great, and the captaines of the armies arose,
and came to Egypt: for they were afraid of the Caldees.</ab>

<fw>Adam, and his genealogies.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ And it
came to passe in the seuen and thirtieth yeere of the captiuitie of
Iehoiachin king of Iudah, in the twelfth moneth, on the seuen and
twentieth day of the moneth, that Euilmerodach king of Babylon, in
the yeere that he began to reigne, did lift vp the head of
Iehoiachin king of Iudah out of prison.</ab>

<fw>Adam, and his genealogies.</fw>
<ab n="28">And he spake
kindly to him, and set his throne aboue the throne of the kings
that were with him in Babylon,<note> Heb. good things with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And changed his
prison garments: and he did eate bread continually before him all
the dayes of his life.</ab>
<ab n="30">And his
allowance was a continuall allowance giuen him of the king, a dayly
rate for euery day, all the dayes of his life.</ab>



</div>