<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Ahaz his wicked reigne. 5 Ahaz
assailed by Rezin and Pekah, hireth Tiglath Pileser against them.
10 Ahaz sending a paterne of an Altar from Damascus to Urijah,
diuerteth the brasen Altar to his owne deuotion. 17 Hee spoileth
the Temple. 19 Hezekiah succeedeth him.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
seuenteenth yeere of Pekah the sonne of Remaliah, Ahaz the sonne of
Iotham King of Iudah began to reigne.<note> 2. Chron. 28.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Twentie yeeres
olde was Ahaz when hee began to reigne, and reigned sixteene yeeres
in Ierusalem, and did not that which was right in the sight of the
Lord his God, like Dauid his father:</ab>
<ab n="3">But hee walked in
the way of the kings of Israel, yea &amp; made his sonne to passe
through the fire, according to the abominations of the heathen,
whom the Lord cast out from before the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee
sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hils,
and vnder euery greene tree.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then Rezin
king of Syria, and Pekah sonne of Remaliah king of Israel, came vp
to Ierusalem to warre: and they besieged Ahaz, but could not
ouercome him.<note> Isa 7.1.</note></ab>

<fw>Ahaz his idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="6">At that time
Rezin king of Syria, recouered Elath to Syria, &amp; draue the
Iewes from Elath: and the Syrians came to Elath, and dwelt there
vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="7">So Ahaz sent
messengers to Tiglath Pileser king of Assyria, saying, I am thy
seruant, and thy sonne: come vp, and saue me out of the hand of the
king of Syria, and out of the hand of the king of Israel, which
rise vp against me.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Ahaz tooke
the siluer and gold that was found in the house of the Lord, and in
the treasures of the kings house, and sent it for a present to the
king of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the king of
Assyria hearkened vnto him: for the king of Assyria went vp against
Damascus, and tooke it, and caried the people of it captiue to Kir,
and slew Rezin.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And King
Ahaz went to Damascus, to meete Tiglath Pileser king of Assyria,
and saw an altar that was at Damascus: and king Ahaz sent to Uriiah
the Priest the fashion of the altar, and the paterne of it,
according to all the workemanship thereof.<note> Heb. Dammesek.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Uriiah the
Priest built an altar: according to all that king Ahaz had sent
from Damascus, so Uriiah the Priest made it, against king Ahaz came
from Damascus.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when the
king was come from Damascus, the King saw the altar: and the King
approched to the altar, and offered thereon.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he burnt his
burnt offering, and his meate offering, and powred his drinke
offering, and sprinkled the blood of his peace offerings vpon the
altar.<note> Heb. which were his.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And hee brought
also the brasen altar which was before the Lord, from the forefront
of the house, from betweene the altar and the house of the Lord,
and put it on the North side of the altar.</ab>
<ab n="15">And king Ahaz
commanded Uriiah the Priest, saying, Upon the great altar, burne
the morning burnt offering, and the euening meate offering, and the
Kings burnt sacrifice, and his meate offering, with the burnt
offering of all the people of the land, and their meate offering,
and their drinke offerings, and sprinkle vpon it all the blood of
the burnt offering, and all the blood of the sacrifice: and the
brasen altar shall be for me to enquire by.</ab>

<fw>Ahaz dieth.</fw>
<ab n="16">Thus did Uriiah
the Priest, according to all that king Ahaz commaunded.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And king
Ahaz cut off the borders of the bases, and remooued the lauer from
off them, and tooke downe the sea from off the brasen oxen that
were vnder it, and put it vpon a pauement of stones:</ab>
<ab n="18">And the couert
for the Sabbath that they had built in the house, and the kings
entry without, turned hee from the house of the Lord, for the king
of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Now the
rest of the actes of Ahaz, which he did, are they not written in
the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="20">And Ahaz slept
with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of
Dauid, and Hezekiah his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>



</div>