<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Iehoiakim, first subdued by
Nebuchadnezzar, then rebelling against him, procureth his owne
ruine. 5 Iehoiachin succeedeth him. 7 The King of Egypt is
vanquished by the King of Babylon. 8 Iehoiachin his euill reigne.
10 Ierusalem is taken and carried captiue into Babylon. 17 Zedekiah
is made King, and reigneth ill, vnto the vtter destruction of
Iudah.</head>

<ab n="1">In his dayes
Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came vp, and Iehoiakim became his
seruant three yeeres: then hee turned and rebelled against
him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord sent
against him bands of the Chaldees, and bandes of the Syrians, and
bandes of the Moabites, and bands of the children of Ammon, and
sent them against Iudah to destroy it, according to the word of the
Lord, which hee spake by his seruants the Prophets.<note> Chap.20.17. and 23.27. , Heb. by the hand of.</note></ab>

<fw>Ierusalem is besieged.</fw>
<ab n="3">Surely at the
commandement of the Lord came this vpon Iudah, to remooue them out
of his sight, for the sinnes of Manasseh, according to all that he
did:</ab>
<ab n="4">And also for the
innocent blood that hee shedde: (for hee filled Ierusalem with
innocent blood) which the Lord would not pardon.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Nowe the
rest of the actes of Iehoiakim, and all that he did, are they not
written in the booke of the Chronicles of the Kings of
Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="6">So Iehoiakim
slept with his fathers: and Iehoiachin his sonne reigned in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the king of
Egypt came not againe any more out of his land: for the King of
Babylon had taken from the riuer of Egypt, vnto the riuer
Euphrates, all that pertained to the King of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Iehoiachin
was eighteene yeres old when he began to reigne, &amp; he reigned
in Ierusalem three moneths: &amp; his mothers name was Nehushta the
daughter of Elnathan, of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, according to all that his
father had done.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ At that
time the seruants of Nebuchadnezzar King of Babylon came vp against
Ierusalem, and the citie was besieged.<note> Dan. 1.1. , Heb. came into siege.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And
Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came against the citie, and his
seruants did besiege it.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Iehoiachin
the King of Iudah went out to the king of Babylon, hee, and his
mother, and his seruants, and his princes, and his officers: and
the king of Babylon tooke him in the eight yeere of his
reigne.<note> Or, Eunuches.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And hee caried
out thence all the treasures of the house of the Lord, and the
treasure of the kings house, and cut in pieces all the vessels of
gold which Solomon King of Israel had made in the Temple of the
Lord, as the Lord had said.<note> Chap. 20.17. esa. 39.6</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And hee caried
away all Ierusalem, and all the princes, &amp; all the mighty men
of valour, euen tenne thousand captiues, and all the craftsmen, and
smiths: none remained, saue the poorest sort of the people of the
land.</ab>

<fw>Ierusalem is besieged.</fw>
<ab n="15">And he caried
away Iehoiachin to Babylon, and the kings mother, and the kings
wiues, and his officers, and the mighty of the land, those caried
hee into captiuitie, from Ierusalem to Babylon.<note> 2. Chron. 36.10. esth. 2.6. , Or, Eunuches.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And all the men
of might, euen seuen thousand, and craftesmen, &amp; smiths a
thousand, all that were strong and apt for warre, euen them the
king of Babylon brought captiue to Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
king of Babylon made Mattaniah his fathers brother king in his
stead, and changed his name to Zedekiah.<note> Iere. 37.1 and 52.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Zedekiah was
twentie and one yeeres olde when hee began to reigne, and he
reigned eleuen yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was
Hamutal, the daughter of Ieremiah of Libnah.</ab>
<ab n="19">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, according to all that
Iehoiachin had done.</ab>
<ab n="20">For through the
anger of the Lord it came to passe in Ierusalem and Iudah, vntill
he had cast them out from his presence, that Zedekiah rebelled
against the king of Babylon.</ab>



</div>