<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Naaman, by the report of a captiue
mayd, is sent to Samaria to be cured of his leprosie. 8 Elisha,
sending him to Iordan, cureth him. 15 He refusing Naamans gifts,
granteth him some of the earth. 20 Gehazi, abusing his masters name
vnto Naaman, is smitten with leprosie.</head>


<fw>Naaman leprous.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now Naaman
captaine of the host of the king of Syria, was a great man with his
master, and honourable, because by him the Lord had giuen
deliuerance vnto Syria: He was also a mighty man in valour, but he
was a leper.<note> Hebr. before. , Or, gracious. Hebr. lifted vp, or accepted in countenance. , Or, victory.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Syrians
had gone out by companies, and had brought away captiue out of the
land of Israel a litle maid, &amp; she waited on Naamans
wife.<note> Hebr. was before.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And shee saide
vnto her mistresse, Would God my lord were with the Prophet that is
in Samaria, for hee would recouer him of his leprosie.<note> Hebr. before. , Hebr. gather in.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And one went in,
and tolde his lord, saying, Thus and thus said the mayd that is of
the land of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the king of
Syria said, Goe to, Goe, and I will send a letter vnto the king of
Israel. And hee departed, and tooke with him ten talents of siluer,
and sixe thousand pieces of gold, and ten changes of
raiment.<note> Hebr. in his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And hee brought
the letter to the king of Israel, saying, Now when this letter is
come vnto thee, behold, I haue therewith sent Naaman my seruant to
thee, that thou mayest recouer him of his leprosie.</ab>
<ab n="7">And it came to
passe when the king of Israel had read the letter, that he rent his
clothes, and said, Am I God, to kill and to make aliue, that this
man doeth send vnto me, to recouer a man of his leprosie? Wherefore
consider, I pray you, and see how he seeketh a quarrell against
me.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And it was
so when Elisha the man of God had heard, that the king of Israel
had rent his clothes, that he sent to the king, saying, Wherefore
hast thou rent thy clothes? Let him come now to mee, and he shall
know that there is a Prophet in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="9">So Naaman came
with his horses, and with his charet, and stood at the doore of the
house of Elisha.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Elisha sent a
messenger vnto him, saying, Goe and wash in Iordane seuen times,
and thy flesh shall come againe to thee, and thou shalt be
cleane.</ab>

<fw>Naaman clensed.</fw>
<ab n="11">But Naaman was
wroth, and went away, and saide, Beholde, I thought, He will surely
come out to me and stand, and call on the Name of the Lord his God,
and strike his hand ouer the place, and recouer the
leper.<note> Hebr. said. Or, I said with my selfe, He will surely come out &amp;c. , Hebr. mooue vp and downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Are not Abana and
Pharpar, riuers of Damascus, better then all the waters of Israel?
May I not wash in them, and be cleane? So he turned, and went away
in a rage.<note> Or, Amana.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And his seruants
came neere and spake vnto him, and said, My father, If the Prophet
had bid thee do some great thing, wouldest thou not haue done it?
How much rather then, when hee saith to thee, Wash and be
cleane?</ab>
<ab n="14">Then went he
downe, and dipped himselfe seuen times in Iordan, according to the
saying of the man of God: and his flesh came againe like vnto the
flesh of a litle childe, and he was cleane.<note> Luke 4. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And he
returned to the man of God, he and all his company, and came, and
stood before him: and he said, Behold, now I know that there is no
God in all the earth, but in Israel: now therefore, I pray thee,
take a blessing of thy seruant.</ab>
<ab n="16">But he said, As
the Lord liueth, before whom I stand, I will receiue none: And hee
vrged him to take it, but he refused.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Naaman said,
Shall there not then, I pray thee, be giuen to thy seruant two
mules burden of earth? for thy seruant wil henceforth offer neither
burnt offering, nor sacrifice vnto other gods, but vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">In this thing the
Lord pardon thy seruant, that when my master goeth into the house
of Rimmon to worship there, and hee leaneth on my hand, and I bow
myselfe in the house of Rimmon: when I bow downe my selfe in the
house of Rimmon, the Lord pardon thy seruant in this thing.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he said vnto
him, Go in peace. So he departed from him, a litle way.<note> Hebr. a litle piece of ground.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ But Gehazi
the seruant of Elisha the man of God, said, Behold, my master hath
spared Naaman this Syrian, in not receiuing at his hands that which
hee brought: but as the Lord liueth, I wil runne after him, and
take somewhat of him.</ab>
<ab n="21">So Gehazi
followed after Naaman: and when Naaman saw him running after him,
hee lighted downe from the charet to meet him, and said, Is all
well?<note> Hebr. Is there peace?</note></ab>

<fw>Gehazi leprous.</fw>
<ab n="22">And he said, All
is well: my master hath sent me, saying, Behold, euen now there be
come to mee from mount Ephraim two yong men, of the sonnes of the
Prophets: Giue them, I pray thee, a talent of siluer, and two
changes of garments.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Naaman said,
Bee content, take two talents: and hee vrged him, and bound two
talents of siluer in two bags, with two changes of garments, and
layde them vpon two of his seruants, and they bare them before
him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And when he came
to the towre, he tooke them from their hand, and bestowed them in
the house, and hee let the men goe, and they departed.<note> Or, secret place.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But he went in,
and stood before his master: and Elisha said vnto him, Whence
commest thou, Gehazi? And hee said, Thy seruant went no
whither.<note> Hebr. Not hither or thither.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And he said vnto
him, Went not mine heart with thee, when the man turned againe from
his charet to meete thee? Is it a time to receiue money, and to
receiue garments, and Oliue yards, and Uineyards, and sheepe, and
oxen, and men seruants, and mayd seruants?</ab>
<ab n="27">The leprosie
therefore of Naaman shall cleaue vnto thee, and vnto thy seede for
euer: And hee went out from his presence a leper as white as
snow.</ab>



</div>