<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Iosiah his good reigne. 3 He
taketh care for the repaire of the Temple. 8 Hilkiah hauing found a
booke of the Lawe, Iosiah sendeth to Huldah to enquire of the Lord.
15 Huldah prophesieth destruction of Ierusalem, but respite thereof
in Iosiahs time.</head>

<ab n="1">Iosiah was eight
yeeres old when hee beganne to reigne, and hee reigned thirtie and
one yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was Iedidah, the
daughter of Adaiah of Boscath.<note> 2. Chron. 34.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he did that
which was right in the sight of the Lord, and walked in all the
wayes of Dauid his father, and turned not aside to the right hand,
or to the left.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And it
came to passe in the eighteenth yeere of king Iosiah, that the king
sent Shaphan the sonne of Azaliah, the sonne of Meshullam the
Scribe to the house of the Lord, saying,</ab>
<ab n="4">Goe vp to Hilkiah
the high priest, that he may summe the siluer which is brought into
the house of the Lord, which the keepers of the doore haue gathered
of the people.<note> Heb. threshold.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And let them
deliuer it into the hand of the doers of the worke, that haue the
ouersight of the house of the Lord: and let them giue it to the
doers of the worke, which is in the house of the Lord, to repaire
the breaches of the house,</ab>
<ab n="6">Unto carpenters,
and builders, and masons, and to buy timber and hewen stone, to
repaire the house.</ab>
<ab n="7">Howbeit, there
was no reckoning made with them, of the money that was deliuered
into their hand, because they dealt faithfully.</ab>

<fw>The Law found, and read openly.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ And
Hilkiah the high Priest said vnto Shaphan the Scribe, I haue found
the booke of the Law in the house of the Lord. And Hilkiah gaue the
booke to Shaphan, and he read it.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Shaphan the
Scribe came to the king, and brought the king word againe, and
said, Thy seruants haue gathered the money that was found in the
house, and haue deliuered it into the hand of them that doe the
worke, that haue the ouersight of the house of the
Lord.<note> Hebr. melted.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Shaphan the
Scribe shewed the king, saying, Hilkiah the Priest hath deliuered
mee a booke: and Shaphan read it before the king.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it came to
passe when the king had heard the words of the booke of the Law,
that he rent his clothes.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the king
commanded Hilkiah the Priest, and Ahikam the sonne of Shaphan, and
Achbor the sonne of Michaiah, and Shaphan the Scribe, and Asahiah a
seruant of the Kings, saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Goe yee, enquire
of the Lord for me, and for the people, and for all Iudah,
concerning the wordes of this booke that is found: for great is the
wrath of the Lord that is kindled against vs, because our fathers
haue not hearkened vnto the woordes of this booke, to doe according
vnto all that which is written concerning vs.</ab>
<ab n="14">So Hilkiah the
Priest, and Ahikam, and Achbor, and Shaphan, and Asahiah, went vnto
Huldah the Prophetesse, the wife of Shallum the sonne of Tikuah,
the sonne of Harhas, keeper of the wardrobe: now she dwelt in
Ierusalem in the colledge: And they communed with her.<note> Hebr. garments. , Or, in the second part.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And she
said vnto them, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Tell the man
that sent you to me;</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus saith the
Lord, Behold, I will bring euill vpon this place, and vpon the
inhabitants thereof, euen all the words of the booke which the king
of Iudah hath read.</ab>
<ab n="17">Because they
haue forsaken me, and haue burnt incense vnto other gods, that they
might prouoke mee to anger with all the woorkes of their handes:
therefore my wrath shall bee kindled against this place, and shall
not be quenched.</ab>

<fw>The Law found, and read openly.</fw>
<ab n="18">But to the king
of Iudah which sent you to enquire of the Lord, Thus shall yee say
to him, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, as touching the woordes
which thou hast heard:</ab>
<ab n="19">Because thine
heart was tender, and thou hast humbled thy selfe before the Lord,
when thou heardest what I spake against this place, and against the
inhabitants thereof, that they should become a desolation and a
curse, and hast rent thy cloathes, and wept before me; I also haue
heard thee, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold
therefore, I will gather thee vnto thy fathers, and thou shalt be
gathered into thy graue in peace, and thine eyes shal not see all
the euil which I will bring vpon this place. And they brought the
king word againe.</ab>



</div>