<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Manasseh his reigne. 3 His great
idolatrie. 10 His wickednesse causeth prophecies against Iudah. 17
Amon succeedeth him. 19 Amons wicked reigne. 23 Hee being slaine by
his seruants, and those murderers slaine by the people, Iosiah is
made King.</head>

<ab n="1">Manasseh was
twelue yeres olde when hee beganne to reigne, and reigned fiftie
and fiue yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was
Hephzibah.<note> 2. Chron. 33.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, after the abominations of
the heathen, whom the Lord cast out before the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">For he built vp
againe the high places, which Hezekiah his father had destroyed,
and hee reared vp altars for Baal, and made a groue, as did Ahab
king of Israel, and worshipped all the hoste of heauen, and serued
them.<note> Cha. 18.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And he built
altars in the house of the Lord, of which the Lord sayd, In
Ierusalem will I put my Name.<note> Iere. 32.34. , 2. Sam. 7.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And he built
altars for all the host of heauen, in the two courts of the house
of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he made his
sonne passe thorow the fire, and obserued times, and vsed
enchantments, and dealt with familiar spirits, and wizards: he
wrought much wickednesse in the sight of the Lord, to prouoke him
to anger.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he set a
grauen image of the groue that he had made, in the house, of which
the Lord said to Dauid, and to Solomon his sonne, In this house and
in Ierusalem, which I haue chosen out of all tribes of Israel, wil
I put my Name for euer:<note> 1. King. 8.29. and 9.3. chap. 23.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Neither will I
make the feete of Israel mooue any more out of the land, which I
gaue their fathers: onely if they will obserue to doe according to
all that I haue commanded them, and according to all the Law, that
my seruant Moses commanded them.</ab>
<ab n="9">But they
hearkened not: and Manasseh seduced them to doe more euill then did
the nations, whome the Lord destroyed before the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
Lord spake by his seruants the Prophets, saying,</ab>

<fw>Manasseh dieth.</fw>
<ab n="11">Because Manasseh
king of Iudah hath done these abominations, and hath done wickedly
aboue all that the Amorites did, which were before him, and hath
made Iudah also to sinne with his idoles:<note> Iere. 15.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God of Israel, Behold, I am bringing such euill vpon
Ierusalem and Iudah, that whosoeuer heareth of it, both his eares
shall tingle.<note> 1 Sam. 3.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I will
stretch ouer Ierusalem the line of Samaria, and the plummet of the
house of Ahab: and I will wipe Ierusalem as a man wipeth a dish,
wiping it and turning it vpside downe.<note> Heb. he wipeth and turneth it vpon the face thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I will
forsake the remnant of mine inheritance, and deliuer them into the
hand of their enemies, and they shall become a pray and a spoile to
all their enemies,</ab>
<ab n="15">Because they
haue done that which was euill in my sight, and haue prouoked me to
anger since the day their fathers came forth out of Egypt, euen
vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="16">Moreouer,
Manasseh shed innocent blood very much, till he had filled
Ierusalem from one end to another, beside his sinne wherwith he
made Iudah to sinne, in doing that which was euill in the sight of
the Lord.<note> Heb. from mouth to mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Now the
rest of the actes of Manasseh, and all that he did, and his sinne
that he sinned, are they not written in the booke of the Chronicles
of the kings of Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="18">And Manasseh
slept with his fathers, and was buried in the garden of his owne
house, in the garden of Uzza: and Amon his sonne reigned in his
stead.<note> 2. Chron. 33.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Amon was
twentie and two yeres old when he began to reigne, and he reigned
two yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was Meshullemeth, the
daughter of Haruz of Iotbah.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, as his father Manasseh
did.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he walked in
all the wayes that his father walked in, and serued the idoles that
his father serued, and worshipped them:</ab>
<ab n="22">And he forsooke
the Lord God of his fathers, and walked not in the way of the
Lord.</ab>

<fw>Amon slaine.</fw>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
seruants of Amon conspired against him, and slew the king in his
owne house.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the people
of the land slew al them that had conspired against king Amon, and
the people of the land made Iosiah his sonne king in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="25">Now the rest of
the acts of Amon, which he did, are they not written in the booke
of the chronicles of the kings of Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="26">And he was
buried in his sepulchre, in the garden of Uzza, and Iosiah his
sonne reigned in his stead.<note> Mat. 1.10 called Iosias.</note></ab>



</div>