<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Elisha multiplieth the widowes
oyle. 8 Hee giueth a sonne to the good Shunammite. 18 Hee raiseth
againe her dead sonne. 38 At Gilgal hee healeth the deadly pottage.
42 Hee satisfieth an hundred men with twentie loaues.</head>

<ab n="1">Now there cryed a
certaine woman of the wiues of the sonnes of the Prophets vnto
Elisha, saying, Thy seruant my husband is dead, and thou knowest
that thy seruant did feare the Lord: and the creditour is come to
take vnto him my two sonnes to be bondmen.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Elisha said
vnto her, What shall I doe for thee? Tell mee, what hast thou in
the house? And shee sayd, Thine handmaid hath not any thing in the
house, saue a pot of oyle.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then hee said,
Goe, borrow thee vessels abroad, of all thy neighbours; euen emptie
vessels, borrow not a few.<note> Or, scant not.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when thou art
come in, thou shalt shut the doore vpon thee, and vpon thy sonnes,
and shalt powre out into all those vessels, and thou shalt set
aside that which is full.</ab>
<ab n="5">So shee went from
him, and shut the doore vpon her, &amp; vpon her sonnes: who
brought the vessels to her, and shee powred out.</ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe, when the vessels were full, that shee said vnto her sonne,
Bring me yet a vessell. And hee said vnto her, There is not a
vessel more. And the oyle stayed.</ab>

<fw>Elisha, and the Shunammite.</fw>
<ab n="7">Then she came, and
told the man of God: and he said, Goe, sell the oyle, and pay thy
debt, and liue thou and thy children of the rest.<note> Or, creditour.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And it fell
on a day, that Elisha passed to Shunem, where was a great woman;
and shee constrained him to eate bread: And so it was, that as oft
as he passed by, hee turned in thither to eate bread.<note> Heb. there was a day. , Heb. laid hold on him.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And shee said vnto
her husband, Behold now, I perceiue that this is an holy man of
God, which passeth by vs continually.</ab>
<ab n="10">Let vs make a
litle chamber, I pray thee, on the wall, and let vs set for him
there a bed, and a table, and a stoole, and a candlesticke: and it
shall be when he commeth to vs, that hee shall turne in
thither.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it fell on a
day that hee came thither, and hee turned into the chamber, and lay
there.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he said to
Gehazi his seruant, Call this Shunammite. And when hee had called
her, she stood before him.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he said vnto
him, Say, now vnto her, Behold, thou hast beene carefull for vs
with all this care; What is to be done for thee? Wouldest thou be
spoken for to the king, or to the captaine of the hoste? And she
answered, I dwell among mine owne people.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he said, What
then is to bee done for her? And Gehazi answered, Uerily she hath
no child, and her husband is old.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he said, Call
her. And when he had called her, she stood in the doore.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he said,
About this season, according to the time of life, thou shalt
imbrace a sonne. And she said, Nay my lord, thou man of God, doe
not lie vnto thine handmaid.<note> Gen. 18. 10. , Heb. set time.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the woman
conceiued, and bare a sonne at that season, that Elisha had said
vnto her, according to the time of life.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And when
the child was growen, it fell on a day that hee went out to his
father, to the reapers.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he said vnto
his father, My head, my head: and he said to a ladde, Carie him to
his mother.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when he had
taken him, and brought him to his mother, hee sate on her knees
till noone, and then died.</ab>

<fw>Elisha, and the Shunammite.</fw>
<ab n="21">And she went vp,
and laid him on the bed of the man of God, and shut the doore vpon
him, and went out.</ab>
<ab n="22">And she called
vnto her husband, and said, Send me, I pray thee, one of the yong
men, and one of the asses, that I may runne to the man of God, and
come againe.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he said,
Wherefore wilt thou goe to him to day? it is neither newe moone nor
Sabbath. And shee said, It shalbe well.<note> Heb. peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Then she sadled
an asse, and said to her seruant, Driue, and goe forward: slacke
not thy riding for mee, except I bid thee.<note> Heb. restraine not for me to ride.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">So she went, and
came vnto the man of God to mount Carmel: and it came to passe when
the man of God saw her afarre off, that hee said to Gehazi his
seruant, Behold, yonder is that Shunammite:</ab>
<ab n="26">Runne now, I pray
thee, to meet her, and say vnto her, Is it wel with thee? is it wel
with thy husband? is it wel with the child? And she answered, It is
well.</ab>
<ab n="27">And when shee
came to the man of God to the hill, shee caught him by the feet:
but Gehazi came neere to thrust her away. And the man of God saide,
Let her alone, for her soule is vexed within her: and the Lord hath
hid it from me, and hath not told me.<note> Heb. by his feete. , Heb. bitter</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Then shee said,
Did I desire a sonne of my Lord ? did I not say, Doe not deceiue
me?</ab>
<ab n="29">Then he said to
Gehazi, Gird vp thy loines, and take my staffe in thine hand, and
goe thy way: if thou meete any man, salute him not: and if any
salute thee, answere him not againe: and lay my staffe vpon the
face of the childe.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the mother of
the childe said, As the Lord liueth, and as thy soule liueth, I
will not leaue thee. And he arose, and followed her.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Gehazi passed
on before them, and laid the staffe vpon the face of the child, but
there was neither voyce, nor hearing: wherefore he went againe to
meete him, and tolde him, saying, The child is not
awaked.<note> Heb. attention.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And when Elisha
was come into the house, behold, the child was dead, and laid vpon
his bed.</ab>
<ab n="33">He went in
therefore, and shut the doore vpon them twaine, and prayed vnto the
Lord.</ab>

<fw>The dead raised.</fw>
<ab n="34">And he went vp,
and lay vpon the child, and put his mouth vpon his mouth, and his
eyes vpon his eyes, and his hands vpon his hands, and he stretched
himselfe vpon the child, and the flesh of the child waxed
warme.</ab>
<ab n="35">Then he returned,
and walked in the house to and fro, and went vp, and stretched
himselfe vpon him: and the child neesed seuen times, and the child
opened his eyes.<note> Heb. once hither, and once thither.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And hee called
Gehazi, and said, Call this Shunammite. So hee called her: and when
shee was come in vnto him, he said, Take vp thy sonne.</ab>
<ab n="37">Then she went in,
and fell at his feet, and bowed her selfe to the ground, and tooke
vp her sonne, and went out.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ And Elisha
came againe to Gilgal, and there was a dearth in the land, and the
sonnes of the Prophets were sitting before him: and hee said vnto
his seruant, Set on the great pot, and seethe pottage for the
sonnes of the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="39">And one went out
into the field to gather herbes, and found a wild vine, and
gathered thereof wilde gourds his lap full, and came and shred them
into the pot of pottage: for they knew them not.</ab>
<ab n="40">So they powred
out for the men to eat: and it came to passe as they were eating of
the pottage, that they cried out, and said, O thou man of God,
there is death in the pot. And they could not eate thereof.</ab>
<ab n="41">But he said, Then
bring meale. And he cast it into the pot: And he said, Powre out
for the people, that they may eat. And there was no harme in the
pot.<note> Hebr. euil thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">¶ And there
came a man from Baal-Shalisha, and brought the man of God bread of
the first fruits, twentie loaues of barley, and full eares of corne
in the huske thereof: and he said, Giue vnto the people, that they
may eate.<note> Or, in his scrip, or garment.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And his seruitour
saide, What should I set this before an hundred men? He said
againe, Giue the people, that they may eate: for thus saith the
Lord, They shall eate, and shall leaue thereof.<note> Iohn 6. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">So he set it
before them, and they did eate, and left thereof, according to the
word of the Lord.</ab>



</div>