<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah his good reigne. 4 He
destroyeth idolatrie, and prospereth. 9 Samaria is caried captiue
for their sins. 13 Sennacherib inuading Iudah, is pacified by a
tribute. 17 Rabshakeh sent by Sennacherib againe, reuileth
Hezekiah, and by blasphemous perswasions, solliciteth the people to
reuolt.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe in the third yere of Hoshea sonne of Elah king of Israel,
that Hezekiah the sonne of Ahaz king of Iudah, began to
reigne.<note> 2.Chron. 28. 27. and 29.1. hee is called Ezekias, Mat. 1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Twentie and fiue
yeeres old was he when hee began to reigne, and hee reigned twentie
and nine yeeres in Ierusalem: His mothers name also was Abi, the
daughter of Zachariah.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he did that
which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that
Dauid his father did.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ He
remooued the high places, and brake the images, and cut downe the
groues, and brake in pieces the brasen serpent that Moses had made:
for vnto those dayes the children of Israel did burne incense to
it: and he called it Nehushtan.<note> Heb. statues. , Numb. 21.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">He trusted in the
Lord God of Israel, so that after him was none like him among all
the kings of Iudah, nor any that were before him.</ab>
<ab n="6">For he claue to
the Lord, and departed not from following him, but kept his
commandements, which the Lord commanded Moses.<note> Heb. from after him.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the Lord was
with him, and hee prospered whithersoeuer hee went forth: and he
rebelled against the king of Assyria, and serued him not.</ab>
<ab n="8">He smote the
Philistines euen vnto Gaza, and the borders thereof, from the towre
of the watchmen to the fenced cities.<note> Heb. Azzah.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And it
came to passe in the fourth yeere of king Hezekiah, (which was the
seuenth yeere of Hoshea, sonne of Elah king of Israel) that
Shalmaneser king of Assyria came vp against Samaria, and besieged
it.<note> Cha.17.3</note></ab>

<fw>Samaria taken.</fw>
<ab n="10">And at the end
of three yeeres they tooke it: euen in the sixt yeere of Hezekiah
(that is the ninth yeere of Hoshea king of Israel) Samaria was
taken.<note> Cha.17.6</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the king of
Assyria did carie away Israel vnto Assyria, and put them in Halah
and in Habor by the riuer of Gozan, &amp; in the cities of the
Medes:</ab>
<ab n="12">Because they
obeyed not the voice of the Lord their God, but transgressed his
Couenant, and all that Moses the seruant of the Lord commanded, and
would not heare them, nor doe them.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Now in
the fourteenth yeere of king Hezekiah, did Sennacherib king of
Assyria come vp against all the fenced cities of Iudah, and tooke
them.<note> 2. Chron. 32.1. esa. 36.1. ecclu. 48.18. , Heb. Sanherib.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Hezekiah
king of Iudah sent to the king of Assyria to Lachish, saying, I
haue offended, returne from me: that which thou puttest on me, wil
I beare. And the king of Assyria appointed vnto Hezekiah king of
Iudah, three hundred talents of siluer, and thirtie talents of
gold.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Hezekiah
gaue him all the siluer that was found in the house of the Lord,
and in the treasures of the kings house.</ab>
<ab n="16">At that time did
Hezekiah cut off the gold from the doores of the temple of the
Lord, and from the pillars which Hezekiah king of Iudah had
ouerlaid, and gaue it to the king of Assyria.<note> Heb. them.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
king of Assyria sent Tartan and Rabsaris, and Rabshakeh, from
Lachish to king Hezekiah, with a great hoste against Ierusalem: and
they went vp, and came to Ierusalem: and when they were come vp,
they came and stood by the conduit of the vpper poole, which is in
the high way of the fullers field.<note> Heb. heauy</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And when they
had called to the king there came out to them Eliakim the sonne of
Helkiah, which was ouer the houshold, and Shebna the Scribe, and
Ioah the sonne of Asaph the Recorder.<note> Or, Secretarie.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Rabshakeh
said vnto them, Speake yee now to Hezekiah, Thus saith the great
king, the king of Assyria, What confidence is this wherein thou
trustest?</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou sayest,
(but they are but vaine words) I haue counsell and strength for the
warre: now on whom doest thou trust, that thou rebellest against
me?<note> Or, talkest. , Heb. word of the lips. , Or, but counsell and strength are for the war.</note></ab>

<fw>Rabshakehs outrage, and
blasphemie.</fw>
<ab n="21">Now behold, thou
trustest vpon the staffe of this bruised reed, euen vpon Egypt, on
which if a man leane, it will goe into his hand, and pierce it: so
is Pharaoh king of Egypt vnto all that trust on him.<note> Heb. trustest thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But if ye say
vnto me, We trust in the Lord our God: is not that hee whose high
places, and whose altars Hezekiah hath taken away, and hath said to
Iudah and Ierusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar in
Ierusalem?</ab>
<ab n="23">Now therefore, I
pray thee, giue pledges to my lord the king of Assyria, and I will
deliuer thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to
set riders vpon them.<note> Or, hostages.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">How then wilt
thou turne away the face of one captaine of the least of my masters
seruants, and put thy trust on Egypt for charets and for
horsemen?</ab>
<ab n="25">Am I now come vp
without the Lord against this place, to destroy it? The Lord sayd
to me, Goe vp against this land, and destroy it.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then said
Eliakim the sonne of Hilkiah, and Shebna, and Ioah, vnto Rabshakeh,
Speake, I pray thee, to thy seruants in the Syrian language, (for
wee vnderstand it) and talke not with vs in the Iewes language, in
the eares of the people that are on the wall.</ab>
<ab n="27">But Rabshakeh
sayd vnto them, Hath my master sent me to thy master, and to thee,
to speake these wordes? hath he not sent me to the men which sit on
the wall, that they may eate their owne doung, and drinke their
owne pisse with you?<note> Heb. the water of their feete?</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Then Rabshakeh
stood and cried with a loude voice in the Iewes language, and
spake, saying, Heare the word of the great king, the king of
Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="29">Thus sayth the
king, Let not Hezekiah deceiue you, for he shall not be able to
deliuer you out of his hand:</ab>
<ab n="30">Neither let
Hezekiah make you trust in the Lord, saying, The Lord will surely
deliuer vs, and this city shall not bee deliuered into the hand of
the king of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="31">Hearken not to
Hezekiah: for thus sayth the king of Assyria, Make an agreement
with me by a present, and come out to me, and then eate yee euery
man of his owne vine, and euery one of his figge tree, and drinke
yee euery one the waters of his cisterne:<note> Or, seeke my fauour. Heb. make with me a blessing. , Or, pit.</note></ab>

<fw>Rabshakehs outrage, and
blasphemie.</fw>
<ab n="32">Untill I come
and take you away to a land like your owne land, a land of corne
and wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of oile Oliue, and
of honie, that yee may liue, and not die: and hearken not vnto
Hezekiah, when hee perswadeth you, saying, The Lord will deliuer
vs.<note> Or, deceiueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Hath any of the
gods of the nations deliuered at all his land out of the hand of
the king of Assyria?</ab>
<ab n="34">Where are the
gods of Hamath, and of Arpad? where are the gods of Sepharuaim,
Hena, and Iuah? haue they deliuered Samaria out of mine
hand?</ab>
<ab n="35">Who are they
among all the gods of the countreys, that haue deliuered their
countrey out of mine hand, that the Lord should deliuer Ierusalem
out of mine hand?</ab>
<ab n="36">But the people
helde their peace, and answered him not a word: for the kings
commaundement was, saying, Answere him not.</ab>
<ab n="37">Then came
Eliakim the sonne of Hilkiah, which was ouer the houshold, and
Shebna the Scribe, and Ioah the sonne of Asaph the Recorder, to
Hezekiah with their clothes rent, and tolde him the words of
Rabshakeh.</ab>



</div>