<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-15-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Azariah his good reigne. 5 He
dying a Leper, Iotham succeedeth. 8 Zachariah, the last of Iehu his
generation, reigning ill, is slaine by Shallum. 13 Shallum reigning
a moneth, is slaine by Menahem. 16 Menahem strengtheneth himselfe
by Pul. 21 Pekahiah succeedeth him. 23 Pekahiah is slaine by Pekah.
27 Pekah is oppressed by Tiglath Pileser, and slaine by Hoshea. 32
Iothams good reigne. 36 Ahaz succeedeth him.</head>

<ab n="1">In the twenty and
seuenth yeere of Ieroboam king of Israel, began Azariah sonne of
Amaziah king of Iudah to reigne.</ab>
<ab n="2">Sixteene yeeres
old was he when he began to reigne, and he reigned two aud fifty
yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was Iecholiah of
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he did that
which was right in the sight of the Lord, according to all that his
father Amaziah had done;</ab>
<ab n="4">Saue that the
high places were not remoued: the people sacrificed, and burnt
incense still on the high places.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
Lord smote the king, so that hee was a Leper vnto the day of his
death, and dwelt in a seuerall house, and Iotham the kings sonne
was ouer the house, iudging the people of the land.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the rest of
the actes of Azariah, and all that hee did, are they not written in
the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="7">So Azariah slept
with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the city
of Dauid, and Iotham his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ In the
thirty and eight yeere of Azariah king of Iudah, did Zachariah the
sonne of Ieroboam reigne ouer Israel in Samaria sixe
moneths.</ab>

<fw>Shallum. Menahem.</fw>
<ab n="9">And hee did that
which was euil in the sight of the Lord, as his fathers had done:
he departed not from the sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who
made Israel to sinne.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Shallum the
sonne of Iabesh, conspired against him, and smote him before the
people, and slewe him, and reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the rest of
the actes of Zachariah, beholde, they are written in the booke of
the chronicles of the kings of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">This was the
word of the Lord which he spake vnto Iehu, saying, Thy sonnes shall
sit on the throne of Israel, vnto the fourth generation. And so it
came to passe.<note> Chap. 10. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Shallum
the sonne of Iabesh began to reigne in the nine and thirtieth yeere
of Uzziah king of Iudah, and he reigned a full moneth in
Samaria.<note> Matth.1. 9. called Ozias. , Hebr. a moneth of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For Menahem the
sonne of Gadi, went vp from Tirzah, and came to Samaria, and smote
Shallum the sonne of Iabesh, in Samaria, and slew him, and reigned
in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the rest of
the actes of Shallum, and the conspiracy which he made, behold,
they are written in the booke of the chronicles of the kings of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then
Menahem smote Tiphsah, and all that were therein, and the coasts
thereof from Tirzah: because they opened not to him, therfore he
smote it, and all the women therein that were with child, he ript
vp.</ab>
<ab n="17">In the nine and
thirtieth yeere of Azariah king of Iudah, began Menahem the sonne
of Gadi to reigne ouer Israel, and reigned tenne yeres in
Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord: hee departed not all his
dayes from the sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who made
Israel to sinne.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Pul the king
of Assyria came against the land: and Menahem gaue Pul a thousand
talents of siluer, that his hand might be with him, to confirm the
kingdome in his hand.<note> 1. Chron. 5.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Menahem
exacted the mony of Israel, euen of all the mightie men of wealth,
of each man fiftie shekels of siluer, to giue to the king of
Assyria: so the king of Assyria turned backe, and stayed not there
in the land.<note> Heb. caused to come forth.</note></ab>

<fw>Pekahiah. Pekah.</fw>
<ab n="21">¶ And the
rest of the acts of Menahem, and all that he did, are they not
written in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of
Israel?</ab>
<ab n="22">And Menahem
slept with his fathers, and Pekahiah his sonne reigned in his
stead.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ In the
fiftieth yere of Azariah king of Iudah, Pekahiah the sonne of
Menahem began to reigne ouer Israel in Samaria, and reigned two
yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="24">And he did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, hee departed not from the
sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who made Israel to
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="25">But Pekah the
sonne of Remaliah, a captaine of his, conspired against him, and
smote him in Samaria, in the palace of the kings house, with Argob,
and Arieh, and with him fiftie men of the Gileadites: and hee
killed him, and reigned in his roume.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the rest of
the actes of Pekahiah, and all that he did, beholde, they are
written in the booke of the chronicles of the kings of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ In the
two and fiftieth yeere of Azariah king of Iudah, Pekah the sonne of
Remaliah began to reigne ouer Israel in Samaria, and reigned
twentie yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, hee departed not from the
sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who made Israel to
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="29">In the dayes of
Pekah king of Israel, came Tiglath Pileser king of Assyria, and
tooke Iion, and Abel-Beth-maachah, and Ianoah, and Kedesh, and
Hazor, and Gilead, and Galilee, all the land of Naphtali, and
caried them captiue to Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Hoshea the
sonne of Elah, made a conspiracie against Pekah the sonne of
Remaliah, and smote him, and slew him, and reigned in his stead, in
the twentieth yeere of Iotham the sonne of Uzziah.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the rest of
the actes of Pekah, and all that he did, behold, they are written
in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ In the
second yeere of Pekah the sonne of Remaliah king of Israel, began
Iotham the sonne of Uzziah king of Iudah to reigne.<note> 2. Chron. 27.1.</note></ab>

<fw>Iothams death.</fw>
<ab n="33">Fiue and twentie
yeeres olde was he when he began to reigne, and hee reigned
sixteene yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was Ierusha, the
daughter of Zadok.</ab>
<ab n="34">And he did that
which was right in the sight of the Lord: hee did according to all
that his father Uzziah had done.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ Howbeit,
the high places were not remoued: the people sacrificed and burnt
incense still in the high places: He built the higher gate of the
house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ Now the
rest of the actes of Iotham, and all that hee did, are they not
written in the booke of the Chronicles of the kings of
Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="37">(In those dayes
the Lord began to send against Iudah, Rezin the king of Syria, and
Pekah the sonne of Remaliah)</ab>
<ab n="38">And Iotham slept
with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the citie of
Dauid his father, and Ahaz his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>




</div>