<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Elisha sendeth a yong Prophet with
instructions to annoint Iehu at Ramoth Gilead. 4 The Prophet hauing
done his message, flieth. 11 Iehu being made king by the souldiers,
killeth Ioram in the field of Naboth. 27 Ahaziah is slaine at Gur,
and buried at Ierusalem. 30 Proud Iezebel is throwen downe out of a
window, and eaten by dogs.</head>

<ab n="1">And Elisha the
Prophet called one of the children of the Prophets, and said vnto
him, Gird vp thy loines, and take this boxe of oile in thine hand,
and goe to Ramoth Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="2">And when thou
commest thither, looke out there Iehu the sonne of Iehoshaphat, the
sonne of Nimshi, and goe in, and make him arise vp from among his
brethren, and carie him to an inner chamber.<note> Heb. chamber in a chamber.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then take the boxe
of oile, and powre it on his head, and say, Thus saith the Lord, I
haue anointed thee king ouer Israel: then open the doore, and flee,
and tary not.<note> 1. King. 19.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ So the yong
man, euen the yong man the Prophet, went to Ramoth Gilead:</ab>
<ab n="5">And when hee came,
behold, the captaines of the host were sitting; and hee said, I
haue an errand to thee, O captaine: And Iehu said, Unto which of
all vs? And he said, To thee, O captaine.</ab>

<fw>Iehu annoynted.</fw>
<ab n="6">And hee arose, and
went into the house, and hee powred the oyle on his head, and said
vnto him, Thus sayth the Lord God of Israel, I haue anoynted thee
king ouer the people of the Lord, euen ouer Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thou shalt
smite the house of Ahab thy master, that I may auenge the blood of
my seruants the Prophets, and the blood of all the seruants of the
Lord, at the hand of Iezebel.<note> 1. Kings 21.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For the whole
house of Ahab shal perish, and I will cut off from Ahab, him that
pisseth against the wall, and him that is shut vp and left in
Israel.<note> 1.Kings 14.10. and 21.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And I will make
the house of Ahab, like the house of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat,
and like the house of Baasha the sonne of Ahiiah.<note> 1.Kings 14.10. and 21.22. , 1.Kings 16.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the dogges
shal eate Iezebel in the portion of Iezreel, and there shal be none
to burie her. And he opened the doore, and fled.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Then Iehu
came foorth to the seruants of his lord, and one said vnto him, Is
all well? wherefore came this madde fellow to thee? And he said
vnto them, Yee know the man, and his communication.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they said, It
is false, tell vs now: And hee sayde, Thus and thus spake he to me,
saying, Thus saith the Lord, I haue anoynted thee King ouer
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then they hasted,
and tooke euery man his garment, and put it vnder him on the top of
the staires, and blewe with trumpets, saying, Iehu is
king.<note> Heb. reigneth.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">So Iehu the sonne
of Iehoshaphat, the sonne of Nimshi, conspired against Ioram: (now
Ioram had kept Ramoth Gilead, hee, and all Israel, because of
Hazael king of Syria:</ab>
<ab n="15">But king Ioram
was returned to bee healed in Iezreel, of the wounds which the
Syrians had giuen him, when he fought with Hazael king of Syria.)
And Iehu said, If it be your minds, then let none goe forth nor
escape out of the citie, to goe to tell it in Iezreel.<note> Cha.8.29 , Heb. Iehoram. , Heb. smote , Heb. let no escaper goe, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">So Iehu rode in a
charet, and went to Iezreel, (for Ioram lay there:) and Ahaziah
king of Iudah was come downe to see Ioram.</ab>

<fw>Iehoram slaine.</fw>
<ab n="17">And there stood a
watchman on the towre in Iezreel, and hee spied the company of Iehu
as he came, and said, I see a companie. And Ioram sayd, Take an
horseman, and send to meete them, and let him say, Is it
peace?</ab>
<ab n="18">So there went one
on horsebacke to meete him, and said, Thus sayth the king, Is it
peace? And Iehu said, What hast thou to doe with peace? turne thee
behinde me. And the watchman tolde, saying, The messenger came to
them, but he commeth not againe.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then he sent out
a second on horsebacke, which came to them, and sayd, Thus sayth
the king, Is it peace? And Iehu answered, What hast thou to doe
with peace? turne thee behinde me.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the watchman
tolde, saying, He came euen vnto them, and commeth not againe: and
the driuing is like the driuing of Iehu the sonne of Nimshi; for he
driueth furiously.<note> Or, marching. , Heb. in madnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Ioram said,
Make readie. And his charet was made ready. And Ioram king of
Israel, and Ahaziah king of Iudah, went out, each in his charet,
and they went out against Iehu, and met him in the portion of
Naboth the Iezreelite.<note> Heb. bind. , Heb. found</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And it came to
passe when Ioram saw Iehu, that hee said, Is it peace, Iehu? And he
answered, What peace, so long as the whoredomes of thy mother
Iezebel, and her witchcrafts are so many?</ab>
<ab n="23">And Ioram turned
his hand, and fled, and said to Ahaziah, There is treachery, O
Ahaziah.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Iehu drew a
bowe with his full strength, and smote Iehoram betweene his armes,
and the arrow went out at his heart, and hee sunke downe in his
charet.<note> Heb. filled his hand with a bow. , Heb. bowed.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then said Iehu to
Bidkar his captaine, Take vp, and cast him in the portion of the
field of Naboth the Iezreelite: for remember, how that when I and
thou rode together after Ahab his father, the Lord laide this
burden vpon him:</ab>
<ab n="26">Surely I haue
seene yesterday the blood of Naboth, and the blood of his sonnes,
sayd the Lord, and I will requite thee in this plat, sayth the
Lord. Now therefore take and cast him into the plat of ground,
according to the word of the Lord.<note> 1.Kings 21.29. , Heb. bloods , Or, portion.</note></ab>

<fw>Iezebels death.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ But when
Ahaziah the king of Iudah saw this, hee fled by the way of the
garden house: and Iehu followed after him, and said, Smite him also
in the charet; and they did so, at the going vp to Gur, which is by
Ibleam: And hee fled to Megiddo, and died there.</ab>
<ab n="28">And his seruants
caried him in a charet to Ierusalem, and buried him in his
sepulchre with his fathers, in the citie of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="29">And in the
eleuenth yeere of Ioram the sonne of Ahab, began Ahaziah to reigne
ouer Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And when
Iehu was come to Iezreel, Iezebel heard of it, and shee painted her
face, and tyred her head, and looked out at a window.<note> Heb. put her eyes in painting.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And as Iehu
entred in at the gate, she said, Had Zimri peace, who slew his
master?</ab>
<ab n="32">And he lift vp
his face to the window, and said, Who is on my side, who? And there
looked out to him two or three Eunuches.<note> Or.chamberlaines.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And he said,
Throw her downe. So they threw her downe, and some of her blood was
sprinkled on the wall, and on the horses: and he trode her vnder
foote.</ab>
<ab n="34">And when he was
come in, hee did eate and drinke, and saide, Goe, see now this
cursed woman, and burie her: for she is a kings daughter.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they went to
burie her, but they found no more of her then the skul, and the
feete, &amp; the palmes of her hands.</ab>
<ab n="36">Wherefore they
came againe, and told him: and he said, This is the word of the
Lord, which he spake by his seruant Elijah the Tishbite, saying, In
the portion of Iezreel shall dogs eate the flesh of
Iezebel:<note> Heb. by the hand of. , 1.King. 21.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And the carkeise
of Iezebel shall be as doung vpon the face of the field in the
portion of Iezreel, so that they shall not say, This is
Iezebel.</ab>




</div>