<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-17-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Hoshea his wicked reigne. 3 Being
subdued by Shalmaneser, hee conspireth against him with So King of
Egypt. 5 Samaria for their sinnes, is captiuated. 24 The strange
nations, which were transplanted in Samaria, beeing plagued with
Lions, make a mixture of Religions.</head>

<ab n="1">In the twelfth
yeere of Ahaz, king of Iudah, began Hoshea the sonne of Elah to
reigne in Samaria, ouer Israel nine yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord, but not as the kings of
Israel that were before him.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Against
him came vp Shalmaneser king of Assyria, and Hoshea became his
seruant, and gaue him presents.<note> Hebr. rendred. , Or, tribute.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">An the king of
Assyria found conspiracie in Hoshea: for hee had sent messengers to
So king of Egypt, and brought no present to the king of Assyria, as
he had done yeere by yeere: therefore the king of Assyria shut him
vp, and bound him in prison.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then the
king of Assyria came vp thorowout all the land, and went vp to
Samaria, and besieged it three yeres.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ In the
ninth yeere of Hoshea, the king of Assyria tooke Samaria, and
caried Israel away into Assyria, and placed them in Halah, and in
Habor by the riuer of Gozan, and in the cities of the
Medes.<note> Chap. 18. 10.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels captiuitie.</fw>
<ab n="7">For so it was,
that the children of Israel had sinned against the Lord their God,
which had brought them vp out of the land of Egypt, from vnder the
hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and had feared other gods,</ab>
<ab n="8">And walked in the
statutes of the heathen, (whom the Lord cast out from before the
children of Israel) and of the kings of Israel, which they had
made.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the children
of Israel did secretly those things that were not right, against
the Lord their God: and they built them high places in all their
cities, from the tower of the watchmen, to the fenced city.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they set
them vp images, and groues in euery high hill, and vnder euery
greene tree.<note> Heb. statues.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And there they
burnt incense in all the high places, as did the heathen whom the
Lord caried away before them, and wrought wicked things to prouoke
the Lord to anger.</ab>
<ab n="12">For they serued
idoles, whereof the Lord had said vnto them, Yee shall not doe this
thing.<note> Deut.4. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Yet the Lord
testified against Israel, and against Iudah, by all the Prophets,
and by all the Seers, saying, Turne ye from your euill wayes, and
keepe my commandements, and my statutes, according to all the law
which I commanded your fathers, and which I sent to you by my
seruants the Prophets.<note> Heb. by the hand of all. , Ierem.18. 11. and 25. 5. &amp; 35.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Notwithstanding,
they would not heare, but hardened their neckes, like to the necke
of their fathers, that did not beleeue in the Lord their
God.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they
reiected his Statutes, and his Couenant that hee made with their
fathers, and his Testimonies which he testified against them, and
they followed vanitie, and became vaine, and went after the heathen
that were round about them, concerning whom the Lord had charged
them, that they should not doe like them.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they left
all the Commandements of the Lord their God, and made them molten
images, euen two calues, and made a groue, and worshipped all the
hoste of heauen, and serued Baal.<note> Exod.32. 8. 1.king. 12.28.</note></ab>

<fw>Lions in Samaria.</fw>
<ab n="17">And they caused
their sonnes and their daughters to passe through the fire, and
vsed diuination, and inchantments, and sold themselues to doe euill
in the sight of the Lord, to prouoke him to anger.</ab>
<ab n="18">Therefore the
Lord was very angry with Israel, and remoued them out of his sight,
there was none left, but the tribe of Iudah onely.</ab>
<ab n="19">Also Iudah kept
not the Commandements of the Lord their God, but walked in the
Statutes of Israel which they made.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord
reiected all the seed of Israel, and afflicted them, and deliuered
them into the hand of spoilers, vntill he had cast them out of his
sight.</ab>
<ab n="21">For he rent
Israel from the house of Dauid, and they made Ieroboam the sonne of
Nebat king, and Ieroboam draue Israel from following the Lord, and
made them sinne a great sinne.</ab>
<ab n="22">For the children
of Israel walked in al the sinnes of Ieroboam which he did, they
departed not from them:</ab>
<ab n="23">Untill the Lord
remoued Israel out of his sight, as hee had said by all his
seruants the Prophets: so was Israel caried away out of their owne
land to Assyria, vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
King of Assyria brought men from Babylon, and from Cuthah, and from
Aua, and from Hamath, and from Sepharuaim, and placed them in the
cities of Samaria, in stead of the children of Israel; and they
possessed Samaria, and dwelt in the cities thereof.</ab>
<ab n="25">And so it was at
the beginning of their dwelling there, that they feared not the
Lord; therefore the Lord sent Lions among them, which slew some of
them.</ab>
<ab n="26">Wherefore they
spake to the king of Assyria, saying, The nations which thou hast
remoued, and placed in the cities of Samaria, know not the maner of
the God of the land: therfore he hath sent Lions among them, and
beholde, they slay them, because they know not the maner of the God
of the land.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then the king of
Assyria commanded, saying, Carie thither one of the priests whom ye
brought from thence, and let them goe and dwell there, and let him
teach them the maner of the God of the land.</ab>

<fw>Diuers religions.</fw>
<ab n="28">Then one of the
priests whom they had caried away from Samaria, came and dwelt in
Bethel, and taught them howe they should feare the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">Howbeit, euery
nation made gods of their owne, and put them in the houses of the
high places which the Samaritanes had made, euery nation in their
cities wherein they dwelt:</ab>
<ab n="30">And the men of
Babylon made Succoth-Benoth, and the men of Cuth made Nergal, and
the men of Hamath made Ashima:</ab>
<ab n="31">And the Auites
made Nibhaz and Tartak; and the Sepharuites burnt their children in
fire to Adrammelech, and Anammelech, the gods of
Sepharuaim.</ab>
<ab n="32">So they feared
the Lord, and made vnto themselues of the lowest of them priests of
the high places, which sacrificed for them in the houses of the
high places.</ab>
<ab n="33">They feared the
Lord, and serued their owne gods, after the maner of the nations
whom they caried away from thence.<note> Sophan.1. 5. , Or, who caried them away from thence.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Unto this day
they doe after the former maners: they feare not the Lord, neither
doe they after their Statutes, or after their Ordinances, or after
the Law and Commaundement which the Lord commaunded the children of
Iacob, whom hee named Israel,<note> Gen.32. 28. 1. king. 18.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">With whom the
Lord had made a Couenant, and charged them, saying, Yee shall not
feare other gods, nor bow your selues to them, nor serue them, nor
sacrifice to them:<note> Iudg.6. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">But the Lord,
who brought you vp out of the land of Egypt, with great power, and
a stretched out arme, him shall ye feare, and him shall ye worship,
and to him shall ye doe sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the
Statutes, and the Ordinances, and the Law, and the Commandement
which he wrote for you, ye shall obserue to doe for euermore, and
ye shall not feare other gods:</ab>
<ab n="38">And the Couenant
that I haue made with you, ye shall no forget, neither shall ye
feare other gods.</ab>
<ab n="39">But the Lord
your God yee shall feare, and he shall deliuer you out of the hand
of all your enemies.</ab>
<ab n="40">Howbeit, they
did not hearken, but they did after their former maner.</ab>

<fw>Hezekiah king.</fw>
<ab n="41">So these nations
feared the Lord, and serued their grauen images, both their
children, and their childrens children: as did their fathers, so
doe they vnto this day.</ab>



</div>