<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Moab rebelleth. 2 Ahaziah, sending
to Baalzebub, hath his iudgement by Eliiah. 5 Eliiah twise bringeth
fire from heauen vpon them whom Ahaziah sent to apprehend him. 13
He pitieth the third captaine, and incouraged by an Angel, telleth
the King of his death. 17 Iehoram succeedeth Ahaziah.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Moab rebelled
against Israel, after the death of Ahab.<note> Chap.3. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Ahaziah fel
downe thorow a lattesse in his vpper chamber that was in Samaria,
and was sicke: and he sent messengers, and said vnto them, Goe,
enquire of Baalzebub the god of Ekron, whether I shal recouer of
this disease.</ab>
<ab n="3">But the Angel of
the Lord said to Eliiah the Tishbite, Arise, goe vp to meete the
messengers of the king of Samaria, and say vnto them, Is it not
because there is not a God in Israel, that ye goe to enquire of
Baalzebub the god of Ekron?</ab>
<ab n="4">Now therefore,
thus sayeth the Lord, Thou shalt not come downe from that bed on
which thou art gone vp, but shalt surely die. And Eliiah
departed.<note> Heb. the bed, whither thou art gone vp, thou shalt not come downe from it.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And when
the messengers turned backe vnto him, he said vnto them, Why are ye
now turned backe?</ab>

<fw>Fire from heauen.</fw>
<ab n="6">And they said vnto
him, There came a man vp to meet vs, and said vnto vs, Goe, turne
againe vnto the king that sent you, and say vnto him, Thus saith
the Lord, Is it not because there is not a God in Israel, that thou
sendest to enquire of Baalzebub the god of Ekron? therefore thou
shalt not come downe from that bedde on which thou art gone vp, but
shalt surely die.</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee said vnto
them, What maner of man was he which came vp to meet you, and told
you these words?<note> Heb. what was the maner of the man?</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And they answered
him, He was an hairy man, and girt with a girdle of leather about
his loynes: and he said, It is Eliiah the Tishbite.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then the King sent
vnto him a captaine of fiftie, with his fiftie: and he went vp to
him, (and behold, he sate on the top of an hill) and hee spake vnto
him, Thou man of God, the king hath said, Come downe.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Eliiah
answered, and said to the captaine of fiftie, If I be a man of God,
then let fire come downe from heauen, and consume thee and thy
fiftie. And there came downe fire from heauen, and consumed him and
his fiftie.</ab>
<ab n="11">Againe also hee
sent vnto him another captaine of fiftie, with his fiftie: And hee
answered, and said vnto him, O man of God, Thus hath the king said,
Come downe quickly.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Eliiah
answered, and saide vnto them, If I be a man of God, let fire come
downe from heauen, and consume thee, and thy fiftie. And the fire
of God came downe from heauen, and consumed him, and his
fiftie.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And hee
sent againe a captaine of the third fiftie, with his fiftie: and
the third captaine of fiftie went vp, and came and fell on his
knees before Eliiah, and besought him, and saide vnto him, Oh man
of God, I pray thee, let my life, and the life of these fiftie thy
seruants, be precious in thy sight.<note> Hebr. bowed.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, there
came fire downe from heauen, and burnt vp the two captaines of the
former fifties, with their fifties: Therefore let my life now be
precious in thy sight.</ab>

<fw>Ahaziah dieth.</fw>
<ab n="15">And the Angel of
the Lord said vnto Elijah, Goe downe with him, be not afraid of
him. And he arose, and went downe with him vnto the king.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he said vnto
him, Thus saith the Lord, Forasmuch as thou hast sent messengers to
enquire of Baalzebub the god of Ekron (is it not because there is
no God in Israel, to enquire of his word?) therefore thou shalt not
come downe off that bed on which thou art gone vp, but shalt surely
die.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ So he
died, according to the worde of the Lord which Eliiah had spoken:
and Iehoram reigned in his stead, in the second yeere of Iehoram
the sonne of Iehoshaphat king of Iudah, because he had no
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now the rest of
the actes of Ahaziah, which hee did, are they not written in the
booke of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?</ab>



</div>