<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah mourning, sendeth to Esay
to pray for them. 6 Esay comforteth them. 8 Sennacherib going to
encounter Tirhakah, sendeth a blasphemous letter to Hezekiah. 14
Hezekiah his prayer. 20 Esay his prophecie of the pride and
destruction of Sennacherib, and the good of Zion. 35 An Angel
slayeth the Assyrians. 36 Sennacherib is slaine at Nineueh by his
owne sonnes.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe when King Hezekiah heard it, that hee rent his clothes, and
couered himselfe with sackecloth, and went into the house of the
Lord.<note> Esai 37.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee sent
Eliakim, which was ouer the houshold, and Shebna the Scribe, and
the Elders of the Priests, couered with sackcloth, to Esai the
Prophet the sonne of Amoz.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they sayd
vnto him, Thus sayth Hezekiah, This day is a day of trouble, and of
rebuke, and blasphemie: for the children are come to the birth, and
there is not strength to bring foorth.<note> Or, prouocation.</note></ab>

<fw>The prayer of Hezekiah is
heard.</fw>
<ab n="4">It may be, the
Lord thy God will heare all the words of Rabshakeh whome the king
of Assyria his master hath sent to reproch the liuing God, and will
reprooue the wordes which the Lord thy God hath heard: wherefore
lift vp thy prayer for the remnant that are left.<note> Heb. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So the seruants
of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Isaiah
said vnto them, Thus shal ye say to your master, Thus saith the
Lord, Be not afraid of the wordes which thou hast heard, with which
the seruants of the king of Assyria haue blasphemed me.<note> Luke 3.4. called Esaias.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Behold, I will
send a blast vpon him, and he shall heare a rumour, and shall
returne to his owne land, and I will cause him to fall by the sword
in his owne land.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ So
Rabshakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against
Libnah: for hee had heard that he was departed from
Lachish.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when he heard
say of Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, Behold, hee is come out to fight
against thee: hee sent messengers againe vnto Hezekiah,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="10">Thus shall ye
speake to Hezekiah king of Iudah, saying, Let not thy God in whome
thou trustest, deceiue thee, saying, Ierusalem shall not be
deliuered into the hande of the king of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, thou
hast heard what the kings of Assyria haue done to all lands, by
destroying them vtterly: and shalt thou be deliuered?</ab>
<ab n="12">Haue the gods of
the nations deliuered them which my fathers haue destroyed? As
Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the children of Eden which were
in Thelasar?</ab>
<ab n="13">Where is the
king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the citie of
Sepharuaim, of Hena, and Iuah?</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
Hezekiah receiued the letter of the hand of the messengers, and
read it: and Hezekiah went vp into the house of the Lord, and
spread it before the Lord.</ab>

<fw>The prayer of Hezekiah is
heard.</fw>
<ab n="15">And Hezekiah
prayed before the Lord, and said, O Lord God of Israel, which
dwellest between the Cherubims, thou art the God, euen thou alone,
of all the kingdomes of the earth, thou hast made heauen and
earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">Lord, bow downe
thine eare, and heare: open, Lord, thine eyes; and see: and heare
the words of Sennacherib which hath sent him to reproch the liuing
God.</ab>
<ab n="17">Of a trueth,
Lord, the kings of Assyria haue destroyed the nations and their
lands,</ab>
<ab n="18">And haue cast
their gods into the fire: for they were no gods, but the work of
mens hands, wood and stone: therfore they haue destroyed
them.<note> Heb. giuen</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Now therefore, O
Lord our God, I beseech thee, saue thou vs out of his hand, that
all the kingdoms of the earth may know, that thou art the Lord God,
euen thou onely.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Then
Isaiah the sonne of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, Thus saith the
Lord God of Israel, That which thou hast prayed to mee against
Sennacherib king of Assyria, I haue heard.</ab>
<ab n="21">This is the word
that the Lord hath spoken concerning him, The Uirgin, the daughter
of Zion hath despised thee, and laughed thee to scorne, the
daughter of Ierusalem hath shaken her head at thee.</ab>
<ab n="22">Whome hast thou
reproched and blasphemed? and against whome hast thou exalted thy
voyce, and lift vp thine eyes on high? euen against the Holy One of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="23">By thy
messengers thou hast reproched the Lord, and hast said, With the
multitude of my charets, I am come vp to the height of the
mountaines, to the sides of Lebanon, and will cut downe the tall
cedar trees thereof, and the choice firre trees thereof: and I will
enter into the lodgings of his borders, and into the forrest of his
Carmel.<note> Heb. by the hand of. , Heb. the talnesse, &amp;c. , Or, the forrest and his fruitful field</note></ab>
<ab n="24">I haue digged
&amp; drunke strange waters, and with the sole of my feete haue I
dried vp all the riuers of besieged places.<note> Or, fenced</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Hast thou not
heard long agoe, how I haue done it, and of ancient times that I
haue formed it? now haue I brought it to passe, that thou shouldest
be to lay waste fenced cities into ruinous heapes.<note> Or, hast thou not heard how I haue made it long agoe, and formed it of ancient times? should I now bring it to be laide waste, and fenced cities to be ruinous heapes?</note></ab>

<fw>Sennacherib slaine.</fw>
<ab n="26">Therefore their
Inhabitants were of small power, they were dismayed and confounded,
they were as the grasse of the field, and as the greene herbe, as
the grasse on the house tops, and as corne blasted before it be
growen vp.<note> Heb. short of hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">But I know thy
abode, and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy rage against
me.<note> Or, sitting.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Because thy rage
against me, and thy tumult is come vp into mine eares, therefore I
will put my hooke in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I
will turne thee backe by the way by which thou camest.</ab>
<ab n="29">And this shalbe
a signe vnto thee, Yee shall eate this yeere such things as grow of
themselues, and in the second yeere that which springeth of the
same, and in the third yeere sow ye and reape, and plant Uineyards,
and eate the fruits thereof.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the remnant
that is escaped of the house of Iudah, shall yet againe take root
downeward, and beare fruit vpward.<note> Hebr. the escaping of the house of Iudah that remaineth.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For out of
Ierusalem shall goe forth a remnant, and they that escape out of
mount Zion: the zeale of the Lord of hostes shall doe
this.<note> Hebr. the escaping.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Therefore thus
saith the Lord concerning the king of Assyria, He shall not come
into this city, nor shoot an arrow there, nor come before it with
shield, nor cast a banke against it:</ab>
<ab n="33">By the way that
hee came, by the same shal he returne, and shal not come into this
city, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="34">For I will
defend this citie, to saue it, for mine owne sake, and for my
seruant Dauids sake.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And it
came to passe that night, that the Angel of the Lord went out, and
smote in the campe of the Assyrians, an hundred foure score and
fiue thousand: and when they arose earely in the morning, behold,
they were all dead corpses.<note> Isa. 37.36. tob. 1.21. ecclus. 48.24. 1 macc. 7.41. 2. macca. 8.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">So Sennacherib
king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and dwelt at
Nineueh.</ab>
<ab n="37">And it came to
passe as hee was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that
Adramelech, and Sharezer his sonnes, smote him with the sword: and
they escaped into the land of Armenia, and Esarhaddon his sonne
reigned in his stead.<note> Hebr. Ararat.</note></ab>



</div>