<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Amaziah his good reigne. 5 His
iustice on the murderers of his father. 7 His victory ouer Edom. 8
Amaziah prouoking Iehoash, is ouercome and spoiled. 15 Ieroboam
succeedeth Iehoash. 17 Amaziah slaine by a conspiracie. 21 Azariah
succeedeth him. 23 Ieroboams wicked reigne. 28 Zachariah succeedeth
him.</head>

<ab n="1">In the second
yeere of Ioash sonne of Iehoahaz king of Israel, reigned Amaziah
the sonne of Ioash king of Iudah.<note> 2. Chron. 25. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Hee was twentie
and fiue yeeres olde when he began to reigne, and reigned twentie
and nine yeeres in Ierusalem: and his mothers name was Iehoaddan of
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he did that
which was right in the sight of the Lord, yet not like Dauid his
father: hee did according to all things as Ioash his father
did.</ab>

<fw>Amaziah taken.</fw>
<ab n="4">Howbeit, the high
places were not taken away: as yet the people did sacrifice, and
burnt incense on the high places.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And it
came to passe assoone as the kingdome was confirmed in his hand,
that he slew his seruants which had slaine the king his
father.<note> Chap. 12. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But the children
of the murderers he slew not, according vnto that which is written
in the booke of the Law of Moses, wherein the Lord commanded,
saying, The fathers shal not be put to death for the children, nor
the children be put to death for the fathers: but euery man shall
be put to death for his owne sinne.<note> Deut. 24. 16. ezek. 18.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">He slew of Edom
in the valley of salt, ten thousand, and tooke Selah by warre, and
called the name of it, Ioktheel, vnto this day.<note> Or, the rocke.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then
Amaziah sent messengers to Iehoash the sonne of Iehoahaz sonne of
Iehu king of Israel, saying, Come, let vs looke one another in the
face.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Iehoash the
king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Iudah, saying, The thistle
that was in Lebanon, sent to the Cedar that was in Lebanon, saying,
Giue thy daughter to my sonne to wife. And there passed by a wilde
beast that was in Lebanon, and trode downe the thistle.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou hast indeed
smitten Edom, and thine heart hath lifted thee vp: glory of this,
and tary at home: for why shouldest thou meddle to thy hurt, that
thou shouldest fall, euen thou, and Iudah with thee?<note> Heb. at thy house.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But Amaziah
would not heare: therefore Iehoash king of Israel went vp, and hee,
and Amaziah king of Iudah, looked one another in the face at
Bethshemesh, which belongeth to Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Iudah was
put to the worse before Israel, and they fled euery man to their
tents.<note> Heb. was smitten.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Iehoash king
of Israel tooke Amaziah king of Iudah, the sonne of Iehoash the
sonne of Ahaziah at Bethshemesh, and came to Ierusalem, and brake
downe the wall of Ierusalem, from the gate of Ephraim, vnto the
corner gate, foure hundred cubites.</ab>

<fw>Amaziah. Ieroboam.</fw>
<ab n="14">And he tooke all
the golde and siluer, and all the vessels that were found in the
house of the Lord, and in the treasures of the kings house, and
hostages, and returned to Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Now the
rest of the acts of Iehoash which he did, and his might, and how he
fought with Amaziah king of Iudah, are they not written in the
booke of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="16">And Iehoash
slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria, with the kings
of Israel, and Ieroboam his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And
Amaziah the sonne of Ioash king of Iudah, liued after the death of
Iehoash sonne of Iehoahaz king of Israel, fifteene yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the rest of
the acts of Amaziah, are they not written in the booke of the
Chronicles of the kings of Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="19">Now they made a
conspiracie against him in Ierusalem: and he fled to Lachish, but
they sent after him to Lachish, and slew him there.<note> 2. Chron. 15.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And they brought
him on horses, and he was buried at Ierusalem with his fathers, in
the city of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And all
the people of Iudah tooke Azariah (which was sixteene yeeres old)
and made him king in stead of his father Amaziah.<note> 2. Chron. 26.1. He is called Vzziah.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">He built Elath,
and restored it to Iudah, after that the king slept with his
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ In the
fifteenth yeere of Amaziah the sonne of Ioash king of Iudah,
Ieroboam the sonne of Ioash king of Israel began to raigne in
Samaria, and raigned forty and one yeeres:</ab>
<ab n="24">And hee did that
which was euill in the sight of the Lord: hee departed not from all
the sinnes of Ieroboam the sonne of Nebat, who made Israel to
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="25">Hee restored the
coast of Israel, from the entring of Hamath, vnto the sea of the
plaine, according to the word of the Lord God of Israel, which he
spake by the hand of his seruant Ionah, the sonne of Amittai the
Prophet, which was of Gath Hepher.<note> Matth.12. 39, 40. called Ionas.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For the Lord saw
the affliction of Israel, that it was very bitter: for there was
not any shut vp, nor any left, nor any helper for Israel.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the Lord
said not, that hee would blot out the name of Israel from vnder
heauen: but he saued them by the hand of Ieroboam the sonne of
Ioash.</ab>

<fw>Azariah a leper.</fw>
<ab n="28">¶ Now the
rest of the actes of Ieroboam, and all that he did, and his might,
how he warred, and how he recouered Damascus and Hamath, which
belonged to Iudah, for Israel, are they not written in the booke of
the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="29">And Ieroboam
slept with his fathers, euen with the kings of Israel, and
Zachariah his sonne reigned in his stead.</ab>



</div>