<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Iehoash, being saued by Iehosheba
his aunt from Athaliahs massacre of the seed royall, is hid sixe
yeeres in the house of God. 4 Iehoiada giuing order to the
captaines, in the seuenth yeere anointeth him King. 13 Athaliah is
slaine. 17 Iehoiada restoreth the worship of God.</head>

<ab n="1">And when Athaliah
the mother of Ahaziah sawe that her sonne was dead, she arose, and
destroyed all the seed royall.<note> 2. Chron. 22.10. , Heb. seede of the kingdome.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But Iehosheba the
daughter of king Ioram, sister of Ahaziah, tooke Ioash the sonne of
Ahaziah, and stale him from among the Kings sonnes which were
slaine; and they hid him, euen him and his nurse in the bed-chamber
from Athaliah, so that he was not slaine.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he was with
her hidde in the House of the Lord, sixe yeeres: and Athaliah did
reigne ouer the land.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And the
seuenth yeere Iehoiada sent and fet the rulers ouer hundreds, with
the captains, and the guard, and brought them to him into the house
of the Lord, and made a couenant with them, and tooke an othe of
them in the house of the Lord, and shewed them the Kings
sonne.<note> 2. Chron. 23.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And he commanded
them, saying, This is the thing that yee shall doe; A third part of
you that enter in on the Sabbath, shall euen be keepers of the
watch of the kings house:</ab>
<ab n="6">And a third part
shall be at the gate of Sur, and a third part at the gate behinde
the guard: so shall yee keepe the watch of the house, that it be
not broken downe.<note> Or, from breaking vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And two parts of
all you, that goe foorth on the Sabbath, euen they shall keepe the
watch of the house of the Lord about the King.<note> Or, companies. Heb. hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And yee shall
compasse the King round about, euery man with his weapons in his
hand: and he that commeth within the ranges, let him bee slaine:
and be yee with the king, as hee goeth out, and as he commeth
in.</ab>

<fw>Shee is slaine.</fw>
<ab n="9">And the captaines
ouer the hundreds did according to all things that Iehoiada the
Priest commanded: and they tooke euery man his men that were to
come in on the Sabbath, with them that should goe out on the
Sabbath, and came to Iehoiada the Priest.</ab>
<ab n="10">And to the
captaines ouer hundreds, did the Priest giue king Dauids speares
and shields, that were in the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the guard
stood, euery man with his weapons in his hand, round about the
king, from the right corner of the Temple, to the left corner of
the Temple, along by the Altar and the Temple.<note> Heb. shoulder.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And he brought
foorth the kings sonne, and put the crowne vpon him, and gaue him
the Testimonie, and they made him King, and anointed him, and they
clapt their hands, and said, God saue the King.<note> Heb. let the king liue.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And when
Athaliah heard the noise of the guard, and of the people, she came
to the people, into the Temple of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when shee
looked, behold, the king stood by a pillar, as the maner was, and
the Princes, and the trumpetters by the King, and all the people of
the land reioyced, and blew with trumpets: and Athaliah rent her
clothes, and cryed, Treason, treason.</ab>
<ab n="15">But Iehoiada the
Priest commanded the captaines of the hundreds, the officers of the
hoste, and sayde vnto them, Haue her foorth without the ranges; and
him that followeth her, kill with the sword: for the Priest had
sayd, Let her not be slaine in the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they laid
hands on her, and she went by the way, by the which the horses came
into the kings house, and there was she slaine.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And
Iehoiada made a couenant betweene the Lord and the king, and the
people, that they should be the Lords people; betweene the king
also and the people.</ab>
<ab n="18">And all the
people of the land went into the house of Baal, and brake it down,
his altars, and his images brake they in pieces throughly, and slew
Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars: and the Priest
appointed officers ouer the house of the Lord.<note> Heb. offices</note></ab>

<fw>Prouision for the Temple.</fw>
<ab n="19">And hee tooke
the rulers ouer hundreds, and the captaines, and the guard, and all
the people of the land, and they brought downe the king from the
house of the Lord, and came by the way of the gate of the guard, to
the kings house, and he sate on the throne of the kings.</ab>
<ab n="20">And all the
people of the land reioyced, and the citie was in quiet, and they
slew Athaliah with the sword, beside the kings house.</ab>
<ab n="21">Seuen yeeres old
was Iehoash when he began to reigne.</ab>



</div>