<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Kings_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Kings-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah hauing receiued a message
of death, by prayer hath his life lengthned. 8 The Sunne goeth
tenne degrees backward, for a signe of that promise. 12 Berodach
Baladan sending to visite Hezekiah, because of the wonder, hath
notice of his treasures. 14 Isaiah vnderstanding thereof,
foretelleth the Babylonian captiuitie. 20 Manasseh succeedeth
Hezekiah.</head>


<fw>Hezekiah sicke.</fw>
<ab n="1">In those dayes
was Hezekiah sicke vnto death: and the Prophet Isaiah the sonne of
Amos came to him, and saide vnto him, Thus saith the Lord, Set
thine house in order: for thou shalt die, and not liue.<note> 2. Chron. 32.24. Isa. 38.1. , Hebr. giue charge concerning thine house.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then hee turned
his face to the wall, and prayed vnto the Lord, saying;</ab>
<ab n="3">I beseech thee, O
Lord, remember now how I haue walked before thee in trueth, and
with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good in thy
sight: and Hezekiah wept sore.<note> Hebr. was a great weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And it came to
passe afore Isaiah was gone out into the middle court, that the
word of the Lord came to him, saying:<note> Or, city.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Turne againe, and
tell Hezekiah the captaine of my people, Thus saith the Lord, the
God of Dauid thy father, I haue heard thy prayer, I haue seene thy
teares: behold, I will heale thee; on the third day thou shalt goe
vp vnto the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I will adde
vnto thy dayes fifteene yeeres, and I will deliuer thee, and this
city, out of the hand of the king of Assyria, and I will defend
this citie for mine owne sake, and for my seruant Dauids
sake.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Isaiah said,
Take a lumpe of figs. And they tooke and layd it on the boile, and
he recouered.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
Hezekiah said vnto Isaiah, What shall bee the signe that the Lord
wil heale me, and that I shall goe vp into the house of the Lord
the third day?</ab>
<ab n="9">And Isaiah said,
This signe shalt thou haue of the Lord, that the Lord will doe the
thing that hee hath spoken: shall the shadow goe forward ten
degrees, or goe backe tenne degrees?<note> Ecclus, 48.24. isa. 38.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Hezekiah
answered, It is a light thing for the shadow to go downe tenne
degrees: nay, but let the shadow returne backward tenne
degrees.</ab>

<fw>Hezekiah dieth.</fw>
<ab n="11">And Isaiah the
Prophet cryed vnto the Lord, and he brought the shadow tenne
degrees backeward, by which it had gone downe in the diall of
Ahaz.<note> Heb. degrees.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ At that
time Berodach-Baladan the sonne of Baladan King of Babylon, sent
letters and a present vnto Hezekiah: for he had heard that Hezekiah
had beene sicke.<note> Isai. 39.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Hezekiah
hearkened vnto them, and shewed them the house of his precious
things, the siluer, and the golde, and the spices, and the precious
oyntment, and all the house of his armour, and all that was found
in his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his
dominion, that Hezekiah shewed them not.<note> Or, spicery. , Or, iewels. Heb. vessels.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then came
Isaiah the Prophet vnto King Hezekiah, and sayde vnto him, What
sayd these men? and from whence came they vnto thee? And Hezekiah
sayde, They are come from a farre countrey, euen from
Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he said,
What haue they seene in thine house? And Hezekiah answered, All the
things that are in mine house haue they seene: there is nothing
among my treasures, that I haue not shewed them.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Isaiah said
vnto Hezekiah, Heare the word of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">Behold, the
dayes come, that all that is in thine house, and that which thy
fathers haue layde vp in store vnto this day, shall be caried vnto
Babylon: nothing shall be left, sayth the Lord.<note> Chap. 24.13. &amp; 25.13 iere. 27.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And of thy
sonnes that shall issue from thee, which thou shalt beget, shall
they take away, and they shall bee Eunuches in the palace of the
king of Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then said
Hezekiah vnto Isaiah, Good is the word of the Lord which thou hast
spoken. And he said, Is it not good, if peace and trueth be in my
dayes?<note> Or, shall there not be peace and trueth? &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
rest of the actes of Hezekiah, and all his might, and how hee made
a poole and a conduit, &amp; brought water into the city, are they
not written in the booke of the Chronicles of the Kings of
Iudah?</ab>
<ab n="21">And Hezekiah
slept with his fathers, and Manasseh his sonne reigned in his
stead.</ab>




</div>