<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-4-4b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Simon slandereth Onias. 7 Iason by
corrupting the king, obteineth the office of the hie Priest. 24
Menelaus getteth the same from Iason by the like corruption. 34
Andronicus traiterously murdereth Onias. 36 The King being informed
thereof, causeth Andronicus to be put to death. 39 The wickednes of
Lysimachus, by the instigation of Menelaus.</head>

<ab n="1">This Simon now
(of whō wee spake afore) hauing bin a bewrayer of the money,
and of his countrey, slandered Onias, as if he had terrified
Heliodorus, and bene the worker of these euils.</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus was hee
bold to call him a traitour, that had deserued well of the citie,
and tendred his owne nation, and was so zealous of the
lawes.</ab>
<ab n="3">But when their
hatred went so farre, that by one of Simons faction murthers were
committed,</ab>
<ab n="4">Onias seeing
the danger of this contention, and that Appollonius, as being the
gouernour of Coelosyria and Phenice, did rage, and increase Simons
malice,</ab>
<ab n="5">He went to the
king, not to be an accuser of his countrey men, but seeking the
good of all, both publike, &amp; priuate.</ab>
<ab n="6">For he saw
that it was impossible, that the state should continue quiet, and
Simon leaue his folly, vnlesse the king did looke
thereunto.</ab>
<ab n="7">But after the
death of Seleucus, when Antiochus called Epiphanes, tooke the
kingdom, Iason the brother of Onias, laboured vnder hand to bee hie
Priest,</ab>
<ab n="8">Promising vnto
the king by intercession, three hundred and threescore talents of
siluer, and of another reuenew, eightie talents:</ab>
<ab n="9">Besides this,
he promised to assigne an hundred and fiftie more, if he might haue
licence to set him vp a place for exercise, and for the training vp
of youth in the fashions of the heathen, and to write them of
Ierusalem [by the name of] Antiochians.</ab>
<ab n="10">Which when
the king had granted, and hee had gotten into his hand the rule, he
foorthwith brought his owne nation to the Greekish fashion.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the royal
priuiledges granted of speciall fauour to the Iewes, by the meanes
of Iohn the father of Eupolemus, who went Embassador to Rome, for
amitie and aid, he tooke away, and putting down the gouernments
which were according to the law, he brought vp new customes against
the law.</ab>
<ab n="12">For he built
gladly a place of exercise vnder the towre it selfe, and brought
the chiefe yong men vnder his subiection, and made them weare a
hat.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now such was
the height of Greek fashions, and increase of heathenish maners,
through the exceeding profanenes of Iason that vngodly wretch, and
no high priest:</ab>
<ab n="14">That the
priests had no courage to serue any more at the altar, but
despising the Temple, and neglecting the sacrifices, hastened to be
partakers of the vnlawfull allowance in the place of exercise,
after the game of Discus called them forth.<note> Or, the Discus which was a stone with an hole in the midst.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Not setting
by the honours of their fathers, but liking the glory of the
Grecians best of all.</ab>
<ab n="16">By reason
whereof sore calamity came vpon them: for they had them to be their
enemies and auengers, whose custome they followed so earnestly, and
vnto whom they desired to be like in all things.</ab>
<ab n="17">For it is not
a light thing to doe wickedly against the lawes of God, but the
time following shall declare these things.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now when the
game that was vsed euery fift yere was kept at Tyrus, the king
being present,</ab>
<ab n="19">This
vngracious Iason sent speciall messengers from Ierusalem, who were
Antiochians, to carie three hundred drachmes of siluer to the
sacrifice of Hercules, which euen the bearers therof thought fit
not to bestow vpon the sacrifice, because it was not conuenient,
but to be reserued for other charges.<note> Gr. who were religious embassadours.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">This money
then in regard of the sender, was appointed to Hercules sacrifice,
but because of the bearers thereof, it was imployed to the making
of gallies.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now when
Apollonius the sonne of Manastheus was sent vnto Egypt, for the
coronation of king Ptolomeus Philometor, Antiochus vnderstanding
him not to bee well affected to his affaires, prouided for his owne
safetie: whereupon he came to Ioppe, &amp; from thence to
Ierusalem.<note> Or, inthronizing.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Where he was
honourably receiued of Iason, and of the citie, and was brought in
with torchlight, and with great shoutings: and so afterward went
with his hoste vnto Phenice.</ab>
<ab n="23">Three yeere
afterward, Iason sent Menelaus the foresaid Simons brother, to
beare the money vnto the king, and to put him in minde of certaine
necessary matters.</ab>
<ab n="24">But he being
brought to the presence of the king, when he had magnified him, for
the glorious appearance of his power, got the priesthood to
himselfe, offering more then Iason by three hundred talents of
siluer.</ab>
<ab n="25">So he came
with the kings Mandate, bringing nothing worthy the high
priesthood, but hauing the fury of a cruell Tyrant, and the rage of
a sauage beast.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then Iason,
who had vndermined his owne brother, being vndermined by another,
was cōpelled to flee into the countrey of the
Ammonites.</ab>
<ab n="27">So Menelaus
got the principalitie: but as for the money that he had promised
vnto the king, hee tooke no good order for it, albeit Sostratus the
ruler of the castle required it.</ab>
<ab n="28">For vnto him
appertained the gathering of the customes. Wherefore they were both
called before the king.</ab>
<ab n="29">Now Menelaus
left his brother Lysimachus in his stead in the priesthood, and
Sostratus left Crates, who was gouernour of the Cyprians.</ab>
<ab n="30">While those
things were in doing, they of Tharsus and Mallos made insurrection,
because they were giuen to the kings concubine called
Antiochis.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then came the
king in all haste to appease matters, leauing Andronicus a man in
authority, for his deputy.</ab>
<ab n="32">Now Menelaus
supposing that he had gotten a conuenient time, stole certaine
vessels of gold, out of the temple, and gaue some of them to
Andronicus, and some he sold into Tyrus, and the cities round
about.</ab>
<ab n="33">Which when
Onias knew of a surety, he reprooued him, and withdrew himselfe
into a Sanctuarie at Daphne, that lieth by Antiochia.</ab>
<ab n="34">Wherefore
Menelaus, taking Andronicus apart, prayed him to get Onias into his
hands, who being perswaded thereunto, and comming to Onias in
deceit, gaue him his right hand with othes, and though hee were
suspected (by him) yet perswaded he him to come forth of the
Sanctuarie: whom forthwith he shut vp without regard of
Iustice.</ab>
<ab n="35">For the which
cause not onely the Iewes, but many also of other nations tooke
great indignation, and were much grieued for the vniust murder of
the man.</ab>
<ab n="36">And when the
king was come againe from the places about Cilicia, the Iewes that
were in the citie, and certaine of the Greekes, that abhorred the
fact also, complained because Onias was slaine without
cause.</ab>
<ab n="37">Therefore
Antiochus was heartily sorry, and mooued to pity, and wept, because
of the sober and modest behauiour of him that was dead.</ab>
<ab n="38">And being
kindled with anger, forthwith he tooke away Andronicus his purple,
and rent off his clothes, and leading him through the whole city
vnto that very place, where he had committed impietie against
Onias, there slew he the cursed murtherer. Thus the Lord rewarded
him his punishment, as he had deserued.</ab>
<ab n="39">Now when many
sacriledges had beene committed in the citie by Lysimachus, with
the consent of Menelaus, and the bruit therof was spread abroad,
the multitude gathered themselues together against Lysimachus, many
vessels of gold being already caried away.</ab>
<ab n="40">Whereupon the
common people rising, and being filled with rage, Lysimachus armed
about three thousand men, and beganne first to offer violence on
Auranus, being the leader, a man farre gone in yeeres, &amp; no
lesse in folly.<note> Or, Tyranuus.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">They then
seeing the attempt of Lysimachus, some of them caught stones, some
clubs, others taking handfuls of dust, that was next at hand, cast
them all together vpon Lysimachus, and those that set vpon
them.</ab>
<ab n="42">Thus many of
them they wounded, &amp; some they stroke to the ground, and all
[of them] they forced to flee: but as for the Churchrobber
himselfe, him they killed besides the treasury.</ab>
<ab n="43">Of these
matters therefore there was an accusation laide against
Menelaus.</ab>
<ab n="44">Now when the
king came to Tyrus, three men that were sent from the Senate,
pleaded the cause before him:</ab>
<ab n="45">But Menelaus
being now conuicted, promised Ptolomee the sonne of Dorymenes, to
giue him much money, if hee would pacifie the King towards
him.</ab>
<ab n="46">Whereupon
Ptolomee taking the king aside into a certaine gallerie, as it were
to take the aire, brought him to be of another minde;</ab>
<ab n="47">Insomuch that
hee discharged Menelaus from the accusations, who notwithstanding
was cause of all the mischiefe: and those poore men, who if they
had told their cause, yea, before the Scythians, should haue bene
iudged innocent, them he condemned to death.</ab>
<ab n="48">Thus they
that followed the matter for the citie, and for the people, and for
the holy vessels, did soone suffer vniust punishment.</ab>
<ab n="49">Wherefore
euen they of Tyrus mooued with hatred of that wicked deed, caused
them to bee honourably buried.</ab>
<ab n="50">And so
through the couetousnesse of them that were in power, Menelaus
remained still in authority, increasing in malice, and being a
great traitour to the citizens.</ab>



</div>