<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Eupator inuadeth Iudea. 15 Iudas
by night slayeth many. 18 Eupators purpose is defeated. 23 He
maketh peace with Iudas.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
hundreth forty and ninth yere it was told Iudas that Antiochus
Eupator was cōming with a great power into Iudea;</ab>
<ab n="2">And with him
Lysias his protector, and ruler of his affaires, hauing either of
them a Grecian power of footemen, an hundred and ten thousand, and
horsmen fiue thousand, &amp; three hundred, and Elephants two &amp;
twenty, and three hundred charets armed [wt] hooks.</ab>
<ab n="3">Menelaus also
ioyned himself with them, and with great dissimulation encouraged
Antiochus, not for the safegard of the countrey, but because hee
thought to haue bin made gouernour.</ab>
<ab n="4">But the King
of kings mooued Antiochus minde against this wicked wretch, and
Lysias enformed the king, that this man was the cause of all
mischiefe, so that the king commanded to bring him vnto Berea, and
to put him to death, as the maner is in that place.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now there was
in that place a towre of fifty cubites high full of ashes, and it
had a round instrumēt which on euery side hanged down into the
ashes.</ab>
<ab n="6">And whosoeuer
was condemned of sacriledge, or had committed any other grieuous
crime, there did all men thrust him vnto death.</ab>
<ab n="7">Such a death
it happened that wicked man to die, not hauing so much as buriall
in the earth, &amp; that most iustly.</ab>
<ab n="8">For inasmuch
as he had committed many sinnes about the altar whose fire and
ashes were holy, hee receiued his death in ashes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now
þ<note/> king came with a barbarous &amp; hautie mind, to
do far worse to þ<note/> Iewes then had beene done in his
fathers time.</ab>
<ab n="10">Which things
when Iudas perceiued, hee commanded the multitude to call vpon the
Lord night &amp; day, that if euer at any other time, he would now
also helpe them, being at the point to be put from their Law, from
their country, and from the holy Temple:</ab>
<ab n="11">And that hee
would not suffer the people, that had euen now been but a little
refreshed, to be in subiection to the blasphemous
nations.<note> Or, had had a litle respite.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So when they
had all done this together, and besought the mercifull Lord with
weeping, and fasting, and lying flat vpon the ground three daies
long, Iudas hauing exhorted them, commanded they should be in a
readinesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Iudas
being apart with the Elders, determined before the kings host
should enter into Iudea and get the city, to goe foorth and try the
matter [in fight] by the helpe of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">So when he
had committed [all] to the Creator of the world, &amp; exhorted his
souldiers to fight manfully, euen vnto death, for the Lawes, the
Temple, the city, the country, and the common-wealth, he camped by
Modin.<note> Or, Lord</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And hauing
giuen the watchword to them that were about him, Uictory is of God;
with the most valiant and choice yong men, he went in into the
kings tent by night, &amp; slewe in the campe about foure thousand
men, and the chiefest of the Elephants, with all that were vpon
him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And at last
they filled the campe with feare and tumult, and departed with good
successe.</ab>
<ab n="17">This was
done in the breake of the day, because the protection of the Lord
did helpe him.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now when the
king had taken a taste of the manlinesse of the Iewes, hee went
about to take the holds by policie,</ab>
<ab n="19">And marched
towards Bethsura, which was a strōghold of þ<note/>
Iews, but he was put to flight, failed, &amp; lost of his
men.</ab>
<ab n="20">For Iudas
had conueyed vnto them þ<note/> were in it, such things
as were necessary.</ab>
<ab n="21">But Rhodocus
who was in þ<note/> Iewes hoste, disclosed the secrets to
the enemies, therefore he was sought out, &amp; when they had
gotten him, they put him in prison.</ab>
<ab n="22">The king
treated with them in Bethsura the second time, gaue his hand, tooke
theirs, departed, fought with Iudas, was ouercome:</ab>
<ab n="23">Heard that
Philip who was left ouer the affaires in Antioch was desperately
bent, confounded, intreated the Iewes, submitted himselfe, and
sware to all equal conditions, agreed with them, and offred
sacrifice, honoured the Temple, and dealt kindly with the
place,<note> Or, rebelled.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And accepted
well of Maccabeus, made him principall gouernor from Ptolemais vnto
the Gerrhenians,</ab>
<ab n="25">Came to
Ptolemais, the people there were grieued for the couenants: for
they stormed because they would make their couenants voide.</ab>
<ab n="26">Lysias went
vp to the iudgement seat, said as much as could be in defence of
the cause, perswaded, pacified, made them well affected, returned
to Antioch. Thus it went touching the kings comming and
departing.</ab>



</div>