<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 What Ieremie the Prophet did. 5
How he hid the Tabernacle, the Arke, and the Altar. 13 What
Neemias, and Iudas wrote. 20 What Iason wrote in fiue bookes, 25
And how those were abridged by the author of this
booke.</head>

<ab n="1">It is also
found in the records, that Ieremie the Prophet, commaunded them
that were caried away, to take of the fire as it hath beene
signified,</ab>
<ab n="2">And how that
the Prophet hauing giuen them the law, charged them not to forget
the commaundements of the Lord, and that they should not erre in
their minds, when they see images of siluer, and gold, with their
ornaments.</ab>
<ab n="3">And with other
such speeches exhorted he them, that the law should not depart from
their hearts.</ab>
<ab n="4">It was also
contained in the same writing, that the Prophet being warned of
God, commanded the Tabernacle, and the Arke to goe with him, as he
went forth into the mountaine, where Moises climed vp, and sawe the
heritage of God.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when
Ieremie came thither, he found an hollow caue wherin he laid the
Tabernacle, and the Arke, and the altar of incense, &amp; so
stopped the doore.</ab>
<ab n="6">And some of
those that followed him, came to marke the way, but they could not
find it.</ab>
<ab n="7">Which when
Ieremie perceiued, hee blamed them, saying, As for that place, it
shall be vnknowen vntill the time that God gather his people againe
together, and receiue them vnto mercy.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then shall the
Lord shew them these things, and the glory of the Lord shall
appeare, and the cloud also as it was shewed vnder Moises, and as
when Solomon desired that the place might be honourably
sanctified.</ab>
<ab n="9">It was also
declared that he being wise, offered the sacrifice of dedication,
and of the finishing of the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="10">And as when
Moises prayed vnto the Lord, the fire came down from heauen, and
consumed the sacrifices: euen so prayed Solomon also, and the fire
came downe from heauen, and consumed the burnt offerings.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Moises
said, because the sinne offering was not to be eaten, it was
consumed.</ab>
<ab n="12">So Solomon
kept those eight dayes.</ab>
<ab n="13">The same
things also were reported in the writings, and commentaries of
Neemias, and how he founding a librarie, gathered together the acts
of the Kings, and the Prophets, and of Dauid, and the Epistles of
the Kings concerning the holy gifts.</ab>
<ab n="14">In like maner
also, Iudas gathered together all those things that were lost, by
reason of the warre we had, and they remaine with vs.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wherefore if
yee haue neede thereof, send some to fetch them vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="16">Whereas we
then are about to celebrate the purification, we haue written vnto
you, and yee shall doe well if yee keepe the same dayes.</ab>
<ab n="17">We hope also
that the God, that deliuered all his people, and gaue them all an
heritage, and the kingdome, and the priesthood, and the
Sanctuarie,<note> Gre. now God it is that saued all his people, and rendred the heritage, and the kingdome, and the priesthood, and the Sanctuarie, as he promised in the lawe. For we hope in God that he will shortly, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">As he
promised in the lawe, will shortly haue mercy vpon vs, and gather
vs together out of euery land vnder heauen into the holy place: for
he hath deliuered vs out of great troubles, and hath purified the
place.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now as
concerning Iudas Maccabeus, and his brethren, and the purification
of the great Temple, and the dedication of the altar,</ab>
<ab n="20">And the
warres against Antiochus Epiphanes, &amp; Eupator his
sonne,</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
manifest signes that came from heauen, vnto those that behaued
themselues manfully to their honour for Iudaisme: so that being but
a few, they ouercame the whole country, and chased barbarous
multitudes,</ab>
<ab n="22">And recouered
againe the Temple renowned all the world ouer, and freed the citie,
and vpheld the lawes, which were going downe, the Lord being
gracious vnto them with al fauour:</ab>
<ab n="23">All these
things (I say) being declared by Iason of Cyrene in fiue books, we
will assay to abridge in one volume.</ab>
<ab n="24">For
considering the infinite number, and the difficulty, which they
find that desire to looke into the narrations of the story, for the
variety of þ<note/> matter,</ab>
<ab n="25">We haue beene
carefull, that they that will read might haue delight, and that
they that are desirous to commit to memorie, might haue ease, and
that all, into whose hands it comes might haue profit.</ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore to
vs that haue taken vpon vs this paineful labour of abridging, it
was not easie, but a matter of sweat, and watching.</ab>
<ab n="27">Euen as it is
no ease vnto him, that prepareth a banquet, and seeketh the benefit
of others: yet for the pleasuring of many we will vndertake gladly
this great paines:<note> Or, to deserue well of many.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Leauing to
the authour the exact handling of euery particular, and labouring
to follow the rules of an abridgement.</ab>
<ab n="29">For as the
master builder of a new house, must care for the whole building:
but hee that vndertaketh to set it out, and paint it, must seeke
out fit things for the adorning thereof: euen so I thinke it is
with vs.</ab>
<ab n="30">To stand vpon
euery point, and goe ouer things at large, and to be curious in
particulars, belongeth to the first authour of the storie.</ab>
<ab n="31">But to vse
breuitie, and auoyde much labouring of the worke, is to bee granted
to him that will make an abridgement.</ab>
<ab n="32">Here then
will we begin the story: onely adding thus much to that which hath
bene said, That it is a foolish thing to make a long prologue, and
to be short in the story it selfe.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>