<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Iudas recouereth the Citie, and
purifieth the Temple. 14 Gorgias vexeth the Iewes. 16 Iudas winneth
their holds. 29 Timotheus and his men are discomfited. 35 Gazara is
taken, and Timotheus slaine.</head>

<ab n="1">Now
Maccabeus, and his company, the Lord guiding them, recouered the
Temple, and the citie.</ab>
<ab n="2">But the
altars, which the heathen had built in the open street, &amp; also
the Chappels they pulled downe.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hauing
cleansed the Temple, they made another Altar, and striking stones,
they tooke fire out of them, and offered a sacrifice after two
yeeres, &amp; set forth incense, &amp; lights, and
Shewbread.</ab>
<ab n="4">When that was
done, they fell flat downe, and besought the Lord that they might
come no more into such troubles: but if they sinned any more
against him, that he himselfe would chasten them with mercie, and
that they might not bee deliuered vnto the blasphemous, and
barbarous nations.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now vpon the
same day that the strangers prophaned the Temple, on the very same
day it was cleansed againe, euen the fiue and twentieth day of the
same moneth, which is Casleu.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they kept
eight dayes with gladnes as in the feast of the Tabernacles,
remembring that not long afore they had helde the feast of the
Tabernacles, when as they wandered in the mountaines, and dennes,
like beasts.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore
they bare branches, and faire boughes and palmes also, and sang
Psalmes vnto him, that had giuen them good successe in clensing his
place.</ab>
<ab n="8">They ordeined
also by a common statute, and decree, That euery yeere those dayes
should be kept of the whole nation of the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="9">And this was
the ende of Antiochus called Epiphanes.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now will wee
declare the acts of Antiochus Eupator, who was the sonne of this
wicked man, gathering briefly the calamities of the warres.</ab>
<ab n="11">So when he
was come to þ<note/> crowne, he set one Lysias ouer the
affaires of his Realme, and [appointed him] chiefe gouernour of
Coelosyria and Phenice.</ab>
<ab n="12">For
Ptolomeus that was called Macron, chosing rather to doe iustice
vnto the Iewes, for the wrong that had bene done vnto them,
endeuoured to continue peace with them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Whereupon
being accused of [the kings] friends, before Eupator, &amp; called
traitor at euery word, because he had left Cyprus that Philometor
had cōmitted vnto him, &amp; departed to Antiochus Epiphanes;
and seeing that hee was in no honorable place, he was so
discouraged, that he poysoned himselfe and died.<note> Or, and not bearing his authoritie as it becommeth a noble man.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But when
Gorgias was gouernour of the holds, hee hired souldiers, and
nourished warre continually with the Iewes:<note> Or, strong places.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And
therewithall the Idumeans hauing gotten into their handes the most
commodious holdes, kept the Iewes occupied, and receiuing those
that were banished from Ierusalem, they went about to nourish
warre.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then they
that were wich Maccabeus made supplication, &amp; besought God,
that he would be their helper, and so they ranne with violence vpon
the strong holds of the Idumeans,</ab>
<ab n="17">And
assaulting them strongly, they wanne the holds, and kept off all
that fought vpon the wall, and slew all that fell into their hands,
and killed no fewer then twentie thousand.</ab>
<ab n="18">And because
certaine (who were no lesse then nine thousand) were fled together
into two very strong castles, hauing all maner of things conuenient
to sustaine the siege,</ab>
<ab n="19">Maccabeus
left Simon, &amp; Ioseph, and Zaccheus also, and them that were
with him, who were enow to besiege them, and departed himselfe vnto
those places, which more needed his helpe.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now they
that were with Simon, being led with couetousnes, were perswaded
for money (through certaine of those that were in the castle) and
tooke seuentie thousand drachmes, and let some of them
escape.<note> Or, Simon.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But when it
was told Maccabeus what was done, hee called the gouernours of the
people together, and accused those men, that they had sold their
brethren for money, &amp; let their enemies free to fight against
them.</ab>
<ab n="22">So he slew
those that were found traitors, and immediatly tooke the two
castles.</ab>
<ab n="23">And hauing
good successe with his weapons in all things hee tooke in hand, hee
slew in the two holdes, more then twentie thousand.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now
Timotheus whom the Iewes had ouercome before, when he had gathered
a great multitude of forraine forces, and horses out of Asia not a
few, came as though hee would take Iewrie by force of
armes.</ab>
<ab n="25">But when hee
drew neere, they that were with Maccabeus, turned themselues to
pray vnto God, and sprinckled earth vpon their heads, and girded
their loynes with sackcloth,<note> Or, Maccabeus, and they that were with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And fell
downe at the foot of the Altar, and besought him to be mercifull to
them, and to be an enemie to their enemies, and an aduersarie to
their aduersaries, as the Law declareth.<note> Deut.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">So after the
prayer, they tooke their weapons, &amp; went on further from the
city: and when they drew neere to their enemies, they kept by
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now the
Sunne being newly risen, they ioyned both together; the one part
hauing, together with their vertue, their refuge also vnto the
Lord, for a pledge of their successe and victorie: the other side
making their rage leader of their battell.<note> Or, warrant, or suretie.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">But when the
battaile waxed strong, there appeared vnto the enemies from heauen,
fiue comely men vpon horses, with bridles of golde, and two of them
ledde the Iewes,</ab>
<ab n="30">And tooke
Maccabeus betwixt them, and couered him on euery side with their
weapons, and kept him safe, but shot arrowes &amp; lightenings
against the enemies: so that being confounded with blindnesse, and
full of trouble, they were killed.</ab>
<ab n="31">And there
were slaine [of footemen] twentie thousand and fiue hundred, and
sixe hundred horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="32">As for
Timotheus himselfe, hee fled into a very strong holde, called
Gazara, where Chereas was gouernour.</ab>
<ab n="33">But they
that were with Maccabeus, laid siege against the fortresse
couragiously foure dayes.</ab>
<ab n="34">And they
þ<note/> were within, trusting to the strength of the
place, blasphemed exceedingly, &amp; vttered wicked words.</ab>
<ab n="35">Neuerthelesse,
vpon the fifth day early, twentie yong men of Maccabeus company,
inflamed with anger because of the blasphemies, assaulted the wall
manly, and with a fierce courage killed all that they met
withall.</ab>
<ab n="36">Others
likewise ascending after them, whiles they were busied with them
that were within, burnt the towres, and kindling fires, burnt the
blasphemers aliue, and others broke open the gates, and hauing
receiued in the rest of the army, tooke the city,</ab>
<ab n="37">And killed
Timotheus that was hidde in a certaine pit, and Chereas his
brother, with Apollophanes.</ab>
<ab n="38">When this
was done, they praised the Lord with Psalmes and thankesgiuing, who
had done so great things for Israel, and giuen them the
victory.</ab>



</div>