<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Iudas gathereth an hoste. 9
Nicanor is sent against him: who presumeth to make much money of
his prisoners. 16 Iudas encourageth his men, and putteth Nicanor to
flight, 28 and diuideth the spoiles. 30 Other enemies are also
defeated, 35 And Nicanor fleeth with griefe to
Antioch.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iudas
Maccabeus and they that were with him, went priuily into the
townes, and called their kinsefolkes together, and tooke vnto them
all such as continued in the Iewes religion, and assembled about
sixe thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="2">And they
called vpon the Lord, that hee would looke vpon the people that was
troden downe of all, and also pitie the Temple, prophaned of
vngodly men,</ab>
<ab n="3">And that he
would haue compassion vpon the city sore defaced and ready to be
made euen with the ground, and heare the blood that cried vnto
him,</ab>
<ab n="4">And remember
the wicked slaughter of harmelesse infants, and the blasphemies
committed against his Name, and that hee would shew his hatred
against the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now when
Maccabeus had his company about him, hee could not be withstood by
the heathen: for the wrath of the Lord was turned into
mercy.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore he
came at vnawares, and burnt vp townes and cities, and got into his
hands the most commodious places, and ouercame &amp; put to flight
no small number of his enemies.</ab>
<ab n="7">But specially
tooke he aduantage of the night, for such priuie attempts, insomuch
that the bruite of his manlinesse was spread euery where.</ab>
<ab n="8">So when Philip
sawe that this man encreased by little and little, &amp; that
things prospered with him still more and more, hee wrote vnto
Ptolemeus, the gouernour of Coelosyria &amp; Phenice, to yeeld more
aide to the kings affaires.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then forthwith
choosing Nicanor the son of Patroclus, one of his speciall friends,
he sent him with no fewer then twentie thousand of all nations
vnder him, to root out the whole generation of the Iewes; and with
him he ioyned also Gorgias a captaine, who in matters of warre had
great experience.</ab>
<ab n="10">So Nicanor
vndertooke to make so much money of the captiue Iewes, as should
defray the tribute of two thousand talents, which the king was to
pay to the Romanes.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore
immediatly he sent to the cities vpon the sea coast, proclaiming a
sale of the captiue Iewes, and promising that they should haue
fourescore and ten bodies for one talent, not expecting the
vengeance that was to follow vpon him from the Almighty
God.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now when word
was brought vnto Iudas of Nicanors cōming, and he had imparted
vnto those that were with him, that the army was at hand,</ab>
<ab n="13">They that
were fearefull, and distrusted the iustice of God, fled, and
conueyed themselues away.</ab>
<ab n="14">Others sold
all that they had left, and withall besought the Lord to deliuer
them, being solde by the wicked Nicanor before they met
together:</ab>
<ab n="15">And if not
for their owne sakes, yet for þ<note/> couenants he had
made with their fathers, and for his holy and glorious Names sake,
by which they were called</ab>
<ab n="16">So Maccabeus
called his men together vnto the number of sixe thousand, and
exhorted them not to be stricken with terrour of the enemie, nor to
feare the great multitude of the heathen who came wrongfully
against them, but to fight manfully,</ab>
<ab n="17">And to set
before their eyes, the iniury that they had vniustly done to the
holy place, and the cruell handling of the city, whereof they made
a mockery, and also the taking away of the gouernment of their
forefathers:</ab>
<ab n="18">For they,
said he, trust in their weapons and boldnesse, but our confidence
is in the Almightie God, who at a becke can cast downe both them
that come against vs, and also all the world.</ab>
<ab n="19">Moreouer, hee
recounted vnto them what helps their forefathers had found, and how
they were deliuered, when vnder Sennacherib an hundred fourescore
and fiue thousand perished.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he told
them of þ<note/> battel that they had in Babylon with the
Galatians, how they came but eight thousand in all to
þ<note/> busines, with foure thousand Macedonians, and
that the Macedonians being perplexed, the eight thousand destroyed
an hundred and twenty thousand, because of the helpe that they had
from heauen, &amp; so receiued a great booty.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thus when hee
had made them bold with these words, and ready to die for the
Lawes, and the countrey, he diuided his army into foure
parts:</ab>
<ab n="22">And ioyned
with himselfe his owne brethren, leaders of each band, to wit,
Simon, and Ioseph, &amp; Ionathan, giuing each one fifteene hundred
men.</ab>
<ab n="23">Also (hee
appointed) Eleazar to reade the holy booke: and when he had giuen
them this watchword, The help of God; himselfe leading the first
band, he ioyned battell with Nicanor:</ab>
<ab n="24">And by the
helpe of the Almightie, they slew aboue nine thousand of their
enemies, and wounded and maimed the most part of Nicanors hoste,
and so put all to flight:</ab>
<ab n="25">And tooke
their money that came to buy them, and pursued them farre: but
lacking time, they returned.</ab>
<ab n="26">For it was
the day before the Sabbath, and therefore they would no longer
pursue them.</ab>
<ab n="27">So when they
had gathered their armour together, and spoiled their enemies, they
occupied themselues about the Sabbath, yeelding exceeding praise,
&amp; thanks to the Lord, who had preserued them vnto
þ<note/> day, which was the beginning of mercy,
distilling vpon them.<note> That is, the enemies armour.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And after the
Sabbath, when they had giuen part of the spoiles to the maimed, and
the widdowes, and Orphanes, the residue they diuided among
themselues, and their seruants.<note> Or, lamed with tortures.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">When this was
done, and they had made a common supplication, they besought the
mercifull Lord to be reconciled with his seruants for euer.</ab>
<ab n="30">Moreouer of
those that were with Timotheus &amp; Bacchides, who fought against
them, they slewe aboue twentie thousand, and very easily got high
and strong holds, &amp; diuided amongst them selues many spoiles
more, and made the maimed, orphanes, widowes, yea, &amp; the aged
also, equal in spoiles [wt] themselues<note> Or, lamed.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And when they
had gathered their armour together, they laid them vp all carefully
in couenient places, and the remnant of the spoiles they brought to
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="32">They slew
also Philarches that wicked persō who was [wt] Timotheus,
&amp; had annoied the Iewes many waies.</ab>
<ab n="33">Furthermore
at such time as they kept the feast for the victorie in their
coūtry, they burnt Calisthenes that had set fire vpon the holy
gates, who was fled into a litle house, and so he receiued a reward
meet for his wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="34">As for that
most vngracious Nicanor, who had brought a thousand merchants to
buy the Iewes,</ab>
<ab n="35">He was
through the helpe of the Lord brought downe by them, of whō he
made least account, &amp; putting off his glorious apparell, and
discharging his company, he came like a fugitiue seruant through
the mid land vnto Antioch, hauing very great dishonour for that his
hoste was destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="36">Thus he that
tooke vpon him to make good to the Romanes, their tribute by meanes
of the captiues in Ierusalem, told abroad, that the Iewes had God
to fight for them, and therfore they could not be hurt, because
they followed the lawes that he gaue them.</ab>



</div>