<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>3 Lysias thinking to get Ierusalem,
8 Is put to flight. 16 The letters of Lysias to the Iewes: 22 Of
the king vnto Lysias: 27 and to the Iewes: 34 Of the Romanes to the
Iewes.</head>

<ab n="1">Not long
after this, Lysias the kings protectour &amp; cousin, who also
managed the affaires, tooke sore displeasure for the things that
were done.<note> Gr. tutour.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And when he
had gathered about fourescore thousand, with all the horsemen, he
came against the Iewes, thinking to make the citie an habitation of
the Gentiles,<note> Or, Grecians.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And to make a
gaine of the Temple, as of the other Chappels of the heathen, and
to set the high Priesthood to sale euery yeere:</ab>
<ab n="4">Not at all
considering the power of God, but puffed vp with his ten thousand
footmen, and his thousand horsemen, and his fourescore
Elephants.</ab>
<ab n="5">So he came to
Iudea, &amp; drew neere to Bethsura, which was a strong town, but
distant from Ierusalem about fiue furlongs, and he laid sore siege
vnto it.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now when they
that were with Maccabeus heard that he besieged the holdes, they
and all the people with lamentation and teares besought the Lord,
that he would send a good Angel to deliuer Israel.<note> Maccabeus and his company.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then
Maccabeus himselfe first of all tooke weapons, exhorting the other,
that they would ieopard themselues together with him, to helpe
their brethren: so they went forth together with a willing
minde.</ab>
<ab n="8">And as they
were at Ierusalem, there appeared before them on horsebacke, one in
white clothing, shaking his armour of gold.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then they
praised the mercifull God altogether, and tooke heart, insomuch
that they were ready not onely to fight with men, but with most
cruell beasts, &amp; to pierce through wals of yron.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thus they
marched forward in their armour, hauing an helper from heauen: for
the Lord was mercifull vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And giuing a
charge vpō their enemies like lions, they slew eleuen thousand
footmen, &amp; sixteene hundred horsemen, and put all the other to
flight.</ab>
<ab n="12">Many of them
also being wounded, escaped naked, and Lysias himselfe fled away
shamefully, and so escaped.</ab>
<ab n="13">Who as hee
was a man of vnderstanding, casting with himselfe what losse he had
had, and considering that the Hebrewes could not be ouercome,
because the Almighty God helped them, he sent vnto them,</ab>
<ab n="14">And
perswaded them to agree to all reasonable conditions, &amp;
[promised] that hee would perswade the king, that he must needs be
a friend vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then
Maccabeus consented to all that Lysias desired, being carefull of
the common good; and whatsoeuer Maccabeus wrote vnto Lysias
concerning the Iewes, the king granted it.</ab>
<ab n="16">For there
were letters written vnto the Iewes from Lysias, to this effect:
Lysias vnto the people of the Iewes, sendeth greeting.</ab>
<ab n="17">Iohn and
Absalon, who were sent from you, deliuered me the petition
subscribed, and made request for the performance of the contents
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="18">Therefore
what things soeuer were meet to be reported to the king, I haue
declared them, and he hath granted as much as might be.</ab>
<ab n="19">If then you
wil keepe your selues loyall to the state, hereafter also will I
endeuour to be a meanes of your good.</ab>
<ab n="20">But of the
particulars I haue giuen order, both to these, &amp; the other that
came from me, to commune with you.</ab>
<ab n="21">Fare ye wel.
The hundred &amp; eight and fortie yeere, the foure and twentie day
of the moneth Dioscorinthius.<note> Or, Dioscoros.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Now the
kings letter conteined these words, King Antiochus vnto his brother
Lysias sendeth greeting.</ab>
<ab n="23">Since our
father is translated vnto þ<note/> gods, our will is,
that they that are in our realme liue quietly, that euery one may
attend vpon his own affaires.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wee
vnderstand also that the Iewes would not consent to our father for
to bee brought vnto the custome of the Gentiles, but had rather
keepe their owne manner of liuing: for the which cause they require
of vs that we should suffer thē to liue after their own
lawes.</ab>
<ab n="25">Wherefore
our mind is, that this nation shall be in rest, and we haue
determined to restore them their Temple, that they may liue
according to the customes of their forefathers.</ab>
<ab n="26">Thou shalt
doe well therefore to send vnto them, and grant them peace, that
whē they are certified of our mind, they may be of good
comfort, &amp; euer goe cheerefully about their owne
affaires.<note> Or, giue them assurance.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the
letter of þ<note/> king vnto the nation of the Iewes was
after this maner: king Antiochus sendeth greeting vnto the counsel,
&amp; the rest of the Iewes</ab>
<ab n="28">If ye fare
well, we haue our desire, we are also in good health.</ab>
<ab n="29">Menelaus
declared vnto vs, that your desire was to returne home, and to
follow your owne businesse.</ab>
<ab n="30">Wherefore
they that will depart shall haue safe conduct, till the thirtieth
day of Xanthicus with securitie.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the
Iewes shal vse their owne kind of meats, and lawes, as before, and
none of them any maner of wayes shal be molested for things
ignorantly done.</ab>
<ab n="32">I haue sent
also Menelaus, that he may comfort you.</ab>
<ab n="33">Fare ye wel.
In the hundred, forty and eight yeere, and the fifteenth day of the
moneth Xanthicus.<note> Or, Aprill.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">The Romanes
also sent vnto them a letter containing these wordes: Quintus
Memmius, &amp; Titus Manlius embassadours of þ<note/>
Romanes, send greeting vnto the people of the Iewes.<note> Or, consuls</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Whatsoeuer
Lysias the kings cousin hath granted, therewith we also are well
pleased.</ab>
<ab n="36">But touching
such things as hee iudged to be referred to the king: after you
haue aduised therof, send one forthwith, that we may declare as it
is conuenient for you: for we are now going to Antioch.</ab>
<ab n="37">Therefore
send some with speed, that we may know what is your mind.</ab>
<ab n="38">Farewell,
this hundred and eight and fortie yeere, the fifteenth day of the
moneth Xanthicus.</ab>



</div>