<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Antiochus is chased from
Persepolis. 5 Hee is striken with a sore disease, 14 and promiseth
to become a Iew. 28 He dieth miserably.</head>

<ab n="1">About that
time came Antiochus with dishonor out of the countrey of
Persia.<note> Or, disorderly.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For he had
entred the citie called Persepolis, and went about to rob the
Temple, and to hold the citie, whereupon the multitude running to
defend thēselues with their weapons, put them to flight, &amp;
so it happened þ<note/> Antiochus being put to flight of
the inhabitants, returned with shame.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now when he
came to Ecbatana, newes was brought him what had happened vnto
Nicanor &amp; Timotheus.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then swelling
with anger, hee thought to auenge vpon the Iewes the disgrace done
vnto him by those that made him flie. Therfore commanded he his
chariot man to driue without ceasing, and to dispatch the iourney,
the iudgement of God now following him. For he had spoken proudly
in this sort, þ<note/> he would come to Ierusalem, &amp;
make it a common burying place of þ<note/> Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="5">But the Lord
almightie, the God of Israel smote him with an incurable and
inuisible plague: for assoone as hee had spoken these words, a
paine of the bowels that was remediles, came vpon him, &amp; sore
torments of the inner parts.</ab>
<ab n="6">And that most
iustly: for hee had tormented other mens bowels with many and
strange torments.</ab>
<ab n="7">Howbeit hee
nothing at all ceased from his bragging, but still was filled with
pride, breathing out fire in his rage against the Iewes, and
commanding to haste the iourney: but it came to passe that he fel
downe frō his chariot, caried violently, so that hauing a sore
fal, al the mēbers of his body were much pained.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thus hee
that a little afore thought he might command the waues of the sea
(so proud was hee beyond the condition of man) and weigh the high
mountaines in a ballance, was now cast on the ground, and carried
in an horselitter, shewing foorth vnto all, the manifest power of
God.</ab>
<ab n="9">So that the
wormes rose vp out of the body of this wicked man, &amp; whiles hee
liued in sorrow and paine, his flesh fell away, and the filthinesse
of his smell was noysome to all his army.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the man
that thought a little afore he could reach to the starres of
heauen, no man could endure to carry for his intollerable
stinke.</ab>
<ab n="11">Here
therefore being plagued, hee began to leaue off his great pride,
and to come to the knowledge [of himselfe] by the scourge of God,
his paine encreasing euery moment.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when hee
himselfe could not abide his owne smell; hee saide these wordes: It
is meete to bee subiect vnto God, and that a man that is mortall,
should not proudly thinke of himselfe, as if he were God.</ab>
<ab n="13">This wicked
person vowed also vnto the Lord, (who now no more would haue mercy
vpon him) saying thus:</ab>
<ab n="14">That the holy
citie (to the which hee was going in haste to lay it euen with the
ground, &amp; to make it a common burying place) he would set at
liberty.</ab>
<ab n="15">And as
touching the Iewes, whom hee had iudged not worthy so much as to be
buried, but to be cast out with their children to be deuoured of
the foules, and wild beasts, he would make them al equals to
þ<note/> citizens of Athens,<note> Or, Antioch.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the holy
Temple, which before he had spoiled, hee would garnish with goodly
gifts, and restore all the holy vessels with many more, and out of
his owne reuenew defray the charges belonging to the
sacrifices:</ab>
<ab n="17">Yea, and that
also hee would become a Iew himselfe, and goe through all the world
that was inhabited, and declare the power of God.</ab>
<ab n="18">But for all
this his paines would not cease: for the iust iudgement of God was
come vpō him: therfore despairing of his health, he wrote vnto
the Iewes the letter vnderwritten, containing the forme of a
supplicatiō, after this maner.</ab>
<ab n="19">Antiochus
king and gouernour, to the good Iewes his Citizens, wisheth much
ioy, health, and prosperity.</ab>
<ab n="20">If ye, and
your children fare well, and your affaires be to your contentment,
I giue very great thankes to God, hauing my hope in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="21">As for mee I
was weake, or else I would haue remembred kindly your honour, and
good will. Returning out of Persia, and being taken with a grieuous
disease, I thought it necessary to care for the common safety of
all:</ab>
<ab n="22">Not
distrusting mine health, but hauing great hope to escape this
sicknes</ab>
<ab n="23">But
considering that euen my father, at what time he led an armie into
the hie countries, appointed a successor,</ab>
<ab n="24">To the end,
that if any thing fell out contrary to expectation, or if any
tidings were brought that were grieuous, they of the land knowing
to whom the state was left, might not be troubled.<note> Or common affaires.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Againe
considering, how that the princes that are borderers, and neighbors
vnto my kingdome, waite for opportunities, and expect what shalbe
the euent, I haue appointed my sonne Antiochus king, whom I often
cōmitted, and cōmended vnto many of you, when I went vp
into the high prouinces, to whom I haue written as
followeth.</ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore I
pray, and request you to remember the benefits that I haue done
vnto you generally, and in speciall, and that euery man will be
still faithfull to me, and my sonne.</ab>
<ab n="27">For I am
perswaded that hee vnderstanding my minde, will fauourably &amp;
graciously yeeld to your desires.<note> Or, following.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Thus the
murtherer, and blasphemer hauing suffered most grieuously, as he
entreated other men, so died he a miserable death in a strange
countrey in the mountaines.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Philip
that was brought vp with him, caried away his body, who also
fearing the son of Antiochus, went into Egypt to Ptolomeus
Philometor.</ab>



</div>