<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The Iewes are compelled to leaue
the Law of God. 4 The Temple is defiled. 8 Crueltie vpon the people
and the women. 12 An exhortation to beare affliction, by the
example of the valiant courage of Eleazarus, cruelly
tortured.</head>

<ab n="1">Not long after
this, the king sent an olde man of Athens, to compell the Iewes to
depart from the lawes of their fathers, and not to liue after the
Lawes of God:<note> Antioch: the Latine interpreters.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And to pollute
also the Temple in Ierusalem, and to call it the Temple of Iupiter
Olympius: and that in Garizim, of Iupiter the defender of
strangers, as they did desire that dwelt in the place.<note> Out of Ios. lib. 12.c.7. or, as they were.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The comming in
of this mischiefe was sore and grieuous to the people:</ab>
<ab n="4">For the Temple
was filled with riot and reuelling, by the Gentiles, who dallied
with harlots, and had to doe with women within the circuit of the
holy places, and besides that, brought in things that were not
lawfull.</ab>
<ab n="5">The Altar also
was filled with profane things, which the Law forbiddeth.</ab>
<ab n="6">Neither was it
lawfull for a man to keepe Sabbath dayes, or ancient Feasts, or to
professe himselfe at all to be a Iewe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And in the day
of the kings birth, euery moneth they were brought by bitter
constraint to eate of the sacrifices; and when the Feast of Bacchus
was kept, the Iewes were compelled to goe in procession to Bacchus,
carying Iuie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Moreouer there
went out a decree to the neighbour cities of the heathen, by the
suggestion of Ptolomee, against the Iewes, that they should obserue
the same fashions, and be partakers of their
sacrifices.<note> Gr. Grecians.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And whoso
would not conforme themselues to the maners of the Gentiles, should
be put to death: then might a man hane seene the present
misery.</ab>
<ab n="10">For there
were two women brought, who had circumcised their children, whom
when they had openly led round about the citie, the babes hanging
at their breasts, they cast them downe headlong from the
wall.</ab>
<ab n="11">And others
that had run together into caues neere by, to keepe the Sabbath day
secretly, being discouered to Philip, were all burnt together,
because they made a conscience to helpe themselues, for the honour
of the most sacred day.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now I beseech
those that reade this booke, that they be not discouraged for these
calamities, but that they iudge those punishments not to be for
destruction, but for a chastening of our nation.</ab>
<ab n="13">For it is a
token of his great goodnesse, when wicked doers are not suffered
any longtime, but forthwith punished.</ab>
<ab n="14">For not as
with other nations whom the Lord patiently forbeareth to punish,
till they be come to the fulnesse of their sinnes, so dealeth he
with vs,</ab>
<ab n="15">Lest that
being come to the height of sinne, afterwards hee should take
vengeance of vs.</ab>
<ab n="16">And therfore
he neuer withdraweth his mercie from vs: and though he punish with
aduersitie, yet doeth he neuer forsake his people.</ab>
<ab n="17">But let this
that we haue spoken be for a warning vnto vs: And nowe will wee
come to the declaring of the matter in few words.</ab>
<ab n="18">Eleazar one
of the principall Scribes, an aged man, and of a well fauoured
countenance, was constrained to open his mouth, and to eate swines
flesh.</ab>
<ab n="19">But he
chusing rather to die gloriously, then to liue stained with such an
abomination, spit it forth, and came of his owne accord to the
torment,</ab>
<ab n="20">As it behoued
them to come, that are resolute to stand out against such things,
as are not lawfull for loue of life to be tasted.</ab>
<ab n="21">But they that
had the charge of that wicked feast, for the olde acquaintance they
had with the man, taking him aside, besought him to bring flesh of
his owne prouision, such as was lawfull for him to vse, and make as
if he did eate of the flesh, taken from the sacrifice commanded by
the king,</ab>
<ab n="22">That in so
doing hee might bee deliuered from death, and for the olde
friendship with them, find fauour.</ab>
<ab n="23">But he began
to consider discreetly, and as became his age, and the excellencie
of his ancient yeeres, and the honour of his gray head, whereunto
hee was come, and his most honest education from a child, or rather
the holy lawe made, and giuen by God: therefore hee answered
accordingly, and willed them straightwaies to send him to the
graue.</ab>
<ab n="24">For it
becommeth not our age, said he, in any wise to dissemble, whereby
many yong persons might thinke, that Eleazar being fourescore yeres
old and ten, were now gone to a strange religion.</ab>
<ab n="25">And so they
through mine hypocrisie, and desire to liue a litle time, and a
moment longer, should bee deceiued by me, and I get a staine to
mine olde age, and make it abominable.</ab>
<ab n="26">For though
for the present time I should be deliuered from the punishment of
men: yet should I not escape the hand of the Almightie, neither
aliue nor dead.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore now
manfully changing this life, I will shew my selfe such an one, as
mine age requireth,</ab>
<ab n="28">And leaue a
notable example to such as bee yong, to die willingly, and
couragiously, for the honourable and holy lawes: and when he had
said these words, immediatly he went to the torment,</ab>
<ab n="29">They that led
him, changing the good will they bare him a litle before, into
hatred, because the foresaid speaches proceeded as they thought,
from a desperate minde.<note> Or, madnes or pride.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But when hee
was readie to die with stripes, he groned, and said, It is manifest
vnto the Lord, that hath the holy knowledge, that wheras I might
haue bin deliuered from death, I [now] endure sore paines in body,
by being beaten: but in soule am well content to suffer these
things, because I feare him.</ab>
<ab n="31">And thus this
man died, leauing his death for an example of a noble courage, and
a memoriall of vertue not only vnto yong men, but vnto all his
nation.</ab>



</div>