<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Maccabees-Chapter-16-16-2-Maccabees.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 A letter of the Iewes from
Ierusalem to them of Egypt, to thanke God for the death of
Antiochus. 19 Of the fire that was hidde in the pit. 24 The prayer
of Nehemias.</head>

<ab n="1">The brethren
the Iewes that bee at Ierusalem, and in the lande of Iudea, wish
vnto the brethren the Iewes that are throughout Egypt, health and
peace.</ab>
<ab n="2">God be
gracious vnto you, and remember his Couenant that hee made with
Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, his faithfull seruants:</ab>
<ab n="3">And giue you
all an heart to serue him, and to doe his will, with a good
courage, and a willing minde:</ab>
<ab n="4">And open your
hearts in his law and commandements, &amp; send you peace:</ab>
<ab n="5">And heare your
prayers, and be at one with you, and neuer forsake you in time of
trouble.</ab>
<ab n="6">And now wee be
here praying for you.</ab>
<ab n="7">What time as
Demetrius reigned, in the hundred threescore and ninth yeere, wee
the Iewes wrote vnto you, in the extremitie of trouble, that came
vpon vs in those yeeres, from the time that Iason and his company
reuolted from the holy land, and kingdome,</ab>
<ab n="8">And burnt the
porch, and shed innocent blood. Then we prayed vnto the Lord, and
were heard: we offered also sacrifices, and fine flowre, and
lighted the lampes, and set forth the loaues.</ab>
<ab n="9">And now see
that ye keepe the feast of Tabernacles in the moneth
Casleu.<note> Leuit. 23. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">In the
hundreth, fourescore, and eight yeere, the people that were at
Ierusalem, and in Iudea, and the counsel, and Iudas, sent greeting
and health vnto Aristobulus, king Ptolomeus master, who was of the
stock of the anointed priests, and to the Iewes that were in
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="11">Insomuch as
God hath deliuered vs from great perils, wee thanke him highly, as
hauing bin in battell against a king.</ab>
<ab n="12">For he cast
them out that fought within the holy citie.</ab>
<ab n="13">For when the
leader was come into Persia, and the armie with him that seemed
inuincible, they were slaine in the temple of Nanea, by the deceit
of Naneas priests.</ab>
<ab n="14">For
Antiochus, as though hee would marrie her, came into the place, and
his friends that were with him, to receiue money in name of a
dowrie.</ab>
<ab n="15">Which when
the priests of Nanea had set forth, and he was entred with a small
company into the compasse of the temple, they shut the temple
assoone as Antiochus was come in.</ab>
<ab n="16">And opening a
priuie doore of the roofe, they threw stones like thunderbolts, and
stroke downe the captaine, hewed them in pieces, smote off their
heads, and cast them to those that were without.</ab>
<ab n="17">Blessed be
our God in all things, who hath deliuered vp the vngodly.</ab>
<ab n="18">Therefore
whereas we are nowe purposed to keep the purification of the Temple
vpon the fiue &amp; twentieth day of the moneth Casleu, we thought
it necessary to certifie you thereof, that ye also might keepe it,
as the [feast] of the tabernacles, and of the fire [which was giuen
vs] when Neemias offered sacrifice, after that he had builded the
Temple, and the Altar.<note> Leuit. 23. numb. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For when our
fathers were led into Persia, the Priests that were then deuout,
took the fire of the Altar priuily, &amp; hid it in a hollow place
of a pit without water, where they kept it sure, so that the place
was vnknowen to all men.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now after
many yeeres, when it pleased God, Neemias being sent from the king
of Persia, did send of the posteritie of those Priests that had hid
it, to the fire: but when they tolde vs they found no fire, but
thicke water,</ab>
<ab n="21">Then
cōmanded he them to draw it vp, and to bring it: and when the
sacrifices were laid on, Neemias cōmanded the Priests to
sprinkle þ<note/> wood, and the things laid thereupon
with þ<note/> water.</ab>
<ab n="22">When this was
done, and the time came that the Sun shone which afore was hid in
the cloude, there was a great fire kindled, so that euery man
marueiled.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
Priests made a prayer whilest the sacrifice was consuming, [I say]
both the Priests, and all the rest, Ionathan beginning, and the
rest answering thereunto, as Neemias did.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the
prayer was after this maner, O Lord, Lord God, Creatour of all
things, who art fearefull, and strong, and righteous, and
mercifull, and the onely, and gracious king,</ab>
<ab n="25">The onely
giuer of all things, the onely iust, almightie &amp; euerlasting,
thou that deliuerest Israel from al trouble, &amp; didst choose the
fathers, &amp; sanctifie them:</ab>
<ab n="26">Receiue the
sacrifice for thy whole people Israel, and preserue thine owne
portion, and sanctifie it.</ab>
<ab n="27">Gather those
together that are scattered frō vs, deliuer them that serue
among the heathen, looke vpon them that are despised &amp;
abhorred, and let the heathen know that thou art our God.</ab>
<ab n="28">Punish them
that oppresse vs, and with pride doe vs wrong.</ab>
<ab n="29">Plant thy
people againe in thy holy place, as Moises hath spoken.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the
Priests sung psalmes of thankesgiuing.</ab>
<ab n="31">Now when the
sacrifice was consumed, Neemias commanded the water that was left,
to bee powred on the great stones.</ab>
<ab n="32">When this was
done, there was kindled a flame: but it was consumed by the light
that shined from the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="33">So when this
matter was knowen, it was told the king of Persia, that in the
place, where the Priests that were led away, had hid the fire,
there appeared water, and that Neemias had purified the sacrifices
therewith.<note> Or, Neemias his company.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Then the king
inclosing the place, made it holy after he had tried
þ<note/> matter.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the king
tooke many gifts, and bestowed thereof, on those whom he would
gratifie.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Neemias
called this thing Naphthar, which is as much to say as a cleansing:
but many men call it Nephi.</ab>



</div>