<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>The constancie and cruell death of
seuen brethren and their mother in one day, because they would not
eate swines flesh at the kings commandement.</head>

<ab n="1">It came to
passe also that seuen brethren with their mother were taken, and
compelled by the king against the lawe to taste swines flesh, and
were tormented with scourges, and whips:</ab>
<ab n="2">But one of
them that spake first said thus: What wouldest thou aske, or learne
of vs? we are ready to die, rather then to transgresse the lawes of
our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then the king
being in a rage, commanded pannes, and caldrons to be made
whot.</ab>
<ab n="4">Which
forthwith being heated, he commanded to cut out the tongue of him
that spake first, and to cut off the vtmost parts of his body, the
rest of his brethren, and his mother looking on.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now when he
was thus maimed in all his members, he commanded him being yet
aliue, to be brought to the fire, and to be fried in the panne: and
as the vapour of the panne was for a good space dispersed, they
exhorted one another, with the mother, to die manfully, saying
thus:</ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord God
looketh vpon vs, and in trueth hath comfort in vs, as Moises in his
song, which witnessed to their faces declared, saying, And he shall
be comforted in his seruants.<note> Deut. 32. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So when the
first was dead, after this maner, they brought the second to make
him a mocking stocke: and when they had pulled off the skin of his
head with the haire, they asked him, Wilt thou eate before thou bee
punished throughout euery member of thy body?</ab>
<ab n="8">But hee
answered in his owne language, and said, No. Wherefore hee also
receiued the next torment in order, as the former did.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when hee
was at the last gaspe, hee said, Thou like a fury takest vs out of
this present life, but the king of the world shall raise vs vp, who
haue died for his lawes, vnto euerlasting life.</ab>
<ab n="10">After him was
the third made a mocking stocke, and when he was required, he put
out his tongue, and that right soone, holding forth his hands
manfully,</ab>
<ab n="11">And said
couragiously, These I had from heauen, and for his lawes I despise
them, and from him I hope to receiue them againe.</ab>
<ab n="12">Insomuch that
the king, and they that were with him marueiled at the yong mans
courage, for that he nothing regarded the paines.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now when this
man was dead also, they tormented and mangled the fourth in like
maner.</ab>
<ab n="14">So when he
was ready to die, he said thus, It is good, being put to death by
men, to looke for hope from God to be raised vp againe by him: as
for thee thou shalt haue no resurrection to life.</ab>
<ab n="15">Afterward
they brought the fift also, and mangled him.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then looked
hee vnto the king and said, Thou hast power ouer men, thou art
corruptible, thou doest what thou wilt, yet thinke not that our
nation is forsaken of God.</ab>
<ab n="17">But abide a
while, and behold his great power, how he will torment thee, and
thy seed.</ab>
<ab n="18">After him
also they brought the sixt, who being ready to die, said, Be not
deceiued without cause: for we suffer these things for our selues,
hauing sinned against our God. Therefore marueilous things are done
(vnto vs.)</ab>
<ab n="19">But thinke
not thou that takest in hand to striue against God, that thou shalt
escape vnpunished.</ab>
<ab n="20">But the
mother was marueilous aboue all, and worthy of honorable memorie:
for when shee sawe her seuen sonnes slaine within the space of one
day, she bare it with a good courage, because of the hope that she
had in þe Lord</ab>
<ab n="21">Yea she
exhorted euery one of them in her owne language, filled with
couragious spirits, and stirring vp her womanish thoughts, with a
manly stomacke, she said vnto them,</ab>
<ab n="22">I cannot tell
how you came into my wombe: for I neither gaue you breath, nor
life, neither was it I that formed the mēbers of euery one of
you.</ab>
<ab n="23">But
doubtlesse the Creator of the world, who formed the generation of
man, and found out the beginning of all things, wil also of his
owne mercy giue you breath, and life againe, as you now regard not
your owne selues for his Lawes sake.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now Antiochus
thinking himselfe despised, and suspecting it to be a reprochfull
speach, whiles the yongest was yet aliue, did not onely exhort him
by wordes, but also assured him with oathes, that he would make him
both a rich, and a happy man, if hee would turne from the Lawes of
his fathers, and that also he would take him for his friend, and
trust him with affaires.</ab>
<ab n="25">But when the
yong man would in no case hearken vnto him, the king called his
mother, and exhorted her, that she would counsell the yong man to
saue his life.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when hee
had exhorted her with many words, she promised him that she would
counsell her sonne.</ab>
<ab n="27">But shee
bowing her selfe towards him, laughing the cruell tyrant to scorne,
spake in her countrey language on this maner; O my sonne, haue
pitie vpon mee that bare thee nine moneths in my wombe, and gaue
thee sucke three yeeres, and nourished thee, and brought thee vp
vnto this age, and endured the troubles of education.</ab>
<ab n="28">I beseech
thee, my sonne, looke vpon the heauen, and the earth, and all that
is therein, and consider that God made them of things that were
not, and so was mankinde made likewise;</ab>
<ab n="29">Feare not
this tormentour, but being worthy of thy brethren, take thy death,
that I may receiue thee againe in mercy with thy brethren.</ab>
<ab n="30">Whiles she
was yet speaking these words, the yong man said, Whom wait ye for?
I will not obey the kings commandement: but I will obey the
commandement of the Law that was giuen vnto our fathers, by
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="31">And thou that
hast bene the authour of all mischiefe against the Hebrewes, shalt
not escape the handes of God.</ab>
<ab n="32">For wee
suffer because of our sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="33">And though
the liuing Lord bee angrie with vs a little while for our
chastening and correction, yet shall hee be at one againe, with his
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="34">But thou, O
godlesse man, and of all other most wicked, be not lifted vp
without a cause, nor puffed vp with vncertaine hopes, lifting vp
thy hand against the seruants of God:</ab>
<ab n="35">For thou hast
not yet escaped the iudgement of Almightie God, who seeth all
things.</ab>
<ab n="36">For our
brethren who now haue suffered a short paine, are dead vnder Gods
Couenant of euerlasting life: but thou through the iudgement of
God, shalt receiue iust punishment for thy pride.</ab>
<ab n="37">But I, as my
brethren, offer vp my body, and life for the Lawes of our fathers,
beseeching God that he would speedily bee mercifull vnto our
nation, and that thou by torments &amp; plagues mayest confesse,
that he alone is God;</ab>
<ab n="38">And that in
me, and my brethren, the wrath of the Almighty, which is iustly
brought vpon all our nation, may cease.</ab>
<ab n="39">Then the King
being in a rage, handled him worse then all the rest, and took it
grieuously that he was mocked.</ab>
<ab n="40">So this man
died vndefiled, and put his whole trust in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="41">Last of all
after the sonnes, the mother died.</ab>
<ab n="42">Let this be
ynough now to haue spoken cōcerning the idolatrous feasts, and
the extreme tortures.</ab>



</div>