<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>6 Alcimus accuseth Iudas. 18 Nicanor
maketh peace with Iudas. 39 He seeketh to take Rhafis, 46 who to
escape his hands, killeth himselfe.</head>

<ab n="1">After three
yeres was Iudas enformed that Demetrius the sonne of Seleucus
hauing entred by the hauen of Tripolis with a great power and
nauie,</ab>
<ab n="2">Had taken the
countrey, and killed Antiochus, and Lysias his protectour.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now one
Alcimus who had beene hie Priest, and had defiled himselfe wilfully
in the times of their mingling (with the Gentiles) seeing that by
no meanes hee could saue himselfe, nor haue any more accesse to the
holy Altar,</ab>
<ab n="4">Came to king
Demetrius in the hundreth and one and fiftieth yeere, presenting
vnto him a crowne of golde, and a palme, and also of the boughes
which were vsed solemnly in the Temple: and so that day he helde
his peace.<note> Or, thought to be of the Temple.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Howbeit
hauing gotten opportunity to further his foolish enterprise, [and]
being called into counsel by Demetrius, &amp; asked how the Iewes
stood affected, and what they intēded, he answered
therunto;</ab>
<ab n="6">Those of the
Iewes that bee called Asideans (whose captaine is Iudas Maccabeus)
nourish warre, and are seditious; and will not let the realme be in
peace.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therfore I
being depriued of mine ancestors honor (I meane the hie Priesthood)
am now come hither.</ab>
<ab n="8">First verily
for the vnfained care I haue of things pertaining to the king, and
secondly, euen for that I intend the good of mine owne countrey
men: for all our nation is in no small misery, through the
vnaduised dealing of them aforesaid.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore, O
king, seeing thou knowest all these things, bee carefull for the
countrey, and our nation, which is pressed on euery side, according
to the clemency that thou readily shewest vnto all.</ab>
<ab n="10">For as long
as Iudas liueth, it is not possible that the state should be
quiet.</ab>
<ab n="11">This was no
sooner spoken of him, but others of the kings friends being
malitiously set against Iudas, did more incense Demetrius.</ab>
<ab n="12">And
foorthwith calling Nicanor, who had bene master of the Elephants,
and making him gouernour ouer Iudea, he sent him forth,</ab>
<ab n="13">Cōmanding
him to slay Iudas, &amp; to scatter them that were [wt] him, &amp;
to make Alcimus high priest of the great Temple.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then the
heathen that had fled out of Iudea from Iudas, came to Nicanor by
flocks, thinking the harme and calamities of the Iewes, to be their
well-fare.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now when the
Iewes heard of Nicanors comming, and that the heathen were vp
against them, they cast earth vpon their heads, and made
supplication to him that had stablished his people for euer, and
who alwayes helpeth his portion with manifestation of his
presence.<note> Or, were ioyned to them.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">So at the
commandement of the captaine, they remooued straightwayes from
thence, and came neere vnto them, at the towne of Deffaro.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now Simon,
Iudas brother, had ioyned battell with Nicanor, but was somewhat
discomfited, through the suddaine silence of his enemies.</ab>
<ab n="18">Neuerthelesse
Nicanor hearing of the manlinesse of them that were with Iudas, and
the courageousnes that they had to fight for their countrey, durst
not try the matter by the sword.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherefore he
sent Posidonius, and Theodotus, &amp; Mattathias to make
peace.</ab>
<ab n="20">So when they
had taken long aduisement thereupon, and the captaine had made
þ<note/> multitude acquainted therewith, and it appeared
that they were all of one minde, they consented to the
couenants,</ab>
<ab n="21">And
appointed a day to meet in together by themselues, &amp; when the
day came, and stooles were set for either of them,</ab>
<ab n="22">Iudas placed
armed men ready in conuenient places, lest some treachery should
bee suddenly practised by the enemies; so they made a peaceable
cōference.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now Nicanor
abode in Ierusalem, and did no hurt, but sent away the people that
came flocking vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And hee
would not willingly haue Iudas out of his sight: for hee loued the
man from his heart.</ab>
<ab n="25">He praied
him also to take a wife, and to beget children: so he maried, was
quiet, and tooke part of this life.<note> Or, liued together with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But Alcimus
perceiuing the loue that was betwixt them, and considering the
couenants that were made, came to Demetrius, and tolde him that
Nicanor was not well affected towards the state, for that he had
ordained Iudas, a traitor to his realme, to be the kings
successour.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then the
king being in a rage, and prouoked with the accusations of the most
wicked man, wrote to Nicanor, signifying that he was much
displeased with the couenants, and commaunding him that hee should
send Maccabeus prisoner in all haste vnto Antioch.</ab>
<ab n="28">When this
came to Nicanors hearing, he was much cōfounded in himselfe,
and tooke it grieuously, that hee should make voyd the articles
which were agreed vpon, the man being in no fault.</ab>
<ab n="29">But because
there was no dealing against the king, hee watched his time to
accomplish this thing by pollicie.</ab>
<ab n="30">Notwithstāding
when Maccabeus saw that Nicanor began to bee churlish vnto him, and
that he entreated him more roughly then he was wont, perceiuing
þ<note/> such sowre behauiour came not of good, hee
gathered together not a few of his men, and withdrew himselfe
frō Nicanor.</ab>
<ab n="31">But the
other knowing that he was notably preuented by Iudas policie, came
into the great and holy Temple, and commanded the Priestes that
were offering their vsual sacrifices, to deliuer him
þ<note/> man.</ab>
<ab n="32">And whē
they sware that they could not tel where þ<note/> man
was, whō he sought,</ab>
<ab n="33">Hee
stretched out his right hand toward the Temple, &amp; made an oath
in this maner: If you wil not deliuer me Iudas as a prisoner, I
will lay this Temple of God euen with the ground, and I will breake
downe the Altar, and erect a notable temple vnto
Bacchus.<note> Greeke, bound.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">After these
words he departed; then the Priests lift vp their handes towards
heauen, &amp; besought him þ<note/> was euer a
defēder of their nation, saying in this maner:</ab>
<ab n="35">Thou, O Lord
of all things, who hast neede of nothing, wast pleased that the
Temple of thine habitation should be among vs.</ab>
<ab n="36">Therefore
now, O holy Lord of all holinesse, keepe this house euer vndefiled,
which lately was cleansed, and stop euery vnrighteous
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="37">Now was
there accused vnto Nicanor, one Razis, one of the Elders of
Ierusalem, a louer of his countrey men, and a man of very good
report, who for his kindnesse was called a father of
þ<note/> Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="38">For in the
former times, when they mingled not themselues with the Gentiles,
he had bin accused of Iudaisme, and did boldly ieopard his body and
life with al vehemency for the religion of þ<note/>
Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="39">So Nicanor
willing to declare the hate that he bare vnto the Iewes, sent aboue
fiue hūdred men of war to take him.</ab>
<ab n="40">For he
thought by taking him to do [the Iewes] much hurt.</ab>
<ab n="41">Now when the
multitude would haue taken the towre, and violently broken into the
vtter doore, and bade that fire should be brought to burne it, he
being ready to be taken on euery side, fell vpon his sword,</ab>
<ab n="42">Chusing
rather to die manfully, then to come into the hands of the wicked
to be abused otherwise then beseemed his noble birth.</ab>
<ab n="43">But missing
his stroke through haste, the multitude also rushing within the
doores, he ran boldly vp to the wall, and cast himselfe downe
manfully among the thickest of them.</ab>
<ab n="44">But they
quickly giuing backe, and a space being made, he fell downe into
the midst of the void place.</ab>
<ab n="45">Neuerthelesse
while there was yet breath within him, being inflamed with anger,
he rose vp, and though his blood gushed out like spouts of water,
and his wounds were grieuous, yet hee ranne through the midst of
the throng, and standing vpon a steepe rocke,</ab>
<ab n="46">When as his
blood was now quite gone, hee pluckt out his bowels, &amp; taking
them in both his hands, hee cast them vpon the throng, and calling
vpon the Lord of life and spirit to restore him those againe, he
thus died.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>