<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-15-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>5 Nicanors blasphemie. 8 Iudas
incourageth his men by his dreame. 28 Nicanor is
slaine.</head>

<ab n="1">But Nicanor
hearing that Iudas and his company were in the strong places about
Samaria, resolued without any danger to set vpon them on
þe sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="2">Neuertheles,
the Iewes that were compelled to go with him, said, O destroy not
so cruelly and barbarously, but giue honour to that day, which he
that seeth all things, hath honoured with holinesse aboue [other
dayes.]</ab>
<ab n="3">Then this
most vngracious wretch demanded, if there were a mightie one in
heauen that had commanded the Sabbath day to be kept.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when they
said, There is in heauen a liuing Lord, and mightie, who commanded
the seuenth day to be kept,</ab>
<ab n="5">Then said the
other, And I also am mightie vpon earth, &amp; I cōmand to
take armes, and to do the kings busines: yet he obteined not to
haue his wicked wil done.</ab>
<ab n="6">So Nicanor in
exceeding pride and haughtinesse, determined to set vp a publike
moument of his victorie ouer Iudas, and them that were with
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">But Maccabeus
had euer sure confidence that the Lord would helpe him.</ab>
<ab n="8">Wherfore he
exhorted his people not to feare the comming of the heathen against
them, but to remember the helpe which in former times they had
receiued from heauen, and now to expect the victory, and aid which
should come vnto them from the Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="9">And so
comforting them out of the law, and the prophets, and withall
putting them in mind of the battels that they won afore, he made
them more cheerefull.</ab>
<ab n="10">And when he
had stirred vp their minds, he gaue them their charge, shewing them
therewithall the falshood of the heathen, and the breach of
othes.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus he
armed euery one of them not so much with defence of shields and
speares, as with comfortable and good words: and besides that, he
tolde them a dreame worthy to be beleeued, as if it had bin so
indeed, which did not a litle reioyce them.</ab>
<ab n="12">And this was
his vision: that Onias, who had bin high Priest, a vertuous, and a
good man, reuerend in conuersation, gentle in condition, well
spoken also, and exercised from a child in all points of vertue,
holding vp his hands, prayed for the whole bodie of the
Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="13">This done,
in like maner there appeared a man with gray haires, &amp;
exceeding glorious, who was of a wonderfull and excellent
maiestie.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then Onias
answered, saying, This is a louer of the brethren, who prayeth much
for the people, and for the holy citie, (to wit) Ieremias
þe prophet of God.</ab>
<ab n="15">Whereupon
Ieremias, holding forth his right hand, gaue to Iudas a sword of
gold, and in giuing it spake thus:</ab>
<ab n="16">Take this
holy sword a gift from God, with the which thou shalt wound the
aduersaries.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thus being
well comforted by the words of Iudas, which were very good, and
able to stirre them vp to valour, and to encourage the hearts of
the yong men, they determined not to pitch campe, but couragiously
to set vpon them, and manfully to trie the matter by conflict,
because the citie, and the Sanctuarie, and the Temple were in
danger.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the care
that they tooke for their wiues, and their children, their
brethren, and kinsfolkes, was in least account with them: but the
greatest, and principall feare, was for the holy Temple.</ab>
<ab n="19">Also they
that were in the citie, tooke not the least care, being troubled
for the conflict abroad.</ab>
<ab n="20">And now when
as all looked what should bee þe triall, &amp; the
enemies were already come neere, and the armie was set in aray, and
the beasts conueniently placed, and the horsemen set in
wings:</ab>
<ab n="21">Maccabeus
seeing the comming of the multitude, and the diuers preparations of
armour, and the fiercenesse of the beasts, stretched out his hands
towards heauen, and called vpon the Lord, that worketh wonders,
knowing that victorie commeth not by armes, but euen as it seemeth
good to him, he giueth it to such as are worthy:</ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore in
his prayer he said after this maner: O Lord, thou diddest send
thine Angel in the time of Ezekias king of Iudea, and diddest slay
in the host of Sennacherib, an hundred, fourescore, and fiue
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="23">Wherfore now
also O Lord of heauen, send a good Angel before vs, for a feare,
and dread vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="24">And through
the might of thine arme, let those bee stricken with terror, that
come against thy holy people to blaspheme. And he ended
thus.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then
Nicanor, and they that were with him came forward with trumpets,
and songs.</ab>
<ab n="26">But Iudas,
and his company encountred the enemies with inuocation, and
prayer.</ab>
<ab n="27">So that
fighting with their hands, and praying vnto God with their hearts,
they slew no lesse then thirty and fiue thousand men: for through
the appearance of God, they were greatly cheered.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now when the
battell was done, returning againe with ioy, they knew that Nicanor
lay dead in his harnesse.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then they
made a great shout, and a noise, praising the Almighty in their
owne language:</ab>
<ab n="30">And Iudas,
who was euer the chiefe defender of the citizens both in body, and
minde, and who continued his loue towards his countrymen all his
life, commanded to strike off Nicanors head, and his hand, with his
shoulder, &amp; bring them to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="31">So when he
was there, and had called them of his nation together, and set the
priests before the altar, he sent for them that were of the
Towre,</ab>
<ab n="32">And shewed
them vile Nicanors head, and the hand of that blasphemer, which
with proud brags he had stretched out against the holy Temple of
the Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="33">And when he
had cut out the tongue of that vngodly Nicanor, he commanded that
they should giue it by pieces vnto the foules, and hang vp the
reward of his madnesse before the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="34">So euery man
praised towards the heauen the glorious Lord, saying, Blessed be
hee that hath kept his owne place vndefiled.</ab>
<ab n="35">He hanged
also Nicanors head vpon the Towre, an euident, and manifest signe
vnto all, of the helpe of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="36">And they
ordained all with a common decree, in no case to let that day passe
without solemnitie: but to celebrate the thirteenth day of the
twelfth moneth, which in the Syrian tongue is called Adar, the day
before Mardocheus day.</ab>
<ab n="37">Thus went it
with Nicanor, and from that time forth, the Hebrewes had the citie
in their power: and heere will I make an end.</ab>
<ab n="38">And if I
haue done well, and as is fitting the story, it is that which I
desired: but if slenderly, and meanly, it is that which I could
attaine vnto.</ab>
<ab n="39">For as it is
hurtfull to drinke wine, or water alone; &amp; as wine mingled with
water is pleasant, and delighteth the tast: euen so speech finely
framed, delighteth the eares of them that read the storie. And
heere shall be an end.</ab>




</div>