<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>2 Of the signes and tokens seene in
Ierusalem. 6 Of the end and wickednesse of Iason. 11 The pursuit of
Antiochus against the Iewes. 15 The spoiling of the Temple. 27
Maccabeus fleeth into the wildernes.</head>

<ab n="1">About the same
time Antiochus prepared his second voyage into Egypt:</ab>
<ab n="2">And then it
happened, that through all the citie, for the space almost of
fourtie dayes, there were seene horsemen running in the aire, in
cloth of golde, and armed with lances, like a band of
souldiers,</ab>
<ab n="3">And troupes of
horsemen in aray, incountring, and running one against another with
shaking of shieldes, and multitude of pikes, and drawing of swords,
and casting of darts, and glittering of golden ornaments, and
harnesse of all sorts.<note> Or, staues.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Wherefore
euery man praied that that apparition might turne to good.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now when there
was gone forth a false rumour, as though Antiochus had bene dead,
Iason tooke at the least a thousand men, and suddenly made an
assault vpon the citie, and they that were vpon the walles, being
put backe, and the citie at length taken, Menelaus fled into the
castle:</ab>
<ab n="6">But Iason slew
his owne citizens without mercy, (not considering that to get the
day of them of his owne nation, would be a most vnhappy day for
him: but thinking they had bene his enemies, and not his countrey
men whom he conquered.)</ab>
<ab n="7">Howbeit, for
all this hee obtained not the principalitie, but at the last
receiued shame for the reward of his treason, and fled againe into
the countrey of the Ammonites.</ab>
<ab n="8">In the end
therefore hee had an vnhappy returne, being accused before Aretas
the king of the Arabians, fleeing from city to city, pursued of all
men, hated as a forsaker of the Lawes, and being had in
abomination, as an open enemie of his countrey, and countreymen, he
was cast out into Egypt.<note> Or, executioner.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thus hee that
had driuen many out of their countrey, perished in a strange land,
retiring to the Lacedemonians, and thinking there to finde succour
by reason of his kindred.</ab>
<ab n="10">And hee that
had cast out many vnburied, had none to mourne for him, nor any
solemne funerals at all, nor sepulchre with his fathers.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now when this
that was done came to the kings eare, he thought that Iudea had
reuolted, whereupon remouing out of Egypt in a furious minde, he
tooke the citie by force of armes,</ab>
<ab n="12">And
commaunded his men of warre not to spare such as they met, and to
slay such as went vp vpon the houses.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thus there
was killing of yong and old, making away of men, women and
children, slaying of virgins and infants.</ab>
<ab n="14">And there
were destroyed within the space of three whole daies, fourescore
thousand, whereof fourty thousand were slaine in the conflict; and
no fewer sold, then slaine.</ab>
<ab n="15">Yet was he
not content with this, but presumed to goe into the most holy
Temple of all the world: Menelaus that traitour to the Lawes, and
to his owne countrey, being his guide.</ab>
<ab n="16">And taking
the holy vessels with polluted handes, and with prophane handes,
pulling downe the things that were dedicated by other kings, to the
augmentation and glory and honour of the place, he gaue them
away.</ab>
<ab n="17">And so
haughtie was Antiochus in minde, that hee considered not that the
Lord was angry for a while for the sinnes of them that dwelt in the
citie, and therefore his eye was not vpon the place.</ab>
<ab n="18">For had they
not beene formerly wrapped in many sinnes, this man as soone as hee
had come, had foorthwith beene scourged, and put backe from his
presumption, as Heliodorus was, whom Seleucus the king sent to view
the treasurie.</ab>
<ab n="19">Neuerthelesse
God did not choose the people for the places sake, but the place
for the peoples sake.</ab>
<ab n="20">And therefore
the place it selfe that was partaker with them of the aduersities
that happened to the nation, did afterward communicate in the
benefits sent from the Lord: and as it was forsaken in the wrath of
the Almighty, so againe the great Lord being reconciled, it was set
vp with all glory.</ab>
<ab n="21">So when
Antiochus had caried out of the Temple, a thousand and eight
hundred talents, hee departed in all haste into Antiochia, weening
in his pride to make the land nauigable, and the Sea passable by
foot: such was the haughtinesse of his minde.</ab>
<ab n="22">And he left
gouernours to vexe the nation: at Ierusalem Philip, for his
countrey a Phrygian, and for manners more barbarous then hee that
set him there:</ab>
<ab n="23">And at
Garizim, Andronicus; and besides, Menelaus, who worse then all the
rest, bare an heauie hand ouer the citizens, hauing a malicious
minde against his countreymen the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="24">He sent also
that detestable ringleader Apollonius, with an armie of two and
twentie thousand, commaunding him to slay all those that were in
their best age, and to sell the women and the yonger sort:</ab>
<ab n="25">Who comming
to Ierusalem, and pretending peace, did forbeare till the holy day
of the Sabbath, when taking the Iewes keeping holy day, hee
commanded his men to arme themselues.</ab>
<ab n="26">And so hee
slewe all them that were gone to the celebrating of the Sabbath,
and running through the city with weapons, slewe great
multitudes.</ab>
<ab n="27">But Iudas
Maccabeus, with nine others, or thereabout, withdrew himselfe into
the wildernesse, and liued in the mountaines after the maner of
beasts, with his company, who fed on herbes continually, lest they
should be partakers of the pollution.<note> Gr. who was the tenth.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>