<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Of the honour done to the Temple
by the Kings of the Gentiles. 4 Simon vttereth what treasures are
in the Temple. 7 Heliodorus is sent to take them away. 24 He is
stricken of God, and healed at the praier of Onias.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when the
holy Citie was inhabited with all peace, and the Lawes were kept
very well, because of the godlinesse of Onias the high Priest, and
his hatred of wickednesse,</ab>
<ab n="2">It came to
passe that euen the Kings themselues did honour the place, and
magnifie the Temple with their best gifts;</ab>
<ab n="3">Insomuch that
Seleucus king of Asia, of his owne reuenues, bare all the costes
belonging to the seruice of the sacrifices.</ab>
<ab n="4">But one Simon
of the tribe of Beniamin, who was made gouernour of the Temple,
fell out with the high Priest about disorder in the citie.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when he
could not ouercome Onias, he gate him to Apollonius the sonne of
Thraseas, who then was gouernour of Coelosyria, and
Phenice,</ab>
<ab n="6">And told him
that the treasurie in Ierusalem was full of infinite summes of
money, so that the multitude of their riches which did not pertaine
to the account of the sacrifices, was innumerable, and that it was
possible to bring all into the kings hand.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now when
Apollonius came to the king, and had shewed him of the money,
whereof he was told, the king chose out Heliodorus his treasurer,
and sent him with a commaundement, to bring him the foresaid
money.</ab>
<ab n="8">So foorthwith
Heliodorus tooke his iourney vnder a colour of visiting the cities
of Coelosyria, and Phenice, but indeed to fulfill the kings
purpose.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when he
was come to Ierusalem, &amp; had bene courteously receiued of the
high Priest of the citie, hee told him what intelligence was giuen
of the money, &amp; declared wherefore hee came, and and asked if
these things were so in deed.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then the high
Priest tolde him that there was such money layde vp for the reliefe
of widowes, and fatherlesse children,</ab>
<ab n="11">And that some
of it belonged to Hircanus, sonne of Tobias, a man of great
dignitie, and not as that wicked Simon had misinformed: the summe
whereof in all was foure hundred talents of siluer, and two hundred
of gold,</ab>
<ab n="12">And that it
was altogether impossible that such wrong should be done vnto them,
that had committed it to the holinesse of the place, and to the
maiestie and inuiolable sanctitie of the Temple, honoured ouer all
the world.</ab>
<ab n="13">But
Heliodorus because of the kings commandement giuen him, said, That
in any wise it must be brought into the kings treasury.</ab>
<ab n="14">So at the day
which hee appointed, hee entred in to order this matter, wherefore,
there was no small agonie throughout the whole citie.</ab>
<ab n="15">But the
Priests prostrating themselues before the Altar in their Priests
Uestments, called vnto heauen vpon him that made a Lawe concerning
things giuen to bee kept, that they should safely bee preserued for
such as had committed them to be kept.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then whoso
had looked the hie Priest in the face, it would haue wounded his
heart: for his countenance, and the changing of his colour,
declared the inward agonie of his minde:</ab>
<ab n="17">For the man
was so compassed with feare, and horror of the body, that it was
manifest to them that looked vpon him, what sorrow hee had now in
his heart.</ab>
<ab n="18">Others ran
flocking out of their houses to the generall Supplication, because
the place was like to come into contempt.<note> Or, to make generall supplication.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the women
girt with sackecloth vnder their breasts, abounded in the streetes,
and the virgins that were kept in, ran some to the gates, and some
to the walles, and others looked out of the windowes:</ab>
<ab n="20">And all
holding their handes towards heauen, made supplication.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then it would
haue pitied a man to see the falling downe of the multitude of all
sorts, and the feare of the hie Priest, being in such an
agony.<note> Gr, expellation.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">They then
called vpon the Almightie Lord, to keepe the things committed of
trust, safe and sure, for those that had committed them.</ab>
<ab n="23">Neuerthelesse
Heliodorus executed that which was decreed.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now as hee
was there present himselfe with his guard about the treasurie, the
Lord of spirits, &amp; the Prince of all power caused a great
apparition, so that all that presumed to come in with him, were
astonished at the power of God, and fainted, and were sore
afraid.<note> Or, Lord of our fathers.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For there
appeared vnto them a horse, with a terrible rider vpon him, and
adorned with a very faire couering, and he ranne fiercely, and
smote at Heliodorus with his forefeet, and it seemed that hee that
sate vpon the horse, had complete harnesse of golde.</ab>
<ab n="26">Moreouer two
other yong men appeared before him, notable in strength, excellent
in beautie, and comely in apparell, who stood by him on either
side, and scourged him continually, and gaue him many sore
stripes.</ab>
<ab n="27">And
Heliodorus fell suddenly vnto the ground, and was compassed with
great darkenesse: but they that were with him, tooke him vp, and
put him into a litter.</ab>
<ab n="28">Thus him that
lately came with a great traine, and with all his guard into the
said treasury, they caried out, being vnable to helpe himselfe with
his weapons: and manifestly they acknowledged the power of
God.</ab>
<ab n="29">For hee by
the hand of God was cast downe, and lay speechlesse without all
hope of life.</ab>
<ab n="30">But they
praised the Lord that had miraculously honoured his owne place: for
the Temple which a little afore was full of feare and trouble, when
the Almightie Lord appeared, was filled with ioy and
gladnesse.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then
straightwayes certaine of Heliodorus friends, prayed Onias that hee
would call vpon the most High to graunt him his life, who lay ready
to giue vp the ghost.</ab>
<ab n="32">So the high
Priest suspecting lest the king should misconceiue that some
treachery had beene done to Heliodorus by the Iewes, offered a
sacrifice for the health of the man.</ab>
<ab n="33">Now as the
high Priest was making an atonement, the same yong men, in the same
clothing, appeared and stood beside Heliodorus, saying, Giue Onias
the high Priest great thankes, insomuch as for his sake the Lord
hath granted thee life.</ab>
<ab n="34">And seeing
that thou hast beene scourged from heauen, declare vnto all men the
mightie power of God: and when they had spoken these wordes, they
appeared no more.</ab>
<ab n="35">So Heliodorus
after he had offered sacrifice vnto the Lord, and made great vowes
vnto him that had saued his life, and saluted Onias, returned with
his hoste to the king.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then
testified hee to all men, the workes of the great God, which he had
seene with his eyes.</ab>
<ab n="37">And when the
king asked Heliodorus, who might be a fit man to be sent yet once
againe to Ierusalem, he said,</ab>
<ab n="38">If thou hast
any enemy or traitor, send him thither, and thou shalt receiue him
well scourged, if he escape with his life: for in that place, no
doubt, there is an especiall power of God.</ab>
<ab n="39">For hee that
dwelleth in heauen hath his eye on that place, and defendeth it,
and hee beateth and destroyeth them that come to hurt it.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the
things concerning Heliodorus, and the keeping of the treasurie,
fell out on this sort.</ab>



</div>