<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Maccabees_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Maccabees-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The Kings lieutenants vexe the
Iewes. 3 They of Ioppe drowne two hundred Iewes. 6 Iudas is auenged
vpon them. 11 Hee maketh peace with the Arabians, 16 and taketh
Caspis. 22 Timotheus armies ouerthrowen.</head>

<ab n="1">When these
Couenants were made, Lysias went vnto the king, and the Iewes were
about their husbandrie.</ab>
<ab n="2">But of the
gouernours of seueral places, Timotheus, and Apollonius the sonne
of Genneus, also Hieronymus, and Demophon, and besides them Nicanor
þe gouernor of Cyprus would not suffer them to be
quiet, and liue in peace.</ab>
<ab n="3">The men of
Ioppe also did such an vngodly deed: they prayed the Iewes that
dwelt among them, to goe with their wiues, and children into the
boats which they had prepared, as though they had meant them no
hurt.</ab>
<ab n="4">Who accepted
of it according to the common decree of the citie, as being
desirous to liue in peace, and suspecting nothing: but when they
were gone forth into the deepe, they drowned no lesse then two
hundred of them.</ab>
<ab n="5">When Iudas
heard of this crueltie done vnto his countrey men, he commanded
those that were with him [to make them ready.]</ab>
<ab n="6">And calling
vpon God the righteous iudge, he came against those murtherers of
his brethren, &amp; burnt the hauen by night, and set the boats on
fire, and those that fled thither, he slew.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when the
towne was shut vp, he went backward, as if he would returne to root
out all them of the citie of Ioppe.<note> Or, with a purpose to returne.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But when he
heard that þe Iamnites were minded to doe in like
maner vnto the Iewes þe dwelt among them,</ab>
<ab n="9">He came vpon
the Iamnites also by night, and set fire on the hauen, &amp; the
nauy, so that the light of the fire was seene at Ierusalem, two
hundred and fortie furlongs off.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now when
they were gone from thence nine furlongs in their iourney toward
Timotheus, no fewer then fiue thousand men on foote, &amp; fiue
hundred horse men of the Arabians, set vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="11">Whereupon
there was a very sore battell; but Iudas side by the helpe of God
got the victory, so that the Nomades of Arabia being ouercome,
besought Iudas for peace, promising both to giue him cattell, and
to pleasure him otherwise.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then Iudas
thinking indeede that they would be profitable in many things,
granted them peace, wherupon they shooke hands, and so they
departed to their tents.<note> Or went from place to place, with their families and cattell.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Hee went
also about to make a bridge to a certaine strong citie, which was
fenced about with walles, and inhabited by people of diuers
countries, and the name of it was Caspis.</ab>
<ab n="14">But they
that were within it put such trust in the strength of the walles,
and prouision of victuals, that they behaued themselues rudely
towards them that were with Iudas, railing, and blaspheming, and
vttering such words, as were not to be spoken.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wherefore
Iudas with his company, calling vpon the great Lord of the world
(who without any rammes, or engines of warre did cast downe Iericho
in the time of Iosua) gaue a fierce assault against the
walles,</ab>
<ab n="16">And tooke
the citie by the will of God, and made vnspeakable slaughters,
insomuch that a lake two furlongs broad, neere adioining thereunto,
being filled ful, was seen running with blood.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then
departed they from thence seuen hundred and fifty furlongs, and
came to Characa vnto the Iewes that are called Tubieni.</ab>
<ab n="18">But as for
Timotheus they found him not in the places, for before hee had
dispatched any thing, he departed from thence, hauing left a very
strong garrison in a certaine hold:</ab>
<ab n="19">Howbeit,
Dositheus, and Sosipater, who were of Maccabeus captaines, went
forth, and slew those that Timotheus had left in the fortresse,
aboue tenne thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="20">And
Maccabeus ranged his armie by bands, &amp; set them ouer the bands,
and went against Timotheus, who had about him &amp; hundred and
twentie thousand men of foote, and two thousand, and fiue hundred
horsemen.<note> Dosubeus, and Sosipater.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Nowe when
Timotheus had knowledge of Iudas comming, he sent the women and
children, and the other baggage vnto a fortresse called Carnion
(for the towne was hard to besiege and vneasie to come vnto, by
reason of the straitnesse of all the places.)</ab>
<ab n="22">But when
Iudas his first band came in sight, the enemies (being smitten with
feare, and terrour through the appearing of him that seeth all
things) fled amaine, one running this way, another that way, so as
that they were often hurt of their owne men, and wounded with
þe points of their owne swords</ab>
<ab n="23">Iudas also
was very earnest in pursuing them, killing those wicked wretches,
of whom he slew about thirtie thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="24">Moreouer,
Timotheus himselfe fell into the hands of Dositheus, &amp;
Sosipater, whom he besought with much craft to let him goe with his
life, because hee had many of the Iewes parents, and the brethren
of some of them, who, if they put him to death, should not be
regarded.</ab>
<ab n="25">So when hee
had assured them with many words, that hee would restore them
without hurt according to the agreement, they let him goe for the
sauing of their brethren.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then
Maccabeus marched forth to Carnion, &amp; to the Temple of
Atargatis, and there he slew fiue and twenty thousand
persons.<note> i. Venus.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And after he
had put to flight, and destroyed them, Iudas remooued the hoste
towards Ephron, a strong citie, wherin Lysias abode, and a great
multitude of diuers nations, and the strong yong men kept the wals,
and defended them mightily: wherin also was great prouision of
engines, and darts.</ab>
<ab n="28">But when
Iudas and his company had called vpon Almighty God (who with his
power breaketh the strength of his enemies) they wanne the citie,
and slew twentie and fiue thousand of them that were
within.</ab>
<ab n="29">From thence
they departed to Scythopolis, which lieth sixe hundreth furlongs
from Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="30">But when the
Iewes that dwelt there had testified that the Scythopolitans dealt
louingly with them, and entreated them kindely in the time of their
aduersitie:</ab>
<ab n="31">They gaue
them thankes, desiring them to be friendly stil vnto them, and so
they came to Ierusalem, the feast of the weekes approching.</ab>
<ab n="32">And after
the feast called Pentecost, they went foorth against Gorgias the
gouernour of Idumea,</ab>
<ab n="33">Who came out
[wt] three thousand men of foot, &amp; foure hundred
horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="34">And it
happened that in their fighting together, a few of the Iewes were
slaine.</ab>
<ab n="35">At which
time Dositheus one of Bacenors company, who was on horsbacke, and a
strong man, was still vpon Gorgias, and taking hold of his coate,
drew him by force, and when he would haue taken that cursed man
aliue, a horseman of Thracia comming vpon him, smote off his
shoulder, so that Gorgias fled vnto Marisa.<note> Put by his armie: wounded him in the shoulder: or stroke him in the shoulder.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Now when
they that were with Gorgias had fought long &amp; were wearie,
Iudas called vpon the Lord that he would shew himselfe to be their
helper, and leader of the battell.</ab>
<ab n="37">And with
that he beganne in his owne language, &amp; sung Psalmes with a
lowd voyce, &amp; rushing vnawares vpon Gorgias men, he put them to
flight.</ab>
<ab n="38">So Iudas
gathered his host, and came into the city of Odollam. And when the
seuenth day came, they purified themselues (as the custome was) and
kept the Sabbath in the same place.</ab>
<ab n="39">And vpon the
day following as the vse had bene, Iudas and his company came to
take vp the bodies of them that were slaine, and to bury them with
their kinsmen, in their fathers graues.<note> Or, at such time, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Now vnder
the coats of euery one that was slaine, they found things
consecrated to the idoles of the Iamnites, which is forbidden the
Iewes by the Law. Then euery man saw that this was
þe cause wherefore they were slaine.<note> Deut. 26. ver. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">All men
therefore praising the Lord the righteous Iudge, who had opened the
things that were hid,</ab>
<ab n="42">Betooke
themselues vnto praier, and besought him that the sinne committed,
might wholy bee put out of remembrance. Besides, that noble Iudas
exhorted the people to keep themselues from sinne, forsomuch as
they saw before their eyes the things that came to passe, for the
sinne of those þe were slaine.</ab>
<ab n="43">And when he
had made a gathering throughout the company, to the sum of two
thousand drachmes of siluer, hee sent it to Ierusalem to offer a
sinne offering, doing therein very well, and honestly, in that he
was mindfull of the resurrection.</ab>
<ab n="44">(For if he
had not hoped that they that were slaine should haue risen againe,
it had bin superfluous and vaine, to pray for the dead.)</ab>
<ab n="45">And also in
that he perceiued that there was great fauour layed vp for those
that died godly. (It was an holy, and good thought) wherupon he
made a reconciliation for the dead, that they might be deliuered
from sinne.</ab>



</div>