<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Peter_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Peter-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Peter-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 He foretelleth them of false
teachers, shewing the impietie, and punishment both of them and
their followers: 7 from which the godly shall bee deliuered, as Lot
was out of Sodom: 10 and more fully describeth the manners of those
prophane, and blasphemous seducers, whereby they may be the better
knowen, and auoided.</head>

<ab n="1">But there were
false prophets also among the people, euen as there shall bee false
teachers among you, who priuily shall bring in damnable heresies,
euen denying the Lord that bought them, and bring vpon themselues
swift destruction.</ab>
<ab n="2">And many shall
follow their pernicious wayes, by reason of whom the way of trueth
shall be euill spoken of:<note> Or lasciuious wayes, as some copies reade.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And through
couetousnesse shall they with fained words, make marchandise of
you, whose iudgement now of a long time lingereth not, and their
damnation slumbreth not.</ab>
<ab n="4">For if God spared
not the Angels that sinned, but cast them downe to hell, and
deliuered them into chaines of darkenesse, to be reserued vnto
iudgment:</ab>
<ab n="5">And spared not the
old world, but saued Noah the eight person a preacher of
righteousnesse, bringing in the flood vpon the world of the
vngodly:</ab>
<ab n="6">And turning the
cities of Sodom and Gomorrha into ashes, condemned them with an
ouerthrowe, making them an ensample vnto those that after should
liue vngodly:</ab>

<fw>Balaams way.</fw>
<ab n="7">And deliuered iust
Lot, vexed with the filthy conuersation of the wicked:</ab>
<ab n="8">(For that
righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing &amp; hearing, vexed
his righteous soule from day to day, with their vnlawfull
deeds.)</ab>
<ab n="9">The Lord knoweth
how to deliuer the godly out of temptations, and to reserue the
vniust vnto the day of iudgement to be punished:</ab>
<ab n="10">But chiefly them
that walke after the flesh in the lust of vncleannesse, and despise
gouernment. Presumptuous are they; selfe willed: they are not
afraid to speake euill of dignities:<note> Or, dominion. , Iude 8.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Whereas Angels
which are greater in power and might, bring not railing accusation
against them before the Lord.<note> Some read against themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But these, as
natural bruit beasts made to bee taken and destroyed speake euill
of the things that they vnderstand not, and shall vtterly perish in
their owne corruption,</ab>
<ab n="13">And shall receiue
the reward of vnrighteousnesse, as they that count it pleasure to
riot in the day time: Spots they are and blemishes, sporting
themselues with their owne deceiuings, while they feast with
you:</ab>
<ab n="14">Hauing eyes ful
of adulterie and that cannot cease from sinne, beguiling vnstable
soules: an heart they haue exercised with couetous practises:
cursed children:<note> Gr. an adulteresse.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Which haue
forsaken the right way, and are gone astray, following the way of
Balaam the sonne of Bosor, who loued the wages of
vnrighteousnesse,</ab>
<ab n="16">But was rebuked
for his iniquity: the dumbe asse speaking with mais voice, forbade
the madnesse of the Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="17">These are welles
without water, cloudes that are caried with a tempest, to whom the
mist of darkenesse is reserued for euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">For when they
speake great svelling words of vanitie, they alure through the
lusts of the flesh, through much wantonnesse, those that were
cleane escaped from them who liue in errour.<note> Or, for a litle, or a while as some read.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">While they
promise them libertie, they themselues are the seruants of
corruption: for of whom a man is ouercome, of the same is he
brought in bondage.</ab>

<fw>Reuolters. The day of the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="20">For if after they
haue escaped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of
the Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ, they are againe intangled
therein, and ouercome, the latter end is worse with them then the
beginning.</ab>
<ab n="21">For it had bin
better for them not to haue knowen the way of righteousnesse, then
after they haue knowen it, to turne from the holy commandement
deliuered vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="22">But it is
happened vnto them according to the true prouerbe: The dog is
turned to his own vomit againe, and the sowe that was washed, to
her wallowing in the mire.</ab>



</div>