<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Peter_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Peter-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>Hee assureth them of the certaintie
of Christes comming to Iudgement, against those scorners who
dispute against it: 8 warning the godly for the long patience of
God, to hasten their repentance. 10 He describeth also the manner
how the world shall bee destroyed: 11 exhorting them from the
expectation thereof, to all holinesse of life: 15 And againe, to
thinke the patience of God to tend to their saluation, as Paul
wrote to them in his Epistles.</head>

<ab n="1">This second
Epistle (beloued) I now write vnto you, in both which I stir vp
your pure mindes by way of remembrance:</ab>
<ab n="2">That yee may be
mindfull of the wordes which were spoken before by the holy
Prophets, and of the Commandement of vs the Apostles of the Lord
and Sauiour:</ab>
<ab n="3">Knowing this
first, that there shall come in the last dayes scoffers, walking
after their owne lusts,</ab>
<ab n="4">And saying, Where
is the promise of his comming? For since the fathers fell asleepe,
all things continue as they were frō the beginning of the
creation.</ab>
<ab n="5">For this they
willingly are ignorant of, that by the word of God the heauens were
of olde, and the earth standing out of the water, and in the
water,<note> Gr. consisting.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Whereby the world
that then was, being ouerflowed with water, perished.</ab>

<fw>The day of the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="7">But the heauens
and the earth which are now, by the same word are kept in store,
reserued vnto fire against the day of Iudgement, and perdition of
vngodly men.</ab>
<ab n="8">But (beloued) bee
not ignorant of this one thing, that one day is with the Lord as a
thousand yeeres, and a thousand yeeres as one day.</ab>
<ab n="9">The Lord is not
slacke cōcerning his promise (as some men count slacknesse)
but is long-suffring to vs-ward, not willing that any should
perish, but that all should come to repentance.</ab>
<ab n="10">But the day of
the Lord wil come as a thiefe in the night, in the which the
heauens shall passe away with a great noise, and the Elements shall
melt with feruent heate, the earth also and the works that are
therin shalbe burnt vp.</ab>
<ab n="11">Seeing then that
all these things shall be dissolued, What maner of persons ought ye
to be in all holy conuersation, and godlinesse,</ab>
<ab n="12">Looking for and
hasting vnto the comming of the day of God, wherein the heauens
being on fire shalbe dissolued, and the Elements shall melt with
feruent heat.<note> Or, hasting the comming.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Neuerthelesse
wee, according to his promise, looke for new heauens, and a new
earth, wherein dwelleth righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="14">Wherefore
(beloued) seeing that ye looke for such things, be diligent that ye
may be found of him in peace, without spot, and blamelesse.</ab>
<ab n="15">And account that
the long suffering of the Lord is saluation, euen as our beloued
brother Paul also, according to the wisedome giuen vnto him, hath
written vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="16">As also in all
his Epistles, speaking in them of these things, in which are some
things hard to be vnderstood, which they that are vnlearned and
vnstable wrest, as they doe also the other Scriptures, vnto their
owne destruction.</ab>
<ab n="17">Ye therefore,
beloued, seeing yee know these things before, beware lest yee also
being led away with the errour of the wicked, fall from your owne
stedfastnesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">But growe in
grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ:
to him be glory both now and for euer. Amen.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>