<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Peter_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Peter-Chapter-5-5-2-Peter.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Peter-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Confirming them in hope of the
increase of Gods graces, 5 he exhorteth them by faith, and good
workes, to make their calling sure: 12 Whereof hee is carefull to
remember them, knowing that his death is at hand: 16 And warneth
them to be constant in the faith of Christ, who is the true Sonne
of God, by the eye witnesse of the Apostles beholding his Maiestie,
and by the testimonie of the Father, and the Prophets.</head>

<ab n="1">Simon Peter, a
seruant &amp; an Apostle of Iesus Christ, to them that haue
obtained like precious Faith with vs, through the righteousnes of
God, and our Sauiour Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="2">Grace and peace be
multiplied vnto you through the knowledge of God, and of Iesus our
Lord,</ab>
<ab n="3">According as his
diuine power hath giuen vnto vs all things that pertain vnto life
and godlines, through the knowledge of him that hath called vs to
glory and vertue.<note> Or, by.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Whereby are giuen
vnto vs exceeding great and precious promises, that by these you
might bee partakers of the diuine nature, hauing escaped the
corruption that is in the world through lust.</ab>
<ab n="5">And besides this,
giuing all diligence, adde to your faith, vertue; and to vertue
knowledge;</ab>
<ab n="6">And to knowledge,
temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to patience,
godlinesse;</ab>

<fw>Who are blinde.</fw>
<ab n="7">And to godlinesse,
brotherly kindnesse; and to brotherly kindnesse, charitie.</ab>
<ab n="8">For if these
things be in you, and abound, they make you that yee shall neither
be barren, nor vnfruitfull in the knowledge of our Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="9">But hee that
lacketh these things, is blind, and cannot see farre off, and hath
forgotten that hee was purged from his old sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wherefore, the
rather, brethren, giue diligence to make your calling and election
sure: for if ye doe these things, ye shall neuer fall.</ab>
<ab n="11">For so an
entrance shall be ministred vnto you abundantly, into the
euerlasting kingdome of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore I wil
not be negligent to put you alwayes in remembrance of these things,
though yee know them, and be stablished in the present
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yea, I thinke it
meete, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stirre you vp, by
putting you in remembrance:</ab>
<ab n="14">Knowing that
shortly I must put off this my Tabernacle, euen as our Lord Iesus
Christ hath shewed mee.<note> Ioh.21.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Moreouer, I will
endeuour, that you may bee able after my decease, to haue these
things alwayes in remembrance.</ab>
<ab n="16">For wee haue not
followed cunningly deuised fables, when wee made knowen vnto you
the power and comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, but were eye
witnesses of his Maiestie.</ab>

<fw>False teachers.</fw>
<ab n="17">For hee receiued
from God the Father, honour and glory, when there came such a voice
to him from the excellent glory, This is my beloued Sonne in whom I
am well pleased.</ab>
<ab n="18">And this voice
which came from heauen wee heard, when we were with him in the holy
mount.</ab>
<ab n="19">We haue also a
more sure word of prophecie, whereunto yee doe well that ye take
heede, as vnto a light that shineth in a darke place, vntill the
day dawne, and the day starre arise in your hearts:</ab>
<ab n="20">Knowing this
first, that no prophecy of the Scripture is of any priuate
Interpretation:</ab>
<ab n="21">For the prophecie
came not in olde time by the will of man: but holy men of God spake
as they were moued by the holy Ghost.<note> Or, at any time.</note></ab>



</div>