<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Ahithophels counsell is
ouerthrowen by Hushais, according to Gods appointment. 15 Secret
intelligence is sent vnto Dauid. 23 Ahithophel hangeth himselfe. 25
Amasa is made captaine. 27 Dauid at Mahanaim is furnished with
prouision.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer
Ahithophel said vnto Absalom, Let mee nowe chuse out twelue
thousand men, and I will arise and pursue after Dauid this
night.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I wil come
vpon him while hee is wearie and weake handed, and wil make him
afraid: and all the people that are with him shall flee, and I will
smite the king onely.</ab>

<fw>Ahithophels and Hushais
counsel.</fw>
<ab n="3">And I wil bring
backe all the people vnto thee: the man whom thou seekest is as if
all returned: so all the people shall be in peace.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the saying
pleased Absalom well, and all the Elders of Israel.<note> Hebr. was right in the eyes of &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then said
Absalom, Call now Hushai the Archite also, and let vs heare
likewise what he saith.<note> Hebr. what is in his mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And when Hushai
was come to Absalom, Absalom spake vnto him, saying, Ahithophel
hath spoken after this maner: shall we doe after his saying? if
not, speake thou.<note> Heb. word.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Hushai said
vnto Absalom, The counsell that Ahithophel hath giuen, is not good
at this time.<note> Heb. counselled.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For, (said
Hushai,) thou knowest thy father and his men, that they bee mightie
men, and they be chafed in their minds, as a beare robbed of her
whelps in the field: and thy father is a man of warre, and will not
lodge with the people.<note> Heb. bitter of soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Behold, he is
hid now in some pit, or in some other place: and it wil come to
passe when some of them bee ouerthrowen at the first, that
whosoeuer heareth it, wil say, There is a slaughter among the
people that followe Absalom.<note> Heb. fallen.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And he also
that is valiant, whose heart is as the heart of a Lyon, shall
vtterly melt: for all Israel knoweth that thy father is a mightie
man, and they which be with him are valiant men.</ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore I
counsell, that all Israel be generally gathered vnto thee, from Dan
euen to Beer-sheba, as the sand that is by the sea for multitude,
and that thou goe to battell in thine owne person.<note> Heb. that thy face or presence goe, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So shall wee
come vpon him in some place where he shall be found, and we will
light vpon him as the dew falleth on the ground: and of him and of
all the men that are with him, there shall not be left so much as
one.</ab>
<ab n="13">Moreouer, if
hee be gotten into a citie, then shall all Israel bring ropes to
that city, and we will draw it into the riuer, vntill there be not
one small stone found there.</ab>

<fw>Ahithophels death.</fw>
<ab n="14">And Absalom and
all the men of Israel said, The counsell of Hushai the Archite, is
better then the counsell of Ahithophel: For the Lord had appointed
to defeate the good counsell of Ahithophel, to the intent that the
Lord might bring euill vpon Absalom.<note> Heb. commanded.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then
said Hushai vnto Zadok and to Abiathar the Priestes, Thus and thus
did Ahithophel counsell Absalom and the Elders of Israel, and thus
and thus haue I counselled.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now therefore
send quickly, and tell Dauid, saying, Lodge not this night in the
plaines of the wildernes, but speedily passe ouer, lest the King be
swallowed vp, and all the people that are with him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now Ionathan
and Ahimaaz stayed by En-rogel: (for they might not be seene to
come into the citie) and a wench went and tolde them: and they
went, and tolde king Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="18">Neuerthelesse,
a ladde saw them, and tolde Absalom: but they went both of them
away quickely, and came to a mans house in Bahurim, which had a
Well in his court, whither they went downe.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the woman
tooke and spread a couering ouer the welles mouth, and spread
ground corne thereon; and the thing was not knowen.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when
Absaloms seruants came to the woman to the house, they said, Where
is Ahimaaz and Ionathan? And the woman said vnto them, They be gone
ouer the brooke of water. And when they had sought, and could not
finde them, they returned to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it came to
passe after they were departed, that they came vp out of the Well,
and went and tolde king Dauid, and said vnto Dauid, Arise, and
passe quickely ouer the water: for thus hath Ahithophel counselled
against you.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then Dauid
arose, and all the people that were with him, and they passed ouer
Iordane: by the morning light there lacked not one of them that was
not gone ouer Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And when
Ahithophel sawe that his counsell was not followed, he sadled his
asse, and arose, and gate him home to his house, to his citie, and
put his houshold in order, and hanged himselfe, and died, and was
buried in the sepulchre of his father.<note> Heb. done. , Heb. gaue charge concerning his house.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Then Dauid came
to Mahanaim: and Absalom passed ouer Iordane, he and all the men of
Israel with him.</ab>

<fw>Dauid relieued.</fw>
<ab n="25">¶ And
Absalom made Amasa captaine of the hoste in stead of Ioab: which
Amasa was a mans sonne whose name was Ithra an Israelite, that went
in to Abigal the daughter of Nahash, sister to Zeruiah Ioabs
mother.</ab>
<ab n="26">So Israel and
Absalom pitched in the land of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And it
came to passe when Dauid was come to Mahanaim, that Shobi the sonne
of Nahash of Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and Machir the sonne
of Ammiel of Lodebar, and Barzillai the Gileadite, of
Rogelim,</ab>
<ab n="28">Brought beds,
and basins, and earthen vessels, and wheat, and barley, and floure,
and parched corne, &amp; beanes, and lentiles, and parched
pulse,<note> Or, cups.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And honie, and
butter, and sheepe, and cheese of kine for Dauid, and for the
people that were with him, to eate: for they said, The people is
hungrie, and wearie, and thirstie in the wildernesse.</ab>



</div>