<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Ziba by presents and false
suggestions, obtaineth his masters inheritance. 5 At Bahurim Shimei
curseth Dauid. 9 Dauid with patience abstaineth, and restraineth
others from reuenge. 15 Hushai insinuateth himselfe into Absaloms
counsaile. 20 Ahithophels counsaile.</head>

<ab n="1">And when Dauid
was a little past the top of the hill, Beholde, Ziba the seruant of
Mephibosheth met him with a couple of asses sadled, and vpon them
two hundred loaues of bread, and an hundred bunches of raisins, and
an hundred of summer fruits, and a bottell of wine.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the King
saide vnto Ziba, What meanest thou by these? And Ziba saide, The
asses bee for the kings houshold to ride on, and the bread and
summer fruit for the yong men to eate, and the wine, that such as
be faint in the wildernesse, may drinke.</ab>

<fw>Shimei curseth.</fw>
<ab n="3">And the king
said, And where is thy masters sonne? and Ziba said vnto the king,
Behold, he abideth at Ierusalem: for hee said, To day shall the
house of Israel restore mee the kingdome of my father.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then said the
king to Ziba, Behold, thine are all that pertained vnto
Mephibosheth. And Ziba saide, I humbly beseech thee that I may
finde grace in thy sight, my lord, O king.<note> Hebr. I doe obeysance.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And when
king Dauid came to Bahurim, behold, thence came out a man of the
family of the house of Saul, whose name was Shimei the sonne of
Gera: hee came foorth, and cursed still as he came.<note> Or, he still came foorth and cursed.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he cast
stones at Dauid, and at all the seruants of king Dauid: and all the
people, and all the mighty men were on his right hand, and on his
left.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thus said
Shimei when hee cursed, Come out, come out thou bloody man, and
thou man of Belial:<note> Hebr. man of blood.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord hath
returned vpon thee all the blood of the house of Saul, in whose
stead thou hast raigned, and the Lord hath deliuered the kingdome
into the hand of Absalom thy sonne: and behold, thou art taken to
thy mischiefe, because thou art a bloody man.<note> Hebr. behold thee in thy euill.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then said
Abishai the sonne of Zeruiah vnto the king, Why should this dead
dogge curse my lord the king? let mee goe ouer, I pray thee, and
take off his head.<note> 1.Sam.24. 15. chap.3. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the king
said, What haue I to doe with you, ye sonnes of Zeruiah? So let him
curse, because the Lord hath said vnto him, Curse Dauid. Who shall
then say, Wherefore hast thou done so?</ab>
<ab n="11">And Dauid said
to Abishai, and to all his seruants, Beholde, my sonne which came
foorth of my bowels, seeketh my life: how much more now may this
Beniamite doe it? let him alone, and let him curse: for the Lord
hath bidden him.</ab>
<ab n="12">It may bee that
the Lord will looke on mine affliction, and that the Lord will
requite good for his cursing this day.<note> Or, teares, Hebr. eye.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And as Dauid
and his men went by the way, Shimei went along on the hilles side
ouer against him, and cursed as hee went, and threw stones at him,
and cast dust.<note> Hebr. dusted him with dust.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the king,
and all the people that were with him, came weary, and refreshed
themselues there.</ab>

<fw>Ahithophels and Hushais
counsel.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ And
Absalom and al the people the men of Israel, came to Ierusalem, and
Ahithophel with him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it came to
passe when Hushai the Archite, Dauids friend, was come vnto
Absalom, that Hushai said vnto Absalom, God saue the king, God saue
the king.<note> Heb. let the king liue.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Absalom
said to Hushai, Is this thy kindnesse to thy friend? Why wentest
thou not with thy friend?</ab>
<ab n="18">And Hushai said
vnto Absalom, Nay, but whom the Lord and this people, and all the
men of Israel chuse, his will I bee, and with him will I
abide.</ab>
<ab n="19">And againe,
whom should I serue? should I not serue in the presence of his
sonne? as I haue serued in thy fathers presence, so will I be in
thy presence.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Then
said Absalom to Ahithophel, Giue counsell among you what we shall
doe.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Ahithophel
said vnto Absalom, Goe in vnto thy fathers concubines, which he
hath left to keepe the house, and all Israel shall heare that thou
art abhorred of thy father, then shall the hands of all that are
with thee be strong.</ab>
<ab n="22">So they spread
Absalom a tent vpon the top of the house, and Absalom went in vnto
his fathers concubines, in the sight of all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
counsell of Ahithophel which he counselled in those dayes, was as
if a man had enquired at the Oracle of God: so was all the counsell
of Ahithophel, both with Dauid and with Absalom.<note> Heb. word.</note></ab>



</div>