<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The tribes come to Hebron to
annoint Dauid ouer Israel. 4 Dauids age. 6 Hee taking Zion from the
Iebusites dwelleth in it. 11 Hiram sendeth to Dauid. 13 Eleuen
sonnes are borne to him in Ierusalem. 17 Dauid directed by God
smiteth the Philistines at Baal Perazim, 22 and againe at the
Mulberie trees.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came all the
tribes of Israel to Dauid vnto Hebron, and spake, saying, Behold,
we are thy bone, and thy flesh.<note> 1. Chron. 11.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Also in time past
when Saul was king ouer vs, thou wast hee that leddest out and
broughtest in Israel: and the Lord said to thee, Thou shalt feed my
people Israel, and thou shalt bee a captaine ouer
Israel.<note> Psal. 78. 71.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">So all the Elders
of Israel came to the King to Hebron, and King Dauid made a league
with them in Hebron before the Lord: and they anointed Dauid King
ouer Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Dauid was
thirtie yeeres old when he began to reigne, and he reigned fourtie
yeeres.</ab>

<fw>Dauids children.</fw>
<ab n="5">In Hebron he
reigned ouer Iudah seuen yeeres, and sixe moneths: and in Ierusalem
he reigned thirty and three yeres ouer all Israel and
Iudah.<note> Chap.2.11</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
king and his men went to Ierusalem, vnto the Iebusites, the
inhabitants of the land: which spake vnto Dauid, saying, Except
thou take away the blind and the lame, thou shalt not come in
hither: Thinking, Dauid cannot come in hither.<note> Or, saying, Dauid shall not &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Neuerthelesse,
Dauid tooke the strong hold of Zion: the same is the citie of
Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Dauid said on
that day, Whosoeuer getteth vp to the gutter, and smiteth the
Iebusites, and the lame, and the blind, that are hated of Dauids
soule, he shall be chiefe and captaine: Wherefore they said, The
blind and the lame shall not come into the house.<note> 1. Chron. 11.6. , Or, because they had said euen the blind &amp; the lame, He shal not come into the house.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So Dauid dwelt in
the fort, and called it the citie of Dauid, and Dauid built round
about, from Millo and inward.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Dauid went
on, and grew great, and the Lord God of hosts was with
him.<note> Heb. went, going and growing.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And Hiram
king of Tyre sent messengers to Dauid, and Cedar trees, and
carpenters, and Masons: and they built Dauid an house.<note> 1. Chron. 14.1. , Hebr. hewers of the stone of the wall.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And Dauid
perceiued that the Lord had established him King ouer Israel, and
that he had exalted his kingdome for his people Israels
sake.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And Dauid
tooke him mo concubines and wiues out of Ierusalem, after he was
come from Hebron, and there were yet sonnes and daughters borne to
Dauid.<note> 1. Chron. 3.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And these be the
names of those that were borne vnto him in Ierusalem, Shammua,
&amp; Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon:<note> 1.Chron. 3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Ibhar also, and
Elishua, and Nepheg, and Iaphia,</ab>
<ab n="16">And Elishama,
and Eliada, and Eliphalet.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ But when
the Philistines heard that they had anointed Dauid King ouer
Israel, all the Philistines came vp to seeke Dauid, and Dauid heard
of it, and went downe to the hold.<note> 1.Chron. 11.16. and 14.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The Philistines
also came, and spred themselues in the valley of Rephaim.</ab>

<fw>The Arke remoued.</fw>
<ab n="19">And Dauid
enquired of the Lord, saying, Shall I goe vp to the Philistines?
wilt thou deliuer them into mine hand? And the Lord said vnto
Dauid, Goe vp: for I will doubtlesse deliuer the Philistines into
thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Dauid came
to Baal-Perazim, and Dauid smote them there, and said, The Lord
hath broken foorth vpon mine enemies before me, as the breach of
waters. Therefore he called the name of that place,
Baal-Perazim.<note> Esa. 28. 21. , That is, the plaine of breaches.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And there they
left their images, and Dauid and his men burnt them.<note> 1. Chron. 14.12. , Or, tooke them away.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
Philistines came vp yet againe, and spread themselues in the valley
of Rephaim.</ab>
<ab n="23">And when Dauid
enquired of the Lord, he said, Thou shalt not goe vp: but fetch a
compasse behinde them, and come vpon them ouer against the Mulbery
trees.</ab>
<ab n="24">And let it be
when thou hearest the sound of a going in the tops of the mulbery
trees, that then thou shalt bestirre thy selfe: for then shal the
Lord goe out before thee, to smite the host of the
Philistines.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Dauid did
so, as the Lord had commaunded him; and smote the Philistines from
Geba, vntil thou come to Gazer.</ab>



</div>