<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Amnon louing Tamar, by Ionadabs
counsell faining himselfe sicke, rauisheth her. 15 Hee hateth her,
and shamefully turneth her away. 19 Absalom entertaineth her, and
concealeth his purpose. 23 At a sheepeshearing, among all the Kings
sonnes, hee killeth Amnon. 30 Dauid grieuing at the newes is
comforted by Ionadab. 37 Absalom flieth to Talmai at
Geshur.</head>


<fw>Amnons lust.</fw>
<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after this, that Absalom the sonne of Dauid had a faire
sister, whose name was Tamar: and Amnon the sonne of Dauid loued
her.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Amnon was so
vexed, that he fell sicke for his sister Tamar: for she was a
virgine, and Amnon thought it hard for him to doe any thing to
her.<note> Heb. it was maruelous or hidden in the eyes of Amnon.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But Amnon had a
friend, whose name was Ionadab, the sonne of Shimeah, Dauids
brother: and Ionadab was a very subtill man.</ab>
<ab n="4">And he saide
vnto him, Why art thou, being the Kings sonne, leane from day to
day? Wilt thou not tel me? and Amnon said vnto him, I loue Tamar my
brother Absaloms sister.<note> Heb. thin. , Heb. morning by morning.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Ionadab said
vnto him, Lay thee downe on thy bed, and make thy selfe sicke: and
when thy father commeth to see thee, say vnto him, I pray thee, let
my sister Tamar come, and giue me meat, and dresse the meat in my
sight, that I may see it, and eate it at her hand.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ So Amnon
lay downe, and made himselfe sicke: and when the king was come to
see him, Amnon said vnto the king, I pray thee, let Tamar my sister
come, &amp; make me a couple of cakes in my sight, that I may eat
at her hand.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then Dauid sent
home to Tamar, saying, Goe now to thy brother Amnons house, and
dresse him meat.</ab>
<ab n="8">So Tamar went to
her brother Amnons house (and hee was laide downe) and she tooke
flowre, and kneaded it, and made cakes in his sight, and did bake
the cakes.<note> Or, paste.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And she tooke a
pan, and powred them out before him, but hee refused to eate: and
Amnon said, Haue out all men from mee: And they went out euery man
from him.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Amnon saide
vnto Tamar, Bring the meate into the chamber, that I may eate of
thine hand. And Tamar tooke the cakes which shee had made, and
brought them into the chamber to Amnon her brother.</ab>

<fw>Tamar rauished.</fw>
<ab n="11">And when shee
had brought them vnto him to eate, hee tooke hold of her, and said
vnto her, Come lye with mee, my sister.</ab>
<ab n="12">And she
answered him, Nay, my brother, doe not force me: for no such thing
ought to bee done in Israel; doe not thou this folly.<note> Heb. humble me. , Leuit. 18.9. , Heb. It ought not so to be done.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I, whither
shall I cause my shame to goe? and as for thee, thou shalt be as
one of the fooles in Israel: now therefore, I pray thee, speake
vnto the king, for he will not withhold me from thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Howbeit hee
would not hearken vnto her voice, but being stronger then shee,
forced her, and lay with her.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then
Amnon hated her exceedingly, so that the hatred wherwith he hated
her, was greater then the loue wherewith hee had loued her: And
Amnon said vnto her, Arise, be gone.<note> Heb. with great hatred greatly.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And she said
vnto him, There is no cause: this euill in sending me away, is
greater then the other that thou diddest vnto me: But he would not
hearken vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then hee called
his seruant that ministred vnto him, and said, Put now this woman
out from mee, and bolt the doore after her.</ab>
<ab n="18">And shee had a
garment of diuers colours vpon her: for with such robes were the
Kings daughters, that were virgins, apparelled. Then his seruant
brought her out, and bolted the doore after her.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And
Tamar put ashes on her head, and rent her garment of diuers colours
that was on her, and layde her hand on her head, and went on,
crying.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Absalom her
brother sayde vnto her, Hath Amnon thy brother beene with thee? But
holde nowe thy peace, my sister: he is thy brother, regard not this
thing. So Tamar remained desolate in her brother Absaloms
house.<note> Heb. set not thine heart. , Heb. and desolate.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ But when
King Dauid heard of all these things, he was very wroth.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Absalom
spake vnto his brother Amnon neither good nor bad: for Absalom
hated Amnon, because he had forced his sister Tamar.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And it
came to passe after two full yeeres, that Absalom had
sheepeshearers in Baal-Hazor, which is beside Ephraim: and Absalom
inuited all the kings sonnes.</ab>

<fw>Amnon murdered.</fw>
<ab n="24">And Absalom
came to the King, and said, Behold now, thy seruant hath
sheepe-shearers, Let the King, I beseech thee, and his seruants,
goe with thy seruant.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the King
sayde to Absalom, Nay, my sonne, let vs not all now goe, lest we be
chargeable vnto thee. And he pressed him: howbeit he would not goe,
but blessed him.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then said
Absalom, If not, I pray thee, let my brother Amnon goe with vs. And
the King said vnto him, Why should he goe with thee?</ab>
<ab n="27">But Absalom
pressed him, that he let Amnon and all the kings sonnes goe with
him.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Now
Absalom had commanded his seruants, saying, Marke yee now when
Amnons heart is merrie with wine, and when I say vnto you, Smite
Amnon, then kill him, feare not: haue not I commanded you? be
couragious, and be valiant.<note> Or, will you not, since I haue commanded you? , Heb. sonnes of valour.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And the
seruants of Absalom did vnto Amnon as Absalom had commanded: then
all the Kings sonnes arose, and euery man gate him vp vpon his
mule, and fled.<note> Heb. rode.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And it
came to passe while they were in the way, that tidings came to
Dauid, saying, Absalom hath slaine all the Kings sonnes, and there
is not one of them left.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then the king
arose, and tare his garments, and lay on the earth: and all his
seruants stoode by with their clothes rent.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Ionadab the
sonne of Shimeah Dauids brother, answered and said, Let not my lord
suppose that they haue slaine all the yong men the Kings sonnes;
for Amnon onely is dead: for by the appointment of Absalom this
hath beene determined, from the day that he forced his sister
Tamar.<note> Heb. mouth , Or, setled.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Now therefore
let not my lord the King take the thing to his heart, to thinke
that all the Kings sonnes are dead: for Amnon onely is
dead.</ab>
<ab n="34">But Absalom
fled: and the yong man that kept the watch, lift vp his eyes, and
looked, and behold, there came much people by the way of the hill
side behind him.</ab>
<ab n="35">And Ionadab
said vnto the king, Behold, the kings sonnes come: as thy seruant
said, so it is.<note> Heb. according to the word of thy seruant.</note></ab>

<fw>The widow of Tekoahs parable.</fw>
<ab n="36">And it came to
passe assoone as hee had made an ende of speaking, that behold, the
kings sonnes came, and lift vp their voice, and wept; and the King
also and all his seruants wept very sore.<note> Hebr. with a great weeping greatly.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">¶ But
Absalom fled, and went to Talmai the sonne of Ammihud king of
Geshur: and Dauid mourned for his sonne euery day.<note> Or, Ammihur.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">So Absalom
fled, and went to Geshur, and was there three yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the soule
of king Dauid longed to goe foorth vnto Absalom: for he was
comforted concerning Amnon, seeing he was dead.<note> Or, was consumed.</note></ab>



</div>