<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-22-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>A Psalme of thankesgiuing for Gods
powerfull deliuerance, and manifold blessings.</head>

<ab n="1">And Dauid spake
vnto the Lord the wordes of this song, in the day that the Lord had
deliuered him out of the hand of all his enemies, and out of the
hand of Saul.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said, The
Lord is my rocke and my fortresse, and my deliuerer:<note> Psal. 18.2. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The God of my
rocke, in him will I trust: hee is my shield, and the horne of my
saluation, my high tower, and my refuge, my Sauiour; thou sauest me
from violence.</ab>
<ab n="4">I will call on
the Lord, who is worthy to be praised: so shall I be saued from
mine enemies.</ab>
<ab n="5">When the waues
of death compassed me: the floods of vngodly men made me
afraid.<note> Or, pangs. , Heb. Belial.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The sorowes of
Hell compassed me about: the snares of death preuented
me.<note> Or, coards.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">In my distresse
I called vpon the Lord, and cryed to my God, and hee did heare my
voice out of his Temple, and my crie did enter into his
eares.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then the earth
shooke and trembled: the foundations of heauen mooued and shooke,
because hee was wroth.</ab>
<ab n="9">There went vp a
smoake out of his nostrils, and fire out of his mouth deuoured:
coales were kindled by it.<note> Heb. by.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee bowed the
heauens also and came downe: and darkenesse was vnder his
feete.</ab>

<fw>The song of Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="11">And he rode
vpon a Cherub, and did flie: and hee was seene vpon the wings of
the winde.</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee made
darkenesse pauilions round about him, darke waters, and thicke
clouds of the skies.<note> Hebr. binding of waters.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Through the
brightnesse before him, were coales of fire kindled.</ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord
thundred from heauen: and the most high vttered his voice.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he sent out
arrowes, and scattered them; lightning, and discomfited
them.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the
channels of the Sea appeared, the foundations of the world were
discouered, at the rebuking of the Lord, at the blast of the breath
of his nostrils.</ab>
<ab n="17">He sent from
aboue, he tooke me: he drew me out of many waters.<note> Or, great.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">He deliuered me
from my strong enemy, and from them that hated mee: for they were
too strong for me.</ab>
<ab n="19">They preuented
me in the day of my calamitie: but the Lord was my stay.</ab>
<ab n="20">Hee brought me
forth also into a large place: he deliuered me, because hee
delighted in me.</ab>
<ab n="21">The Lord
rewarded mee according to my righteousnesse: according to the
cleannesse of my hands, hath hee recompensed me.</ab>
<ab n="22">For I haue kept
the wayes of the Lord, and haue not wickedly departed from my
God.</ab>
<ab n="23">For all his
iudgements were before me: and as for his Statutes, I did not
depart from them.</ab>
<ab n="24">I was also
vpright before him: and haue kept my selfe from mine
iniquitie.<note> Hebr. to him.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore the
Lord hath recompensed me, according to my righteousnesse: according
to my cleannesse in his eye sight.<note> Hebr. before his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">With the
merciful thou wilt shew thy selfe mercifull, and with the vpright
man thou wilt shew thy selfe vpright.</ab>
<ab n="27">With the pure
thou wilt shew thy selfe pure: and with the froward, thou wilt shew
thy selfe vnsauoury.<note> Or, wrestle. ps. 18.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And the
afflicted people thou wilt saue: but thine eyes are vpon the
hautie, that thou mayest bring them downe.</ab>
<ab n="29">For thou art my
lampe, O Lord: and the Lord wil lighten my darkenesse.<note> Or, candle.</note></ab>

<fw>The song of Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="30">For by thee I
haue run through a troupe: by my God haue I leaped ouer a
wall.<note> Or, broken a troupe.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">As for God, his
way is perfect, the word of the Lord is tried: he is a buckler to
all them that trust in him.<note> Or, refined.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For who is God,
saue the Lord ? and who is a rocke, saue our God?</ab>
<ab n="33">God is my
strength and power: and he maketh my way perfect.<note> Hebr. riddeth, or, looseth.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Hee maketh my
feet like hindes feet: and setteth mee vpon my high
places.<note> Heb. equalleth.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">He teacheth my
hands to warre: so that a bow of steele is broken by mine
armes.<note> Hebr. for the warre.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Thou hast also
giuen mee the shield of thy saluation: and thy gentlenesse hath
made me great.<note> Hebr. multiplied me.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Thou hast
enlarged my steps vnder me: so that my feet did not
slip.<note> Hebr. ancles.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">I haue pursued
mine enemies, and destroyed them: and turned not againe vntill I
had consumed them.</ab>
<ab n="39">And I haue
consumed them and wounded them, that they could not arise: yea,
they are fallen vnder my feet.</ab>
<ab n="40">For thou hast
girded mee with strength to battel: them that rose vp against me,
hast thou subdued vnder me.<note> Hebr. caused to bow.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">Thou hast also
giuen mee the necks of mine enemies, that I might destroy them that
hate me.</ab>
<ab n="42">They looked,
but there was none to saue: euen vnto the Lord, but he answered
them not.</ab>
<ab n="43">Then did I beat
them as small as the dust of the earth: I did stampe them as the
myre of the street, and did spread them abroad.</ab>
<ab n="44">Thou also hast
deliuered mee from the striuings of my people, thou hast kept mee
to be head of the heathen: a people which I knew not, shall serue
me.</ab>
<ab n="45">Strangers shall
submit themselues vnto me: as soone as they heare, they shall be
obedient vnto me.<note> Heb. sonnes of the stranger. , Or, yeeld fained obedience. Heb. lye.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">Strangers shall
fade away: and they shall bee afraid out of their close
places.</ab>
<ab n="47">The Lord
liueth, and blessed be my rocke: and exalted be the God of the
rocke of my saluation.</ab>
<ab n="48">It is God that
auengeth mee, and that bringeth downe the people vnder
me:<note> Hebr. giueth auengement for me.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids worthies, and valiant
men.</fw>
<ab n="49">And that
bringeth me forth from mine enemies: thou also hast lifted mee vp
on high aboue them that rose vp against me: thou hast deliuered me
from the violent man.</ab>
<ab n="50">Therefore I
will giue thankes vnto thee, O Lord, among the heathen: and I will
sing praises vnto thy Name.<note> Rom. 15.9</note></ab>
<ab n="51">He is the towre
of saluation for his king: and sheweth mercy to his Anointed, vnto
Dauid, and to his seede for euermore.<note> Cha. 7.13</note></ab>



</div>