<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid fetcheth the Arke from
Kiriath-iearim on a new cart. 6 Vzzah is smitten at Perez-Vzzah. 9
God blesseth Obed-Edom for the Arke. 12 Dauid bringing the Arke
into Zion with sacrifices, daunceth before it, for which Michol
despiseth him. 17 Hee placeth it in a tabernacle with great ioy and
feasting. 20 Michal reproouing Dauid for his religious ioy, is
childlesse to her death.</head>

<ab n="1">Againe, Dauid
gathered together all the chosen men of Israel, thirtie
thousand:</ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid arose
and went with all the people that were with him, from Baale of
Iudah, to bring vp from thence the Arke of God, whose Name is
called by the Name of the Lord of hostes, that dwelleth betweene
the Cherubims.<note> 1. Chro. 13,5,6. , Or, at which the Name, euen the Name of the Lord of hosts was called vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And they set the
Arke of God vpon a new cart, and brought it out of the house of
Abinadab that was in Gibeah: and Uzzah and Ahio the sonnes of
Abinadab, draue the new cart.<note> Heb. made to ride. , Or, the hill.</note></ab>

<fw>Vzzah slaine.</fw>
<ab n="4">And they brought
it out of the house of Abinadab which was at Gibeah, accompanying
the Arke of God; and Ahio went before the Arke.<note> 1. Sam. 7. 2. , Hebr. with.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Dauid and all
the house of Israel played before the Lord on all manner of
instruments made of Firrewood, euen on harpes, and on Psalteries,
and on timbrels, and on cornets, and on cimbals.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And when
they came to Nachons threshing floore, Uzzah put forth his hand to
the Arke of God, and tooke hold of it, for the oxen shooke
it.<note> 1. Chron. 13.9. , Or, stumbled.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the anger of
the Lord was kindled against Uzzah, and God smote him there for his
errour, and there he died by the Arke of God.<note> Or, rashnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Dauid was
displeased, because the Lord had made a breach vpon Uzzah: And hee
called the name of the place, Perez-Uzzah to this day.<note> Hebr. broken. , That is, The breach of Vzzah.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Dauid was
afraide of the Lord that day, and said, How shall the Arke of the
Lord come to me?</ab>
<ab n="10">So Dauid would
not remoue the Arke of the Lord vnto him into the citie of Dauid:
but Dauid caried it aside into the house of Obed Edom, the
Gittite.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Arke of
the Lord continued in the house of Obed Edom the Gittite, three
moneths: and the Lord blessed Obed Edom, and all his
household.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And it
was told king Dauid, saying, The Lord hath blessed the house of
Obed Edom, and all that pertained vnto him, because of the Arke of
God. So Dauid went, and brought vp the Arke of God, from the house
of Obed Edom, into the citie of Dauid, with gladnesse.<note> 1. Chron. 15.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And it was so,
that when they that bare the Arke of the Lord, had gone sixe paces,
hee sacrificed oxen and fatlings.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Dauid
daunced before the Lord with all his might, and Dauid was girded
with a linnen Ephod.</ab>
<ab n="15">So Dauid and all
the house of Israel brought vp the Arke of the Lord with shouting,
and with the sound of the trumpet.</ab>
<ab n="16">And as the Arke
of the Lord came into the citie of Dauid, Michal Sauls daughter
looked through a window, and saw king Dauid leaping and dauncing
before the Lord, and she despised him in her heart.</ab>

<fw>Michal childlesse.</fw>
<ab n="17">¶ And they
brought in the Arke of the Lord, and set it in his place, in the
midst of the Tabernacle that Dauid had pitched for it: and Dauid
offered burnt offerings, and peace offrings before the
Lord.<note> Heb. stretched.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And assoone as
Dauid had made an end of offering burnt offerings and peace
offerings, hee blessed the people in the Name of the Lord of
hostes.<note> 1. Chron. 16.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And hee dealt
among all the people, euen among the whole multitude of Israel, as
well to the women as men, to euery one a cake of bread, and a good
piece of flesh, and a flagon of wine: so all the people departed
euery one to his house.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Then
Dauid returned to blesse his houshold: and Michal the daughter of
Saul came out to meete Dauid, and said, How glorious was the King
of Israel to day, who vncouered himselfe to day in the eyes of the
handmaids of his seruants, as one of the vaine fellowes
shamelessely vncouereth himselfe!<note> Or, openly.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Dauid said
vnto Michal, It was before the Lord, which chose me before thy
father, &amp; before all his house, to appoint me ruler ouer the
people of the Lord, ouer Israel: therefore will I play before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">And I will yet
be more vile then thus, and will be base in mine owne sight: and of
the maid seruants which thou hast spoken of, of them shall I be had
in honour.<note> Or, of the handmaids of my seruants.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore Michal
the daughter of Saul had no childe vnto the day of her
death.</ab>



</div>