<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Samuel-Chapter-31-31-2-Samuel.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The Amalekite, who brought tidings
of the ouerthrow, and accused himselfe of Sauls death, is slaine.
17 Dauid lamenteth Saul and Ionathan with a song.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe after þ<note/> death of Saul, when Dauid was
returned from the slaughter of the Amalekites, and Dauid had abode
two daies in Ziklag,<note> 1. Sam. 30.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">It came euen to
passe on the third day, that behold, a man came out of the campe
from Saul, with his clothes rent, and earth vpon his head: and so
it was when he came to Dauid, that hee fell to the earth, and did
obeysance.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Dauid said
vnto him, From whence commest thou? And he said vnto him, Out of
the campe of Israel am I escaped.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Dauid said
vnto him, How went the matter? I pray thee, tell mee. And he
answered, That the people are fled from the battell, and many of
the people also are fallen and dead, and Saul and Ionathan his
sonne are dead also.<note> Heb. what was &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauid heareth of Sauls death.</fw>
<ab n="5">And Dauid said
vnto the yong man that told him, How knowest thou that Saul and
Ionathan his sonne be dead?</ab>
<ab n="6">And the yong man
that told him, said, As I happened by chance vpon mount Gilboa,
behold, Saul leaned vpon his speare: and loe, the charets and
horsemen followed hard after him.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when he
looked behind him, he saw me, and called vnto mee: and I answered,
Here am I.<note> Hebr. behold me.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And hee said vnto
mee, Who art thou? and I answered him, I am an Amalekite.</ab>
<ab n="9">He said vnto me
againe, Stand, I pray thee, vpon me, and slay me: for anguish is
come vpon mee, because my life is yet whole in me.<note> Or, my coat of male, (or, my embroidered coat) hindereth mee, that my, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So I stood vpon
him, and slew him, because I was sure that hee could not liue after
that hee was fallen: And I tooke the crowne that was vpon his head,
and the bracelet that was on his arme, and haue brought them hither
vnto my lord.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then Dauid tooke
hold on his clothes, and rent them, and likewise all the men that
were with him.<note> Chap. 3. 31. and 13. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they mourned
and wept, and fasted vntill Euen, for Saul and for Ionathan his
sonne, and for the people of the Lord, and for the house of Israel,
because they were fallen by the sword.</ab>

<fw>Dauid lamenteth.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ And Dauid
said vnto the yong man that told him, Whence art thou? And he
answered, I am the sonne of a stranger, an Amalekite.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Dauid said
vnto him, How wast thou not afraid to stretch foorth thine hand, to
destroy the Lords Anointed?<note> Psal. 105. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Dauid called
one of the yong men, and sayd, Goe neere, and fall vpon him. And
hee smote him, that hee dyed.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Dauid said
vnto him, Thy blood be vpon thy head: for thy mouth hath testified
against thee, saying, I haue slaine the Lords Annoynted.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And Dauid
lamented with this lamentation ouer Saul, and ouer Ionathan his
sonne:</ab>
<ab n="18">(Also hee bade
them teach the children of Iudah the vse of the bow: behold, it is
written in the booke of Iasher.)<note> Iosh. 10. 13. , Or, of the vpright.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The beauty of
Israel is slaine vpon thy high places: how are the mightie
fallen!</ab>
<ab n="20">Tell it not in
Gath, publish it not in the streetes of Askelon: lest the daughters
of the Philistines reioyce, lest the daughters of the vncircumcised
triumph.<note> Micah 1. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Yee mountaines
of Gilboa, let there bee no dewe, neither let there be raine vpon
you, nor fields of offerings: for there the shield of the mightie
is vilely cast away, the shield of Saul, as though hee had not
beene annointed with oile.</ab>
<ab n="22">From the blood
of the slaine, from the fat of the mightie, the bow of Ionathan
turned not backe, and the sword of Saul returned not
emptie.</ab>
<ab n="23">Saul and
Ionathan were louely and pleasant in their liues, and in their
death they were not diuided: they were swifter then Eagles, they
were stronger then Lions.<note> Or, sweet.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Yee daughters of
Israel, weepe ouer Saul, who clothed you in scarlet, with other
delights, who put on ornaments of golde vpon your apparell.</ab>
<ab n="25">How are the
mightie fallen in the midst of the battell! O Ionathan, thou wast
slaine in thine high places.</ab>
<ab n="26">I am distressed
for thee, my brother Ionathan, very pleasant hast thou beene vnto
mee: thy loue to mee was wonderfull, passing the loue of
women.</ab>
<ab n="27">How are the
mightie fallen, and the weapons of warre perished!</ab>




</div>