<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-15-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Absalom, by faire speeches and
courtesies, stealeth the hearts of Israel. 7 Vnder pretence of a
vow he obtaineth leaue to go to Hebron. 10 He maketh there a great
conspiracie. 13 Dauid vpon the newes fleeth from Ierusalem. 19
Ittai would not leaue him. 24 Zadok and Abiathar are sent backe
with the Arke. 30 Dauid and his companie go vp mount Oliuet
weeping. 31 He curseth Ahithophels counsel. 32 Hushai is sent backe
with instructions.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after this, that Absalom prepared him charets and horses, and
fiftie men to runne before him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Absalom rose
vp earely, and stood beside the way of the gate: and it was so,
that when any man that had a controuersie, came to the king for
iudgment, then Absalom called vnto him, and said, Of what citie art
thou? And he said, Thy seruant is of one of the tribes of
Israel.<note> Hebr. to come.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Absalom said
vnto him, See, thy matters are good &amp; right, but there is no
man deputed of the king to heare thee.<note> Or, none will heare you from the king downward.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Absalom said
moreouer, Oh that I were made Iudge in the land, that euery man
which hath any suit or cause, might come vnto me, and I would do
him iustice.</ab>
<ab n="5">And it was so,
that when any man came nigh to him, to doe him obeisance, he put
foorth his hand, and tooke him, and kissed him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And on this
maner did Absalom to all Israel, that came to the King for
iudgement: so Absalom stole the hearts of the men of
Israel.</ab>

<fw>Absaloms treason.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ And it
came to passe after fourtie yeeres, that Absalom said vnto the
king, I pray thee, let mee goe and pay my vow which I haue vowed
vnto the Lord in Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="8">For thy seruant
vowed a vowe while I abode at Geshur in Syria, saying, If the Lord
shall bring mee againe in deed to Ierusalem, then I will serue the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the king
said vnto him, Goe in peace. So he arose, and went to
Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ But
Absalom sent spies thorowout all the tribes of Israel, saying, As
soone as yee heare the sound of the trumpet, then yee shall say,
Absalom reigneth in Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="11">And with
Absalom went two hundred men out of Ierusalem, that were called,
and they went in their simplicitie, and they knew not any
thing.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Absalom
sent for Ahithophel the Gilonite, Dauids counseller, from his
citie, euen from Giloh, while he offered sacrifices: and the
conspiracie was strong, for the people encreased continually with
Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
there came a messenger to Dauid, saying, The hearts of the men of
Israel are after Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Dauid said
vnto all his seruants that were with him at Ierusalem, Arise, and
let vs flee; for wee shall not else escape from Absalom: make
speede to depart, lest hee ouertake vs suddenly, and bring euill
vpon vs, and smite the city with the edge of the sword.<note> Heb. thrust</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the kings
seruants said vnto the king, Behold, thy seruants are readie to doe
whatsoeuer my lord the king shall appoint.<note> Heb. chuse.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the king
went foorth, and all his houshold after him: and the King left
tenne women, which were concubines, to keepe the house.<note> Heb. at his feete.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the king
went forth, and all the people after him, and taried in a place
that was farre off.</ab>
<ab n="18">And all his
seruants passed on beside him: and all the Cherethites, and all the
Pelethites, and all the Gittites, sixe hundred men, which came
after him from Gath, passed on before the king.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then
said the king to Ittai the Gittite, Wherefore goest thou also with
vs? Returne to thy place, and abide with the King: for thou art a
stranger, and also an exile.</ab>

<fw>Dauid fleeth.</fw>
<ab n="20">Whereas thou
camest but yesterday, should I this day make thee goe vp and downe
with vs? Seeing I goe whither I may, returne thou, and take backe
thy brethren: mercie and trueth be with thee.<note> Heb. make thee wander in going?</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Ittai
answered the King, and said, As the Lord liueth, and as my lord the
king liueth, surely in what place my lord the king shall be,
whether in death or life, euen there also will thy seruant
be.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Dauid said
to Ittai, Goe, and passe ouer. And Ittai the Gittite passed ouer,
and all his men, and all the little ones that were with
him.</ab>
<ab n="23">And all the
countrey wept with a loude voice, and all the people passed ouer:
the King also himselfe passed ouer the brooke Kidron, and all the
people passed ouer, toward the way of the wildernesse.<note> Called Ioh. 18.1. Cedron.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And loe,
Zadok also, and all the Leuites were with him, bearing the Arke of
the Couenant of God, and they set downe the Arke of God; and
Abiathar went vp, vntill all the people had done passing out of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the King
said vnto Zadok, Cary backe the Arke of God into the citie: if I
shall finde fauour in the eyes of the Lord, he wil bring me againe,
and shew me both it, and his habitation.</ab>
<ab n="26">But if he thus
say, I haue no delight in thee: beholde, here am I, let him doe to
me, as seemeth good vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="27">The king said
also vnto Zadok the Priest, Art not thou a Seer? Returne into the
citie in peace, and your two sonnes with you, Ahimaaz thy sonne,
and Ionathan the sonne of Abiathar.<note> 1. Sam. 9.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">See, I will
tarie in the plaine of the wildernesse, vntill there come word from
you to certifie me.</ab>
<ab n="29">Zadok therefore
and Abiathar caried the Arke of God againe to Ierusalem; and they
taried there.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And
Dauid went vp by the ascent of mount Oliuet, and wept as he went
vp, and had his head couered, and he went barefoote, and all the
people that was with him, couered euery man his head, and they went
vp, weeping as they went vp.<note> Heb. going vp and weeping.</note></ab>

<fw>Hushais friendship.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ And one
tolde Dauid, saying, Ahithophel is among the conspirators with
Absalom. And Dauid sayde, O Lord, I pray thee turne the counsell of
Ahithophel into foolishnesse.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And it
came to passe, that when Dauid was come to the top of the mount,
where he worshipped God, behold, Hushai the Archite came to meet
him, with his coat rent, and earth vpon his head:</ab>
<ab n="33">Unto whom Dauid
said, If thou passest on with me, then thou shalt be a burden vnto
me.</ab>
<ab n="34">But if thou
returne to the citie, and say vnto Absalom, I wil be thy seruant, O
king: as I haue bene thy fathers seruant hitherto, so will I now
also be thy seruant: then mayest thou for mee defeat the counsell
of Ahithophel.</ab>
<ab n="35">And hast thou
not there with thee Zadok, and Abiathar the Priests? therefore it
shall be, that what thing soeuer thou shalt heare out of the kings
house, thou shalt tell it to Zadok and Abiathar the
Priests.</ab>
<ab n="36">Behold, they
haue there with them their two sonnes, Ahimaaz Zadoks sonne, and
Ionathan Abiathars sonne: and by them ye shall send vnto me euery
thing that ye can heare.</ab>
<ab n="37">So Hushai
Dauids friend came into the citie, and Absalom came into
Ierusalem.</ab>



</div>