<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 By occasion of the quarrell, Sheba
maketh a party in Israel. 3 Dauids ten concubines are shut vp in
perpetual prison. 4 Amasa made captaine ouer Iudah, is slaine by
Ioab. 14 Ioab pursueth Sheba vnto Abel. 16 A wise woman saueth the
citie by Shebaes head. 23 Dauids Officers.</head>

<ab n="1">And there
happened to bee there a man of Belial, whose name was Sheba the
sonne of Bichri, a Beniamite, &amp; hee blew a trumpet, and said,
Wee haue no part in Dauid, neither haue we inheritance in the sonne
of Iesse: euery man to his tents, O Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">So euery man of
Israel went vp from after Dauid, and followed Sheba the sonne of
Bichri: but the men of Iudah claue vnto their king, from Iordane
euen to Ierusalem.</ab>

<fw>Amasa slaine.</fw>
<ab n="3">¶ And Dauid
came to his house at Ierusalem, and the king tooke the ten women
his concubines, whom he had left to keep the house, and put them in
ward, and fed them, but went not in vnto them: so they were shut vp
vnto the day of their death, liuing in widowhood.<note> Chap.16. 22. , Hebr. a house of ward. , Hebr. bound. , Hebr. in widowhood of life.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then said
the king to Amasa, Assemble me the men of Iudah within three dayes,
and be thou here present.<note> Hebr. call.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So Amasa went to
assemble the men of Iudah; but hee taried longer then the set time
which he had appointed him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Dauid said
to Abishai, Now shall Sheba the sonne of Bichri doe vs more harme
then did Absalom: take thou thy lords seruants, and pursue after
him, lest he get him fenced cities, and escape vs.<note> Hebr. deliuer himselfe from our eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And there went
out after him Ioabs men, and the Cherethites, and the Pelethites,
and all the mighty men: and they went out of Ierusalem, to pursue
after Sheba the sonne of Bichri.<note> Chap.8. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">When they were
at the great stone which is in Gibeon, Amasa went before them: and
Ioabs garment that he had put on, was girded vnto him, and vpon it
a girdle with a sword fastned vpon his loynes in the sheath
thereof, and as hee went forth, it fell out.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Ioab saide
to Amasa, Art thou in health, my brother? And Ioab tooke Amasa by
the beard with the right hand to kisse him.</ab>
<ab n="10">But Amasa tooke
no heed to the sword that was in Ioabs hand: so hee smote him
therewith in the fifth rib, and shed out his bowels to the ground,
and strake him not againe, and he died: so Ioab and Abishai his
brother pursued after Sheba the sonne of Bichri.<note> Hebr. doubled not his stroke.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And one of
Ioabs men stood by him, and said, He that fauoureth Ioab, and hee
that is for Dauid, let him goe after Ioab.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Amasa
wallowed in blood in the mids of the high way: and when the man saw
that all the people stood still, he remoued Amasa out of the high
way into the field, and cast a cloth vpon him, when hee saw that
euery one that came by him, stood still.</ab>
<ab n="13">When he was
remoued out of the high way, all the people went on after Ioab, to
pursue after Sheba the sonne of Bichri.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And hee
went thorow all the tribes of Israel vnto Abel, and to Bethmaachah,
and all the Berites: and they were gathered together, and went also
after him.</ab>

<fw>Sheba beheaded.</fw>
<ab n="15">And they came
and besieged him in Abel of Bethmaachah, and they cast vp a banke
against the citie, and it stood in the trench: and all the people
that were with Ioab, battered the wall, to throw it
downe.<note> Or, it stood against the outmost wall , Heb. marred to throw downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then
cried a wise woman out of the citie, Heare, heare; say, I pray you,
vnto Ioab, Come neere hither, that I may speake with thee.</ab>
<ab n="17">And when he was
come neere vnto her, the woman said, Art thou Ioab? And he
answered, I am he: Then shee said vnto him, Heare the words of
thine handmaid. And he answered, I doe heare.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then she spake,
saying, They were wont to speake in old time, saying, They shall
surely aske counsell at Abel: and so they ended the
matter.<note> Or, They plainly spake in the beginning, saying, surely they will aske of Abel, and so make an end</note></ab>
<ab n="19">I am one of
them that are peaceable and faithfull in Israel: thou seekest to
destroy a citie, and a mother in Israel: Why wilt thou swallow vp
the inheritance of the Lord ?</ab>
<ab n="20">And Ioab
answered and saide, Farre be it, farre be it from me, that I should
swallow vp or destroy.</ab>
<ab n="21">The matter is
not so: but a man of mount Ephraim (Sheba the sonne of Bichri by
name) hath lift vp his hand against the king, euen against Dauid:
deliuer him onely, and I will depart from the city. And the woman
said vnto Ioab, Behold, his head shall be throwen to thee ouer the
wall.<note> Heb. by his name.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then the woman
went vnto all the people in her wisedome, and they cut off the head
of Sheba the sonne of Bichri, and cast it out to Ioab: and hee blew
a trumpet, and they retired from the citie, euery man to his tent:
&amp; Ioab returned to Ierusalem vnto the king.<note> Heb. were scattered.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Now Ioab
was ouer all the hoste of Israel, and Benaiah the sonne of Iehoiada
was ouer the Cherethites, and ouer the Pelethites.<note> Chap.8. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Adoram was
ouer the tribute, and Iehoshaphat the sonne of Ahilud was
Recorder.<note> Or, remembrancer</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Sheua was
scribe, and Zadok, and Abiathar were the Priests.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Ira also
the Iairite, was a chiefe ruler about Dauid.<note> Or, a prince.</note></ab>



</div>