<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The Israelites being troubled at
the death of Abner, 2 Baanah and Rechab slay Ishbosheth, and bring
his head to Hebron. 9 Dauid causeth them to be slaine, and
Ishbosheths head to be buried.</head>

<ab n="1">And when Sauls
sonne heard that Abner was dead in Hebron, his hands were feeble,
and all the Israelites were troubled.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Sauls sonne
had two men that were captaines of bands: the name of the one was
Baanah, and the name of the other Rechab, the sonnes of Rimmon a
Beerothite, of the children of Beniamin: (for Beeroth also was
reckoned to Beniamin:<note> Heb. second.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the
Beerothites fled to Gittaim, and were soiourners there vntill this
day.)</ab>
<ab n="4">And Ionathan,
Sauls sonne, had a sonne that was lame of his feete, and was fiue
yeeres olde when the tidings came of Saul and Ionathan out of
Iezreel, and his nource tooke him vp, and fled: and it came to
passe as she made haste to flee, that hee fell, and became lame,
and his name was Mephibosheth.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the sonnes of
Rimmon the Beerothite, Rechab and Baanah, went, and came about the
heat of the day to the house of Ishbosheth, who lay on a bed at
noone.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they came
thither into the midst of the house, as though they would haue
fetched wheat, and they smote him vnder the fift rib, and Rechab
and Baanah his brother escaped.</ab>
<ab n="7">For when they
came into the house, hee lay on his bedde in his bedchamber, and
they smote him, and slew him, and beheaded him, and tooke his head,
and gate them away thorow the plaine all night.</ab>

<fw>Rechab &amp;c, slaine.</fw>
<ab n="8">And they brought
the head of Ishbosheth vnto Dauid to Hebron, and said to the King,
Behold the head of Ishbosheth the sonne of Saul, thine enemie,
which sought thy life, and the Lord hath auenged my lord the king
this day of Saul and of his seed.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Dauid
answered Rechab and Baanah his brother, the sonnes of Rimmon the
Beerothite, and said vnto them, As the Lord liueth, who hath
redeemed my soule out of all aduersitie,</ab>
<ab n="10">When one told
me, saying, Behold, Saul is dead, ( thinking to haue brought good
tidings) I tooke hold of him, and slew him in Ziklag, who thought
that I would haue giuen him a reward for his tidings:<note> Chap. 1. 15. , Heb. hee was in his owne eyes as a bringer, &amp;c. , Or, which was the reward I gaue him for his tidings.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">How much more,
when wicked men haue slaine a righteous person, in his owne house,
vpon his bed? Shall I not therefore now require his blood of your
hand, and take you away from the earth?</ab>
<ab n="12">And Dauid
commanded his yong men, and they slew them, and cut off their hands
and their feete, and hanged them vp ouer the poole in Hebron: but
they tooke the head of Ishbosheth, and buried it in the sepulchre
of Abner, in Hebron.<note> Chap. 3. 32.</note></ab>



</div>