<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Dauid by Gods direction, with his
companie goeth vp to Hebron, where he is made King of Iudah. 5 He
commendeth them of Iabesh Gilead, for their kindnesse to Saul. 8
Abner maketh Ishbosheth king of Israel. 12 A mortall skirmish
betweene twelue of Abners, and twelue of Ioabs men. 18 Asahel is
slaine. 25 At Abners motion Ioab soundeth a retreat. 32 Asahels
buriall.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after this, that Dauid enquired of the Lord, saying, Shall I
goe vp into any of the Cities of Iudah? And the Lord said vnto him,
Goe vp. And Dauid said, Whither shall I goe vp? And he said, Unto
Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="2">So Dauid went vp
thither, and his two wiues also, Ahinoam the Iezreelitesse, and
Abigail Nabals wife the Carmelite.</ab>
<ab n="3">And his men that
were with him, did Dauid bring vp, euery man with his houshold: and
they dwelt in the cities of Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the men of
Iudah came, and there they anointed Dauid king ouer the house of
Iudah: and they tolde Dauid, saying; That the men of Iabesh Gilead
were they that buried Saul.<note> 1. Macc. 2.57. , 1. Sam. 31. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And Dauid
sent messengers vnto the men of Iabesh Gilead, and said vnto them,
Blessed be ye of the Lord, that ye haue shewed this kindnesse vnto
your lord, euen vnto Saul, and haue buried him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And now the Lord
shewe kindnesse and trueth vnto you: and I also will requite you
this kindnesse, because ye haue done this thing.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore now let
your handes be strengthened, and be ye valiant: for your master
Saul is dead, and also the house of Iudah haue anointed me king
ouer them.<note> Heb. be ye the sonnes of valour.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But Abner
the sonne of Ner, captaine of Sauls hoste, tooke Ishbosheth the
sonne of Saul, and brought him ouer to Mahanaim.<note> Heb. the hoste which was Sauls.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And hee made him
king ouer Gilead, and ouer the Ashurites, and ouer Iezreel, and
ouer Ephraim, and ouer Beniamin, and ouer all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="10">Ishbosheth Sauls
sonne was fortie yeeres olde when he began to reigne ouer Israel,
and reigned two yeres: but the house of Iudah followed
Dauid.</ab>

<fw>Dauids warre with Ishbosheth.</fw>
<ab n="11">(And the time
that Dauid was King in Hebron ouer the house of Iudah, was seuen
yeeres, and sixe moneths)<note> Heb. number of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Abner
the sonne of Ner, and the seruants of Ishbosheth the sonne of Saul,
went out from Mahanaim, to Gibeon.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Ioab the
sonne of Zeruiah, and the seruants of Dauid went out, and met
together by the poole of Gibeon: and they sate downe, the one on
the one side of the poole, and the other on the other side of the
poole.<note> Heb. them together.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Abner said
to Ioab, Let the yong men now arise, and play before vs: and Ioab
saide, Let them arise.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then there arose
and went ouer by number twelue of Beniamin, which pertained to
Ishbosheth the sonne of Saul, and twelue of the seruants of
Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they caught
euery one his fellow by the head, and thrust his sword in his
fellowes side, so they fell downe together: Wherfore that place was
called Helkath-hazzurim, which is in Gibeon.<note> That is, the field of strong men.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And there was a
very sore battell that day: and Abner was beaten, and the men of
Israel, before the seruants of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And there
were three sonnes of Zeruiah there, Ioab, and Abishai, and Asahel:
and Asahel was as light of foot as a wilde Roe.<note> Heb. of his feete. , Heb. as one of the Roes that is in the field.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Asahel
pursued after Abner, and in going he turned not to the right hand
nor to the left from following Abner.<note> Heb. from after Abner.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then Abner
looked behind him, and said, Art thou Asahel? And he answered, I
am.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Abner said
to him, Turne thee aside to thy right hand, or to thy left, and lay
thee holde on one of the yong men, and take thee his armour. But
Asahel would not turne aside from following of him.<note> Or, spoile.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And Abner said
againe to Asahel, Turne thee aside from following me: Wherefore
should I smite thee to the ground? how then should I holde vp my
face to Ioab thy brother?</ab>

<fw>Dauids warre with Ishbosheth.</fw>
<ab n="23">Howbeit he
refused to turne aside: wherefore Abner with the hinder ende of the
speare smote him vnder the fift ribbe, that the speare came out
behinde him, and hee fell downe there, and died in the same place:
and it came to passe, that as many as came to the place where
Asahel fell downe and died, stood still.</ab>
<ab n="24">Ioab also and
Abishai pursued after Abner: and the Sunne went downe when they
were come to the hill of Ammah, that lieth before Giah by the way
of the wildernesse of Gibeon.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And the
children of Beniamin gathered themselues together after Abner, and
became one troupe, and stood on the top of an hill.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then Abner
called to Ioab, and said, Shall the sword deuoure for euer? Knowest
thou not that it wil be bitternesse in the latter end? How long
shall it bee then, yer thou bid the people returne from following
their brethren?</ab>
<ab n="27">And Ioab said,
As God liueth, vnlesse thou hadst spoken, surely then in the
morning the people had gone vp euery one from following his
brother.<note> Heb. from the morning. , Or, gone away.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">So Ioab blew a
trumpet, and all the people stood still, and pursued after Israel
no more, neither fought they any more.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Abner and
his men walked all that night thorow the plaine, and passed ouer
Iordane, and went thorow all Bithron, and they came to
Mahanaim.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Ioab
returned from folowing Abner; and when he had gathered all the
people together, there lacked of Dauids seruants nineteene men, and
Asahel.</ab>
<ab n="31">But the seruants
of Dauid had smitten of Beniamin and of Abners men, so that three
hundred and threescore men died.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And they
tooke vp Asahel, and buried him in the sepulchre of his father
which was in Bethlehem: and Ioab and his men went all night, and
they came to Hebron at breake of day.</ab>



</div>