<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in his last words,
professeth his faith in Gods promises to be beyond sence or
experience. 6 The different state of the wicked. 8 A catalogue of
Dauids mightie men.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe these bee
the last words of Dauid: Dauid the sonne of Iesse saide, and the
man who was raised vp on high, the Anointed of the God of Iacob,
and the sweet Psalmist of Israel, said,</ab>
<ab n="2">The spirit of
the Lord spake by me, and his word was in my tongue.</ab>
<ab n="3">The God of
Israel said, the Rocke of Israel spake to me: he that ruleth ouer
men must be iust, ruling in the feare of God:<note> Or, be thou ruler, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And he shall be
as the light of the morning, when the Sunne riseth, euen a morning,
without cloudes; as the tender grasse springing out of the earth by
cleare shining after raine:</ab>
<ab n="5">Although my
house be not so with God: yet he hath made with mee an euerlasting
couenant, ordred in al things and sure: for this is all my
saluation, and all my desire, although he make it not to
grow.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ But the
sonnes of Belial shall bee all of them as thornes thrust away,
because they cannot be taken with hands,</ab>
<ab n="7">But the man that
shal touch them, must be fenced with yron, and the staffe of a
speare, and they shall bee vtterly burnt with fire in the same
place.<note> Heb. filled.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ These be
the names of the mightie men whome Dauid had: The Tachmonite that
sate in the seat, chiefe among the captaines, (the same was Adino
the Eznite:) hee lift vp his speare against eight hundred, whom he
slew at one time.<note> Or, Ioshebbassebet the Tachmonite head of the three. , See 1. chr. 11.11. , Heb. slaine.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids worthies, and valiant
men.</fw>
<ab n="9">And after him
was Eleazar the sonne of Dodo the Ahohite, one of the three mightie
men with Dauid, when they defied the Philistines that were there
gathered together to battell, and the men of Israel were gone
away.<note> 1.Chron. 11.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">He arose, and
smote the Philistines vntill his hand was wearie, and his hand
claue vnto the sword: and the Lord wrought a great victorie that
day, and the people returned after him onely to spoile.</ab>
<ab n="11">And after him
was Shammah the sonne of Agee the Hararite: and the Philistines
were gathered together into a troupe, where was a piece of ground
full of lentiles: and the people fled from the
Philistines.<note> 1. Chron. 11.27. , Or, for forraging.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But hee stood
in the midst of the ground, and defended it, and slewe the
Philistines: and the Lord wrought a great victorie.</ab>
<ab n="13">And three of
the thirtie chiefe went downe and came to Dauid in the haruest
time, vnto the caue of Adullam: and the troupe of the Philistines
pitched in the valley of Rephaim.<note> Or, the three captaines ouer the thirtie.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Dauid was
then in an holde, and the garison of the Philistines was then in
Bethlehem.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Dauid
longed, and said, Oh that one would giue mee drinke of the water of
the well of Bethlehem which is by the gate.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the three
mightie men brake through the host of the Philistines, and drew
water out of the Well of Bethlehem, that was by the gate, and tooke
it, and brought it to Dauid: neuerthelesse he would not drinke
thereof, but powred it out vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said, Be
it farre from me, O Lord, that I should doe this: is not this the
blood of the men that went in ieopardie of their liues? therefore
he would not drinke it. These things did these three mightie
men.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Abishai the
brother of Ioab, the sonne of Zeruiah, was chiefe among three, and
he lift vp his speare against three hundred, and slew them, and had
the name among three.<note> 1. Chron. 11.20. , Heb. slaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Was hee not
most honourable of three? therefore he was their captaine: howbeit,
hee attained not vnto the first three.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Benaiah the
sonne of Iehoiada the sonne of a valiant man, of Kabzeel, who had
done many actes, he slew two lion-like men of Moab: hee went downe
also, and slewe a Lyon in the middest of a pit in time of
snow.<note> Heb. great of acts. , Hebr. lion of God.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids worthies.</fw>
<ab n="21">And he slew an
Egyptian a goodly man: and the Egyptian had a speare in his hand;
but he went downe to him with a staffe, and plucked the speare out
of the Egyptians hand, and slewe him with his owne
speare.<note> Heb. a man of countenance or sight: called 1. Chro. 11. 23. a man of great stature.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">These things
did Benaiah the sonne of Iehoiada, and had the name among three
mightie men.</ab>
<ab n="23">Hee was more
honourable then the thirtie, but hee attained not to the first
three: and Dauid set him ouer his guard.<note> Or, honourable among the thirtie. , Or, Councill: Heb. at his command</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Asahel the
brother of Ioab was one of the thirtie: Elhanan the sonne of Dodo
of Bethlehem,<note> Chap. 2. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Shammah the
Harodite, Elika the Harodite,</ab>
<ab n="26">Helez the
Paltite, Ira the sonne of Ikkesh the Tekoite,<note> 1. Chron. 11.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Abiezer the
Anethothite, Mebunnai the Hushathite,</ab>
<ab n="28">Zalmon the
Ahohite, Maharai the Netophathite,</ab>
<ab n="29">Heleb the sonne
of Baanah, a Netophathite, Ittai the sonne of Ribai out of Gibeah
of the children of Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="30">Benaiah the
Pirathonite, Hiddai of the brookes of Gaash,<note> Or, valleys.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Abialbon the
Arbathite, Azmaueth the Barhumite,</ab>
<ab n="32">Elihaba the
Shaalbonite: of the sonnes of Iashen, Ionathan,</ab>
<ab n="33">Shammah the
Hararite, Ahiam the sonne of Sharar the Hararite,</ab>
<ab n="34">Eliphelet the
sonne of Ahasbai, the sonne of the Maachathite, Eliam the sonne of
Ahithophel the Gilonite,</ab>
<ab n="35">Hezrai the
Carmelite, Paarai the Arbite,</ab>
<ab n="36">Igal the sonne
of Nathan of Zobah, Bani the Gadite,</ab>
<ab n="37">Zelek the
Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, armour-bearer to Ioab the sonne of
Zeruiah,</ab>
<ab n="38">Ira an Ithrite,
Gareb an Ithrite,</ab>
<ab n="39">Uriah the
Hittite: thirtie and seuen in all.</ab>



</div>