<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Nathans parable of the Ewe lambe,
causeth Dauid to be his owne Iudge. 7 Dauid, reproued by Nathan,
confesseth his sinne and is pardoned. 15 Dauid mourneth and prayeth
for the childe, while it liued. 24 Salomon is borne and named
Iedidiah. 26 Dauid taketh Rabbah, and tortureth the people
thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
sent Nathan vnto Dauid: and he came vnto him, and said vnto him,
There were two men in one citie; the one rich, and the other
poore.</ab>
<ab n="2">The rich man had
exceeding many flockes and herds.</ab>
<ab n="3">But the poore
man had nothing saue one litle ewe lambe, which he had bought and
nourished vp: and it grew vp together with him, and with his
children, it did eate of his owne meate, and dranke of his owne
cup, and lay in his bosome, and was vnto him as a
daughter.<note> Heb. morsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And there came a
traueller vnto the rich man, and he spared to take of his owne
flocke, and of his owne herd, to dresse for the wayfaring man that
was come vnto him, but tooke the poore mans lambe, and dressed it
for the man that was come to him.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Dauids anger
was greatly kindled against the man, and he said to Nathan, As the
Lord liueth, the man that hath done this thing, shall surely
die.<note> Or, is worthy to die.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he shall
restore the Lambe fourefold, because he did this thing, and because
he had no pittie.<note> Exo. 22. 1</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
Nathan said to Dauid, Thou art the man: thus saith the Lord God of
Israel, I anointed thee king ouer Israel, and I deliuered thee out
of the hand of Saul,<note> Sam. 16. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I gaue thee
thy Masters house, and thy Masters wiues into thy bosome, and gaue
thee the house of Israel and of Iudah, and if that had bene too
litle, I would moreouer haue giuen vnto thee such and such
things.</ab>

<fw>Dauid repenteth.</fw>
<ab n="9">Wherefore hast
thou despised the commandement of the Lord, to doe euill in his
sight? thou hast killed Uriah the Hittite with the sword, and hast
taken his wife to be thy wife, and hast slaine him with the sword
of the children of Ammon.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now therefore
the sword shall neuer depart from thine house, because thou hast
despised me, and hast taken the wife of Uriah the Hittite, to be
thy wife.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus saith the
Lord, Behold, I will raise vp euill against thee out of thine owne
house, and I will take thy wiues before thine eyes, and giue them
vnto thy neighbour, and he shall lie with thy wiues in the sight of
this Sunne.<note> Deut. 28. 30. chap. 16. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For thou
diddest it secretly: but I will do this thing before all Israel,
and before the Sunne.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Dauid saide
vnto Nathan, I haue sinned against the Lord. And Nathan saide vnto
Dauid, The Lord also hath put away thy sinne, thou shalt not
die.<note> Ecclus. 47.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Howbeit,
because by this deede thou hast giuen great occasion to the enemies
of the Lord to blaspheme, the childe also that is borne vnto thee,
shall surely die.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And
Nathan departed vnto his house: and the Lord strake the childe that
Uriahs wife bare vnto Dauid, and it was very sicke.</ab>
<ab n="16">Dauid therfore
besought God for the childe, and Dauid fasted, and went in, and lay
all night vpon the earth.<note> Heb. fasted a fast.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the Elders
of his house arose, and went to him, to raise him vp from the
earth: but he would not, neither did he eate bread with
them.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it came to
passe on the seuenth day, that the childe died: and the seruants of
Dauid feared to tell him that the child was dead: for they saide,
Behold, while the childe was yet aliue, we spake vnto him, and he
would not hearken vnto our voice: how will he then vexe himselfe,
if we tell him that the childe is dead?<note> Heb. doe hurt.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">But when Dauid
saw that his seruants whispered, Dauid perceiued that the childe
was dead: therefore Dauid said vnto his seruants, Is the child
dead? and they said, He is dead.</ab>

<fw>Solomon borne.</fw>
<ab n="20">Then Dauid
arose from the earth and washed, and anointed himselfe, and changed
his apparell, and came into the house of the Lord, and worshipped:
then hee came to his owne house, and when he required, they set
bread before him, and he did eate.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then said his
seruants vnto him, What thing is this that thou hast done? thou
didst fast and weepe for the childe, while it was aliue, but when
the childe was dead, thou didst rise and eat bread.</ab>
<ab n="22">And he said,
While the child was yet aliue, I fasted and wept: for I said, Who
can tell, whether God will be gracious to me, that the child may
liue?</ab>
<ab n="23">But now hee is
dead, Wherefore should I fast? Can I bring him backe againe? I
shall goe to him, but he shall not returne to me.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And
Dauid comforted Bathsheba his wife, and went in vnto her, and lay
with her: and she bare a sonne, and he called his name Solomon, and
the Lord loued him.<note> Matt.1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And hee sent by
the hand of Nathan the Prophet, and hee called his name Iedidiah,
because of the Lord.<note> 1.Chron. 22.9. , That is, Beloued of the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And Ioab
fought against Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and tooke the
royall citie.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Ioab sent
messengers to Dauid, and said, I haue fought against Rabbah, and
haue taken the citie of waters.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now therefore,
gather the rest of the people together, and encampe against the
citie, and take it: lest I take the citie, and it be called after
my name.<note> Hebr. my name be called vpon it.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And Dauid
gathered all the people together, and went to Rabbah, and fought
against it, and tooke it.</ab>
<ab n="30">And he tooke
their kings crowne from off his head (the weight whereof was a
talent of gold, with the precious stones) and it was set on Dauids
head, and he brought forth the spoile of the citie in great
abundance.<note> 1. Chron. 20.2. , Hebr. very great.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And he brought
foorth the people that were therein, and put them vnder sawes, and
vnder harrowes of yron, and vnder axes of yron, and made them passe
through the bricke-kilne: And thus did he vnto all the cities of
the children of Ammon. So Dauid and all the people returned vnto
Ierusalem.</ab>



</div>