<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-18-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid viewing the armies in their
march, giueth them charge of Absalom. 6 The Israelites are sore
smitten in the wood of Ephraim. 9 Absalom hanging in an Oke, is
slaine by Ioab, and cast into a pit. 18 Absaloms place. 19 Ahimaaz
and Cushi bring tidings to Dauid. 33 Dauid mourneth for
Absalom.</head>

<ab n="1">And Dauid
numbred the people that were with him, and set captaines of
thousands, and captaines of hundreds ouer them.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Dauid sent
forth a third part of the people vnder the hand of Ioab, and a
third part vnder the hand of Abishai the sonne of Zeruiah Ioabs
brother, and a third part vnder the hand of Ittai the Gittite: and
the king said vnto the people, I will surely goe foorth with you my
selfe also.</ab>
<ab n="3">But the people
answered, Thou shalt not goe foorth: for if we flee away, they will
not care for vs, neither if halfe of vs die will they care for vs:
but now thou art worth ten thousand of vs: therfore now it is
better that thou succour vs out of the citie.<note> Heb. set their heart on vs. , Heb. as ten thousand of vs. , Heb. be to succour.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the King
sayde vnto them, What seemeth you best, I will doe. And the King
stood by the gate side, and all the people came out by hundreds,
and by thousands.</ab>

<fw>Absalom slaine.</fw>
<ab n="5">And the king
commanded Ioab, and Abishai, and Ittai, saying, Deale gently for my
sake with the yong man, euen with Absalom. And all the people heard
when the king gaue all the captaines charge concerning
Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ So the
people went out into the field against Israel: and the battell was
in the wood of Ephraim,</ab>
<ab n="7">Where the people
of Israel were slaine before the seruants of Dauid, and there was
there a great slaughter that day of twenty thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="8">For the battell
was there scattered ouer the face of all the countrey: and the wood
deuoured more people that day, then the sword deuoured.<note> Hebr. multiplied to deuoure.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Absalom met the seruants of Dauid; and Absalom rode vpon a mule,
and the mule went vnder the thicke boughs of a great Oke, and his
head caught hold of the Oke, and hee was taken vp betweene the
heauen and the earth, and the mule that was vnder him, went
away.</ab>
<ab n="10">And a certaine
man saw it, and told Ioab, and said, Behold, I saw Absalom hanged
in an Oke.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Ioab said
vnto the man that told him, And behold, thou sawest him, and why
didst thou not smite him there to the ground, and I would haue
giuen thee tenne shekels of siluer, and a girdle?</ab>
<ab n="12">And the man
saide vnto Ioab, Though I should receiue a thousand shekels of
siluer in mine hand, yet would I not put foorth mine hand against
the Kings sonne: for in our hearing the King charged thee, and
Abishai, and Ittai, saying, Beware that none touch the yong man
Absalom.<note> Heb. weigh vpon mine hand. , Hebr. beware whosoeuer ye be, of &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Otherwyse, I
should haue wrought falshood against mine owne life: for there is
no matter hid from the King, and thou thy selfe wouldest haue set
thy selfe against me.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then said Ioab,
I may not tary thus with thee. And hee tooke three darts in his
hand, and thrust them thorow the heart of Absalom, while hee was
yet aliue in the midst of the Oke.<note> Hebr. before thee. , Heb. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And ten yong
men that bare Ioabs armour, compassed about and smote Absalom, and
slew him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Ioab blew
the trumpet, and the people returned from pursuing after Israel:
for Ioab helde backe the people.</ab>

<fw>Absaloms pillar.</fw>
<ab n="17">And they tooke
Absalom, and cast him into a great pit in the wood, and layd a very
great heape of stones vpon him: and all Israel fled euery one to
his tent.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Now
Absalom in his life time had taken and reared vp for himselfe a
pillar, which is in the Kings dale: for hee said, I haue no sonne
to keepe my name in remembrance: And hee called the pillar after
his owne name, and it is called vnto this day, Absaloms
place.<note> Gene.14. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then
said Ahimaaz the sonne of Zadok, Let mee now runne, and beare the
King tidings, how that the Lord hath auenged him of his
enemies.<note> Hebr. iudged him from the hand &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Ioab said
vnto him, Thou shalt not beare tidings this day, but thou shalt
beare tidings another day: but this day thou shalt beare no
tidings, because the Kings sonne is dead.<note> Hebr. be a man of tidings.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Then said Ioab
to Cushi, Goe tell the King what thou hast seene. And Cushi bowed
himselfe vnto Ioab, and ranne.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then said
Ahimaaz the sonne of Zadok yet againe to Ioab, But howsoeuer, let
mee, I pray thee, also runne after Cushi. And Ioab said, Wherefore
wilt thou runne, my sonne, seeing that thou hast no tidings
ready?<note> Hebr. be what may. , Or, conuenient.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But howsoeuer,
(said he) let mee runne: And hee said vnto him, Runne. Then Ahimaaz
ranne by the way of the plaine, and ouerranne Cushi.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Dauid sate
betweene the two gates: and the watchman went vp to the roofe ouer
the gate vnto the wall, and lift vp his eyes, and looked, and
behold, a man running alone.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the
watchman cried, and told the King. And the king said, If he bee
alone, there is tidings in his mouth. And he came apace, and drew
neere.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the
watchman saw another man running, and the watchman called vnto the
porter, and said, Behold, another man running alone. And the King
said, He also bringeth tidings.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the
watchman said, Mee thinketh the running of the foremost is like the
running of Ahimaaz the sonne of Zadok. And the King said, Hee is a
good man, and commeth with good tidings.<note> Hebr. I see the running.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauid mourneth.</fw>
<ab n="28">And Ahimaaz
called, and said vnto the King, All is well. And hee fell downe to
the earth vpon his face before the King, and saide, Blessed bee the
Lord thy God which hath deliuered vp the men that lift vp their
hande against my lord the King.<note> Or, peace be to thee. Hebr. peace , Heb. shut vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And the king
said, Is the yong man Absalom safe? And Ahimaaz answered, When Ioab
sent the kings seruant, and me thy seruant, I saw a great tumult,
but I knew not what it was.<note> Hebr. Is there peace?</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And the king
said vnto him, Turne aside and stand here. And hee turned aside,
and stood still.</ab>
<ab n="31">And behold,
Cushi came, and Cushi said, Tidings my lord the king: for the Lord
hath auenged thee this day of all them that rose vp against
thee.<note> Hebr. tidings is brought.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And the king
said vnto Cushi, Is the yong man Absalom safe? And Cushi answered,
The enemies of my lord the king, and all that rise against thee to
doe thee hurt, be as that yong man is.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And the
king was much moued, and went vp to the chamber ouer the gate, and
wept: and as he went, thus hee said, O my sonne Absalom, my sonne,
my sonne Absalom: would God I had died for thee, O Absalom, my
sonne, my sonne.</ab>




</div>