<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Nathan first approouing the
purpose of Dauid to build God an house, 4 after by the word of God
forbiddeth him. 12 He promiseth him benefites and blessings in his
seede. 18 Dauids prayer and thankesgiuing.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when the King sate in his house, and the Lord had giuen him
rest round about frō all his enemies;<note> 1. Chron. 17.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">That the king
said vnto Nathan the Prophet, See now, I dwell in an house of
Cedar, but the Arke of God dwelleth within curtaines.</ab>

<fw>Gods promise.</fw>
<ab n="3">And Nathan sayde
to the King, Go, doe all that is in thine heart: for the Lord is
with thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And it
came to passe that night, that the word of the Lord came vnto
Nathan, saying;</ab>
<ab n="5">Goe and tell my
seruant Dauid, Thus sayth the Lord, Shalt thou build me an house
for me to dwell in?<note> Heb. to my seruant to Dauid.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Whereas I haue
not dwelt in any house, since the time that I brought vp the
children of Israel out of Egypt, euen to this day, but haue walked
in a tent and in a tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="7">In all the places
wherein I haue walked with all the children of Israel, spake I a
word with any of the tribes of Israel, whome I commanded to feede
my people Israel, saying, Why build ye not me an house of
Cedar?<note> In the 1. Chro. 17.6. any of the Iudges.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Now therefore so
shalt thou say vnto my seruant Dauid; Thus sayth the Lord of
hostes, I tooke thee from the sheepe-cote, from following the
sheepe, to be ruler ouer my people, ouer Israel.<note> 1.Sam.16. 12. psal.78. 70. , Heb. from after.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And I was with
thee withersoeuer thou wentest, and haue cut off all thine enemies
out of thy sight, and haue made thee a great name, like vnto the
name of the great men that are in the earth.<note> Heb. from thy face.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">(Moreouer I will
appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that
they may dwell in a place of their owne, and mooue no more: neither
shall the children of wickednesse afflict them any more, as
beforetime,</ab>
<ab n="11">And as since the
time that I commanded Iudges to bee ouer my people Israel, and haue
caused thee to rest from all thine enemies:) Also the Lord telleth
thee, that he will make thee an house.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And when
thy dayes be fulfilled, and thou shalt sleepe with thy fathers, I
will set vp thy seede after thee, which shall proceede out of thy
bowels, and I will establish his kingdome.<note> 1. King. 8.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Hee shall build
an house for my Name, and I will stablish the throne of his
kingdome for euer.<note> 1. King. 5.5. and 6. 12. 1. chro. 22.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I will be his
father, and he shall be my sonne: if hee commit iniquitie, I will
chasten him with the rodde of men, and with the stripes of the
children of men.<note> Heb.1. 5. , Psal.89. 31,32.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But my mercie
shall not depart away from him, as I tooke it from Saul, whom I put
away before thee.</ab>

<fw>Dauids thankes, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="16">And thine house,
and thy kingdome shall be stablished for euer before thee: thy
throne shall be stablished for euer.</ab>
<ab n="17">According to all
these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speake
vnto Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then went
king Dauid in, and sate before the Lord, and hee said, Who am I, O
Lord God? and what is my house, that thou hast brought me
hitherto?</ab>
<ab n="19">And this was yet
a small thing in thy sight, O Lord God: but thou hast spoken also
of thy seruants house for a great while to come, and is this the
maner of man, O Lord God?<note> Heb. Law.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And what can
Dauid say more vnto thee? for thou, Lord God, knowest thy
seruant.</ab>
<ab n="21">For thy words
sake, and according to thine own heart hast thou done all these
great things, to make thy seruant know them.</ab>
<ab n="22">Wherefore thou
art great, O Lord God: for there is none like thee, neither is
there any God beside thee, according to all that we haue heard with
our eares.</ab>
<ab n="23">And what one
nation in the earth is like thy people, euen like Israel, whom God
went to redeeme for a people to himselfe, &amp; to make him a name,
and to doe for you great things, and terrible, for thy lande,
before thy people which thou redeemedst to thee from Egypt, from
the nations, and their gods?<note> Deut.4.7</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For thou hast
confirmed to thy selfe thy people Israel to be a people vnto thee
for euer: and thou, Lord art become their God.</ab>
<ab n="25">And now, O Lord
God, the word that thou hast spoken, concerning thy seruant, and
concerning his house, establish it for euer, and doe as thou hast
said.</ab>
<ab n="26">And let thy name
bee magnified for euer, saying, The Lord of hosts is the God ouer
Israel: and let the house of thy seruant Dauid bee established
before thee.</ab>
<ab n="27">For thou, O Lord
of hostes, God of Israel, hast reuealed to thy seruant, saying, I
will build thee an house: therfore hath thy seruant found in his
heart to pray this prayer vnto thee.<note> Heb. opened the eare.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids thankes, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="28">And now, O Lord
GOD, (thou art that God, and thy words be true, and thou hast
promised this goodnesse vnto thy seruant.)<note> Ioh.17. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Therefore now
let it please thee to blesse the house of thy seruant, that it may
continue for euer before thee: for thou, O Lord God, hast spoken
it, and with thy blessing let the house of thy seruant be blessed
for euer.<note> Heb. bee thou pleased and blesse.</note></ab>



</div>