<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Ioab causeth the king to cease his
mourning. 9 The Israelites are earnest to bring the king backe. 11
Dauid sendeth to the Priests to incite them of Iudah. 18 Shimei is
pardoned. 24 Mephibosheth excused. 32 Barzillai dismissed, Chimham
his sonne is taken into the Kings familie. 41 The Israelites
expostulate with Iudah for bringing home the King without
them.</head>

<ab n="1">And it was told
Ioab, Beholde, the king weepeth and mourneth for Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the victorie
that day was turned into mourning vnto all the people: for the
people heard say that day, how the king was grieued for his
sonne.<note> Heb. saluation or deliuerance.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the people
gate them by stealth that day into the citie, as people beeing
ashamed steale away when they flee in battell.</ab>
<ab n="4">But the king
couered his face, and the king cried with a loud voyce, O my sonne
Absalom, O Absalom my sonne, my sonne.</ab>

<fw>Dauid returneth.</fw>
<ab n="5">And Ioab came
into the house to the king, and said, Thou hast shamed this day the
faces of all thy seruants, which this day haue saued thy life, and
the liues of thy sonnes, &amp; of thy daughters, and the liues of
thy wiues, and the liues of thy concubines,</ab>
<ab n="6">In that thou
louest thine enemies, and hatest thy friends; for thou hast
declared this day, that thou regardest neither princes, nor
seruants: for this day I perceiue, that if Absalom had liued, and
all we had died this day, then it had pleased thee
well.<note> Heb. by louing, &amp;c. , Heb. that princes or seruants are not to thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
arise, goe foorth, and speake comfortably vnto thy seruants: for I
sweare by the Lord, if thou goe not forth, there wil not tarie one
with thee this night, and that will be worse vnto thee then all the
euill that befell thee from thy youth vntill now.<note> Heb. to the heart of thy seruants.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then the King
rose, and sate in the gate: and they told vnto all the people,
saying, Behold, the king doth sit in the gate: and all the people
came before the king: for Israel had fled euery man to his
tent.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And all
the people were at strife throughout all the tribes of Israel,
saying, The king saued vs out of the hand of our enemies, and he
deliuered vs out of the hand of the Philistines, and now he is fled
out of the land for Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Absalom
whom wee anointed ouer vs, is dead in battell: nowe therefore why
speake ye not a word of bringing the king backe?<note> Heb are ye silent?</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And King
Dauid sent to Zadok and to Abiathar the priests, saying, Speake
vnto the Elders of Iudah, saying, Why are ye the last to bring the
king backe to his house? (seeing the speech of all Israel is come
to the king, euen to his house.)</ab>
<ab n="12">Yee are my
brethren, Yee are my bones and my flesh: wherfore then are ye the
last to bring backe the king?</ab>
<ab n="13">And say ye to
Amasa: Art thou not of my bone, and of my flesh? God do so to me,
and more also, if thou be not captaine of the hoste before me
continually in the roome of Ioab.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he bowed
the heart of all the men of Iudah, euen as the heart of one man, so
that they sent this word vnto the King, Returne thou and all thy
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="15">So the King
returned, and came to Iordan: and Iudah came to Gilgal, to goe to
meet the King, to conduct the king ouer Iordane.</ab>

<fw>Shimeis submission.</fw>
<ab n="16">¶ And
Shimei the sonne of Gera, a Beniamite, which wass of Bahurim,
hasted, &amp; came downe with the men of Iudah, to meet King
Dauid.<note> 1.King. 2.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And there were
a thousand men of Beniamin with him, and Ziba the seruant of the
house of Saul, and his fifteene sonnes and his twenty seruants with
him, and they went ouer Iordane before the King.<note> Chap. 16.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And there went
ouer a ferry-boat to cary ouer the kings houshold, and to doe what
he thought good: and Shimei the sonne of Gera fell downe before the
king as he was come ouer Iordane;<note> Heb. the good in his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And said vnto
the king, Let not my lord impute iniquitie vnto me, neither do thou
remember that which thy seruant did peruersly the day that my lord
the king went out of Ierusalem, that the king should take it to his
heart.<note> Chap.16. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For thy seruant
doeth know that I haue sinned: therefore behold, I am come the
first this day of all the house of Ioseph, to goe downe to meete my
lord the king.</ab>
<ab n="21">But Abishai the
sonne of Zeruiah answered, and sayd, Shall not Shimei be put to
death for this, because hee cursed the Lords Anointed?</ab>
<ab n="22">And Dauid said,
What haue I to doe with you, yee sonnes of Zeruiah, that yee should
this day be aduersaries vnto me? shall there any man be put to
death this day in Israel? for doe not I know, that I am this day
King ouer Israel?</ab>
<ab n="23">Therfore the
king said vnto Shimei, Thou shalt not die: and the King sware vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And
Mephibosheth the sonne of Saul came downe to meet the king, and had
neither dressed his feete, nor trimmed his beard, nor washed his
clothes, from the day the King departed, vntill the day hee came
againe in peace.</ab>
<ab n="25">And it came to
passe when he was come to Ierusalem to meete the King, that the
King sayd vnto him, Wherefore wentest not thou with me,
Mephibosheth?</ab>
<ab n="26">And hee
answered, My lord O king, my seruant deceiued mee; for thy seruant
sayd, I will saddle me an asse that I may ride thereon, and goe to
the king, because thy seruant is lame:</ab>

<fw>Barzillai aged.</fw>
<ab n="27">And hee hath
slandered thy seruant vnto my lord the king, but my lord the King
is as an Angel of God: doe therefore what is good in thine
eyes.<note> Chap. 16.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For all of my
fathers house were but dead men before my lord the king: yet
diddest thou set thy seruant among them that did eate at thine owne
table: what right therefore haue I yet to crie any more vnto the
king?<note> Heb. men of death.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And the king
said vnto him, Why speakest thou any more of thy matters? I haue
said, Thou and Ziba diuide the land.</ab>
<ab n="30">And
Mephibosheth said vnto the king, Yea, let him take all, forasmuch
as my lorde the king is come againe in peace vnto his owne
house.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And
Barzillai the Gileadite came downe from Rogelim, and went ouer
Iordane with the king, to conduct him ouer Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="32">Now Barzillai
was a very aged man, euen fourescore yeeres olde, and he had
prouided the king of sustenance while he lay at Mahanaim: for he
was a very great man.<note> Chap.17. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the king
said vnto Barzillai, Come thou ouer with me, and I will feede thee
with me in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="34">And Barzillai
sayde vnto the king, How long haue I to liue, that I should goe vp
with the King vnto Ierusalem?<note> How many dayes are the yeeres of my life?</note></ab>
<ab n="35">I am this day
fourescore yeeres olde: and can I discerne betweene good and euill?
Can thy seruant taste what I eate, or what I drinke? can I heare
any more the voice of singing men and singing women? wherfore then
should thy seruant bee yet a burden vnto my lord the king?</ab>
<ab n="36">Thy seruant
will goe a little way ouer Iordane with the king: and why should
the king recompense it me with such a reward?</ab>
<ab n="37">Let thy
seruant, I pray thee, turne backe againe, that I may die in mine
owne citie, and be buried by the graue of my father, and of my
mother: but behold thy seruant Chimham, let him go ouer with my
lord the king, and doe to him what shall seeme good vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the king
answered, Chimham shal goe ouer with me, and I will doe to him that
which shall seeme good vnto thee: and whatsoeuer thou shalt require
of me, that will I doe for thee.<note> Heb. chuse.</note></ab>

<fw>Sheba rebelleth.</fw>
<ab n="39">And all the
people went ouer Iordane: and when the king was come ouer, the king
kissed Barzillai, and blessed him, and he returned vnto his owne
place.</ab>
<ab n="40">Then the King
went on to Gilgal, and Chimham went on with him: and all the people
of Iudah conducted the king, and also halfe the people of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
behold, all the men of Israel came to the king, and said vnto the
king, Why haue our brethren the men of Iudah stollen thee away, and
haue brought the King and his houshold, and all Dauids men with
him, ouer Iordane?</ab>
<ab n="42">And all the men
of Iudah answered the men of Israel, Because the king is neere of
kinne to vs: wherefore then be ye angrie for this matter? Haue we
eaten at all of the kings cost? or hath he giuen vs any
gift?</ab>
<ab n="43">And the men of
Israel answered the men of Iudah, and said, Wee haue ten parts in
the king, and we haue also more right in Dauid then yee: why then
did yee despise vs, that our aduice should not be first had in
bringing backe our king? And the wordes of the men of Iudah were
fiercer then the words of the men of Israel.<note> Hebr. set vs at light.</note></ab>



</div>