<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Dauids messengers sent to comfort
Hanun the sonne of Nahash, are villenously intreated. 6 The
Ammonites, strengthened by the Syrians, are ouercome by Ioab and
Abishai. 15 Shobach making a new supply of the Syrians at Helam, is
slaine by Dauid.</head>


<fw>Hanuns villenie is reuenged.</fw>
<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, after this, that the king of the children of Ammon died, and
Hanun his sonne reigned in his stead.<note> 1. Chron. 19.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then said Dauid,
I will shewe kindnes vnto Hanun the sonne of Nahash, as his father
shewed kindnes vnto me. And Dauid sent to comfort him by the hand
of his seruants, for his father: and Dauids seruants came into the
land of the children of Ammon.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the princes
of the children of Ammon saide vnto Hanun their lord, Thinkest thou
that Dauid doeth honour thy father, that he hath sent comforters
vnto thee? Hath not Dauid rather sent his seruants vnto thee, to
search the citie, and to spie it out, and to ouerthrow
it?<note> Hebr. in thine eyes doth Dauid?</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Wherefore Hanun
tooke Dauids seruants, and shaued off the one halfe of their
beards, and cut off their garments in the middle, euen to their
buttocks, and sent them away.</ab>
<ab n="5">When they told
it vnto Dauid, he sent to meet them, because the men were greatly
ashamed: and the King saide, Tarie at Iericho vntill your beards be
growen, and then returne.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And when
the children of Ammon saw that they stanke before Dauid, the
children of Ammon sent, and hired the Syrians of Beth-Rehob, and
the Syrians of Zoba, twentie thousand footmen, and of king Maacah,
a thousand men, and of Ishtob twelue thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when Dauid
heard of it, he sent Ioab, and all the hoste of the mightie
men.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the children
of Ammon came out, and put the battell in aray at the entring in of
the gate: and the Syrians of Zoba and of Rehob, and Ishtob, and
Maacah, were by themselues in the field.</ab>
<ab n="9">When Ioab saw
that the front of the battell was against him, before and behind,
he chose of all the choise men of Israel, and put them in aray
against the Syrians.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the rest of
the people he deliuered into the hand of Abishai his brother, that
he might put them in aray against the children of Ammon.</ab>

<fw>Hanuns villenie is reuenged.</fw>
<ab n="11">And he said, If
the Syrians bee too strong for me, then thou shalt helpe me: but if
the children of Ammon bee too strong for thee, then I will come and
helpe thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Be of good
courage, and let vs play the men, for our people, and for the
cities of our God: and the Lord doe that which seemeth him
good.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Ioab drew
nigh, and the people that were with him, vnto the battell against
the Syrians: and they fled before him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when the
children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fledde, then fled they
also before Abishai, and entred into the citie: so Ioab returned
from the children of Ammon, and came to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And when
the Syrians sawe that they were smitten before Israel, they
gathered themselues together.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Hadarezer
sent, and brought out the Syrians that were beyond the riuer, and
they came to Helam, and Shobach the captaine of the hoste of
Hadarezer went before them.</ab>
<ab n="17">And when it was
told Dauid, he gathered all Israel together, and passed ouer
Iordane, and came to Helam: and the Syrians set themselues in aray
against Dauid, and fought with him.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Syrians
fled before Israel, and Dauid slew the men of seuen hundred charets
of the Syrians, and fourtie thousand horsemen, and smote Shobach
the captaine of their hoste, who died there.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when all
the kings that were seruants to Hadarezer sawe, that they were
smitten before Israel, they made peace with Israel, and serued
them: so the Syrians feared to helpe the children of Ammon any
more.</ab>



</div>