<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Ioab, suborning a widow of Tekoah,
by a parable to incline the Kings heart to fetch home Absalom,
bringeth him to Hierusalem. 25 Absaloms beautie, haire, and
children. 28 After two yeres, Absalom by Ioab is brought into the
Kings presence.</head>

<ab n="1">Now Ioab the
sonne of Zeruiah, perceiued that the kings heart was toward
Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Ioab sent to
Tekoah, and fetcht thence a wise woman, and said vnto her, I pray
thee, faine thy selfe to be a mourner, and put on now mourning
apparel, and anoint not thy selfe with oile, but be as a woman that
had a long time mourned for the dead:</ab>
<ab n="3">And come to the
king, and speake on this maner vnto him: so Ioab put the words in
her mouth.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And when
the woman of Tekoah spake to the king, shee fell on her face to the
ground, and did obeysance, and said, Helpe, O king.<note> Hebr. saue.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the king
said vnto her, What aileth thee? And she answered, I am indeed a
widow woman, and mine husband is dead.</ab>
<ab n="6">And thy handmayd
had two sonnes, and they two stroue together in the field, and
there was none to part them, but the one smote the other, and slew
him.<note> Hebr. no deliuerer betweene them.</note></ab>

<fw>The widow of Tekoahs parable.</fw>
<ab n="7">And behold, the
whole family is risen against thine handmayd, and they said,
Deliuer him that smote his brother, that we may kill him, for the
life of his brother whom he slew, and we will destroy the heire
also: and so they shall quench my cole which is left, and shall not
leaue to my husband neither name nor remainder vpon the
earth.<note> Hebr. vpon the face of the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the king
saide vnto the woman, Goe to thine house, and I will giue charge
concerning thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the woman of
Tekoah said vnto the king, My lord, O king, the iniquitie bee on
mee, and on my fathers house: and the king and his throne bee
guiltlesse.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the king
said, Whosoeuer saith ought vnto thee, bring him to mee, and he
shall not touch thee any more.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then said she,
I pray thee, let the king remember the Lord thy God, that thou
wouldest not suffer the reuengers of blood to destroy any more,
lest they destroy my sonne. And he said, As the Lord liueth, there
shall not one haire of thy sonne fall to the earth.<note> Hebr. that the reuenger of blood doe not multiply to destroy.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then the woman
said, Let thine handmayd, I pray thee, speake one word vnto my lord
the king. And hee said, Say on.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the woman
said, Wherefore then hast thou thought such a thing against the
people of God? For the king doeth speake this thing as one which is
faulty, in that the king doeth not fetch home againe his
banished.</ab>
<ab n="14">For we must
needs die, and are as water spilt on the ground, which cannot bee
gathered vp againe: neither doeth God respect any person, yet doeth
he deuise meanes, that his banished bee not expelled from
him.<note> Or, because God hath not taken away his life, he hath also deuised meanes, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Now therefore
that I am come to speake of this thing vnto my lord the king, it is
because the people haue made me afraid: and thy handmayd said, I
will now speake vnto the king; it may bee that the king will
performe the request of his handmayd.</ab>
<ab n="16">For the king
wil heare, to deliuer his handmayd out of the hand of the man that
would destroy mee, and my sonne together out of the inheritance of
God:</ab>
<ab n="17">Then thine
handmaid said, The word of my lord the king shall now be
comfortable: for as an Angel of God, so is my lord the king to
discerne good and bad: therfore the Lord thy God will be with
thee.<note> Hebr. for rest. , Hebr. to heare.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Then the king
answered and said vnto the woman, Hide not from me, I pray thee,
the thing that I shall aske thee. And the woman said, Let my lord
the king now speake.</ab>

<fw>Absaloms beautie.</fw>
<ab n="19">And the king
said, Is not the hand of Ioab with thee in all this? And the woman
answered and said, As thy soule liueth, my lord the king, none can
turne to the right hand or to the left from ought that my lord the
king hath spoken: for thy seruant Ioab, hee bade me, and he put all
these wordes in the mouth of thine handmaid:</ab>
<ab n="20">To fetch about
this forme of speech hath thy seruant Ioab done this thing: and my
lord is wise, according to the wisedome of an Angel of God, to know
all things that are in the earth.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And the
king said vnto Ioab, Behold now, I haue done this thing: goe
therefore, bring the yong man Absalom againe.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Ioab fell
to the ground on his face, &amp; bowed himselfe, and thanked the
king: and Ioab said, To day thy seruant knoweth that I haue found
grace in thy sight, my lord O king, in that the king hath fulfilled
the request of his seruant.<note> Heb. blessed. , Or, thy.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">So Ioab arose,
and went to Geshur, &amp; brought Absalom to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the king
said, Let him turne to his owne house, &amp; let him not see my
face. So Absalom returned to his owne house, and sawe not the kings
face.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ But in
all Israel there was none to be so much praised as Absalom, for his
beautie: from the sole of his foot euen to the crowne of his head,
there was no blemish in him.<note> Heb. and as Absalom there was not a beautifull man in all Israel, to praise greatly.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And when he
polled his head, (for it was at euery yeres end that he polled it:
because the haire was heauy on him, therefore he polled it) hee
weighed the haire of his head at two hundred shekels after the
kings weight.</ab>
<ab n="27">And vnto
Absalom there were borne three sonnes, and one daughter, whose name
was Tamar: shee was a woman of a faire countenance.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ So
Absalom dwelt two full yeeres in Ierusalem, and saw not the kings
face.</ab>
<ab n="29">Therefore
Absalom sent for Ioab, to haue sent him to the king, but hee would
not come to him: and when hee sent againe the second time, hee
would not come.</ab>
<ab n="30">Therefore hee
said vnto his seruants, See, Ioabs field is neere mine, and he hath
barley there: goe, and set it on fire: and Absaloms seruants set
the field on fire.<note> Heb. neere my place.</note></ab>

<fw>His flatterie.</fw>
<ab n="31">Then Ioab
arose, and came to Absalom vnto his house, and said vnto him,
Wherefore haue thy seruants set my field on fire?</ab>
<ab n="32">And Absalom
answered Ioab, Behold, I sent vnto thee, saying, come hither, that
I may send thee to the king to say, Wherefore am I come from
Geshur? It had bene good for mee to haue bene there still: now
therefore let me see the kings face: and if there bee any iniquitie
in me, let him kill me.</ab>
<ab n="33">So Ioab came to
the King, and told him: and when hee had called for Absalom, he
came to the king, and bowed himselfe on his face to the ground
before the king, and the King kissed Absalom.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>