<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 During the warre Dauid still
waxeth stronger. 2 Sixe sonnes were borne to him in Hebron. 6 Abner
displeased with Ishbosheth, 12 reuolteth to Dauid. 13 Dauid
requireth a condition to bring him his wife Michal. 17 Abner hauing
communed with the Israelites, is feasted by Dauid, and dismissed.
22 Ioab returning from battell, is displeased with the king, and
killeth Abner. 28 Dauid curseth Ioab, 31 and mourneth for
Abner.</head>


<fw>Abner reuolteth to Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now there was
long war betweene the house of Saul, and the house of Dauid: but
Dauid waxed stronger and stronger, and the house of Saul waxed
weaker and weaker.</ab>
<ab n="2">¶ And vnto
Dauid were sonnes borne in Hebron: and his first borne was Ammon,
of Ahinoam the Iezreelitesse.</ab>
<ab n="3">And his second,
Chileab, of Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite: and the third,
Absalom the sonne of Maacah, the daughter of Talmai king of
Geshur;</ab>
<ab n="4">And the fourth,
Adoniiah the son of Haggith: and the fifth, Shephatiah the sonne of
Abital;</ab>
<ab n="5">And the sixth,
Ithream by Eglah Dauids wife: these were borne to Dauid in
Hebron.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And it
came to passe while there was warre between the house of Saul and
the house of Dauid, that Abner made himselfe strong for the house
of Saul.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Saul had a
concubine, whose name was Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah: and
Ishbosheth saide to Abner, Wherefore hast thou gone in vnto my
fathers concubine?<note> Chap. 21. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then was Abner
very wroth for the words of Ishbosheth, and said, Am I a dogs head,
which against Iudah doe shew kindnesse this day vnto the house of
Saul thy father, to his brethren, and to his friends, and haue not
deliuered thee into the hand of Dauid, that thou chargest mee to
day with a fault concerning this woman?</ab>
<ab n="9">So doe God to
Abner, and more also, except, as the Lord hath sworne to Dauid,
euen so I doe to him:</ab>
<ab n="10">To translate the
kingdome from the house of Saul, and to set vp the throne of Dauid
ouer Israel, and ouer Iudah, from Dan euen to Beer-sheba.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he could not
answere Abner a word againe, because he feared him.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Abner
sent messengers to Dauid on his behalfe, saying, Whose is the land?
saying also, Make thy league with me, and behold, my hand shall bee
with thee, to bring about all Israel vnto thee.</ab>

<fw>Abner reuolteth to Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ And he
said, Well, I will make a league with thee: but one thing I require
of thee, that is, Thou shalt not see my face, except thou first
bring Michal Sauls daughter, when thou commest to see my
face.<note> Hebr. saying.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Dauid sent
messengers to Ishbosheth Sauls sonne, saying, Deliuer mee my wife
Michal, which I espoused to mee for an hundred foreskinnes of the
Philistines.<note> 1.Sam. 18.25, 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Ishbosheth
sent, and tooke her from her husband, euen from Phaltiel the sonne
of Laish.<note> 1 Sam.25. 44. Phalti.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And her husband
went with her along weeping behinde her to Bahurim: then said Abner
vnto him, Goe, returne. And he returned.<note> Hebr. going, and weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And Abner
had communication with the Elders of Israel, saying, Yee sought for
Dauid in times past, to be king ouer you.<note> Hebr. both yesterday, and the third day.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Now then doe it,
for the Lord hath spoken of Dauid, saying; By the hand of my
seruant Dauid I will saue my people Israel out of the hand of the
Philistines, and out of the hand of all their enemies.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Abner also
spake in the eares of Beniamin: and Abner went also to speake in
the eares of Dauid in Hebron, all that seemed good to Israel, and
that seemed good to the whole house of Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="20">So Abner came to
Dauid to Hebron, and twenty men with him: and Dauid made Abner, and
the men that were with him, a feast.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Abner said
vnto Dauid, I will arise, and goe, and will gather all Israel vnto
my lord the king, that they may make a league with thee, and that
thou mayest raigne ouer all that thine heart desireth. And Dauid
sent Abner away, and he went in peace.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
behold, the seruants of Dauid, and Ioab came from pursuing a
troupe, and brought in a great spoile with them: (but Abner was not
with Dauid in Hebron, for he had sent him away, and he was gone in
peace.)</ab>
<ab n="23">When Ioab and
all the host that was with him, were come, they told Ioab, saying,
Abner the sonne of Ner came to the king, and he hath sent him away,
and he is gone in peace.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then Ioab came
to the king, and said, What hast thou done? behold, Abner came vnto
thee, why is it that thou hast sent him away, &amp; he is quite
gone?</ab>

<fw>Ioab slayeth Abner.</fw>
<ab n="25">Thou knowest
Abner the sonne of Ner, that he came to deceiue thee, and to know
thy going out, and thy comming in, &amp; to know all that thou
doest.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when Ioab
was come out from Dauid, hee sent messengers after Abner, which
brought him againe from the well of Siriah; but Dauid knew it
not.</ab>
<ab n="27">And when Abner
was returned to Hebron, Ioab tooke him aside in the gate to speake
with him quietly: and smote him there vnder the fift ribbe, that he
died, for the blood of Asahel his brother.<note> 1. King. 2.5. , Or, peaceably. , Chap.2. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And
afterward when Dauid heard it, hee said, I and my kingdome are
guiltlesse before the Lord for euer, from the blood of Abner the
sonne of Ner:<note> Heb. bloods</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Let it rest on
the head of Ioab, and on all his fathers house, &amp; let there not
faile from the house of Ioab one that hath an issue, or that is a
leper, or that leaneth on a staffe, or that falleth on the sword,
or that lacketh bread.<note> Heb. be cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">So Ioab and
Abishai his brother slew Abner, because he had slaine their brother
Asahel at Gibeon in the battell.<note> Chap. 2. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And Dauid
said to Ioab, and to all the people that were with him, Rent your
clothes, and girde you with sackecloth, and mourne before Abner.
And king Dauid himselfe followed the biere.<note> Heb. bed.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And they buried
Abner in Hebron, and the king lift vp his voice, and wept at the
graue of Abner; and all the people wept.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the king
lamented ouer Abner, and said, Died Abner as a foole dieth?</ab>
<ab n="34">Thy hands were
not bound, nor thy feete put into fetters: as a man falleth before
wicked men, so fellest thou. And all the people wept againe ouer
him.<note> Heb. children of iniquitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And when all the
people came to cause Dauid to eate meate while it was yet day,
Dauid sware, saying, So doe God to mee, and more also, if I taste
bread or ought else, till the Sunne be downe.</ab>
<ab n="36">And all the
people tooke notice of it, and it pleased them: as whatsoeuer the
King did, pleased all the people.<note> Heb. was good in their eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">For all the
people, and all Israel vnderstood that day, that it was not of the
King to slay Abner the sonne of Ner.</ab>

<fw>Ishbosheth slaine.</fw>
<ab n="38">And the King
said vnto his seruants, Knowe yee not that there is a prince and a
great man fallen this day in Israel?</ab>
<ab n="39">And I am this
day weake, though anointed King, and these men the sonnes of
Zeruiah be too hard for me: the Lord shall reward the doer of
euill, according to his wickednesse.<note> Heb. tender.</note></ab>



</div>