<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Samuel_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Samuel-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid subdueth the Philistines and
the Moabites. 3 He smiteth Hadadezer, and the Syrians. 9 Toi
sendeth Ioram with Presents to blesse him. 11 The Presents and the
spoile Dauid dedicateth to God. 14 He putteth garisons in Edom. 16
Dauids officers.</head>

<ab n="1">And after this it
came to passe, that Dauid smote the Philistines, and subdued them:
and Dauid tooke Metheg-Ammah out of the hand of the
Philistines.<note> 1. Chron. 18.1. &amp;c. psal. 60.2. , Or, the bridle of Ammah.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he smote
Moab, and measured them with a line, casting them downe to the
ground: euen with two lines measured he, to put to death, and with
one full line to keepe aliue: and so the Moabites became Dauids
seruants, and brought gifts.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Dauid
smote also Hadadezer the sonne of Rehob, king of Zobah, as he went
to recouer his border at the riuer Euphrates.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Dauid tooke
from him a thousand charets, and seuen hundred horsemen, and
twentie thousand footemen: and Dauid houghed all the charet horses,
but reserued of them for an hundred charets.<note> Or, of his. , As 1. Chr. 18.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And when the
Syrians of Damascus came to succour Hadadezer king of Zobah, Dauid
slew of the Syrians two and twentie thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Dauid put
garisons in Syria of Damascus: And the Syrians became seruants to
Dauid, and brought gifts: and the Lord preserued Dauid
whithersoeuer he went.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Dauid tooke
the shields of gold that were on the seruants of Hadadezer, and
brought them to Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="8">And from Betah
and from Berothai, cities of Hadadezer, King Dauid tooke exceeding
much brasse.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ When Toi
king of Hamath heard that Dauid had smitten all the hoste of
Hadadezer,</ab>

<fw>Dauids kindnesse to
Mephibosheth.</fw>
<ab n="10">Then Toi sent
Ioram his sonne vnto king Dauid to salute him, and to blesse him,
because hee had fought against Hadadezer, and smitten him: (for
Hadadezer had warres with Toi) and Ioram brought with him vessels
of siluer, and vessels of gold, and vessels of brasse;<note> Hebr. aske him of peace. , Hebr. was a man of warres with. , Hebr. in his hand were.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Which also king
Dauid did dedicate vnto the Lord, with the siluer and gold that he
had dedicate of all nations which he subdued:</ab>
<ab n="12">Of Syria, and of
Moab, and of the children of Ammon, and of the Philistines, &amp;
of Amalek, and of the spoile of Hadadezer sonne of Rehob king of
Zobah.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Dauid gate
him a name when he returned from smiting of the Syrians in the
valley of salt, being eighteene thousand men.<note> Hebr. his smiting.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And he
put garrisons in Edom; thorowout all Edom put he garrisons, and all
they of Edom became Dauids seruants: and the Lord preserued Dauid
whithersoeuer he went.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Dauid
reigned ouer all Israel, and Dauid executed iudgement and iustice
vnto all his people.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Ioab the
sonne of Zeruiah was ouer the host, and Iehoshaphat the sonne of
Ahilud was Recorder.<note> Or, remembrancer, or writer of Chronicles.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Zadok the
sonne of Ahitub, and Ahimelech the sonne of Abiathar, were the
Priests, and Seraiah was the scribe.<note> Or, secretary.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Benaiah the
sonne of Iehoiada was ouer both the Cherethites, and the
Pelethites, and Dauids sonnes were chiefe rulers.<note> 1. Chron. 18. 17. , Or, Princes.</note></ab>



</div>