<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Thessalonians_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Thessalonians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 S. Paul certifieth them of the
good opinion which hee had of their faith, loue, and patience: 11
And therewithall vseth diuers reasons for the comforting of them in
persecution, whereof the chiefest is taken from the righteous
iudgement of God.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul and
Siluanus, and Timotheus vnto the Church of the Thessaloniās,
in God our Father, and the Lord Iesus Christ:</ab>
<ab n="2">Grace vnto
you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lorde Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="3">Wee are
bound to thanke God alwayes for you, brethren, as it is meete,
because that your faith groweth exceedingly, and the charitie of
euery one of you al towards each other aboundeth:</ab>
<ab n="4">So that
wee our selues glorie in you in the Churches of God, for your
patience and faith in all your persecutions and tribulations that
yee endure.</ab>
<ab n="5">Which is a
manifest token of the righteous iudgement of God, that yee may bee
counted worthy of the kingdome of God, for which yee also
suffer;</ab>
<ab n="6">Seeing it
is a righteous thing with God to recompence tribulation to them
that trouble you:</ab>
<ab n="7">And to you
who are troubled, rest with vs, when the Lord Iesus shalbe reuealed
from heauen, with his mightie Angels,<note> Gr. the angels of his power.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">In flaming
fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not
the Gospel of our Lorde Iesus Christ,<note> Or, yeelding.</note></ab>

<fw>Christ glorified in his Saints.</fw>
<ab n="9">Who shalbe
punished with euerlasting destruction from the presence of the
Lord, and from the glory of his power:</ab>
<ab n="10">When hee
shall come to bee glorified in his Saints, and to bee admired in
all them that beleeue (because our testimony among you was
beleeued) in that day.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore
also we pray alwayes for you, that our God would count you worthy
of this calling, and fulfill all the good pleasure of his
goodnesse, and the worke of faith with power:<note> Or, vouchsafe.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">That the
Name of our Lord Iesus Christ may bee glorified in you, and ye in
him, according to the grace of our God, and the Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>



</div>