<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Thessalonians_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Thessalonians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Thessalonians-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Hee willeth them to continue
stedfast in the trueth receiued, 3 Sheweth that there shall bee a
departure from the faith, 9 and a discouery of Antichrist, before
the day of the Lord come. 15 And thereupon repeateth his former
exhortation, &amp; prayeth for them.</head>

<ab n="1">Now wee
beseech you, brethren, by the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ, and
by our gathering together vnto him,</ab>
<ab n="2">That yee
bee not soone shaken in minde, or bee troubled, neither by spirit,
nor by word, nor by letter, as from vs, as that the day of Christ
is at hand,</ab>
<ab n="3">Let no man
deceiue you by any meanes, for that day shall not come, except
there come a falling away first, and that man of sinne bee
reuealed, the sonne of perdition,</ab>
<ab n="4">Who
opposeth and exalteth himselfe aboue all that is called God, or
that is worshipped: so that he as God, sitteth in the Temple of
God, shewing himselfe that he is God.</ab>
<ab n="5">Remember
yee not, that when I was yet with you, I tolde you these
things?</ab>

<fw>Strong delusion.</fw>
<ab n="6">And now
yee know what withholdeth, that hee might bee reuealed in his
time.<note> Or, holdeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For the
mysterie of iniquitie doth alreadie worke: onely he who now
letteth, will let, vntill he be taken out of the way.</ab>
<ab n="8">And then
shall that wicked bee reuealed, whome the Lord shall consume with
the spirit of his mouth, and shall destroy with the brightnesse of
his comming:</ab>
<ab n="9">Euen him
whose comming is after the working of Satan, with all power and
signes, and lying wonders,</ab>
<ab n="10">And with
all deceiueablenesse of vnrighteousnesse, in them that perish:
because they receiued not the loue of the trueth, that they might
be saued.</ab>
<ab n="11">And for
this cause God shall send them strong delusion, that they should
beleeue a lye:</ab>
<ab n="12">That they
all might bee damned who beleeued not the trueth, but had pleasure
in vnrighteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="13">But we
are bound to giue thanks alway to God for you, brethren, beloued of
the Lord, because God hath from the beginning chosen you to
saluation, through sanctification of the spirit, and beleefe of the
trueth,</ab>
<ab n="14">Whereunto
he called you by our Gospel, to the obteining of the glorie of the
Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="15">Therefore,
brethren, stand fast, and hold the traditions which yee haue beene
taught, whether by word or our Epistle.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now our
Lorde Iesus Christ himselfe, and God euen our Father, which hath
loued vs, and hath giuen vs euerlasting consolation, and good hope
through grace,</ab>
<ab n="17">Comfort
your hearts, and stablish you in euery good word and worke.</ab>



</div>