<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Thessalonians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Thessalonians-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>He craueth their prayers for
himselfe, 3 testifieth what confidence hee hath in them, 5 maketh
request to God in their behalfe, 6 giueth them diuers precepts,
especially to shun idlenesse, and ill company, 16 And last of all
concludeth with prayer and salutation.</head>

<ab n="1">Finally,
brethren, pray for vs, that the word of the Lord may haue free
course, and be glorified, euen as it is with you:<note> Gr. may runne.</note></ab>

<fw>Of the idle.</fw>
<ab n="2">And that
we may bee deliuered from vnreasonable and wicked men: for all men
haue not faith.<note> Gr. absurd.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But the
Lord is faithfull, who shall stablish you, and keepe you from
euill.</ab>
<ab n="4">And wee
haue confidence in the Lord touching you, that yee both doe, and
will doe the things which we command you.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the
Lord direct your hearts into the loue of God, and into the patient
waiting for Christ.<note> Or, the patience of Christ.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Now we
command you, brethren, in the Name of our Lord Iesus Christ, that
ye withdraw your selues from euery brother that walketh disorderly,
and not after the tradition which hee receiued of vs.</ab>
<ab n="7">For your
selues know how yee ought to follow vs: for wee behaued not our
selues disorderly among you,</ab>
<ab n="8">Neither
did wee eate any mans bread for nought: but wrought with labour and
trauaile night and day, that wee might not bee chargeable to any of
you.</ab>
<ab n="9">Not
because we haue not power, but to make our selues an ensample vnto
you to follow vs.</ab>
<ab n="10">For euen
when wee were with you, this wee commanded you, that if any would
not worke, neither should he eate.</ab>
<ab n="11">For we
heare that there are some which walke among you disorderly, working
not at all, but are busi-bodies.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now them
that are such, we command, and exhort by our Lord Iesus Christ,
that with quietnesse they worke, and eat their owne bread.</ab>
<ab n="13">But ye,
brethren, be not wearie in well doing.<note> Or, faint not.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And if
any man obey not our word, by this Epistle note that man, and haue
no company with him, that he may be ashamed,<note> Or, signifie that man by an Epistle.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Yet count
him not as an enemie, but admonish him as a brother.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now the
Lord of peace himselfe, giue you peace alwayes, by all meanes. The
Lord be with you all.</ab>
<ab n="17">The
salutation of Paul, with mine owne hand, which is the token in
euery Epistle: so I write.</ab>
<ab n="18">The grace
of our Lord Iesus Christ be with you all, Amen. The second Epistle
to the Thessalonians was written from Athens.</ab>



</div>