<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Timothy_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/1-Timothy-Chapter-6-6-2-Timothy.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Timothy-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>Pauls loue to Timothie, and the
vnfained faith which was in Timothie himselfe, his mother, and
grandmother. 6 Hee is exhorted to stirre vp the gift of God which
was in him, 8 to be stedfast and patient in persecution, 13 and to
persist in the fourme and trueth of that doctrine which hee had
learned of him. 15 Phygellus and Hermogenes, and such like are
noted, and Onesiphorus is highly commended.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul an Apostle
of Iesus Christ by the will of God, according to the promise of
life, which is in Christ Iesus,</ab>
<ab n="2">To Timothie my
dearely beloued sonne: grace, mercie, and peace from God the
Father, and Christ Iesus our Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">I thanke God,
whom I serue from my forefathers with pure conscience, that without
ceasing I haue remembrance of thee in my prayers night and
day,</ab>
<ab n="4">Greatly desiring
to see thee, being mindfull of thy teares, that I may bee filled
with ioy,</ab>
<ab n="5">When I call to
remembrance the vnfained faith that is in thee, which dwelt first
in thy grandmother Lois, and thy mother Eunice: and I am perswaded
that in thee also.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore I put
thee in remembrance, that thou stirre vp the gift of God which is
in thee, by the putting on of my hands.</ab>

<fw>Holy calling.</fw>
<ab n="7">For God hath not
giuen vs the spirit of feare, but of power, of loue, and of a sound
minde.</ab>
<ab n="8">Bee not thou
therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his
prisoner, but bee thou partaker of the afflictions of the Gospel
according to the power of God,</ab>
<ab n="9">Who hath saued
vs, and called vs with an holy calling, not according to our
workes, but according to his owne purpose and grace, which was
giuen vs in Christ Iesus, before the world began,</ab>
<ab n="10">But is now made
manifest by the appearing of our Sauiour Iesus Christ, who hath
abolished death, and hath brought life and immortalitie to light,
through the Gospel:</ab>
<ab n="11">Whereunto I am
appointed a Preacher, and an Apostle, and a teacher of the
Gentiles.</ab>
<ab n="12">For the which
cause I also suffer these things; neuerthelesse, I am not ashamed:
for I know whom I haue beleeued, and I am perswaded that he is able
to keepe that which I haue committed vnto him against that
day.<note> Or, trusted.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Holde fast the
fourme of sound words, which thou hast heard of mee, in faith and
loue, which is in Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="14">That good thing
which was committed vnto thee, keepe, by the holy Ghost which
dwelleth in vs.</ab>
<ab n="15">This thou
knowest, that all they which are in Asia be turned away from me, of
whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes.</ab>

<fw>Strong in grace.</fw>
<ab n="16">The Lord giue
mercie vnto the house of Onesiphorus, for hee oft refreshed mee,
and was not ashamed of my chaine.</ab>
<ab n="17">But when he was
in Rome, hee sought mee out very diligently, and found me.</ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord grant
vnto him, that he may finde mercie of the Lord in that day: And in
how many things hee ministred vnto mee at Ephesus, thou knowest
very well.</ab>



</div>