<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Timothy_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The birth, trade, and religion of
Cain and Abel. 8 The murder of Abel. 9 The curse of Cain. 17 Enoch
the first citie. 19 Lamech and his two wiues. 25 The birth of Seth,
26 and Enos.</head>

<ab n="1">And Adam knew Eue
his wife, and shee conceiued, and bare Cain, and said, I haue
gotten a man from the LORD.</ab>

<fw>Abel murthered.</fw>
<ab n="2">And she againe
bare his brother Abel, and Abel was a keeper of sheep, but Cain was
a tiller of the ground.<note> Heb. Hebel. , Heb. a feeder.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And in processe of
time it came to passe, that Cain brought of the fruite of the
ground, an offering vnto the LORD.<note> Heb. at the end of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Abel, he also
brought of the firstlings of his flocke, and of the fat thereof:
and the LORD had respect vnto Abel, and to his
offering.<note> Heb. sheep, or goates. , Heb.11.4</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But vnto Cain, and
to his offring he had not respect: and Cain was very wroth, and his
countenance fell.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the LORD said
vnto Cain, Why art thou wroth? And why is thy countenance
fallen?</ab>
<ab n="7">If thou doe well,
shalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doest not well, sinne lieth
at the doore: And vnto thee shall be his desire, and thou shalt
rule ouer him.<note> Or, haue the excellencie? , Or, subiect vnto thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Cain talked
with Abel his brother: and it came to passe when they were in the
field, that Cain rose vp against Abel his brother, and slew
him.<note> Wis.10.3 matth.23. 35. 1. iohn 3. 12. iude 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
LORD said vnto Cain, Where is Abel thy brother? And hee said, I
know not: Am I my brothers keeper?</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said, What
hast thou done? the voyce of thy brothers blood cryeth vnto me,
from the ground.<note> Heb. bloods</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And now art thou
cursed from the earth, which hath opened her mouth to receiue thy
brothers blood from thy hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">When thou tillest
the ground, it shall not henceforth yeeld vnto thee her strength: A
fugitiue and a vagabond shalt thou be in the earth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Cain said
vnto the LORD, My punishment is greater, then I can
beare.<note> Or, my iniquitie is greater, then that it may be forgiuen.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, thou hast
driuen me out this day from the face of the earth, and from thy
face shall I be hid, and I shall be a fugitiue, and a vagabond in
the earth: and it shall come to passe, that euery one that findeth
me, shall slay me.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the LORD said
vnto him, Therefore whosoeuer slayeth Cain, vengeance shalbe taken
on him seuen fold. And the LORD set a marke vpon Cain, lest any
finding him, should kill him.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And Cain
went out from the presence of the LORD, and dwelt in the land of
Nod, on the East of Eden.</ab>

<fw>The genealogie of the Patriarchs,
&amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="17">And Cain knew his
wife, and she conceiued and bare Enoch, and hee builded a City, and
called the name of the City, after the name of his sonne,
Enoch.<note> Heb. Chanoch.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And vnto Enoch
was borne Irad: and Irad begate Mehuiael, and Mehuiael begate
Methusael, and Methusael begate Lamech.<note> Hebr. Lemech.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And Lamech
tooke vnto him two wiues: the name of the one was Adah, and the
name of the other Zillah.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Adah bare
Iabal: he was the father of such as dwell in tents, and of such as
haue cattell.</ab>
<ab n="21">And his brothers
name was Iubal: hee was the father of all such as handle the harpe
and organ.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Zillah, she
also bare Tubal-Cain, an instructer of euery artificer in brasse
and iron: and the sister of Tubal-Cain was Naamah.<note> Heb. whetter.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Lamech sayd
vnto his wiues, Adah and Zillah, Heare my voyce, yee wiues of
Lamech, hearken vnto my speech: for I haue slaine a man to my
wounding, and a yong man to my hurt.<note> Or, I would slay a man in my wound, &amp;c. , Or, in my hurt.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">If Cain shall bee
auenged seuen fold, truely Lamech seuenty and seuen folde.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And Adam
knew his wife againe, and she bare a sonne, &amp; called his name
Seth: For God, said she, hath appointed mee another seed in stead
of Abel, whom Cain slew.<note> Hebr. Sheth.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And to Seth, to
him also there was borne a sonne, and he called his name Enos: then
began men to call vpon the Name of the LORD.<note> Hebr. Enosh. , Or, to call themselues by the Name of the Lord.</note></ab>




</div>