<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Timothy_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Timothy-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Timothy-Chapter-4-4-Titus.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Hee exhorteth him to doe his duety
with all care and diligence, 6 certifieth him of the neerenesse of
his death, 9 willeth him to come speedily vnto him, and to bring
Marcus with him, and certaine other things which he wrote for, 14
warneth him to beware of Alexander the smith, 16 informeth him what
had befallen him at his first answering, 19 and soone after hee
concludeth.</head>

<ab n="1">I charge thee
therefore before God, and the Lord Iesus Christ, who shall iudge
the quicke and the dead at his appearing, and his kingdome:</ab>
<ab n="2">Preach the word,
be instant in season, out of season, reprooue, rebuke, exhort with
all long suffering &amp; doctrine.</ab>
<ab n="3">For the time wil
come when they will not endure sound doctrine, but after their owne
lusts shall they heape to themselues teachers, hauing itching
eares:</ab>
<ab n="4">And they shall
turne away their eares from the trueth, and shall be turned vnto
fables.</ab>
<ab n="5">But watch thou
in all things, indure afflictions, doe the worke of an Euangelist,
make full proofe of thy ministery.<note> Or, fulfill.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For I am now
readie to bee offered, and the time of my departure is at
hand.</ab>
<ab n="7">I haue fought a
good fight, I haue finished my course, I haue kept the
faith.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hencefoorth
there is layde vp for me a crowne of righteousnesse, which the Lord
the righteous iudge shall giue me at that day: and not to me only,
but vnto them also that loue his appearing.</ab>
<ab n="9">Doe thy
diligence to come shortly vnto me:</ab>
<ab n="10">For Demas hath
forsaken me, hauing loued this present world, and is departed vnto
Thessalonica: Crescens to Galatia, Titus vnto Dalmatia.</ab>
<ab n="11">Onely Luke is
with me. Take Marke and bring him with thee: for he is profitable
to me for the ministerie.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Tychicus
haue I sent to Ephesus.</ab>

<fw>Pauls charitie.</fw>
<ab n="13">The cloke that
I left at Troas with Carpus, when thou commest, bring with thee,
but especially the parchments.</ab>
<ab n="14">Alexander the
Coppersmith did mee much euill, the Lord reward him according to
his works.</ab>
<ab n="15">Of whom bee
thou ware also, for he hath greatly withstood our
words.<note> Or, our preachings.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">At my first
answere no man stood with mee, but all men forsooke mee: I pray God
that it may not bee laid to their charge.</ab>
<ab n="17">Notwithstanding
the Lord stood with me, and strengthened me, that by me the
preaching might be fully knowen, and that all the Gentiles might
heare: and I was deliuered out of the mouth of the Lyon.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Lord
shall deliuer mee from euery euill worke, and will preserue me vnto
his heauenly kingdome; to whom bee glory for euer, and euer.
Amen.</ab>
<ab n="19">Salute Prisca
and Aquila, and the houshold of Onesiphorus.</ab>
<ab n="20">Erastus abode
at Corinth: but Trophimus haue I left at Miletum sicke.</ab>
<ab n="21">Doe thy
diligence to come before winter. Eubulus greeteth thee, and Pudens,
and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren.</ab>
<ab n="22">The Lord Iesus
Christ bee with thy spirit. Grace be with you. Amen. [The second
Epistle vnto Timotheus, ordeined the first Bishop of the Church of
the Ephesians, was written from Rome, when Paul was brought before
Nero the second time.]</ab>



</div>