<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Timothy_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Timothy-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Hee aduertiseth him of the times
to come, 6 describeth the enemies of the trueth, 10 propoundeth
vnto him his owne example, 16 and commendeth the holy
Scriptures.</head>


<fw>Perillous times.</fw>
<ab n="1">This know also,
that in the last dayes perillous times shall come.</ab>
<ab n="2">For men shall
bee louers of their owne selues, couetous, boasters, proude,
blasphemers, disobedient to parents, vnthankfull, vnholy,</ab>
<ab n="3">Without naturall
affection, trucebreakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce,
despisers of those that are good,<note> Or, makebates.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Traitours,
heady, high minded, louers of pleasures more then louers of
God,</ab>
<ab n="5">Hauing a forme
of godlinesse, but denying the power thereof: from such turne
away.</ab>
<ab n="6">For of this sort
are they which creep into houses, and leade captiue silly women
laden with sinnes, led away with diuers lusts,</ab>
<ab n="7">Euer learning,
and neuer able to come to the knowledge of the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now as Iannes
and Iambres withstood Moses, so do these also resist the trueth:
men of corrupt mindes, reprobate concerning the faith.<note> Or, of no iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But they shal
proceede no further: for their folly shall be manifest vnto all
men, as theirs also was.</ab>
<ab n="10">But thou hast
fully knowen my doctrine, maner of life, purpose, faith, long
suffering, charitie, patience,<note> Or, thou hast been a diligent follower of.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Persecutions,
afflictions which came vnto me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra,
what persecutions I indured: but out of them all the Lord deliuered
me.</ab>
<ab n="12">Yea, and all
that will liue godly in Christ Iesus, shall suffer
persecution.</ab>
<ab n="13">But euill men
and seducers shall waxe worse and worse, deceiuing, and being
deceiued.</ab>
<ab n="14">But continue
thou in the things which thou hast learned, and hast been assured
of, knowing of whome thou hast learned them.</ab>
<ab n="15">And that from a
childe thou hast knowen the holy Scriptures, which are able to make
thee wise vnto saluation through faith which is in Christ
Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="16">All Scripture
is giuen by inspiration of God, &amp; is profitable for doctrine,
for reproofe, for correction, for instrution in
righteousnesse,</ab>

<fw>Itching eares.</fw>
<ab n="17">That the man of
God may be perfect, throughly furnished vnto all good
workes.<note> Or, perfected.</note></ab>



</div>