<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C2-Timothy_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Timothy-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 He is exhorted againe to
constancie and perseuerance, and to doe the duetie of a faithfull
seruant of the Lord in diuiding the word aright, and staying
prophane and vaine bablings. 17 Of Hymeneus and Philetus. 19 The
foundation of the Lord is sure. 22 Hee is taught whereof to beware,
and what to follow after, and in what sort the seruant of the Lord
ought to behaue himselfe.</head>

<ab n="1">Thou therefore,
my sonne, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the things
that thou hast heard of mee among many witnesses, the same commit
thou to faithfull men, who shall be able to teach others
also.<note> Or, by.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thou therefore
indure hardnesse, as a good souldier of Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="4">No man that
warreth, intangleth himselfe with the affaires of this life, that
hee may please him who hath chosen him to be a souldier.</ab>
<ab n="5">And if a man
also striue for masteries, yet is hee not crowned except hee striue
lawfully.</ab>
<ab n="6">The husbandman
that laboureth, must bee first partaker of the fruites.<note> Or, the husbandman labouring first, must be partaker of the fruites.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Consider what I
say, and the Lord giue thee vnderstanding in all things.</ab>
<ab n="8">Remember that
Iesus Christ of the seede of Dauid, was raised from the dead,
according to my Gospel:</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherein I suffer
trouble as an euill doer, euen vnto bonds: but the word of God is
not bound.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore I
indure all things for the elects sakes, that they may also obtaine
the saluation which is in Christ Iesus, with eternall
glory.</ab>
<ab n="11">It is a
faithfull saying: for if we bee dead with him, wee shall also liue
with him.</ab>

<fw>Of sundry vessels.</fw>
<ab n="12">If we suffer,
we shall also reigne with him: if wee denie him, hee also will
denie vs.</ab>
<ab n="13">If we beleeue
not, yet he abideth faithfull, he cannot denie himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="14">Of these things
put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord, that they
striue not about words to no profite, but to the subuerting of the
hearers.</ab>
<ab n="15">Studie to shewe
thy selfe approued vnto God, a workman that needeth not to be
ashamed, rightly diuiding the word of trueth.</ab>
<ab n="16">But shun
profane and vaine bablings, for they will increase vnto more
vngodlinesse.</ab>
<ab n="17">And their word
will eate as doth a canker: of whom is Hymeneus and
Philetus.<note> Or, gangrene.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Who concerning
the trueth haue erred, saying that the resurrection is past
alreadie, and ouerthrow the faith of some.</ab>
<ab n="19">Neuerthelesse
the foundation of God standeth sure, hauing the seale, the Lord
knoweth them that are his. And, let euery one that nameth the Name
of Christ, depart from iniquitie.<note> Or, steady.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But in a great
house, there are not onely vessels of gold, and of siluer, but also
a wood, &amp; of earth: and some to honour, and some to
dishonour.</ab>
<ab n="21">If a man
therefore purge himselfe from these, he shal be a vessell vnto
honour, sanctified, and meete for the Masters vse, and prepared
vnto euery good worke.</ab>
<ab n="22">Flie also
youthfull lusts: but follow righteousnesse, faith, charitie, peace
with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart.</ab>
<ab n="23">But foolish and
vnlearned questions auoid, knowing that they doe gender
strifes.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the seruant
of the Lord must not striue: but bee gentle vnto all men, apt to
teach, patient,<note> Or, forbearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">In meekenesse
instructing those that oppose themselues, if God peraduenture will
giue them repentance to the acknowledging of the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="26">And that they
may recouer themselues out of the snare of the deuill, who are
taken captiue by him at his will.<note> Gr. awake. , Gr. taken aliue.</note></ab>



</div>