<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C3-John_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/3-John-Chapter-1-1-Jude.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>Hee commendeth Gaius for his pietie
5 and hospitalitie 7 to true preachers: 9 Complaining of the vnkind
dealing of ambitious Diotrephes on the contrary side: 11 Whose
euill example is not to bee followed: 12 And giueth speciall
testimonie to the good report of Demetrius.</head>

<ab n="1">The Elder
vnto the welbeloued Gaius, whom I loue in the trueth:<note> Or, truely.</note></ab>

<fw>Walking in trueth and loue.</fw>
<ab n="2">Beloued, I
wish aboue all things that thou mayest prosper and be in health,
euen as thy soule prospereth.<note> Or, pray.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For I
reioyced greatly when the brethren came and testified of the truth
that is in thee, euen as thou walkest in the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="4">I haue no
greater ioy, then to heare that my children walke in truth.</ab>
<ab n="5">Beloued, thou
doest faithfully whatsoeuer thou doest to the Brethren, and to
strangers:</ab>

<fw>Called in Christ.</fw>
<ab n="6">Which haue
borne witnesse of thy charitie before the Church: whome if thou
bring forward on their iourney after a godly sort, thou shalt doe
well:</ab>
<ab n="7">Because that
for his Names sake they went foorth, taking nothing of the
Gentiles.</ab>
<ab n="8">We therefore
ought to receiue such, that we might be fellow helpers to the
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="9">I wrote vnto
the Church, but Diotrephes, who loueth to haue the preeminence
among them, receiueth vs not.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wherefore if I
come, I will remember his deeds which he doeth, prating against vs
with malicious words: and not content therewith, neither doth hee
himselfe receiue the brethren, and forbiddeth them that would, and
casteth them out of the Church.</ab>
<ab n="11">Beloued, follow
not that which is euill, but that which is good. He that doth good,
is of God: but hee that doth euill, hath not seene God.</ab>
<ab n="12">Demetrius hath
good report of all men, and of the trueth it selfe: yea, and we
also beare record, and ye know that our record is true.</ab>
<ab n="13">I had many things
to write, but I will not with inke and pen write vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">But I trust I
shall shortly see thee, and wee shall speake face to face. Peace
bee to thee. Our friends salute thee. Greet the friends by
name.<note> Gr. mouth to mouth.</note></ab>



</div>