<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Lot entertaineth two Angels. 4 The
vicious Sodomites are striken with blindnesse. 12 Lot is sent for
safety into the mountaines. 18 Hee obtaineth leaue to goe into
Zoar. 24 Sodome and Gomorrah are destroyed. 26 Lots wife is a
pillar of salt. 30 Lot dwelleth in a caue. 31 The incestuous
originall of Moab and Ammon.</head>

<ab n="1">And there came
two Angels to Sodome at euen, and Lot sate in the gate of Sodome:
and Lot seeing them, rose vp to meet them, and he bowed himselfe
with his face toward the ground.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said,
Beholde now my Lords, turne in, I pray you, into your seruants
house, and tarie all night, and wash your feete, and ye shall rise
vp early and goe on your wayes. And they said, Nay: but we wil
abide in the street all night.<note> Chap. 18. 4.</note></ab>

<fw>Lots house beset.</fw>
<ab n="3">And he pressed
vpon them greatly, and they turned in vnto him, and entred into his
house: and he made them a feast, and did bake vnleauened bread, and
they did eate.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ But before
they lay downe, the men of the citie, euen the men of Sodom,
compassed the house round, both old and yong, all the people from
euery quarter.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they called
vnto Lot, and said vnto him, Where are the men which came in to
thee this night? bring them out vnto vs, that we may know
them.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Lot went out
at the doore vnto them, &amp; shut the doore after him,</ab>
<ab n="7">And said, I pray
you, brethren, doe not so wickedly.</ab>
<ab n="8">Behold now, I
haue two daughters, which haue not knowen man; let mee, I pray you,
bring them out vnto you, and doe ye to them, as is good in your
eyes: onely vnto these men do nothing: for therefore came they
vnder the shadow of my roofe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they said,
Stand backe. And they said againe, This one fellow came in to
soiourne, and he will needs bee a Iudge: Now wil we deale worse
with thee, then with them. And they pressed sore vpon the man, euen
Lot, and came neere to breake the doore.</ab>
<ab n="10">But the men put
forth their hand, and pulled Lot into the house to them, and shut
to the doore.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they smote
the men that were at the doore of the house, with blindnes, both
small and great: so that they wearied themselues to finde the
doore.<note> Wisd. 19. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
men said vnto Lot, Hast thou here any besides? sonne in law, and
thy sonnes, and thy daughters, and whatsoeuer thou hast in the
citie, bring them out of this place.</ab>
<ab n="13">For we will
destroy this place, because the crie of them is waxen great before
the face of the LORD: and the LORD hath sent vs to destroy
it.<note> Chap. 18. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Lot went
out, and spake vnto his sonnes in law, which married his daughters,
and said, Up, get yee out of this place: for the LORD wil destroy
this citie: but hee seemed as one that mocked, vnto his sonnes in
law.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And when
the morning arose, then the Angels hastened Lot, saying, Arise,
take thy wife, &amp; thy two daughters, which are here, lest thou
be consumed in the iniquitie of the citie.<note> Heb. are found. , Or, punishment.</note></ab>

<fw>Sodome burnt.</fw>
<ab n="16">And while he
lingred, the men laid hold vpon his hand, and vpon the hand of his
wife, and vpon the hand of his two daughters, the LORD being
mercifull vnto him: and they brought him forth, and set him without
the citie.<note> Wisd. 10. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And it
came to passe, when they had brought them forth abroad, that he
said, Escape for thy life, looke not behind thee, neither stay thou
in all the plaine: escape to the mountaine, lest thou bee
consumed.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Lot said
vnto them, Oh not so, my Lord.</ab>
<ab n="19">Beholde now, thy
seruant hath found grace in thy sight, and thou hast magnified thy
mercy, which thou hast shewed vnto me, in sauing my life, and I
cannot escape to the mountaine, lest some euill take me, and I
die.</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold now, this
citie is neere to flee vnto, and it is a litle one: Oh let me
escape thither, (is it not a litle one?) and my soule shall
liue.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he said vnto
him, See, I haue accepted thee concerning this thing, that I will
not ouerthrow this citie, for the which thou hast
spoken.<note> Heb. thy face.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Haste thee,
escape thither: for I cannot doe any thing till thou bee come
thither: therefore the name of the citie was called Zoar.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ The sunne
was risen vpon the earth, when Lot entred into Zoar.<note> Hebr. gone forth.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Then the LORD
rained vpon Sodome &amp; vpon Gomorrah, brimstone and fire, from
the LORD out of heauen.<note> Deut. 29. 23. luk. 17. 29. isa.13. 19. ier.50. 40. amos 4. 11. iude 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And he ouerthrew
those cities, and all the plaine, and all the inhabitants of the
cities, and that which grew vpon the ground.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ But his
wife looked backe from behind him, and she became a pillar of
salt.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And
Abraham gate vp earely in the morning, to the place, where hee
stood before the LORD.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he looked
toward Sodome and Gomorrah, &amp; toward all the land of the
plaine, and beheld, and loe, the smoke of the countrey went vp as
the smoke of a furnace.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And it
came to passe, when God destroyed the cities of the plaine, that
God remembred Abraham, and sent Lot out of the midst of the
ouerthrow, when he ouerthrew the cities, in the which Lot
dwelt.</ab>

<fw>Lots incest.</fw>
<ab n="30">¶ And Lot
went vp out of Zoar, and dwelt in the mountaine, and his two
daughters with him: for hee feared to dwell in Zoar, and he dwelt
in a caue, he and his two daughters.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the first
borne saide vnto the yonger, Our father is old, and there is not a
man in the earth, to come in vnto vs, after the maner of all the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="32">Come, let vs
make our father drinke wine, and we will lye with him, that we may
preserue seed of our father.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they made
their father drinke wine that night, &amp; the first borne went in,
and lay with her father: and he perceiued not, when shee lay downe,
nor when she arose.</ab>
<ab n="34">And it came to
passe on the morrow, that the first borne said vnto the yonger,
Behold, I lay yesternight with my father: let vs make him drinke
wine this night also, and goe thou in, and lye with him, that we
may preserue seed of our father.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they made
their father drinke wine that night also, and the yonger arose, and
lay with him: and he perceiued not, when she lay downe, nor when
she arose.</ab>
<ab n="36">Thus were both
the daughters of Lot with childe by their father.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the first
borne bare a sonne, and called his name Moab: the same is the
father of the Moabites vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the yonger,
she also bare a sonne, and called his name, Ben-ammi: the same is
the father of the children of Ammon, vnto this day.</ab>



</div>