<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Paul goeth to Macedonia. 7 He
celebrateth the Lords Supper, and preacheth. 9 Eutychus hauing
fallen downe dead, 10 is raised to life. 17 At Miletum he calleth
the Elders together, telleth them what shall befall to himselfe, 28
committeth Gods flocke to them, 29 warneth them of false teachers,
32 commendeth them to God, 36 prayeth with them, and goeth his
way.</head>

<ab n="1">And after the
vprore was ceased, Paul called vnto him the disciples, and imbraced
them, &amp; departed, for to go into Macedonia.</ab>
<ab n="2">And when he
had gone ouer those parts, and had giuen them much exhortation, he
came into Greece,</ab>
<ab n="3">And there
abode three moneths: and when the Iewes layed waite for him, as hee
was about to saile into Syria, hee purposed to returne thorow
Macedonia.</ab>
<ab n="4">And there
accompanied him into Asia, Sopater of Berea: and of the
Thessalonians, Aristarchus, and Secundus, and Gaius of Derbe, and
Timotheus: and of Asia Tychicus and Trophimus.</ab>
<ab n="5">These going
before, taried for vs at Troas:</ab>
<ab n="6">And wee sailed
away from Philippi, after the dayes of vnleauened bread, and came
vnto them to Troas in fiue dayes, where we abode seuen
daies.</ab>

<fw>Eutychus raised.</fw>
<ab n="7">And vpon the
first day of the weeke, when the disciples came together to breake
bread, Paul preached vnto them, ready to depart on the morrow, and
continued his speach vntill midnight.<note> Chap.2. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And there were
many lights in the vpper chamber where they were gathered
together.</ab>
<ab n="9">And there sate
in a window a certaine yong man named Eutychus, being fallen into a
deepe sleepe, and as Paul was long preaching, hee sunke downe with
sleepe, and fel downe from the third loft, and was taken vp
dead.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Paul went
downe, and fell on him, and embracing him, saide, Trouble not your
selues, for his life is in him.</ab>
<ab n="11">When hee therefore
was come vp againe, &amp; had broken bread, and eaten, and talked a
long while, euen till breake of day, so he departed.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they brought
the yong man aliue, and were not a little comforted.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And wee went
before to ship, and sailed vnto Assos, there intending to take in
Paul: for so had hee appointed, minding himselfe to goe
afoote.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when he met
with vs at Assos, wee tooke him in, and came to Mitylene.</ab>
<ab n="15">And wee sailed
thence, and came the next day ouer against Chios, and the next day
we arriued at Samos, and taried at Trogyllium: and the next day we
came to Miletus.</ab>
<ab n="16">For Paul had
determined to saile by Ephesus, because he would not spend the time
in Asia: for he hasted, if it were possible for him, to be at
Hierusalem the day of Pentecost.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And from
Miletus hee sent to Ephesus, and called the Elders of the
Church.</ab>
<ab n="18">And when they were
come to him, he said vnto them, Ye know from the first day that I
came into Asia, after what maner I haue bene with you at all
seasons,</ab>
<ab n="19">Seruing the Lord
with all humilitie of minde, and with many teares, and temptations,
which befell me by the lying in wait of the Iewes:</ab>
<ab n="20">And how I kept
backe nothing that was profitable vnto you, but haue shewed you,
and haue taught you publikely, and from house to house,</ab>
<ab n="21">Testifying both to
the Iewes and also to the Greekes, repentance toward God, and faith
toward our Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>

<fw>Pauls integritie.</fw>
<ab n="22">And now behold, I
goe bound in the spirit vnto Hierusalem, not knowing the things
that shal befall me there:</ab>
<ab n="23">Saue that the holy
Ghost witnesseth in euery city, saying that bonds and afflictions
abide me.<note> Or, waite for me.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But none of these
things mooue me, neither count I my life deare vnto my self, so
that I might finish my course with ioy, &amp; the ministery which I
haue receiued of the Lord Iesus, to testifie the Gospel of the
grace of God.</ab>
<ab n="25">And now behold, I
know that ye all, among whom I haue gone preaching the kingdom of
God, shall see my face no more.</ab>
<ab n="26">Wherefore I take
you to record this day, that I am pure from the blood of all
men.</ab>
<ab n="27">For I haue not
shunned to declare vnto you all the counsell of God.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Take heed
therefore vnto your selues, &amp; to all the flocke, ouer the which
the holy Ghost hath made you ouerseers, to feed the Church of God,
which he hath purchased with his own blood.</ab>
<ab n="29">For I know this,
that after my departing shall grieuous wolues enter in among you,
not sparing the flocke.</ab>
<ab n="30">Also of your owne
selues shal men arise, speaking peruerse things, to draw away
disciples after them.</ab>
<ab n="31">Therefore watch,
and remember that by the space of three yeeres, I ceased not to
warne euery one night and day with teares.</ab>
<ab n="32">And now brethren, I
commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to
build you vp, and to giue you an inheritance among all them which
are sanctified.</ab>
<ab n="33">I haue coueted no
mans siluer, or golde, or apparell.</ab>
<ab n="34">Yea, you your
selues know, that these handes haue ministred vnto my necessities,
and to them that were with me.<note> 1.Cor.4. 12. 1.thess. 2.9. 2.thes. 3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">I haue shewed you
all things, how that so labouring, yee ought to support the weake,
and to remember the words of the Lord Iesus, how he said, It is
more blessed to giue, then to receiue.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And when he
had thus spoken, he kneeled downe, &amp; prayed with them
all.</ab>
<ab n="37">And they all wept
sore, and fell on Pauls necke, and kissed him,</ab>
<ab n="38">Sorrowing most of
all for the words which he spake, that they should see his face no
more. And they accompanied him vnto the ship.</ab>



</div>