<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The rulers of the Iewes offended
with Peters Sermon, 4 (though thousands of the people were
conuerted that heard the word) imprison him, and Iohn. 5 After,
vpon examination Peter boldly auouching the lame man to be healed
by the Name of Iesus, and that by the same Iesus onely we must bee
eternally saued, 13 They command him and Iohn to preach no more in
that Name, adding also threatning, 23 Whereupon the Church fleeeth
to prayer. 31 And God by mouing the place where they were
assembled, testified that he heard their prayer: confirming the
Church with the gift of the holy Ghost, and with mutuall loue and
charitie.</head>

<ab n="1">And as they
spake vnto the people, the Priests and the captaine of the Temple,
and the Sadduces came vpon them,<note> Or, ruler.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Being grieued
that they taught the people, and preached through Iesus the
resurrection from the dead.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they laid
hands on them, and put them in hold vnto the next day: for it was
now euentide.</ab>
<ab n="4">Howbeit, many
of them which heard the word, beleeued, and the number of the men
was about fiue thousand.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And it
came to passe on the morow, that their rulers, and Elders, and
Scribes,</ab>
<ab n="6">And Annas the
high Priest, and Caiphas, and Iohn, and Alexander, and as many as
were of the kinred of the high Priest, were gathered together at
Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when they
had set them in the middest, they asked, By what power, or by what
name haue ye done this?</ab>
<ab n="8">Then Peter
filled with the holy Ghost, said vnto them, Ye rulers of the
people, and Elders of Israel,</ab>
<ab n="9">If we this day
be examined of the good deed done to the impotent man, by what
meanes he is made whole,</ab>
<ab n="10">Be it knowen
vnto you all, and to all the people of Israel, that by the Name of
Iesus Christ of Nazareth, whom ye crucified, whome God raised from
the dead, euen by him, doeth this man stand here before you,
whole.</ab>
<ab n="11">This is the
stone which was set at nought of you builders, which is become the
head of the corner.<note> Psal.118. 22. mat. 21. 42.</note></ab>

<fw>The examination of the
Apostles.</fw>
<ab n="12">Neither is
there saluation in any other: for there is none other name vnder
heauen giuen among men whereby we must be saued.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Now
when they sawe the boldnesse of Peter and Iohn, and perceiued that
they were vnlearned and ignorant men, they marueiled, and they
tooke knowledge of them, that they had bene with Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="14">And beholding
the man which was healed, standing with them, they could say
nothing against it.</ab>
<ab n="15">But when they
had commanded them to go aside out of the Council, they conferred
among themselues,</ab>
<ab n="16">Saying, What
shall we do to these men? for that indeed a notable miracle hath
bene done by them, is manifest to all them that dwell in
Hierusalem, and we cannot denie it.</ab>
<ab n="17">But that it
spread no farther among the people, let vs straitly threaten them,
that they speake henceforth to no man in this Name.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they
called them, and commanded them, not to speake at all, nor teach in
the Name of Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="19">But Peter and
Iohn answered, and said vnto them, Whether it be right in the sight
of God, to hearken vnto you more then vnto God, iudge ye.</ab>
<ab n="20">For wee cannot
but speake the things which we haue seene and heard.</ab>
<ab n="21">So when they
had further threatned them, they let them goe, finding nothing how
they might punish them, because of the people: for all men
glorified God for that which was done.</ab>
<ab n="22">For the man
was aboue fourtie yeeres olde, on whome this miracle of healing was
shewed.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
being let goe, they went to their owne company, and reported all
that the chiefe Priests and Elders had said vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="24">And when they
heard that, they lift vp their voyce to God with one accord, &amp;
said, Lord, thou art God which hast made heauen and earth, and the
sea, and all that in them is,</ab>
<ab n="25">Who by the
mouth of thy seruant Dauid hast saide, Why did the heathen rage,
and the people imagine vaine things?<note> Psal.2.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The Kings of
the earth stood vp, and the rulers were gathered together against
the Lord, &amp; against his Christ.</ab>

<fw>All things common.</fw>
<ab n="27">For of a
trueth against thy holy child Iesus, whom thou hast anointed, both
Herod, and Pontius Pilate, with the Gentiles, and the people of
Israel were gathered together,</ab>
<ab n="28">For to doe
whatsoeuer thy hand and thy counsell determined before to be
done.</ab>
<ab n="29">And now Lord,
behold their threatnings, and graunt vnto thy seruants, that with
all boldnesse they may speake thy word,</ab>
<ab n="30">By stretching
foorth thine hand to heale: and that signes and wonders may be done
by the Name of thy holy child Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And
when they had prayed, the place was shaken where they were
assembled together, and they were all filled with the holy Ghost,
and they spake the word of God with boldnesse.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the
multitude of them that beleeued, were of one heart, and of one
soule: Neither said any of them, that ought of the things which he
possessed, was his owne, but they had all things common.</ab>
<ab n="33">And with great
power gaue the Apostles witnesse of the resurrection of the Lord
Iesus, and great grace was vpon them all.</ab>
<ab n="34">Neither was
there any among them that lacked: For as many as were possessors of
lands, or houses, sold them, and brought the prices of the things
that were solde,</ab>
<ab n="35">And laide them
downe at the Apostles feete: And distribution was made vnto euery
man according as hee had neede.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Ioses, who
by the Apostles was surnamed Barnabas (which is, being interpreted,
The sonne of consolation) a Leuite, and of the Countrey of
Cyprus,</ab>
<ab n="37">Hauing land,
sold it, and brought the money, &amp; laid it at the Apostles
feet.</ab>



</div>