<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-21-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>Paul will not by any meanes be
disswaded from going to Ierusalem. 9 Philips daughters
Prophetesses. 17 Paul commeth to Ierusalem: 27 where he is
apprehended, &amp; in great danger, 31 but by the chiefe captaine
is rescued, and permitted to speake to the people.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, that after wee were gotten frō them, and had lanched,
wee came with a straight course vnto Choos, and the day following
vnto Rhodes, and from thence vnto Patara.</ab>
<ab n="2">And finding a
ship sailing ouer vnto Phenicea, wee went abroad, and set
foorth.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now when wee
had discouered Cyprus, we left it on the left hand, and sailed into
Syria, and landed at Tyre: for there the shippe was to vnlade her
burden.</ab>
<ab n="4">And finding
disciples, wee taried there seuen dayes: who said to Paul through
the Spirit, that hee should not goe vp to Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when we
had accomplished those dayes, we departed, and went our way, and
they all brought vs on our way, with wiues and children, till wee
were out of the citie: and wee kneeled downe on the shore, and
prayed.</ab>
<ab n="6">And when we
had taken our leaue one of another, we tooke ship, and they
returned home againe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when wee
had finished our course from Tyre, wee came to Ptolemais, and
saluted the brethren, and abode with them one day.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the next
day we that were of Pauls company, departed, and came vnto Cesarea,
and wee entred into the house of Philip the Euangelist (which was
one of the seuen) &amp; abode with him.<note> Chap.6.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And
þe same man had foure daughters, virgins, which did
prophesie.</ab>
<ab n="10">And as wee taried
there many dayes, there came downe from Iudea a certaine Prophet,
named Agabus.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when he was
come vnto vs, he tooke Pauls girdle, and bound his owne hands and
feete, and said, Thus sayth the holy Ghost, So shall the Iewes at
Hierusalem binde the man that oweth this girdle, and shall deliuer
him into the hands of the Gentiles.</ab>

<fw>Pauls constancie. He is taken and
bound.</fw>
<ab n="12">And when we heard
these things, both we and they of that place, besought him not to
goe vp to Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then Paul answered,
What meane ye to weepe and to breake mine heart? for I am ready,
not to bee bound onely, but also to die at Hierusalem for the Name
of the Lord Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when he would
not bee perswaded, we ceased, saying, The will of the Lord be
done.</ab>
<ab n="15">And after those
dayes we tooke vp our cariages, &amp; went vp to
Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="16">There went with vs
also certaine of the disciples of Cesarea, and brought with them
one Mnason of Cyprus, an old disciple, with whō we should
lodge.</ab>
<ab n="17">And when we were
come to Hierusalem, the brethren receiued vs gladly</ab>
<ab n="18">And the day
following Paul went in with vs vnto Iames, and all the Elders were
present.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when hee had
saluted them, hee declared particularly what things God had wrought
among the Gentiles by his ministerie.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when they heard
it, they glorified the Lord, &amp; said vnto him, Thou seest,
brother, how many thousands of Iewes there are which beleeue, and
they are all zealous of the Law.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they are
informed of thee, that thou teachest all the Iewes which are among
the Gentiles, to forsake Moses, saying, that they ought not to
circumcise their children, neither to walke after the
customes.</ab>
<ab n="22">What is it
therefore? the multitude must needs come together: for they will
heare that thou art come.</ab>
<ab n="23">Doe therefore this
that we say to thee: Wee haue foure men which haue a vow on
them,</ab>
<ab n="24">Then take, and
purifie thy selfe with them, &amp; bee at charges with them, that
they may shaue their heads: and all may know that those things
wherof they were informed concerning thee, are nothing, but that
thou thy selfe also walkest orderly, and keepest the
Law.<note> Num.6. 18. chap. 18.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">As touching the
Gentiles which beleeue, wee haue written and concluded, that they
obserue no such thing, saue onely that they keepe themselues from
things offered to idoles, and from blood, and from strangled, and
from fornication.<note> Chap.15. 20.</note></ab>

<fw>Pauls constancie. He is taken and
bound.</fw>
<ab n="26">Then Paul tooke the
men, and the next day purifying himselfe with them, entred into the
Temple, to signifie the accomplishment of the dayes of
purification, vntill that an offering should be offered for euery
one of them:<note> Num.6.13</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And when the seuen
dayes were almost ended, the Iewes which were of Asia, when they
saw him in the Temple, stirred vp all the people, and laide hands
on him,</ab>
<ab n="28">Crying out, Men of
Israel, helpe: this is þe man that teacheth al men
euery where against the people, and the law, and this place: and
farther brought Greeks also into the Temple, and hath polluted this
holy place.</ab>
<ab n="29">(For they had seene
before with him in the citie, Trophimus an Ephesian, whome they
supposed that Paul had brought into the Temple.)</ab>
<ab n="30">And all the citie
was moued, and the people ran together: and they tooke Paul, and
drew him out of the Temple: and forthwith the doores were
shut.</ab>
<ab n="31">And as they went
about to kil him, tidings came vnto the chiefe captaine of the
band, that all Hierusalem was in an vprore.</ab>
<ab n="32">Who immediatly
tooke souldiers, and Centurions, and ran downe vnto them: and when
they saw the chiefe captaine and the souldiers, they left beating
of Paul.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then the chiefe
captain came neere, and tooke him, &amp; commanded him to be bound
with two chains, and demanded who he was, and what hee had
done.</ab>
<ab n="34">And some cried one
thing, some another, among the multitude: and when he could not
know the certaintie for the tumult, he commanded him to be caried
into the castle.</ab>
<ab n="35">And when he came
vpon þe staires, so it was that he was borne of the
souldiers, for the violence of the people.</ab>
<ab n="36">For the multitude
of the people followed after, crying, Away with him.</ab>
<ab n="37">And as Paul was to
bee led into the castle, hee saide vnto the chiefe captaine, May I
speake vnto thee? Who saide, Canst thou speake Greeke?</ab>
<ab n="38">Art not thou that
Egyptian which before these daies madest an vprore, and leddest out
into the wildernesse foure thousand men that were
murtherers?<note> Chap.5. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">But Paul said, I am
a man which am a Iew of Tarsus, a citie in Cilicia, a citizen of no
meane citie: &amp; I beseech thee suffer me to speake vnto the
people.</ab>

<fw>Paul answereth for himselfe.</fw>
<ab n="40">And when he had
giuen him licence, Paul stood on the staires, and beckened with the
hand vnto the people: and when there was made a great silence, he
spake vnto them in the Hebrew tongue, saying.</ab>



</div>