<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Cornelius a deuout man, 5 being
commaunded by an Angel, sendeth for Peter: 11 Who by a vision, 15.
20 is taught not to despise the Gentiles. 34 As he preacheth Christ
to Cornelius and his companie, 44 The holy Ghost falleth on them,
48 and they are baptized.</head>

<ab n="1">There was a
certaine man in Cesarea, called Cornelius, a Centurion of
þe band called the Italian band,</ab>
<ab n="2">A deuout man,
and one that feared God with all his house, which gaue much almes
to the people, and prayed to God alway.</ab>
<ab n="3">He saw in a
vision euidently, about the ninth houre of the day, an Angel of God
comming in to him, and saying vnto him Cornelius.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when he
looked on him, hee was afraid, and said, What is it, Lord? And he
said vnto him, Thy praiers and thine almes are come vp for a
memorial before God.</ab>

<fw>Peters vision. He goeth to
Cornelius.</fw>
<ab n="5">And now send
men to Ioppa, and call for one Simon, whose sirname is
Peter.</ab>
<ab n="6">Hee lodgeth
with one Simon a Tanner, whose house is by the Sea side; he shall
tell thee what thou oughtest to doe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when the
Angel which spake vnto Cornelius, was departed, he called two of
his houshold seruants, and a deuout souldier of them that waited on
him continually.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when he
had declared all these things vnto them, he sent them to
Ioppa.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ On the
morrow as they went on their iourney, and drew nigh vnto the citie,
Peter went vp vpon the house to pray, about the sixth
houre.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he became very
hungry, and would haue eaten: But while they made ready, he fell
into a traunce,</ab>
<ab n="11">And saw heauen
opened, and a certaine vessell descending vnto him, as it had beene
a great sheete, knit at the foure corners, and let downe to the
earth:</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherein were all
maner of foure footed beasts of the earth, and wilde beasts, and
creeping things, and foules of the ayre.</ab>
<ab n="13">And there came a
voyce to him, Rise, Peter: kill, and eate.</ab>
<ab n="14">But Peter said, Not
so, Lord; for I haue neuer eaten any thing that is common or
vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the voice spake
vnto him againe the second time, What God hath cleansed, that call
not thou common.</ab>
<ab n="16">This was done
thrise: &amp; the vessel was receiued vp againe into
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now while Peter
doubted in himselfe what this vision which he had seene, should
meane: behold, the men which were sent from Cornelius, had made
inquirie for Simons house, and stood before the gate,</ab>
<ab n="18">And called, and
asked whether Simon, which was sirnamed Peter, were lodged
there.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ While Peter
thought on the vision, the spirit said vnto him, Behold, three men
seeke thee.</ab>
<ab n="20">Arise therefore,
and get thee downe, and goe with them, doubting nothing: for I haue
sent them.</ab>

<fw>He goeth to Cornelius.</fw>
<ab n="21">Then Peter went
downe to the men, which were sent vnto him from Cornelius, and
said, Behold, I am hee, whom ye seeke: what is the cause wherefore
ye are come?</ab>
<ab n="22">And they saide,
Cornelius the Centurion, a iust man, and one that feareth God, and
of good report among all the nation of the Iewes, was warned from
God by an holy Angel, to send for thee into his house, and to heare
words of thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then called he them
in, and lodged them: And on the morrowe Peter went away with them,
and certaine brethren from Ioppa accōpanied him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the morrow
after they entred into Cesarea: and Cornelius waited for them, and
had called together his kinsmen and neere friends.</ab>
<ab n="25">And as Peter was
comming in, Cornelius met him, and fell downe at his feete, and
worshipped him.</ab>
<ab n="26">But Peter tooke him
vp, saying, Stand vp, I my selfe also am a man.</ab>
<ab n="27">And as he talked
with him, hee went in, and found many that were come
together.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he said vnto
them, Ye know how that it is an vnlawfull thing for a man that is a
Iewe, to keepe company or come vnto one of another nation: but God
hath shewed me, that I should not call any man common or
vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="29">Therfore came I
vnto you without gainesaying, as soone as I was sent for. I aske
therefore, for what intent ye haue sent for me.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Cornelius said,
Foure daies agoe I was fasting vntill this houre, and at the ninth
houre I prayed in my house, and behold, a man stood before me in
bright clothing,</ab>
<ab n="31">And said,
Cornelius, thy prayer is heard, and thine almes are had in
remembrance in the sight of God.</ab>
<ab n="32">Send therfore to
Ioppa, and call hither Simon, whose sirname is Peter; he is lodged
in the house of one Simon a Tanner, by the Sea side, who when he
cōmeth, shall speake vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="33">Immediately
therefore I sent to thee, and thou hast well done, that thou art
come. Now therefore are we all heere present before God, to heare
all things that are cōmanded thee of God.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Then Peter
opened his mouth, and said, Of a trueth I perceiue
þt God is no respecter of persons:<note> Deut.10. 17. rom.2. 11. 1.pet.1. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">But in euery
nation, he that feareth him, and worketh righteousnesse, is
accepted with him.</ab>

<fw>Peters Sermon.</fw>
<ab n="36">The word which God
sent vnto the children of Israel, preaching peace by Iesus Christ
(he is Lord of all.)</ab>
<ab n="37">That word (I say)
you knowe which was published thorowout all Iudea, and began from
Galilee, after the baptisme which Iohn preached:</ab>
<ab n="38">How God anointed
Iesus of Nazareth with the holy Ghost, and with power, who went
about doing good, and healing all that were oppressed of the
deuill: for God was with him.</ab>
<ab n="39">And we are
witnesses of all things which hee did both in the land of the
Iewes, and in Hierusalem, whom they slew and hanged on a
tree,</ab>
<ab n="40">Him God raised vp
the third day, and shewed him openly,</ab>
<ab n="41">Not to all the
people, but vnto witnesses, chosen before of God, euen to vs who
did eate and drinke with him after he rose from the dead.</ab>
<ab n="42">And he commanded vs
to preach vnto the people, and to testifie that it is he which was
ordeined of God to be the Iudge of quicke and dead.</ab>
<ab n="43">To him giue all the
Prophets witnesse, that through his Name whosoeuer beleeueth in
him, shall receiue remission of sinnes.<note> Ier.31.34. mich.7.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ While Peter
yet spake these words, the holy Ghost fell on all them which heard
the word.</ab>
<ab n="45">And they of the
circumcision which beleeued, were astonished, as many as came with
Peter, because that on the Gentiles also was powred out the gift of
the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="46">For they heard them
speake with tongues, and magnifie God. Then answered Peter,</ab>
<ab n="47">Can any man forbid
water, that these should not bee baptized, which haue receiued the
holy Ghost, as well as wee?</ab>
<ab n="48">And hee commanded
them to be baptized in the Name of the Lord. Then prayed they him
to tarie certaine dayes.</ab>



</div>