<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Paul hauing circumcised Timothy, 7
and being called by the Spirit from one countrey to another, 14
conuerteth Lydia, 16 casteth out a spirit of diuination. 19 For
which cause he and Silas are whipped and imprisoned. 26 The prison
doores are opened. 31 The Iayler is conuerted, 37 and they are
deliuered.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came he
to Derbe, and Lystra: and behold, a certaine disciple was there,
named Timotheus, the son of a certaine woman which was a Iewesse,
and beleeued: but his father was a Greeke:<note> Rom.16. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Which was well
reported of by the brethren that were at Lystra and
Iconium.</ab>
<ab n="3">Him would Paul
haue to go forth with him, and tooke, and circumcised him, because
of the Iewes which were in those quarters: for they knew all, that
his father was a Greeke.</ab>

<fw>Lydia conuerted.</fw>
<ab n="4">And as they
went through the cities, they deliuered them the decrees for to
keepe, that were ordeined of the Apostles and Elders, which were at
Hierusalem.<note> Chap.15. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And so were
the Churches established in the faith, and increased in number
dayly.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now when they
had gone thorowout Phrygia, and the region of Galatia, and were
forbidden of the holy Ghost to preach the word in Asia,</ab>
<ab n="7">After they
were come to Mysia, they assayed to goe into Bithynia: but the
Spirit suffered them not.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they
passing by Mysia, came downe to Troas.</ab>
<ab n="9">And a vision
appeared to Paul in the night: There stood a man of Macedonia, and
prayed him, saying, Come ouer into Macedonia, and helpe vs.</ab>
<ab n="10">And after he had
seene the vision, immediatly we endeuoured to goe into Macedonia,
assuredly gathering, that the Lord had called vs for to preach the
Gospel vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="11">Therfore loosing
from Troas, we came with a straight course to Samothracia, and the
next day to Neapolis:</ab>
<ab n="12">And from thence to
Philippi, which is the chiefe citie of that part of Macedonia, and
a Colonie: and we were in that citie abiding certaine
dayes.<note> Or, the first.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And on the Sabboth
we went out of the citie by a riuer side, where prayer was wont to
be made, &amp; we sate downe, and spake vnto the women which
resorted thither.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And a
certaine woman named Lydia, a seller of purple, of the citie of
Thyatira, which worshipped God, heard vs: whose heart the Lord
opened, that she attended vnto the things which were spoken of
Paul.</ab>
<ab n="15">And when she was
baptized, and her houshold, she besought vs, saying, If ye haue
iudged me to bee faithfull to the Lord, come into my house, and
abide there. And she constrained vs.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And it came
to passe, as we went to prayer, a certaine Damosell possessed with
a spirit of diuination, met vs: which brought her masters much
gaine by soothsaying.<note> Or, of Pythom,</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The same followed
Paul and vs, and cried, saying, These men are the seruants of the
most hie God, which shew vnto vs the way of saluation.</ab>

<fw>Prisoners sing.</fw>
<ab n="18">And this did she
many dayes: but Paul being grieued, turned and said to the spirit,
I command thee in the Name of Iesus Christ, to come out of her. And
he came out the same houre.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And when her
Masters saw that the hope of their gaines was gone, they caught
Paul and Silas, and drew them into the market place, vnto the
rulers,<note> Or, court</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And brought them to
the Magistrates, saying, These men being Iewes, do exceedingly
trouble our city,</ab>
<ab n="21">And teach customes
which are not lawfull for vs to receiue, neither to obserue, being
Romanes.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the multitude
rose vp together against them, and the Magistrates rent off their
clothes, and commanded to beate them.<note> 2.Cor.11 25. 1.thes. 2.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And when they had
layed many stripes vpon them, they cast them into prison, charging
the Iaylour to keepe them safely.</ab>
<ab n="24">Who hauing receiued
such a charge, thrust them into the inner prison, &amp; made their
feet fast in the stockes.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And at
midnight, Paul and Silas prayed, and sang praises vnto God: and the
prisoners heard them.</ab>
<ab n="26">And suddenly there
was a great earthquake, so that the foundations of the prison were
shaken: and immediately all the doores were opened, and euery ones
bands were loosed.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the keeper of
the prison awaking out of his sleepe, and seeing the prison doores
open, he drew out his sword, and would haue killed himselfe,
supposing that the prisoners had beene fled.</ab>
<ab n="28">But Paul cried with
a loud voice, saying, Doe thy selfe no harme, for we are all
heere.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then hee called for
a light, and sprang in, and came trembling, and fell downe before
Paul and Silas,</ab>
<ab n="30">And brought them
out, and said, Sirs, what must I doe to be saued?</ab>
<ab n="31">And they saide,
Beleeue on the Lord Iesus Christ, and thou shalt be saued, and thy
house.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they spake vnto
him the word of the Lord, and to all that were in his
house.</ab>
<ab n="33">And hee tooke them
the same houre of the night, and washed their stripes, and was
baptized, hee and all his, straightway.</ab>

<fw>Paul preacheth.</fw>
<ab n="34">And when he had
brought them into his house, hee set meat before them, and
reioyced, beleeuing in God with all his house.</ab>
<ab n="35">And when it was
day, the Magistrates sent the Sergeants, saying, Let those men
goe.</ab>
<ab n="36">And the keeper of
the prison told this saying to Paul, The Magistrates haue sent to
let you goe: Now therefore depart, and goe in peace.</ab>
<ab n="37">But Paul said vnto
them, They haue beaten vs openly vncondemned, being Romanes, and
haue cast vs into prison, and now doe they thrust vs out priuily?
Nay verily, but let them come themselues, and fetch vs out.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the Sergeants
tolde these words vnto the Magistrates: and they feared when they
heard that they were Romanes.</ab>
<ab n="39">And they came and
besought them, and brought them out, and desired them to depart out
of the citie.</ab>
<ab n="40">And they went out
of the prison, and entred into the house of Lydia, and when they
had seene the brethren, they comforted them, and
departed.<note> Chap.16. 14.</note></ab>



</div>