<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>By occasion of the persecution in
Hierusalem, the Church being planted in Samaria, 5 By Philip the
Deacon who preached, did miraracles, and baptized many, among the
rest Simon the sorcerer a great seducer of the people: 14 Peter and
Iohn come to confirme, and inlarge the Church: where by prayer, and
imposition of hands giuing the holy Ghost, 18 When Simon would haue
bought the like power of them, 20 Peter sharpely reprouing his
hypocrisie, and couetousnesse, and exhorting him to repentance:
together with Iohn preaching the word of the Lord, returne to
Hierusalem. 26 But the Angel sendeth Philip to teach, &amp; baptize
the Ethiopian Eunuch.</head>

<ab n="1">And Saul was
consenting vnto his death. And at that time there was a great
persecution against the Church which was at Hierusalem, and they
were all scattered abroad through out the regions of Iudea, and
Samaria, except the Apostles.</ab>
<ab n="2">And deuout men
carried Steuen to his buriall, and made great lamentation ouer
him.</ab>

<fw>Simon the sorcerer.</fw>
<ab n="3">As for Saul, he
made hauocke of the Church, entring into euery house, and hailing
men and women, committed them to prison.</ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore they
that were scattered abroad, went euery where preaching the
word.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then Philip
went downe to the citie of Samaria, and preached Christ vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the people
with one accord gaue heed vnto those things which Philip spake,
hearing and seeing the miracles which he did.</ab>
<ab n="7">For vncleane
spirits, crying with lowd voyce, came out of many that were
possessed with them: and many taken with palsies, and that were
lame, were healed.</ab>
<ab n="8">And there was
great ioy in that citie.</ab>
<ab n="9">But there was a
certaine man called Simon, which before time in the same citie vsed
sorcery, and bewitched the people of Samaria, giuing out that
himselfe was some great one.</ab>
<ab n="10">To whom they
all gaue heed from the least to the greatest, saying, This man is
the great power of God.</ab>
<ab n="11">And to him
they had regard, because that of long time he had bewitched them
with sorceries.</ab>
<ab n="12">But when they
beleeued Philip preaching the things concerning the kingdome of
God, and the Name of Iesus Christ, they were baptized, both men and
women.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then Simon
himselfe beleeued also: and when hee was baptized, hee continued
with Philip, and wondered, beholding the miracles and signes which
were done.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now when the
Apostles which were at Hierusalem, heard that Samaria had receiued
the word of God, they sent vnto them Peter and Iohn.</ab>
<ab n="15">Who when they
were come downe, praied for them that they might receiue the holy
Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="16">(For as yet
hee was fallen vpon none of them: onely they were baptized in the
Name of the Lord Iesus.)</ab>
<ab n="17">Then layde
they their hands on them, and they receiued the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="18">And when Simon
saw that through laying on of the Apostles hands, the holy Ghost
was giuen, hee offered them money,</ab>

<fw>Of the Eunuch.</fw>
<ab n="19">Saying, Giue
me also this power, that on whomsoeuer I lay handes, hee may
receiue the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="20">But Peter said
vnto him, Thy money perish with thee, because thou hast thought
that the gift of God may be purchased with money.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thou hast
neither part nor lot in this matter, for thy heart is not right in
the sight of God.</ab>
<ab n="22">Repent
therefore of this thy wickednesse, and pray God, if perhaps the
thought of thine heart may be forgiuen thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">For I perceiue
that thou art in the gall of bitternesse, and in the bond of
iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then answered
Simon, and said, Pray ye to the Lord for mee, that none of these
things which ye haue spoken, come vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they, when
they had testified and preached the word of the Lord, returned to
Hierusalem, and preached the Gospel in many villages of the
Samaritanes.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the Angel
of the Lord spake vnto Philip, saying, Arise, and goe toward the
South, vnto the way that goeth downe from Hierusalem vnto Gaza,
which is desert.</ab>
<ab n="27">And hee arose,
and went: and behold, a man of Ethiopia, an Eunuch of great
authority vnder Candace queene of the Ethiopians, who had the
charge of all her treasure, and had come to Hierusalem for to
worship,</ab>
<ab n="28">Was returning,
and sitting in his charet, read Esaias the Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then the
Spirit saide vnto Philip, Goe neere, and ioyne thy selfe to this
charet.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Philip ran
thither to him, and heard him reade the Prophet Esaias, and said,
Understandest thou what thou readest?</ab>
<ab n="31">And hee said,
How can I, except some man should guide me? And he desired Philip,
that hee would come vp, and sit with him.</ab>
<ab n="32">The place of
the Scripture, which hee read, was this, Hee was led as a sheepe to
the slaughter, &amp; like a Lambe dumbe before the shearer, so
opened he not his mouth:<note> Esay.53. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">In his
humiliation, his Iudgement was taken away: and who shall declare
his generation? For his life is taken from the earth.</ab>

<fw>The conuersion of Saul.</fw>
<ab n="34">And the Eunuch
answered Philip, and said, I pray thee, of whom speaketh the
Prophet this? of himselfe, or of some other man?</ab>
<ab n="35">Then Philip
opened his mouth, and began at the same Scripture, and preached
vnto him Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="36">And as they
went on their way, they came vnto a certaine water: and the Eunuch
said, See, here is water, what doeth hinder me to be
baptized?</ab>
<ab n="37">And Philip
said, If thou beleeuest with all thine heart, thou mayest. And he
answered, and said, I beleeue that Iesus Christ is the Sonne of
God.</ab>
<ab n="38">And he
commanded the charet to stand still: and they went downe both into
the water, both Philip, and the Eunuch, and he baptized
him.</ab>
<ab n="39">And when they
were come vp out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord caught away
Philip, that the Eunuch saw him no more: and hee went on his way
reioycing.</ab>
<ab n="40">But Philip was
found at Azotus: and passing thorow he preached in all the cities,
till he came to Cesarea.</ab>



</div>