<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-5-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>After that Ananias and Sapphira his
wife for their hypocrisie at Peters rebuke had fallen downe dead,
12 and that the rest of the Apostles had wrought many miracles, 14
to the increase of the faith: 17 The Apostles are againe
imprisoned, 19 But deliuered by an Angel bidding them to preach
openly to all: 21 When, after their teaching accordingly in the
temple, 29 and before the Councill, 33 they are in danger to be
killed, through the aduise of Gamaliel, a great councellour among
the Iewes, they be kept aliue, 40 and are but beaten: for which
they glorifie God, and cease no day from preaching.</head>


<fw>Lying to God.</fw>
<ab n="1">But a certaine
man named Ananias, with Sapphira his wife, solde a
possession,</ab>
<ab n="2">And kept backe
part of the price, his wife also being priuy to it, and brought a
certaine part, and layd it at the Apostles feete.</ab>
<ab n="3">But Peter said,
Ananias, Why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie to the holy
Ghost, and to keepe backe part of the price of the
land?<note> Or, to deceiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Whiles it
remained, was it not thine owne? and after it was sold, was it not
in thine owne power? why hast thou conceiued this thing in thine
heart? thou hast not lied vnto men, but vnto God.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Ananias
hearing these words, fell downe, and gaue vp the ghost: and great
feare came on all them that heard these things.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the yong
men arose, wound him vp, and caried him out, and buried
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">And it was
about the space of three houres after, when his wife, not knowing
what was done, came in.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Peter
answered vnto her, Tell me whether ye sold the land for so much.
And she saide, Yea, for so much.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then Peter
saide vnto her, How is it that ye haue agreed together, to tempt
the Spirit of the Lord? behold, the feete of them which haue buried
thy husband, are at the doore, and shall cary thee out.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then fell she
downe straightway at his feete, and yeelded vp the ghost: And the
yong men came in, and found her dead, and carying her forth, buried
her by her husband.</ab>
<ab n="11">And great
feare came vpon all the Church, and vpon as many as heard these
things.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And by
the hands of the Apostles, were many signes and wonders wrought
among the people. (And they were all with one accord in Solomons
porch.</ab>
<ab n="13">And of the
rest durst no man ioyne himselfe to them: But the people magnified
them.</ab>
<ab n="14">And beleeuers
were the more added to the Lord, multitudes both of men and
women.)</ab>

<fw>To obey God, rather then men.</fw>
<ab n="15">Insomuch
þt they brought foorth the sicke into the streetes,
and layed them on beds and couches, that at the least the shadow of
Peter passing by, might ouershadow some of them.<note> Or, in euery streete.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">There came
also a multitude out of the cities round about vnto Hierusalem,
bringing sicke folkes, and them which were vexed with vncleane
spirits: and they were healed euery one.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Then
the high Priest rose vp, and al they that were with him, (which is
the sect of the Sadduces) and were filled with
indignation,<note> Or, enuie.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And laid their
hands on the Apostles, &amp; put them in the common prison.</ab>
<ab n="19">But the Angel
of the Lord by night opened the prison doores, and brought them
foorth, and said,</ab>
<ab n="20">Goe, stand and
speake in the Temple to the people all the words of this
life.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when they
heard that, they entred into the Temple early in the morning, &amp;
taught: but the high Priest came, and they that were with him, and
called the Councill together, and all the Senate of the children of
Israel, and sent to the prison to haue them brought.</ab>
<ab n="22">But when the
officers came, and found them not in the prison, they returned, and
told,</ab>
<ab n="23">Saying, The
prison truely found we shut with all safety, and the keepers
standing without before the doores, but when we had opened, we
found no man within.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now when the
high Priest, and the captaine of the Temple, and the chiefe Priests
heard these things, they doubted of them wherunto this would
grow.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then came one,
and told them, saying, Behold, the men whom ye put in prison, are
standing in the Temple, and teaching the people.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then went the
captaine with the officers, and brought them without violence: (For
they feared the people, lest they should haue bene stoned.)</ab>
<ab n="27">And when they
had brought them, they set them before the Councill, and the high
Priest asked them,</ab>
<ab n="28">Saying, Did
not wee straitly command you, that you should not teach in this
Name? And behold, yee haue filled Hierusalem with your doctrine,
and intend to bring this mans blood vpon vs.<note> Chap.4. 18.</note></ab>

<fw>To obey God, rather then men.</fw>
<ab n="29">¶ Then
Peter, and the other Apostles answered, and saide, Wee ought to
obey God rather then men.</ab>
<ab n="30">The God of our
fathers raised vp Iesus, whom yee slew and hanged on a
tree.</ab>
<ab n="31">Him hath God
exalted with his right hand to bee a Prince and a Sauiour, for to
giue repentance to Israel, and forgiuenesse of sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="32">And we are his
witnesses of these things, and so is also the holy Ghost, whom God
hath giuen to them that obey him.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ When
they heard that, they were cut to the heart, and tooke counsell to
slay them.</ab>
<ab n="34">Then stood
there vp one in the Councill, a Pharisee, named Gamaliel, a doctour
of Law, had in reputation among all the people, and commanded to
put the Apostles forth a litle space,</ab>
<ab n="35">And said vnto
them, Yee men of Israel, take heed to your selues, what ye intend
to doe as touching these men.</ab>
<ab n="36">For before
these dayes rose vp Theudas, boasting himselfe to be some body, to
whom a number of men, about foure hundred, ioyned themselues: who
was slaine, and all, as many as obeied him, were scattered, &amp;
brought to nought.<note> Or, beleeued.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">After this man
rose vp Iudas of Galilee, in the dayes of the taxing, and drew away
much people after him: hee also perished, and all, euen as many as
obeyed him, were dispersed.</ab>
<ab n="38">And now I say
vnto you, refraine from these men, and let them alone: for if this
counsell or this worke be of men, it will come to nought.</ab>
<ab n="39">But if it be
of God, ye cannot ouerthrow it, lest haply yee be found euen to
fight against God.</ab>
<ab n="40">And to him
they agreed: and when they had called the Apostles, and beaten
them, they commanded that they should not speake in the Name of
Iesus, and let them goe.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
they departed from the presence of the Councill, reioycing that
they were counted worthy to suffer shame for his Name.</ab>
<ab n="42">And dayly in
the Temple, and in euery house, they ceased not to teach and preach
Iesus Christ.</ab>



</div>