<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>Great dissention ariseth touching
Circumcision. 6 The Apostles consult about it, 22 and send their
determination by letters to the Churches. 36 Paul and Barnabas
thinking to visit the brethren together, fall at strife, and depart
asunder.</head>

<ab n="1">And certaine
men which came downe from Iudea, taught the brethren, and said,
Except ye be circumcised after the manner of Moses, ye cannot be
saued.<note> Galat.5.1.</note></ab>

<fw>The Apostles Councill.</fw>
<ab n="2">When therefore
Paul and Barnabas had no small dissention and disputation with
them, they determined that Paul and Barnabas, and certeine other of
them, should goe vp to Hierusalem vnto the Apostles and Elders
about this question.</ab>
<ab n="3">And being
brought on their way by the Church, they passed thorow Phenice and
Samaria, declaring the conuersion of the Gentiles: and they caused
great ioy vnto all the brethren.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when they
were come to Hierusalem, they were receiued of the Church, and of
the Apostles, and Elders, and they declared all things that God had
done with them.</ab>
<ab n="5">But there rose
vp certaine of the sect of the Pharisees which beleeued, saying,
that it was needfull to circumcise them, and to cōmand them to
keepe the Law of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
Apostles &amp; Elders came together for to consider of this
matter.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when there
had bene much disputing, Peter rose vp, and said vnto them, Men and
brethren, ye know how that a good while agoe, God made choise among
vs, that the Gentiles by my mouth should heare the worde of the
Gospel, and beleeue.<note> Chap.10. 20.and 11. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And God which
knoweth the hearts, bare them witnes, giuing them the holy Ghost,
euen as he did vnto vs,</ab>
<ab n="9">And put no
difference between vs &amp; them, purifying their hearts by
faith.<note> Chap.10. 43. 1.cor. 1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Now therfore why
tempt ye God, to put a yoke vpon the necke of the disciples, which
neither our fathers nor we were able to beare?<note> Mat.23.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But we beleeue that
through the grace of the Lord Iesus Christ, we shal be saued euen
as they.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then all the
multitude kept silence, and gaue audience to Barnabas and Paul,
declaring what miracles and wonders God had wrought among the
Gentiles by them.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And after
they had helde their peace, Iames answered, saying, Men and
brethren, hearken vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="14">Simeon hath
declared how God at the first did visite the Gentiles to take out
of them a people for his Name.</ab>
<ab n="15">And to this agree
the words of the Prophets, as it is written,</ab>
<ab n="16">After this I will
returne, and wil build againe the Tabernacle of Dauid, which is
fallen downe: and I will build againe the ruines thereof, and I
will set it vp:<note> Amos 9.11</note></ab>

<fw>The Apostles epistle.</fw>
<ab n="17">That the residue of
men might seeke after the Lord, and all the Gentiles, vpon whom my
Name is called, sayth the Lord, who doeth all these things.</ab>
<ab n="18">Knowen vnto God are
all his workes frō the beginning of the world.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherefore my
sentence is, that we trouble not them, which from among the
Gentiles are turned to God:</ab>
<ab n="20">But that wee write
vnto them, that they abstaine from pollutions of Idoles, and from
fornication, and from things strangled, and from blood.</ab>
<ab n="21">For Moses of olde
time hath in euery citie them that preach him, being read in the
Synagogues euery Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then pleased it the
Apostles and Elders with the whole Church, to send chosen men of
their owne company to Antioch, with Paul and Barnabas: namely,
Iudas surnamed Barsabas, &amp; Silas, chiefe men among the
brethren,</ab>
<ab n="23">And wrote letters
by them after this maner, The Apostles and Elders, and brethren,
send greeting vnto the brethren, which are of the Gentiles in
Antioch, and Syria, and Cilicia.</ab>
<ab n="24">Forasmuch as we
haue heard, that certaine which went out from vs, haue troubled you
with words, subuerting your soules, saying, Ye must be circumcised,
and keepe the Law, to whom we gaue no such commandement:</ab>
<ab n="25">It seemed good vnto
vs, being assembled with one accord, to send chosen men vnto you,
with our beloued Barnabas and Paul,</ab>
<ab n="26">Men that haue
hazarded their liues for the Name of our Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wee haue sent
therefore Iudas and Silas, who shall also tell you the same things
by mouth.</ab>
<ab n="28">For it seemed good
to the holy Ghost, and to vs, to lay vpon you no greater burden
then these necessarie things;</ab>
<ab n="29">That ye abstaine
from meates offered to idoles, and from blood, &amp; from things
strangled, and from fornication: from which if ye keepe your
selues, yee shall doe well. Fare ye well.</ab>
<ab n="30">So when they were
dismissed, they came to Antioch: and when they had gathered the
multitude together, they deliuered the Epistle.</ab>

<fw>Paul and Barnabas.</fw>
<ab n="31">Which when they had
read, they reioyced for the consolation.<note> Or, exhortation.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And Iudas and
Silas, being Prophets also themselues, exhorted the brethren with
many words, and confirmed them:</ab>
<ab n="33">And after they had
taried there a space, they were let goe in peace from the breehren
vnto the Apostles.</ab>
<ab n="34">Notwithstanding it
pleased Silas to abide there still.</ab>
<ab n="35">Paul also and
Barnabas continued in Antioch, teaching and preaching the word of
the Lord, with many others also.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And some
dayes after, Paul said vnto Barnabas, Let vs go againe and visit
our brethren, in euery city where we haue preached the word of the
Lord, and see how they doe.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Barnabas
determined to take with them Iohn, whose surname was Marke.</ab>
<ab n="38">But Paul thought
not good to take him with them; who departed from them from
Pamphylia, and went not with them to the worke.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the contention
was so sharpe betweene them, that they departed asunder one from
the other: &amp; so Barnabas tooke Marke, &amp; sailed vnto
Cyprus.</ab>
<ab n="40">And Paul chose
Silas, and departed, being recommended by the brethren vnto the
grace of God.</ab>
<ab n="41">And he went thorow
Syria and Cilicia, confirming the Churches.</ab>



</div>