<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>6 The holy Ghost is giuen by Pauls
hands. 9 The Iewes blaspheme his doctrine, which is confirmed by
miracles. 13 The Iewish exorcists 16 are beaten by the deuill. 19
Coniuring books are burnt. 24 Demetrius, for loue of gaine, raiseth
an vprore against Paul, 35 which is appeased by the
Towne-clerke.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, that while Apollos was at Corinth, Paul hauing passed thorow
the vpper coasts, came to Ephesus, and finding certaine
disciples,</ab>
<ab n="2">He said vnto
them, Haue ye receiued the holy Ghost since yee beleeued? And they
saide vnto him, Wee haue not so much as heard whether there be any
holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he said
vnto them, Unto what then were ye baptized? And they saide, Unto
Iohns Baptisme.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then saide
Paul, Iohn verely baptized with the baptisme of repentance, saying
vnto the people, that they should beleeue on him which should come
after him, that is, on Christ Iesus.<note> Mat.3.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">When they
heard this, they were baptized in the Name of the Lord
Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="6">And when Paul
had laide his hands vpon them, the holy Ghost came on them, and
they spake with tongues, and prophecied.</ab>
<ab n="7">And all
þe men were about twelue.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee went
into the Synagogue, and spake boldly for the space of three
moneths, disputing and perswading the things concerning the
Kingdome of God.</ab>

<fw>Exorcists beaten.</fw>
<ab n="9">But when
diuers were hardened, and beleeued not, but spake euill of that way
before the multitude, he departed from them, and separated the
disciples, disputing daily in the schoole of one Tyrannus.</ab>
<ab n="10">And this continued
by the space of two yeeres, so that all they which dwelt in Asia,
heard the word of the Lord Iesus, both Iewes and Greeks.</ab>
<ab n="11">And God wrought
speciall miracles by the hands of Paul:</ab>
<ab n="12">So that from his
body were brought vnto the sicke handkerchiefs or aprons, and the
diseases departed from them, and the euill spirits went out of
them.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then
certaine of the vagabond Iewes, exorcistes, tooke vpon them to call
ouer them which had euill spirits, the Name of the Lord Iesus,
saying, We adiure you by Iesus whom Paul preacheth.</ab>
<ab n="14">And there were
seuen sonnes of one Sceua a Iewe, and chiefe of the Priests, which
did so.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the euill
spirit answered, and said, Iesus I knowe, and Paul I know, but who
are ye?</ab>
<ab n="16">And the man in whom
the euill spirit was, leapt on them, and ouercame them, and
preuailed against them, so that they fled out of that house naked
and wounded.</ab>
<ab n="17">And this was knowen
to all the Iewes and Greekes also dwelling at Ephesus, and feare
fell on them all, and the Name of the Lord Iesus was
magnified.</ab>
<ab n="18">And many that
beleeued came, and confessed, and shewed their deedes.</ab>
<ab n="19">Many also of them
which vsed curious arts, brought their bookes together and burned
them before all men: and they counted the price of them, and found
it fifty thousand pieces of siluer.</ab>
<ab n="20">So mightily grew
the word of God, and preuailed.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ After these
things were ended, Paul purposed in the spirit, when hee had passed
thorow Macedonia and Athaia, to go to Hierusalem, saying, After I
haue bin there, I must also see Rome.</ab>
<ab n="22">So hee sent into
Macedonia two of them that ministred vnto him, Timotheus and
Erastus, but he himselfe stayed in Asia for a season.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the same time
there arose no small stirre about that way.</ab>

<fw>Idolaters rage.</fw>
<ab n="24">For a certaine man
named Demetrius, a siluer smith, which made siluer shrines for
Diana, brought no small gaine vnto the craftsmen:</ab>
<ab n="25">Whom he called
together, with the workemen of like occupation, and said, Sirs, ye
know that by this craft we haue our wealth.</ab>
<ab n="26">Moreouer, ye see
&amp; heare, that not alone at Ephesus, but almost throughout all
Asia, this Paul hath perswaded and turned away much people, saying,
that they bee no gods, which are made with hands.</ab>
<ab n="27">So that not only
this our craft is in danger to be set at nought: but also that the
Temple of the great goddesse Diana should be despised, and her
magnificence should be destroyed, whom all Asia, and the world
worshippeth.</ab>
<ab n="28">And when they heard
these sayings, they were ful of wrath, &amp; cried out, saying,
Great is Diana of þe Ephesians.</ab>
<ab n="29">And the whole citie
was filled with confusion, and hauing caught Gaius and Aristarchus
men of Macedonia Pauls companions in trauaile, they rushed with one
accord into the Theatre.</ab>
<ab n="30">And when Paul would
haue entred in vnto the people, the disciples suffered him
not.</ab>
<ab n="31">And certaine of the
chiefe of Asia, which were his friends, sent vnto him, desiring him
that he would not aduenture himselfe into the Theatre.</ab>
<ab n="32">Some therefore
cried one thing, and some another: for the assembly was confused,
and the more part knew not wherefore they were come
together.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they drew
Alexander out of the multitude, the Iewes putting him forward. And
Alexander beckened with the hand, and would haue made his defence
vnto the people.</ab>
<ab n="34">But when they knew
that he was a Iewe, all with one voyce about the space of two
houres cried out, Great is Diana of the Ephesians.</ab>
<ab n="35">And when the towne
clarke had appeased the people, he said, Ye men of Ephesus, what
man is there þt knoweth not how that the citie of
the Ephesians is a worshipper of the great goddesse Diana, and of
the image which fell downe from Iupiter?<note> Gre. the temple keeper.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Seeing then that
these things cannot be spoken against, ye ought to be quiet, and to
doe nothing rashly.</ab>

<fw>The Lords Supper.</fw>
<ab n="37">For ye haue brought
hither these men, which are neither robbers of Churches, nor yet
blasphemers of your goddesse:</ab>
<ab n="38">Wherefore if
Demetrius, and the craftesmen which are with him, haue a matter
against any man, the law is open, and there are deputies, let them
implead one another.<note> Or, the Court dayes are kept.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">But if yee enquire
any thing concerning other matters, it shalbe determined in a
lawfull assembly.<note> Or, ordinary.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">For we are in
danger to be called in question for this dayes vprore, there being
no cause whereby we may giue an accompt of this concourse.</ab>
<ab n="41">And when hee had
thus spoken, he dismissed the assembly.</ab>



</div>