<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>Peter preaching to the people that
came to see a lame man restored to his feete, 12 professeth the
cure not to haue beene wrought by his, or Iohns owne power, or
holinesse, but by God, and his sonne Iesus, and through faith in
his Name: 13 Withall reprehending them for crucifying Iesus. 17
Which because they did it through ignorance, and that thereby were
fulfilled Gods determinate counsell, and the Scriptures: 19 He
exhorteth them by repentance and faith to seeke remission of their
sinnes, and saluation in the same Iesus.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe Peter and
Iohn went vp together into the Temple at the houre of prayer,
beeing the ninth houre.</ab>
<ab n="2">And a certaine
man lame from his mothers womb was caried, whom they laide daily at
the gate of the Temple which is called Beautifull, to aske almes of
them that entred into the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="3">Who seeing
Peter &amp; Iohn about to go into the Temple, asked an
almes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Peter
fastening his eyes vpon him, with Iohn, said, Looke on vs.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he gaue
heede vnto them, expecting to receiue something of them.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Peter
said, Siluer and gold haue I none, but such as I haue, giue I thee:
In the Name of Iesus Christ of Nazareth, rise vp and walke.</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee tooke
him by the right hand, &amp; lift him vp: aud immediatly his feete
and ancle bones receiued strength.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee leaping
vp, stood, and walked, and entred with them into the Temple,
walking, and leaping, and praising God.</ab>
<ab n="9">And all the
people saw him walking, and praising God.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they knew
that it was hee which sate for almes at the beautifull gate of the
Temple: and they were filled with wonder and amazement at that
which had happened vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="11">And as the
lame man which was healed, helde Peter and Iohn, all the people
ranne together vnto them in the porch, that is called Solomons,
greatly wondring.</ab>

<fw>Peter preacheth.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And
when Peter sawe it, hee answered vnto the people, Yee men of
Israel, why marueile ye at this? or why looke yee so earnestly on
vs, as though by our owne power or holinesse we had made this man
to walke?</ab>
<ab n="13">The God of
Abraham, and of Isaac, and of Iacob, the God of our fathers hath
glorified his sonne Iesus, whom ye deliuered vp, and denied him in
the presence of Pilate, when hee was determined to let him
goe.</ab>
<ab n="14">But ye denied
the Holy one, and the Iust, and desired a murderer to be granted
vnto you,<note> Matt.27. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And killed the
Prince of life, whom God hath raised from the dead, whereof we are
witnesses.<note> Or, author.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And his Name
through faith in his Name hath made this man strong, whom ye see
and know: yea, the faith which is by him, hath giuen him this
perfect soundnesse in the presence of you all.</ab>
<ab n="17">And now
brethren, I wote that through ignorance yee did it, as did also
your rulers.</ab>
<ab n="18">But those
things which God before had shewed by the mouth of all his
Prophets, that Christ should suffer, hee hath so fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Repent
yee therefore, and bee conuerted, that your sins may be blotted
out, when the times of refreshing shal come from the presence of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">And hee shall
send Iesus Christ, which before was preached vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="21">Whom the
heauen must receiue, vntill the times of restitution of all things,
which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy Prophets since
the world began.</ab>
<ab n="22">For Moses
truely said vnto the fathers, A Prophet shall the Lord your God
raise vp vnto you of your brethren, like vnto me; him shall yee
heare in all things whatsoeuer he shal say vnto you.<note> Deut.18. 15. chap. 7.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And it shall
come to passe, that euery soule which will not heare that Prophet,
shalbe destroyed from among the people.</ab>
<ab n="24">Yea and all
the Prophets from Samuel, and those that follow after, as many as
haue spoken, haue likewise foretold of these dayes.</ab>
<ab n="25">Yee are the
children of the Prophets, and of the couenant which God made with
our fathers, saying vnto Abraham, And in thy seed shall all the
kinreds of the earth be blessed.<note> Gen.12.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Unto you
first, God hauing raised vp his Sonne Iesus, sent him to blesse
you, in turning away euery one of you from his iniquities.</ab>



</div>