<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-27-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Paul shipping toward Rome, 10
foretelleth of the danger of the voyage, 11 but is not beleeued. 14
They are tossed to and fro with tempest, 41 and suffer shipwracke,
22 34. 44 yet all come safe to land.</head>

<ab n="1">And when it
was determined, that wee should saile into Italy, they deliuered
Paul, &amp; certaine other prisoners, vnto one named Iulius, a
centurion of Augustus band.</ab>
<ab n="2">And entring
into a ship of Adramyttium, wee lanched, meaning to saile by the
coasts of Asia, one Aristarchus a Macedonian, of Thessalonica,
beeing with vs.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the next
day wee touched at Sidon: And Iulius courteously entreated Paul,
and gaue him libertie to goe vnto his friends to refresh
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when we
had lanched from thence, we sailed vnder Cyprus, because the winds
were contrary.</ab>

<fw>Pauls dangerous voyage to Rome.</fw>
<ab n="5">And when we
had sailed ouer the sea of Cilicia and Pamphylia, wee came to Myra
a citie of Lysia.</ab>
<ab n="6">And there the
Centurion found a ship of Alexandria sailing into Italy, and he put
vs therein.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when wee
had sailed slowly many dayes, and scarse were come ouer against
Gnidus, the wind not suffering vs, wee sailed vnder Creete, ouer
against Salmone,<note> Or, Candy.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And hardly
passing it, came vnto a place which is called the Faire hauens,
nigh whereunto was the citie of Lasea.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now when much
time was spent, and when sailing was now dangerous, because the
Fast was now alreadie past, Paul admonished them,</ab>
<ab n="10">And said vnto them,
Sirs, I perceiue that this voyage will be with hurt and much
damage, not onely of the lading &amp; ship, but also of our
liues.<note> Or, inuirie.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Neuerthelesse, the
Centurion beleeued the master and the owner of the shippe, more
then those things which were spoken by Paul.</ab>
<ab n="12">And because the
hauen was not commodious to winter in, the more part aduised to
depart thence also, if by any meanes they might attaine to Phenice,
and there to winter; which is an hauen of Creete, and lieth toward
the Southwest, and Northwest.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when the South
wind blew softly, supposing that they had obtained their purpose,
loosing thence, they sailed close by Creete.</ab>
<ab n="14">But not long after,
there arose against it a tempestuous winde, called
Euroclydon.<note> Or, beat.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And when the ship
was caught, and could not beare vp into the winde, we let her
driue.</ab>
<ab n="16">And running vnder a
certaine yland, which is called Clauda, wee had much worke to come
by the boate:</ab>
<ab n="17">Which when they had
taken vp, they vsed helps, vnder-girding the ship; and fearing lest
they should fall into the quicke-sands, strake saile, and so were
driuen.</ab>
<ab n="18">And being
exceedingly tossed with a tempest the next day, they lightened the
ship:</ab>
<ab n="19">And the third day
we cast out with our owne handes the tackling of the
shippe.</ab>

<fw>Pauls dangerous voyage to Rome.</fw>
<ab n="20">And when neither
Sunne nor starres in many dayes appeared, and no small tempest lay
on vs; all hope that wee should be saued, was then taken
away.</ab>
<ab n="21">But after long
abstinence, Paul stood foorth in the middes of them, and said,
Sirs, yee should haue hearkened vnto mee, and not haue loosed from
Creete, and to haue gained this harme and losse.</ab>
<ab n="22">And now I exhort
you to be of good cheere: for there shall be no losse of any mans
life among you, but of the shippe.</ab>
<ab n="23">For there stood by
me this night the Angel of God, whose I am, and whom I
serue,</ab>
<ab n="24">Saying, Feare not
Paul, thou must be brought before Cesar, and loe, God hath giuen
thee all them that saile with thee.</ab>
<ab n="25">Wherefore, sirs, be
of good cheere: for I beleeue God, that it shall be euen as it was
tolde me.</ab>
<ab n="26">Howbeit, we must be
cast vpon a certaine Iland.</ab>
<ab n="27">But when the
fourteenth night was come, as wee were driuen vp and downe in Adria
about midnight, the shipmen deemed that they drew neere to some
countrey:</ab>
<ab n="28">And sounded, and
found it twentie fathoms: and when they had gone a little further,
they sounded againe, and found it fifteene fathoms.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then fearing lest
we should haue fallen vpon rockes, they cast foure ancres out of
the sterne, and wished for the day.</ab>
<ab n="30">And as the shipmen
were about to flee out of the ship, when they had let downe the
boat into the sea, vnder colour as though they would haue cast
ancres out of the fore-ship,</ab>
<ab n="31">Paul said to the
Centurion, and to the souldiers, Except these abide in the ship, ye
cannot be saued.</ab>
<ab n="32">Then the souldiers
cut off the ropes of the boat, and let her fall off.</ab>
<ab n="33">And while the day
was comming on, Paul besought them all to take meat, saying, This
day is the fourteenth day that ye haue taried, and continued
fasting, hauing taken nothing.</ab>
<ab n="34">Wherefore, I pray
you to take some meat, for this is for your health: for there shall
not an haire fall from the head of any of you.</ab>

<fw>Shipwracke.</fw>
<ab n="35">And when hee had
thus spoken, hee tooke bread, and gaue thankes to God in presence
of them all, and when he had broken it, he began to eate.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then were they all
of good cheere, and they also tooke some meat.</ab>
<ab n="37">And we were in all,
in the ship, two hundred, threescore and sixteene soules.</ab>
<ab n="38">And when they had
eaten enough, they lightened the ship, and cast out the wheat into
the sea.</ab>
<ab n="39">And when it was
day, they knew not the land: but they discouered a certaine creek,
with a shore, into the which they were minded, if it were possible,
to thrust in the ship.</ab>
<ab n="40">And when they had
taken vp the ankers, they committed themselues vnto the sea, &amp;
loosed the rudder bands, and hoised vp the maine saile to the
winde, and made toward shore.<note> Or, cut the ankers, they left them in the sea, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And falling into a
place where two seas met, they ranne the shippe a ground, and the
forepart stucke fast, and remained vnmoueable, but the hinder part
was broken with the violence of the waues.</ab>
<ab n="42">And the souldiers
counsel was to kil the prisoners, lest any of them should swimme
out, and escape.</ab>
<ab n="43">But the Centurion,
willing to saue Paul, kept them from their purpose, and commanded
that they which could swimme, should cast themselues first into the
sea, and get to land:</ab>
<ab n="44">And the rest, some
on boords, and some on broken pieces of the ship: and so it came to
passe that they escaped all safe to land.</ab>



</div>