<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Paul and Barnabas are persecuted
from Iconium. 7 At Lystra Paul healeth a creeple, wherupon they are
reputed as gods. 19 Paul is stoned. 21 They passe through diuers
Churches, confirming the disciples in faith and patience. 26
Returning to Antioch, they report what God had done with
them.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe in Iconium, that they went both together into the synagogue
of the Iewes, and so spake, that a great multitude both of the
Iewes, and also of the Greekes, beleeued.</ab>

<fw>The lame healed.</fw>
<ab n="2">But the
vnbeleeuing Iewes stirred vp the Gentiles, and made their mindes
euill affected against the brethren.</ab>
<ab n="3">Long time
therefore abode they speaking boldly in the Lord, which gaue
testimonie vnto the word of his grace, and granted signes and
wonders to be done by their hands.</ab>
<ab n="4">But the
multitude of the city was diuided: and part held with the Iewes,
and part with the Apostles.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when there
was an assault made both of the Gentiles, and also of the Iewes,
with their rulers, to vse them despitefully, and to stone
them,</ab>
<ab n="6">They were ware
of it, and fled vnto Lystra and Derbe, cities of Lycaonia, and vnto
the region that lyeth round about.</ab>
<ab n="7">And there they
preached the Gospell.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
there sate a certaine man at Lystra, impotent in his feete, being a
creeple from his mothers wombe, who neuer had walked.</ab>
<ab n="9">The same heard
Paul speake: who stedfastly beholding him, and perceiuing that he
had faith to be healed,</ab>
<ab n="10">Said with a lowd
voice, Stand vpright on thy feete; And he leaped and
walked.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when the people
saw what Paul had done, they lift vp their voyces, saying in the
speech of Lycaonia, The gods are come downe to vs in the likenesse
of men.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they called
Barnabas Iupiter, and Paul Mercurius, because hee was the chiefe
speaker.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then the priest of
Iupiter, which was before their city, brought oxen, and garlands
vnto the gates, and would haue done sacrifice with the
people.</ab>
<ab n="14">Which when the
Apostles, Barnabas and Paul heard of, they rent their clothes, and
ranne in among the people, crying out,</ab>
<ab n="15">And saying, Sirs,
Why doe yee these things? Wee also are men of like passions with
you, and preach vnto you, that ye should turne from these vanities,
vnto the liuing God, which made heauen and earth, and the sea, and
all things that are therein.<note> Gen.1.1. psal.146.5. reuel.14.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Who in times past,
suffred all nations to walke in their owne wayes.<note> Psal.81. 13.</note></ab>

<fw>Paul stoned. The Apostles
Councill.</fw>
<ab n="17">Neuerthelesse, he
left not himselfe without witnesse, in that he did good, and gaue
vs raine from heauen, and fruitful seasons, filling our hearts with
food and gladnesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">And with these
sayings scarse restrained they the people, that they had not done
sacrifice vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And there
came thither certaine Iewes from Antioch and Iconium, who perswaded
the people, and hauing stoned Paul, drew him out of the citie,
supposing he had beene dead.<note> 2.Cor.11. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Howbeit, as the
disciples stood round about him, he rose vp, and came into the
citie, and the next day he departed with Barnabas to Derbe.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when they had
preached the Gospel to that city, and had taught many, they
returned againe to Lystra, and to Iconium, and Antioch,</ab>
<ab n="22">Confirming the
soules of the disciples, and exhorting them to continue in the
faith, aud that we must through much tribulation enter into the
kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="23">And when they had
ordeined them Elders in euery Church, and had prayed with fasting,
they commended them to the Lord, on whom they beleeued.</ab>
<ab n="24">And after they had
passed throughout Pisidia, they came to Pamphylia.</ab>
<ab n="25">And when they had
preached the word in Perga, they went downe into Attalia,</ab>
<ab n="26">And thence sailed
to Antioch, from whence they had been recommended to the grace of
God, for the worke which they fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="27">And when they were
come, and had gathered the Church together, they rehearsed all that
God had done with them, and how he had opened the doore of faith
vnto the Gentiles.</ab>
<ab n="28">And there they
abode long time with the disciples.</ab>



</div>