<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Paul declareth at large, how he
was conuerted to the faith, 17 and called to his Apostleship. 22 At
the very mentioning of the Gentiles, the people exclaime on him. 24
He should haue bene scourged, 25 but clayming the priuilege of a
Romane, he escapeth.</head>

<ab n="1">Men, brethren,
and fathers, heare ye my defence which I make now vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="2">(And when they
heard that hee spake in the Hebrew tongue to them, they kept the
more silence: and he saith,)</ab>
<ab n="3">I am verely a
man which am a Iew, borne in Tarsus a citie in Cilicia, yet brought
vp in this citie at the feete of Gamaliel, and taught according to
the perfect maner of the law of the fathers, and was zealous
towards God, as ye all are this day.<note> Chap.21. 39.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I
persecuted this way vnto the death, binding and deliuering into
prisons both men and women,<note> Chap.8. 3</note></ab>
<ab n="5">As also the
high Priest doth beare me witnesse, and all the estate of the
elders: from whom also I receiued letters vnto the brethren, and
went to Damascus, to bring them which were there, bound vnto
Hierusalem, for to be punished.</ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe, that as I made my iourney, &amp; was come nigh vnto Damascus
about noone, suddenly there shone from heauen a great light round
about me.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I fell
vnto the ground, and heard a voice saying vnto mee, Saul, Saul, why
persecutest thou me?</ab>
<ab n="8">And I
answered, Who art thou, Lord? And he said vnto me, I am Iesus of
Nazareth whō thou persecutest.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they that
were with me saw indeede the light, and were afraid; but they heard
not the voice of him that spake to me.</ab>
<ab n="10">And I saide, What
shall I doe, Lord? And the Lord said vnto me, Arise, and goe into
Damascus, and there it shall be told thee of all things which are
appointed for thee to doe.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when I could
not see for the glory of that light, being led by the hand of them
that were with me, I came into Damascus.</ab>

<fw>Paul answereth for himselfe.</fw>
<ab n="12">And one Ananias, a
deuout man according to the law, hauing a good report of al the
Iewes which dwelt there,</ab>
<ab n="13">Came vnto me, and
stood, &amp; said vnto me, Brother Saul, receiue thy sight. And the
same houre I looked vp vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he said, The
God of our fathers hath chosen thee, þt thou
shouldest know his will, &amp; see that Iust one, and shouldest
heare the voice of his mouth.</ab>
<ab n="15">For thou shalt be
his witnes vnto al men, of what thou hast seene &amp;
heard.</ab>
<ab n="16">And now, why
tariest thou? Arise, and be baptized, and wash away thy sinnes,
calling on the name of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">And it came to
passe, that when I was come againe to Hierusalem, euen while I
prayed in the temple, I was in a trance,</ab>
<ab n="18">And saw him saying
vnto mee, Make haste, and get thee quickly out of Hierusalem: for
they will not receiue thy testimony concerning me.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I said, Lord,
they know that I imprisoned, and beat in euery synagogue them that
beleeued on thee.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when
þe blood of thy martyr Steuen was shed, I also was
standing by, and consenting vnto his death, and kept the raiment of
them that slew him.<note> Chap.7. 58.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And he said vnto
me, Depart: for I will send thee farre hence, vnto the
Gentiles.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they gaue him
audience vnto this word, and then lift vp their voices, and said,
Away with such a fellow from the earth: for it is not fit that he
should liue.</ab>
<ab n="23">And as they cried
out, and cast off their clothes, &amp; threw dust into the
aire,</ab>
<ab n="24">The chiefe captaine
commanded him to be brought into the castle, and bade that hee
should be examined by scourging: that he might know wherfore they
cried so against him.</ab>
<ab n="25">And as they bound
him with thongs, Paul said vnto the Centurion that stood by, Is it
lawfull for you to scourge a man that is a Romane, and
vncondemned?</ab>
<ab n="26">When the Centurion
heard that, hee went and told the chiefe captaine, saying, Take
heede what thou doest, for this man is a Romane.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then the chiefe
captaine came; and said vnto him, Tell me, art thou a Romane? He
said, Yea.</ab>

<fw>Paul smitten.</fw>
<ab n="28">And the chiefe
captaine answered, With a great summe obteined I this freedome. And
Paul said, But I was free borne.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then straightway
they departed from him which should haue examined him: and the
chiefe captaine also was afraid after he knew that he was a Romane,
&amp; because he had bound him.<note> Or, tortured him.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">On the morrow,
because he would haue knowen the certaintie wherefore he was
accused of the Iewes, he loosed him from his bands, and commanded
the chiefe Priests and all their Councill to appeare, and brought
Paul downe, and set him before them.</ab>



</div>