<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The Apostles desirous to haue the
poore regarded for their bodily sustenance, as also carefull
themselues to dispense the word of God, the foode of the soule: 3
Appoint the office of Deaconship to seuen chosen men. 5 Of whom,
Steuen a man full of faith, &amp; of the holy Ghost, is one. 12 Who
is taken of those, whom he confounded in disputing, 13 and after
falsely accused of blasphemie against the law and the
temple.</head>


<fw>Seuen Deacons.</fw>
<ab n="1">And in those
dayes when the number of the Disciples was multiplied, there arose
a murmuring of the Grecians against the Hebrewes, because their
widowes were neglected in the daily ministration.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then the twelue
called the multitude of the disciples vnto them, and said, It is
not reason that we should leaue the word of God, and serue
tables.</ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore
brethren, looke ye out among you seuen men of honest report, full
of the holy Ghost, and wisedome, whom we may appoint ouer this
businesse.</ab>
<ab n="4">But we will
giue our selues continually to prayer, and to the ministerie of the
word.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
saying pleased the whole multitude: and they chose Steuen, a man
full of faith and of the holy Ghost, and Philip, and Prochorus, and
Nicanor, and Timon, and Permenas, and Nicolas a proselyte of
Antioch.</ab>
<ab n="6">Whom they set
before the Apostles: and when they had praied, they layd their
hands on them.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the word of
God encreased, and the number of the Disciples multiplied in
Hierusalem greatly, and a great company of the Priests were
obedient to the faith.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Steuen full
of faith and power, did great wonders and miracles among the
people.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then
there arose certaine of the Synagogue, which is called the
Synagogue of the Libertines, and Cyrenians, and Alexandrians, and
of them of Cilicia, and of Asia, disputing with Steuen.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they were
not able to resist the wisedome and the spirit by which he
spake.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then they
suborned men which said, We haue heard him speake blasphemous words
against Moses, and against God.</ab>

<fw>Steuen accused.</fw>
<ab n="12">And they
stirred vp the people, and the Elders, and the Scribes, and came
vpon him, and caught him, and brought him to the Councell,</ab>
<ab n="13">And set vp
false witnesses, which said, This man ceaseth not to speake
blasphemous words against this holy place, and the Law.</ab>
<ab n="14">For we haue
heard him say, that this Iesus of Nazareth shall destroy this
place, &amp; shall change the Customes which Moses deliuered
vs.<note> Or, rites.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And all that
sate in the Councell, looking stedfastly on him, saw his face as it
had bene the face of an Angel.</ab>



</div>