<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The Apostles filled with the holy
Ghost, and speaking diuers languages, are admired by some, and
derided by others. 14 Whom Peter disprouing, and shewing that the
Apostles spake by the power of the holy Ghost, that Iesus was risen
from the dead, ascended into heauen, had powred downe the same holy
Ghost, and was the Messias, a man knowen to them to be approued of
God by his miracles, wonders, and signes, and not crucified without
his determinate counsell, and fore knowledge: 37 He baptizeth a
great number that were conuerted. 41 Who afterwards deuoutly, and
charitably conuerse together: the Apostles working many miracles,
and God daily increasing his Church.</head>


<fw>The fiery tongues.</fw>
<ab n="1">And when the
day of Pentecost was fully come, they were all with one accord in
one place.</ab>
<ab n="2">And suddenly
there came a sound from heauen as of a rushing mighty wind, and it
filled all the house where they were sitting.</ab>
<ab n="3">And there
appeared vnto them clouen tongues, like as of fire, and it sate
vpon each of them.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they were
all filled with the holy Ghost, and began to speake with other
tongues, as the spirit gaue them vtterance.</ab>
<ab n="5">And there were
dwelling at Hierusalem Iewes, deuout men, out of euery nation vnder
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now when this
was noised abroad, the multitude came together, and were
confounded, because that euery man heard them speake in his owne
language.<note> Gre. when this voice was made. , Or, troubled in mind.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they were
all amazed, and marueiled, saying one to another, Behold, are not
all these which speake, Galileans?</ab>
<ab n="8">And how heare
we euery man in our owne tongue, wherein we were borne?</ab>
<ab n="9">Parthians, and
Medes, and Elamites, and the dwellers in Mesopotamia, and in Iudea,
and Cappadocia, in Pontus, and Asia,</ab>
<ab n="10">Phrygia, and
Pamphylia, in Egypt, and in the parts of Libya, about Cyrene, &amp;
strangers of Rome, Iewes and Proselites,</ab>
<ab n="11">Cretes, and
Arabians, we doe heare them speake in our tongues the wonderfull
workes of God.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they were
all amazed, and were in doubt, saying one to another, What meaneth
this?</ab>
<ab n="13">Others mocking
said, These men are full of new wine.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ But
Peter standing vp with the eleuen, lift vp his voyce, and said vnto
them, Ye men of Iudea, &amp; all ye that dwell at Hierusalem, be
this knowen vnto you, and hearken to my words:</ab>
<ab n="15">For these are
not drunken, as ye suppose, seeing it is but the third houre of the
day.</ab>
<ab n="16">But this is
that which was spoken by the Prophet Ioel,<note> Ioel.2.28. esai.44.3.</note></ab>

<fw>The day of the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="17">And it shall
come to passe in the last dayes (saith God) I will powre out of my
Spirit vpon all flesh: and your sonnes and your daughters shall
prophesie, and your yong men shall see visions, and your old men
shall dreame dreames:</ab>
<ab n="18">And on my
seruants, and on my handmaidens, I will powre out in those daies of
my Spirit, and they shall prophesie:</ab>
<ab n="19">And I wil shew
wonders in heauen aboue, and signes in the earth beneath: blood,
and fire, and vapour of smoke.</ab>
<ab n="20">The Sunne
shall be turned into darkenesse, and the Moone into blood, before
that great and notable day of the Lord come.<note> Ioel 2.31</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And it shall
come to passe, that whosoeuer shall call on the Name of the Lord,
shalbe saued.<note> Rom.10. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Yee men of
Israel, heare these words, Iesus of Nazareth, a man approued of God
among you, by miracles, wonders, and signes, which God did by him
in the midst of you, as yee your selues also know:</ab>
<ab n="23">Him, being
deliuered by the determinate counsell and foreknowledge of God, yee
haue taken, and by wicked hands, haue crucified, and
slaine:</ab>
<ab n="24">Whom God hath
raised vp, hauing loosed the paines of death: because it was not
possible that hee should be holden of it.</ab>
<ab n="25">For Dauid
speaketh concerning him, I foresaw the Lord alwayes before my face,
for he is on my right hand, that I should not be moued.<note> Psal.16.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore did
my heart reioyce, and my tongue was glad: Moreouer also, my flesh
shall rest in hope,</ab>
<ab n="27">Because thou
wilt not leaue my soule in hell, neither wilt thou suffer thine
Holy one to see corruption.</ab>
<ab n="28">Thou hast made
knowen to mee the wayes of life, thou shalt make mee full of ioy
with thy countenance.</ab>
<ab n="29">Men and
brethren, let me freely speake vnto you of the Patriarch Dauid,
that he is both dead &amp; buried, and his sepulchre is with vs
vnto this day:<note> Or, I may. , 1.King.2. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Therefore
being a Prophet, and knowing that God had sworne with an oath to
him, that of the fruit of his loines, according to the flesh, hee
would raise vp Christ, to sit on his throne:<note> Psal.132. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">He seeing this
before, spake of the resurrection of Christ, that his soule was not
left in hell, neither his flesh did see corruption.<note> Psal.16. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>The heart pricked.</fw>
<ab n="32">This Iesus
hath God raised vp, whereof we all are witnesses.</ab>
<ab n="33">Therefore
being by the right hand of God exalted, and hauing receiued of the
Father the promise of the holy Ghost, he hath shed forth this,
which ye now see and heare.</ab>
<ab n="34">For Dauid is
not ascended into the heauens, but he saith himselfe, The Lord said
vnto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand,<note> Psal.110. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Untill I make
thy foes thy footstoole.</ab>
<ab n="36">Therefore let
all the house of Israel know assuredly, that God hath made that
same Iesus, whom ye haue crucified, both Lord and Christ.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ Now
when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said
vnto Peter, and to the rest of the Apostles, Men and brethren, What
shall we doe?</ab>
<ab n="38">Then Peter
said vnto them, Repent, and be baptized euery one of you in the
Name of Iesus Christ, for the remission of sinnes, and ye shal
receiue the gift of the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="39">For the
promise is vnto you, and to your children, and to all that are
afarre off, euen as many as the Lord our God shall call.</ab>
<ab n="40">And with many
other words did hee testifie and exhort, saying, Saue your selues
from this vntoward generation.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ Then
they that gladly receiued his word, were baptized: and the same day
there were added vnto them about three thousand soules.</ab>
<ab n="42">And they
continued stedfastly in the Apostles doctrine and fellowship, and
in breaking of bread, and in praiers.</ab>
<ab n="43">And feare came
vpon euery soule: and many wonders and signes were done by the
Apostles.</ab>
<ab n="44">And all that
beleeued were together, and had all things common,</ab>
<ab n="45">And solde
their possessions and goods, and parted them to all men, as euery
man had need.</ab>
<ab n="46">And they
continuing daily with one accord in the Temple, and breaking bread
from house to house, did eat their meat with gladnesse and
singlenesse of heart,<note> Or, at home.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Praising God,
and hauing fauour with all the people. And the Lord added to the
Church dayly such as should be saued.</ab>



</div>