<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>2 Paul, in the presence of Agrippa,
declareth his life from his childhood, 12 and how miraculously he
was conuerted, and called to his Apostleship. 24 Festus chargeth
him to be mad, whereunto he answereth modestly. 28 Agrippa is
almost perswaded to be a christian. 31 The whole company pronounce
him innocent.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Agrippa
said vnto Paul, Thou art permitted to speake for thy selfe. Then
Paul stretched foorth the hand, and answered for himselfe,</ab>
<ab n="2">I thinke my
selfe happy, king Agrippa, because I shall answere for my selfe
this day before thee touching all the things whereof I am accused
of the Iewes:</ab>
<ab n="3">Especially,
because I know thee to be expert in all customes and questions
which are among the Iewes: wherefore I beseech thee to heare mee
patiently.</ab>
<ab n="4">My maner of
life from my youth, which was at the first among mine owne nation
at Hierusalem, know all the Iewes,</ab>
<ab n="5">Which knew me
from the beginning, (if they would testifie) that after the most
straitest sect of our religion, I liued a Pharisee.</ab>
<ab n="6">And now I
stand, and am iudged for the hope of the promise made of God vnto
our fathers:</ab>
<ab n="7">Vnto which
promise our twelue tribes instantly seruing God day and night, hope
to come: For which hopes sake, King Agrippa, I am accused of the
Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="8">Why should it
be thought a thing incredible with you, that God should raise the
dead?</ab>
<ab n="9">I verily
thought with my selfe, that I ought to doe many things contrary to
the name of Iesus of Nazareth:</ab>
<ab n="10">Which thing I also
did in Hierusalem, and many of the Saints did I shut vp in prison,
hauing receiued authoritie from the chiefe Priests, and when they
were put to death, I gaue my voyce against them.<note> Chap. 8.3.</note></ab>

<fw>Pauls vision. He is counted
mad.</fw>
<ab n="11">And I punished them
oft in euery Synagogue, and compelled them to blaspheme, and being
exceedingly mad against them, I persecuted them euen vnto strange
cities.</ab>
<ab n="12">Whereupon, as I
went to Damascus, with authoritie and commission from the chiefe
Priests:<note> Chap.9.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">At midday, O king,
I saw in the way a light from heauen, aboue the brightnes of the
Sunne, shining round about mee, and them which iourneyed with
me.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when wee were
all fallen to the earth, I heard a voice speaking vnto me, and
saying in the Hebrew tongue, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me?
It is hard for thee to kicke against the prickes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And I said, Who art
thou, Lord? And hee said, I am Iesus whom thou persecutest.</ab>
<ab n="16">But rise, and stand
vpon thy feete, for I haue appeared vnto thee for this purpose, to
make thee a minister and a witnesse, both of these things which
thou hast seene, &amp; of those things in the which I will appeare
vnto thee,</ab>
<ab n="17">Deliuering thee
from the people, and from the Gentiles, vnto whom now I send
thee,</ab>
<ab n="18">To open their eyes,
and to turne them from darknesse to light, and from the power of
Satan vnto God, that they may receiue forgiuenesse of sinnes, and
inheritance among them which are sanctified by faith that is in
me.</ab>
<ab n="19">Whereupon, O king
Agrippa, I was not disobedient vnto the heauenly vision:</ab>
<ab n="20">But shewed first
vnto them of Damascus, and at Hierusalem, and thorowout all the
coasts of Iudea, and then to the Gentiles, that they should repent
and turne to God, and do works meete for repentance.</ab>
<ab n="21">For these causes
the Iewes caught mee in the Temple, and went about to kill
me.</ab>
<ab n="22">Hauing therefore
obteined helpe of God, I continue vnto this day, witnessing both to
small and great, saying none other things then those which the
Prophets and Moses did say should come:</ab>
<ab n="23">That Christ should
suffer, and that hee should be the first that should rise from the
dead, &amp; should shew light vnto the people, and to the
Gentiles.</ab>

<fw>He is counted mad.</fw>
<ab n="24">And as hee thus
spake for himselfe, Festus saide with a lowd voyce, Paul, thou art
beside thy selfe, much learning doeth make thee mad.</ab>
<ab n="25">But he said, I am
not mad, most noble Festus, but speake foorth the words of trueth
and sobernesse.</ab>
<ab n="26">For the King
knoweth of these things, before whom also I speake freely: for I am
perswaded, that none of these things are hidden from him, for this
thing was not done in a corner.</ab>
<ab n="27">King Agrippa,
beleeuest thou the Prophets? I know that thou beleeuest.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then Agrippa saide
vnto Paul, Almost thou perswadest mee to bee a Christian.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Paul said, I
would to God, that not onely thou, but also all that heare mee this
day, were both almost, and altogether such as I am, except these
bonds.</ab>
<ab n="30">And when hee had
thus spoken, the king rose vp, and the gouernour, and Bernice,
&amp; they that sate with them.</ab>
<ab n="31">And when they were
gone aside, they talked betweene themselues, saying, This man doeth
nothing worthy of death, or of bonds.</ab>
<ab n="32">Then said Agrippa
vnto Festus, This man might haue bene set at libertie, if he had
not appealed vnto Cesar.</ab>



</div>