<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 King Herode persecuteth the
Christians, killeth Iames, and imprisoneth Peter; whome an Angel
deliuereth vpon the prayers of the Church. 20 In his pride taking
to himselfe the honour due to God, he is stricken by an Angel, and
dieth miserably. 24 After his death, the word of God
prospereth.</head>


<fw>Peter imprisoned.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now about that
time, Herode the King stretched foorth his hands, to vexe certaine
of the Church.<note> Or, began.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he killed
Iames the brother of Iohn with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="3">And because he
saw it pleased the Iewes, hee proceeded further, to take Peter
also. (Then were the dayes of vnleauened bread.)</ab>
<ab n="4">And when hee
had apprehended him, hee put him in prison, and deliuered him to
foure quaternions of souldiers to keepe him, intending after Easter
to bring him forth to the people.</ab>
<ab n="5">Peter
therefore was kept in prison, but prayer was made without ceasing
of the Church vnto God for him.<note> Or, instant and earnest prayer was made.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And when
Herode would haue brought him foorth, the same night Peter was
sleeping betweene two Souldiers, bound with two chaines, and the
Keepers before the doore kept the prison.</ab>
<ab n="7">And beholde,
the Angel of the Lord came vpon him, and a light shined in the
prison: and hee smote Peter on the side, and raised him vp, saying,
Arise vp quickely. And his chaines fell off from his hands.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the Angel
said vnto him, Girde thy selfe, and binde on thy sandales: And so
he did. And he sayth vnto him, Cast thy garment about thee, and
follow me.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee went
out, and followed him, and wist not that it was true which was done
by the Angel: but thought he saw a vision.</ab>
<ab n="10">When they were past
the first and the second ward, they came vnto the yron gate that
leadeth vnto the citie, which opened to them of his owne accord:
and they went out and passed on thorow one streete, and foorthwith
the Angel departed from him.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when Peter was
come to himselfe, hee said, Now I know of a suretie, that the Lord
hath sent his Angel, and hath deliuered mee out of the hand of
Herode, and from all the expectation of the people of the
Iewes.</ab>

<fw>Herodes death.</fw>
<ab n="12">And when he had
considered the thing, he came to the house of Mary the mother of
Iohn whose sirname was Marke, where many were gathered together
praying.</ab>
<ab n="13">And as Peter
knocked at the doore of the gate, a damosell came to hearken, named
Rhoda.<note> Or, to aske who was there.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And when she knew
Peters voice, she opened not the gate for gladnes, but ran in, and
told how Peter stood before the gate.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they said vnto
her, Thou art mad. But she constantly affirmed that it was euen so.
Then said they, It it his Angel.</ab>
<ab n="16">But Peter continued
knocking: and when they had opened the doore, and saw him, they
were astonished.</ab>
<ab n="17">But he beckening
vnto them with the hand, to hold their peace, declared vnto them
how the Lord had brought him out of the prison: And he said, Goe
shew these things vnto Iames, and to the brethren. And he departed,
and went into another place.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now assoone as it
was day, there was no smal stirre among the souldiers, what was
become of Peter.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when Herode had
sought for him, and found him not, hee examined the keepers, and
commanded that they should be put to death. And hee went downe from
Iudea to Cesarea, &amp; there abode.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And Herode
was highly displeased with them of Tyre and Sidon: but they came
with one accord to him, and hauing made Blastus the kings
chamberlaine their friend, desired peace, because their countrey
was nourished by the kings countrey.<note> Or, bare an hostile mind intending warre. , Gr. that was ouer the kings bed-chamber.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And vpon a set day
Herod arayed in royall apparell, sate vpon his throne, and made an
Oration vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the people gaue
a shout, saying, It is the voice of a God, and not of a
man.</ab>
<ab n="23">And immediatly the
Angel of the Lord smote him, because hee gaue not God the glory,
and hee was eaten of wormes, and gaue vp the ghost.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ But the word
of God grewe, and multiplied.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Barnabas and
Saul returned from Hierusalem, when they had fulfilled their
ministerie, and tooke with them Iohn, whose syrname was
Marke.<note> Or, charge, chap.11.29, 30.</note></ab>



</div>