<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 God calleth Abram, and blesseth
him with a promise of Christ. 4 He departeth with Lot from Haran. 6
He iourneyeth through Canaan, 7 which is promised him in a vision.
10 Hee is driuen by a famine into Egypt. 11 Feare maketh him faine
his wife to be his sister. 14 Pharaoh hauing taken her from him, by
plagues is compelled to restore her.</head>

<ab n="1">Now the LORD had
said vnto Abram, Get thee out of thy countrey, and from thy kinred,
and from thy fathers house, vnto a land that I will shew
thee.<note> Acts. 7. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And I will make
of thee a great nation, and I wil blesse thee, and make thy name
great; and thou shalt bee a blessing.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I will blesse
them that blesse thee, and curse him, that curseth thee: and in
thee shal all families of the earth be blessed.<note> Chap. 18. 18. and 22. 18. acts. 3. 25. galat. 3. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">So Abram
departed, as the LORD had spoken vnto him, and Lot went with him:
And Abram was seuentie and fiue yeeres old when he departed out of
Haran.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Abram tooke
Sarai his wife, and Lot his brothers sonne, and all their substance
that they had gathered, and the soules that they had gotten in
Haran, and they went foorth to goe into the land of Canaan: and
into the land of Canaan they came.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Abram
passed through the land, vnto the place of Sichem, vnto the plaine
of Moreh. And the Canaanite was then in the land.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the LORD
appeared vnto Abram, and said, Unto thy seed wil I giue this land:
and there builded hee an altar vnto the LORD, who appeared vnto
him.<note> Chap.13. 15. , Chap. 13 4.</note></ab>

<fw>Abram in Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="8">And he remoued
from thence vnto a mountaine, on the East of Beth-el, and pitched
his tent hauing Beth-el on the West, and Hai on the East: and there
hee builded an altar vnto the LORD, and called vpon the Name of the
LORD.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Abram
iourneyed, going on still toward the South.<note> Heb. in going and iourneying.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And there
was a famine in the land, and Abram went downe into Egypt, to
soiourne there: for the famine was grieuous in the land.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it came to
passe when he was come neere to enter into Egypt, that he said vnto
Sarai his wife, Behold now, I know that thou art a faire woman to
looke vpon.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore it
shall come to passe, when the Egyptians shall see thee, that they
shall say, This is his wife: and they will kill me, but they will
saue thee aliue.</ab>
<ab n="13">Say, I pray
thee, thou art my sister, that it may be wel with me, for thy sake;
and my soule shall liue, because of thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And it
came to passe, that when Abram was come into Egypt, the Egyptians
beheld the woman, that shee was very faire.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Princes also
of Pharaoh saw her, and commended her before Pharaoh: and the woman
was taken into Pharaohs house.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he entreated
Abram well for her sake: and he had sheepe, and oxen, and hee
asses, and men seruants, and maid seruants, and shee asses, and
camels.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the LORD
plagued Pharaoh &amp; his house with great plagues, because of
Sarai Abrams wife.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Pharaoh
called Abram, and said, What is this that thou hast done vnto me?
Why diddest thou not tell me, that she was thy wife?</ab>
<ab n="19">Why saidest
thou, Shee is my sister? so I might haue taken her to mee to wife:
now therfore behold, thy wife, take her and goe thy way.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Pharaoh
cōmanded his men concerning him: and they sent him away, and
his wife, and all that he had.</ab>



</div>