<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Christ preparing his Apostles to
the beholding of his ascension, gathereth them together into the
mount Oliuet, commandeth them to expect in Hierusalem the sending
downe of the holy Ghost, promiseth after fewe dayes to send it: by
vertue whereof they should be witnesses vnto him euen to the vtmost
parts of the earth. 9 After his ascension they are warned by two
Angels to depart, and to set their mindes vpon his second comming.
12 They accordingly returne, and giuing themselues to prayer, chuse
Matthias Apostle in the place of Iudas.</head>

<ab n="1">The former
treatise haue I made, O Theophilus, of al that Iesus began both to
doe and teach,</ab>
<ab n="2">Untill the day
in which hee was taken vp, after that he through the holy Ghost had
giuen commaundements vnto the Apostles, whom he had chosen.</ab>
<ab n="3">To whom also he
shewed himselfe aliue after his passion, by many infallible
proofes, being seene of them fourty dayes, and speaking of the
things perteining to the kingdome of God:</ab>
<ab n="4">And being
assembled together with them, commanded them that they should not
depart from Hierusalem, but wait for the promise of the Father,
which, saith he, ye haue heard of me.<note> Or, eating together with them. , Luke 24. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For Iohn truely
baptized with water, but ye shall be baptized with the holy Ghost,
not many dayes hence.<note> Matth.3. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">When they
therefore were come together, they asked of him, saying, Lord, wilt
thou at this time restore againe the kingdome to Israel?</ab>

<fw>The Ascension of Christ.</fw>
<ab n="7">And he said
vnto them, It is not for you to knowe the times or the seasons,
which the Father hath put in his owne power.</ab>
<ab n="8">But ye shall
receiue power after that the holy Ghost is come vpon you, and ye
shall be witnesses vnto me, both in Hierusalem, and in all Iudea,
and in Samaria, and vnto the vttermost part of the
earth.<note> Chap.2.1. , Or, the power of the holy Ghost comming vpon you.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And when hee
had spoken these things, while they beheld, hee was taken vp, and a
cloud receiued him out of their sight.<note> Luke 24. 51.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And while they
looked stedfastly toward heauen, as he went vp, behold, two men
stood by them in white apparell,</ab>
<ab n="11">Which also
said, Yee men of Galililee, why stand yee gazing vp into heauen?
This same Iesus, which is taken vp from you into heauen, shall so
come, in like maner as yee haue seene him goe into heauen.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then returned
they vnto Hierusalem, from the mount called Oliuet, which is from
Hierusalem a Sabbath dayes iourney.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when they
were come in, they went vp into an vpper roome, where abode both
Peter &amp; Iames, &amp; Iohn, and Andrew, Philip, and Thomas,
Bartholomew, and Matthew, Iames the sonne of Alpheus, and Simon
Zelotes, and Iudas the brother of Iames.</ab>
<ab n="14">These all
continued with one accord in prayer and supplication, with the
women, and Mary the mother of Iesus, and with his brethen.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And in
those dayes Peter stood vp in the mids of the disciples, and said,
(The number of names together were about an hundred and
twentie)</ab>
<ab n="16">Men and
brethren, This Scripture must needs haue beene fulfilled, which the
holy Ghost by the mouth of Dauid spake before concerning Iudas,
which was guide to them þt took Iesus.<note> Psal.41.9.</note></ab>

<fw>Matthias chosen.</fw>
<ab n="17">For hee was
numbred with vs, and had obtained part of this ministerie.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now this man
purchased a field with the reward of iniquity, and falling
headlong, he burst asunder in the mids, and all his bowels gushed
out.<note> Mat.27.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And it was
knowen vnto all the dwellers at Hierusalem, insomuch as that field
is called in their proper tongue, Aceldama, that is to say, The
field of blood.</ab>
<ab n="20">For it is
written in the booke of Psalmes, Let his habitation be desolate,
and let no man dwell therein: And his Bishopricke let another
take.<note> Psal.69. 26. , Psal.109. 7. , Or, office: or, charge.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Wherefore of
these men which haue companied with vs all the time that the Lord
Iesus went in and out among vs,</ab>
<ab n="22">Beginning from
the baptisme of Iohn, vnto that same day that he was taken vp from
vs, must one be ordained to be a witnesse with vs of his
resurrection.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they
appointed two, Ioseph called Barsabas, who was surnamed Iustus, and
Matthias.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they
prayed, and said, Thou Lord, which knowest the hearts of all men,
shew whether of these two thou hast chosen,</ab>
<ab n="25">That hee may
take part of this ministerie and Apostleship, from which Iudas by
transgression fell, that hee might goe to his owne place.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they gaue
foorth their lots, and the lot fell vpon Matthias, and hee was
numbred with the eleuen Apostles.</ab>



</div>