<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CActs_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Acts-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>2 The Iewes accuse Paul before
Festus. 8 He answereth for himselfe, 11 and appealeth vnto Cesar.
14 Afterwards, Festus openeth his matter to king Agryppa, 23 and he
is brought forth. 25 Festus cleareth him to haue done nothing
worthy of death.</head>


<fw>Pauls appeale.</fw>
<ab n="1">Nowe when
Festus was come into the prouince, after three dayes he ascended
frō Cesarea to Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then the high
Priest, and the chiefe of the Iewes informed him against Paul, and
besought him,</ab>
<ab n="3">And desired
fauour against him, that he would send for him to Hierusalem,
laying wait in the way to kill him.</ab>
<ab n="4">But Festus
answered, that Paul should be kept at Cesarea, and that hee
himselfe would depart shortly thither.</ab>
<ab n="5">Let them
therefore, said he, which among you are able, go downe with me, and
accuse this man, if there be any wickednesse in him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And when hee
had taried among them more then ten dayes, hee went downe vnto
Cesarea, and the next day sitting in the iudgement seat, commanded
Paul to be brought.<note> Or, as some copies reade, no more then eight or ten dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And when hee
was come, the Iewes which came downe from Hierusalem, stood round
about, and laide many and grieuous complaints against Paul, which
they could not proue,</ab>
<ab n="8">While hee
answered for himselfe, Neither against the law of the Iewes,
neither against the Temple, nor yet against Cesar, haue I offended
any thing at all.</ab>
<ab n="9">But Festus
willing to doe the Iewes a pleasure, answered Paul, and said, Wilt
thou goe vp to Hierusalem, and there be iudged of these things
before me?</ab>
<ab n="10">Then said Paul, I
stand at Cesars iudgement seat, where I ought to bee iudged; to the
Iewes haue I done no wrong, as thou very well knowest.</ab>
<ab n="11">For if I be an
offender, or haue committed any thing worthy of death, I refuse not
to die: but if there be none of these things whereof these accuse
me, no man may deliuer me vnto them. I appeale vnto Cesar.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then Festus when he
had conferred with the Councill, answered, Hast thou appealed vnto
Cesar? vnto Cesar shalt thou goe.</ab>
<ab n="13">And after certaine
dayes, king Agrippa and Bernice, came vnto Cesarea, to salute
Festus.</ab>

<fw>King Agrippa heareth Paul.</fw>
<ab n="14">And when they had
beene there many dayes, Festus declared Pauls cause vnto the king,
saying, There is a certaine man left in bonds by Felix:</ab>
<ab n="15">About whom when I
was at Hierusalem, the chiefe Priests and the Elders of the Iewes
enformed me, desiring to haue iudgement against him.</ab>
<ab n="16">To whom I answered,
It is not the maner of the Romanes to deliuer any man to die,
before that he which is accused, haue the accusers face to face,
and haue licence to answere for himselfe concerning the crime laid
against him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Therefore when they
were come hither, without any delay, on the morrow I sate on the
iudgement seate, and cōmanded the man to be brought
forth.</ab>
<ab n="18">Against whom when
the accusers stood vp, they brought none accusation of such things
as I supposed:</ab>
<ab n="19">But had certaine
questions against him of their owne superstition, and of one Iesus,
which was dead, whom Paul affirmed to be aliue.</ab>
<ab n="20">And because I
doubted of such maner of questions, I asked him whether he would
goe to Hierusalem, and there be iudged of these
matters.<note> Or, I was doubtfull how to inquire heereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But when Paul had
appealed to bee reserued vnto the hearing of Augustus, I commanded
him to be kept, till I might send him to Cesar.<note> Or, iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then Agrippa said
vnto Festus, I would also heare the man my selfe. To morrow, said
he, thou shalt heare him.</ab>
<ab n="23">And on the morrow
when Agrippa was come and Bernice, with great pompe, and was entred
into the place of hearing, with the chiefe captaines, and
principall men of the citie; at Festus commaundement Paul was
brought foorth.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Festus said,
King Agrippa, and all men which are heere present with vs, ye see
this man, about whom all the multitude of the Iewes haue dealt with
me, both at Hierusalem, and also heere, crying that he ought not to
liue any longer.</ab>
<ab n="25">But when I found
that he had committed nothing worthy of death, and that he himselfe
hath appealed to Augustus, I haue determined to send him.</ab>

<fw>King Agrippa heareth Paul.</fw>
<ab n="26">Of whom I haue no
certaine thing to write vnto my Lord: Wherefore I haue brought him
foorth before you, and specially before thee, O king Agrippa, that
after examination had, I might haue somewhat to write.</ab>
<ab n="27">For it seemeth to
me vnreasonable, to send a prisoner, and not withall to signifie
the crimes laid against him.</ab>



</div>