<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CAmos_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The wantonnes of Israel, 7 shalbe
plagued with desolation, 12 and their incorrigiblenes.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to them
that are at ease in Zion, and trust in the mountaine of Samaria,
which are named chiefe of the nations, to whom the house of Israel
came.<note> Luke 6. 24. , Or, are secure. , Exod. 19. 5. , Or, first fruits.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Passe ye vnto
Calneh, and see, and from thence go ye to Hemath the great: then
goe downe to Gath of the Philistines: bee they better then these
kingdomes? or their border greater then your border?</ab>
<ab n="3">Ye that put
farre away the euil day, and cause the seat of violence to come
neere:<note> Exek.12. 27. , Chap. 5. 18. , Or, habitation.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">That lie vpon
beds of Yuorie, and stretch themselues vpon their couches, and eate
the lambes out of the flocke, and the calues out of the midst of
the stall:<note> Or, abound with superfluities.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">That chaunt to
the sound of the Uiole, and inuent to themselues instruments of
musicke, like Dauid:<note> Or, quauer.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">That drinke
wine in bowles, and anoint themselues with the chiefe ointments:
but they are not grieued for the affliction of Ioseph.<note> Or, in bowles of wine. , Hebr. breach.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶
Therefore now shall they goe captiue, with the first that goe
captiue, and the banquet of them that stretched themselues, shalbe
remoued.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord God
hath sworne by himselfe, saith the Lord the God of hostes, I
abhorre the excellencie of Iacob, and hate his palaces: therefore
wil I deliuer vp the citie, with all that is therein.<note> Iere. 52. 14. , Hebr. the fulnes thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall
come to passe, if there remaine tenne men in one house, that they
shall die.</ab>
<ab n="10">And a mans
vncle shall take him vp, and he that burneth him, to bring out the
bones out of the house, and shall say vnto him that is by the sides
of the house; Is there yet any with thee? and hee shall say, No.
Then shall he say, Holde thy tongue: for wee may not make mention
of the Name of the Lord.<note> Chap.5. 13. , Or, they will not, or haue not.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels wantonnesse is
threatned.</fw>
<ab n="11">For beholde,
the Lord commandeth, and hee will smite the great house with
breaches, and the little house with clefts.<note> Or, droppings.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Shall
horses runne vpon the rocke? wil one plow there with oxen? for ye
haue turned iudgement into gall, and the fruite of righteousnesse
into hemlocke.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yee which
reioyce in a thing of nought, which say, Haue we not taken to vs
hornes by our owne strength?</ab>
<ab n="14">But beholde, I
wil raise vp against you a nation, O house of Israel, saith the
Lord, the God of hostes, and they shall afflict you from the
entring in of Hemath, vnto the riuer of the
wildernesse.<note> Or, valley.</note></ab>



</div>