<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CAmos_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 The iudgements of the grashoppers,
4 and of the fire, are diuerted hy the prayer of Amos. 7 By the
wall of a plumb-line, is signified the reiection of Israel. 10
Amaziah complaineth of Amos. 14 Amos sheweth his calling, 16 and
Amaziahs iudgement.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus hath the
Lord God shewed vnto me, and behold, he formed grassehoppers in the
beginning of the shooting vp of the latter grouth: and loe, it was
the latter grouth after the kings mowings.<note> Or greene-wormes.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it came to
passe, that when they had made an ende of eating the grasse of the
land, then I said; O Lord God, forgiue, I beseech thee, by whom
shal Iacob arise? for he is small.<note> Or, who of (or for) Iacob shall stand?</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The Lord
repented for this. It shall not be, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Thus
hath the Lord God shewed vnto me; and behold, the Lord God called
to contend by fire, and it deuoured the great deepe, and did eate
vp a part.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then said I, O
Lord God , cease, I beseech thee, by whom shal Iacob arise? for he
is small.</ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord
repented for this. This also shall not bee, saith the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Thus hee
shewed mee, and behold, the Lord stood vpon a wall made by a
plumbline, with a plumbline in his hand.</ab>

<fw>Amos is accused.</fw>
<ab n="8">And the Lord
said vnto mee, Amos, what seest thou? And I sayd, A plumb-line.
Then sayd the Lord, Behold, I will set a plumb-line in the midst of
my people Israel, I will not againe passe by them any more.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the high
places of Isaac shall be desolate, and the Sanctuaries of Israel
shalbe laide waste: and I will rise against the house of Ieroboam
with the sword.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Then
Amaziah the Priest of Beth-el sent to Ieroboam king of Israel,
saying; Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst of the house
of Israel: the land is not able to beare all his words.</ab>
<ab n="11">For thus Amos
saith, Ieroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall surely be
led away captiue, out of their owne land.</ab>
<ab n="12">Also Amaziah
said vnto Amos, O thou Seer, goe, flee thee away into the land of
Iudah, and there eate bread, and prophecie there.</ab>
<ab n="13">But prophecie
not againe any more at Beth-el: for it is the Kings Chappell, and
it is the Kings Court.<note> Or, Sanctuarie. , Heb. house of the kingdome.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then
answered Amos, and sayde to Amaziah; I was no Prophet, neither was
I a Prophets sonne, but I was an heardman, and a gatherer of
Sycomore fruit.<note> Or, wilde figges.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the Lord
tooke me as I followed the flocke, and the Lord said vnto me, Goe,
prophecie vnto my people Israel.<note> Heb. from behind.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Now
therefore heare thou the worde of the Lord; Thou sayest, Prophecie
not against Israel, and drop not thy word against the house of
Isaac.<note> Eze.21.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Therfore thus
sayth the Lord; Thy wife shall be an harlot in the city, and thy
sonnes and thy daughters shall fall by the sword, and thy land
shall be diuided by line: and thou shalt die in a polluted land,
and Israel shall surely goe into captiuitie foorth of his
land.</ab>



</div>