<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CAmos_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 By a basket of Summer fruite, is
shewed the propinquitie of Israels end. 4 Oppression is reproued.
11 A famine of the word threatned.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus hath the
Lord God shewed vnto me, and beholde, a basket of Summer
fruit.</ab>

<fw>Summer fruit.</fw>
<ab n="2">And he said,
Amos, what seest thou? And I sayde, A basket of Summer fruite. Then
said the Lord vnto mee, The ende is come vpon my people of Israel;
I will not againe passe by them anymore.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the songs
of the Temples shalbe howlings in that day, sayth the Lord God:
there shall be many dead bodies in euery place, they shall cast
them foorth with silence.<note> Heb. shall howle. , Heb. be silent.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Heare
this, O ye that swallow vp the needy, euen to make the poore of the
land to faile,</ab>
<ab n="5">Saying, When
will the newe Moone be gone, that we may sell corne? and the
Sabbath, that wee may set forth wheat, making the Ephah small, and
the shekel great, and falsifying the balances by
deceit?<note> Or, moneth. , Heb. open. , Heb. peruerting the balances of deceit.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">That wee may
buy the poore for siluer, &amp; the needie for a paire of shoes;
yea, and sell the refuse of the wheate?<note> Chap.2.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The Lord hath
sworne by the excellencie of Iacob, Surely I will neuer forget any
of their workes.</ab>
<ab n="8">Shall not the
land tremble for this, and euery one mourne that dwelleth therein?
and it shall rise vp wholly as a flood; and it shall be cast out
and drowned, as by the flood of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall
come to passe in that day, saith the Lord God, that I will cause
the Sunne to go downe at noone, and I will darken the earth in the
cleare day.</ab>
<ab n="10">And I will
turne your feasts into mourning, and all your songs into
lamentation, and I will bring vp sackcloth vpon all loynes, and
baldnesse vpon euery head: and I will make it as the mourning of an
onely sonne, and the end thereof as a bitter day.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Behold,
the daies come, saith the Lord God, that I will send a famine in
the land, not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for water, but of
hearing the words of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they shall
wander from Sea to Sea, and from the North euen to the East they
shall runne to and fro, to seeke the worde of the Lord, and shall
not finde it.</ab>
<ab n="13">In that day
shall the faire virgines and young men faint for thirst.</ab>
<ab n="14">They that
sweare by the sinne of Samaria, and say, Thy God, O Dan, liueth,
and the manner of Beer-sheba liueth, euen they shall fall, and
neuer rise vp againe.</ab>



</div>