<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CAmos_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 He reproueth Israel, for
oppression. 4 for idolatry, 6 and for their
incorrigiblenesse.</head>


<fw>Israels obstinacie.</fw>
<ab n="1">Heare this word
yea kine of Bashan, that are in the mountaine of Samaria, which
oppresse the poore, which crush the needy, which say to their
masters; Bring, and let vs drinke.</ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord God
hath sworne by his holinesse, that loe, the dayes shall come vpon
you, that he will take you away with hookes, and your posteritie
with fish-hookes.</ab>
<ab n="3">And yee shall
goe out at the breaches, euery Cow at that which is before her, and
yee shall cast them into the palace, saith the Lord.<note> Or, yee shall cast away the things of the palace.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Come to
Bethel and transgresse, at Gilgal multiplie transgression; and
bring your sacrifices euery morning, and your tithes after three
yeeres.<note> Heb. three yeeres of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And offer a
sacrifice of thanksgiuing with leauen, and proclaime and publish
the free offrings; for this liketh you, O yee children of Israel,
saith the Lord God.<note> Heb. offer by burning. , Heb. so yee loue.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And I
also haue giuen you cleannesse of teeth in all your cities, and
want of bread in all your places: yet haue yee not returned vnto
me, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">And also I haue
withholden the raine from you, when there were yet three moneths to
the haruest, and I caused it to raine vpon one citie, and caused it
not to raine vpon an other city: one piece was rained vpon, &amp;
the piece wherupon it rained not, withered.</ab>
<ab n="8">So two or three
cities wandered vnto one citie, to drinke water; but they were not
satisfied: yet haue yee not returned vnto me, saith the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">I haue smitten
you with blasting and mildew; when your gardens and your vineyards,
and your fig trees, and your oliue trees increased, the palmer
worme deuoured them: yet haue yee not returned vnto me, saith the
Lord.<note> Or, the multitude of your gardens &amp;c: did the palmer worme &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">I haue sent
among you the pestilence, after the maner of Egypt: your yongmen
haue I slain with the sword, and haue taken away your horses, &amp;
I haue made the stinke of your campes to come vp vnto your
nostrils, yet haue ye not returned vnto me, saith the
Lord.<note> Or, in the way. , Heb. with the captiuitie of your horses.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">I haue
ouerthrowen some of you, as God ouerthrew Sodome &amp; Gomorrah,
and yee were as a firebrand pluckt out of the burning: yet haue yee
not returned vnto me, saith the Lord.<note> Gen.19. 24.</note></ab>

<fw>Seeke the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="12">Therefore thus
will I doe vnto thee, O Israel: and because I will doe this vnto
thee, prepare to meete thy God, O Israel.</ab>
<ab n="13">For loe, he
that formeth the mountaines, and createth the wind, and declareth
vnto man, what is his thought, that maketh the morning darkenesse,
and treadeth vpon the high places of the earth: the Lord, the God
of hostes is his Name.<note> Or, spirit.</note></ab>



</div>