<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CAmos_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Amos-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 A Lamentation for Israel. 4 An
exhortation to repentance. 21 God reiecteth their hypocriticall
seruice.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare ye this
word which I take vp against you, euen a lamentation, O house of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">The virgin of
Israel is fallen, she shall no more rise: she is forsaken vpon her
land, there is none to raise her vp.</ab>
<ab n="3">For thus saith
the Lord God, The citie that went out by a thousand, shall leaue an
hundred, and that which went foorth by an hundred, shall leaue ten
to the house of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ For thus
saith the Lord vnto the house of Israel, Seeke ye mee, and ye shall
liue.</ab>
<ab n="5">But seeke not
Bethel, nor enter into Gilgal and passe not to Beer-sheba: for
Gilgal shall surely goe into captiuitie, and Bethel shal come to
nought.<note> Ier.4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Seeke the Lord,
and ye shall liue, lest hee breake out like fire in the house of
Ioseph and deuoure it, and there be none to quench it in
Bethel,</ab>
<ab n="7">Ye who turne
iudgment to wormwood, and leaue off righteousnesse in the
earth:</ab>
<ab n="8">Seeke him that
maketh the seuen starres and Orion, and turneth the shadow of death
into the morning, and maketh the day darke with night: that calleth
for the waters of the Sea, and powreth them out vpon the face of
the earth: the Lord is his Name.<note> Iob.9.9. and 38. 31. , Chap.9.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">That
strengtheneth the spoiled against the strong: so that the spoiled
shall come against the fortresse.<note> Heb. spoile.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They hate him
that rebuketh in the gate: and they abhorre him that speaketh
vprightly.</ab>

<fw>Loue the good.</fw>
<ab n="11">Forasmuch
therfore as your treading is vpon the poore, and ye take from him
burdens of wheate, ye haue built houses of hewen stone, but ye
shall not dwell in them: yee haue planted pleasant vineyards, but
ye shall not drinke wine of them.<note> Zeph.1. 13. , Heb. vineyards of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For I know
your manifold transgressions, and your mighty sinnes: they afflict
the iust, they take a bribe, and they turne aside the poore in the
gate from their right.<note> Or, a ransome.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore the
prudent shall keepe silence in that time, for it is an euill
time.</ab>
<ab n="14">Seeke good and
not euill, that ye may liue: and so the Lord, the God of hosts
shall be with you, as yee haue spoken.</ab>
<ab n="15">Hate the
euill, and loue the good, and establish iudgement in the gate: it
may be that the Lord God of hostes will bee gracious vnto the
remnant of Ioseph.<note> Psal.74. 15. &amp; 79. 10. rom. 12. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore the
Lord, the God of hostes, the Lord saith thus: Wailing shall be in
all streets, and they shall say in all the high wayes, Alas, Alas:
and they shall call the husbandman to mourning, and such as are
skilful of lamentation, to wailing.</ab>
<ab n="17">And in all
vineyards shall be wailing: for I will passe through thee, saith
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">Woe vnto you
that desire the day of the Lord: to what ende is it for you? the
day of the Lord is darknes and not light.<note> Isai. 5. 19. ier.30.7. ioel 2.2. zeph. 1. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">As if a man
did flee from a lyon, and a beare met him, or went into the house,
and leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent bit him.</ab>
<ab n="20">Shall not the
day of the Lord be darkenes, and not light? euen very darke, and no
brightnesse in it?</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ I hate,
I despise your feast dayes, and I will not smell in your solemne
assemblies.<note> Isa.1.11. ier.6.20. , Or, smell your holy dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Though ye
offer me burnt offerings, and your meat offerings, I will not
accept them: neither will I regard the peace offerings of your fat
beasts.<note> Or, thanke offerings.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Take thou away
from mee the noise of thy songs: for I will not heare the melodie
of thy violes.</ab>
<ab n="24">But let
iudgement run downe as waters, and righteousnesse as a mightie
streame.<note> Heb. roule.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Haue yee
offered vnto mee sacrifices and offerings in the wildernesse
fourtie yeeres, O house of Israel?<note> Acts 7.42</note></ab>

<fw>Israels wantonnesse is
threatned.</fw>
<ab n="26">But yee haue
borne the tabernacle of your Moloch, and Chiun your images, the
starre of your god, which ye made to your selues.<note> Or, Siccuth your king.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Therefore wil
I cause you to go into captiuitie beyond Damascus, saith the Lord,
whose Name is the God of hostes.</ab>



</div>