<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CBaruch_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>3 The rest of their prayer &amp;
confession contained in that book, which Baruch writ and sent to
Hierusalem. 30 Wisdome was shewed first to Iacob, and was seene
vpon the earth.</head>

<ab n="1">O Lord
almighty, God of Israel, the soule in anguish, the troubled spirit
crieth vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">Heare O Lord,
and haue mercy: for thou art mercifull, and haue pitty vpon vs,
because we haue sinned before thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">For thou
endurest for euer, and we perish vtterly.</ab>
<ab n="4">O Lord
almighty, thou God of Israel, heare now the prayers of the dead
Israelites, and of their children, which haue sinned before thee,
and not hearkened vnto the voice of thee their God: for the which
cause these plagues cleaue vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="5">Remember not
the iniquities of our forefathers: but thinke vpon thy power and
thy name, now at this time.</ab>
<ab n="6">For thou art
the Lord our God, and thee, O Lord, will we praise.</ab>
<ab n="7">And for this
cause thou hast put thy feare in our hearts, to the intent that we
should call vpon thy name, and praise thee in our captiuity: for we
haue called to minde all the iniquity of our forefathers that
sinned before thee.<note> Deu. 30.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Behold, we
are yet this day in our captiuity, where thou hast scattered vs,
for a reproch and a curse, and to be subiect to payments, according
to all the iniquities of our fathers which departed from the Lord
our God.</ab>
<ab n="9">Heare,
Israel, the commandements of life, giue eare to vnderstand
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="10">How happeneth it,
Israel, that thou art in thine enemies land, that thou art waxen
old in a strange countrey, that thou art defiled with the
dead?</ab>
<ab n="11">That thou art
counted with them that goe downe into the graue?</ab>
<ab n="12">Thou hast forsaken
the fountaine of wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="13">For if thou hadst
walked in the way of God, thou shouldest haue dwelled in peace for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="14">Learne where is
wisedome, where is strength, where is vnderstanding, that thou
mayest know also where is length of daies, and life, where is the
light of the eyes and peace.</ab>
<ab n="15">Who hath found out
her place? or who hath come into her treasures?<note> Iob. 28. 12.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Where are the
princes of the heathen become, and such as ruled the beasts vpon
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">They that had
their pastime with the foules of the aire, and they that hoorded vp
siluer and gold wherein men trust, and made no end of their
getting?</ab>
<ab n="18">For they that
wrought in siluer, and were so carefull, and whose workes are
vnsearchable,</ab>
<ab n="19">They are vanished,
and gone downe to the graue, and others are come vp in their
steads.</ab>
<ab n="20">Young men haue
seene light, and dwelt vpon the earth: but the way of knowledge
haue they not knowen,</ab>
<ab n="21">Nor vnderstood the
pathes thereof; nor laid hold of it: their children were farre off
from that way.</ab>
<ab n="22">It hath not beene
heard of in Chanaan: neither hath it beene seene in Theman.</ab>
<ab n="23">The Agarenes that
seek wisdome vpon earth, the marchants of Merran, and of Theman,
the authors of fables, and searchers out of vnderstanding: none of
these haue knowen the way of wisedome, or remember her
pathes.<note> Or, expounders.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">O Israel, how
great is the house of God? and how large is the place of his
possession?</ab>
<ab n="25">Great, and hath
none end: high, and vnmeasurable.</ab>
<ab n="26">There were the
gyants, famous from the beginning, that were of so great stature,
and so expert in warre.</ab>
<ab n="27">Those did not the
Lord chuse, neither gaue he the way of knowledge vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="28">But they were
destroyed, because they had no wisedome, and perished through their
owne foolishnesse.</ab>
<ab n="29">Who hath gone vp
into heauen and taken her, and brought her downe from the
clouds?</ab>
<ab n="30">Who hath gone ouer
the Sea, and found her, &amp; wil bring her for pure gold?</ab>
<ab n="31">No man knoweth her
way, nor thinketh of her path.</ab>
<ab n="32">But he that
knoweth all things, knoweth her, and hath found her out with his
vnderstanding: he that prepared the earth for euermore, hath filled
it with fourefooted beasts.</ab>
<ab n="33">He that sendeth
forth light, and it goeth: calleth it againe, and it obeyeth him
with feare.</ab>
<ab n="34">The starres shined
in their watches, and reioyced: when he calleth them, they say,
Here we be, and so with cheerefulnesse they shewed light vnto him
that made them.</ab>
<ab n="35">This is our God,
and there shall none other be accounted of in comparison of
him.</ab>
<ab n="36">He hath found out
all the way of knowledge, and hath giuen it vnto Iacob his seruant,
&amp; to Israel his beloued.</ab>
<ab n="37">Afterward did he
shew himselfe vpon earth, and conuersed with men.<note> Pro.8.31. Iohn 1.14.</note></ab>



</div>