<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CBaruch_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>The prayer and confession which the
Iewes at Babylon made, and sent in that booke vnto the brethren in
Ierusalem.</head>

<ab n="1">Therefore the
Lord hath made good his worde, which hee pronounced against vs, and
against our Iudges that iudged Israel, and against our kings, and
against our princes, and against the men of Israel and
Iuda,</ab>
<ab n="2">To bring vpon
vs great plagues, such as neuer happened vnder the whole heauen, as
it came to passe in Ierusalem, according to the things that were
written in the Law of Moses,</ab>
<ab n="3">That a man
should eat the flesh of his owne sonne, and the flesh of his owne
daughter.<note> Deut.28. 53.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Moreouer, he
hath deliuered them to be in subiection to all the kingdomes that
are round about vs, to be as a reproch and desolation among all the
people round about, where the Lord hath scattered them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Thus wee were
cast downe and not exalted, because wee haue sinned against the
Lord our God, and haue not beene obedient vnto his
voice.<note> Gr. were beneath and not aboue.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">To the Lord
our God appertaineth righteousnesse: but vnto vs and to our fathers
open shame, as appeareth this day.<note> Cha. 1. 15</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For all these
plagues are come vpon vs, which the Lord hath pronounced against
vs,</ab>
<ab n="8">Yet haue we
not prayed before the Lord, þ<note/> we might turne euery
one from the imaginations of his wicked heart.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore the
Lord watched ouer vs for euill, and the Lord hath brought it vpon
vs: for the Lord is righteous in all his works, which he hath
commanded vs.</ab>
<ab n="10">Yet we haue not
hearkened vnto his voice, to walk in the cōmandements of the
Lord, that he hath set before vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">And now O Lord God
of Israel, that hast brought thy people out of the land of Egypt
with a mighty hand, and high arme, and with signes &amp; with
wonders, &amp; with great power, and hast gotten thy selfe a name,
as appeareth this day:<note> Dan. 9.15</note></ab>
<ab n="12">O Lord our God, we
haue sinned, we haue done vngodly, wee haue dealt vnrighteously in
all thine ordinances.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let thy wrath
turne from vs: for we are but a few left among the heathen, where
thou hast scattered vs.</ab>
<ab n="14">Heare our prayers,
O Lord, and our petitions, and deliuer vs for thine owne sake, and
giue vs fauour in the sight of them which haue led vs away:</ab>
<ab n="15">That all the earth
may know that thou art þ<note/> Lord our God, because
Israel &amp; his posterity is called by thy name.<note> Gr. thy name is called vpon Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">O Lord looke downe
from thy holy house, &amp; consider vs: bow downe thine eare, O
Lord, to heare vs.<note> Deut.26. 15. esa.63. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Open thine eyes
and behold: for the dead that are in the graues, whose soules are
taken from their bodies, wil giue vnto the Lord neither praise nor
righteousnesse.<note> Psal. 6.5. and 115.17 esa. 38.18. 19. , Gr. spirit or life.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">But
þ<note/> soule that is greatly vexed, which goeth
stouping &amp; feeble, and the eyes that faile, and the hungry
soule wil giue thee praise &amp; righteousnes O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="19">Therfore wee doe
not make our humble supplication before thee, O Lord our God, for
the righteousnes of our fathers, and of our kings.<note> Dan.9.20</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For thou hast sent
out thy wrath &amp; indignation vpon vs, as thou hast spoken by thy
seruants þ<note/> prophets, saying,</ab>
<ab n="21">Thus saith the
Lord, bow down your shoulders to serue the king of Babylon: so
shall ye remaine in the lande that I gaue vnto your
fathers.<note> Ier.27.7,8</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But if ye will not
heare the voice of the Lord to serue þ<note/> king of
Babylon,</ab>
<ab n="23">I will cause to
cease out of the cities of Iuda, and from without Ierusalem the
voice of mirth, and the voice of ioy: the voice of the bridegrome,
and the voice of the bride, and the whole land shall be desolate of
inhabitants.</ab>
<ab n="24">But we would not
hearken vnto thy voyce, to serue the king of Babylon: therefore
hast thou made good the wordes that thou spakest by thy seruants
the prophets, namely that the bones of our kings, and the bones of
our fathers should be taken out of their places.</ab>
<ab n="25">And loe, they are
cast out to the heat of the day, and to the frost of the night, and
they died in great miseries, by famine, by sword, and by
pestilence.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the house
which is called by thy name (hast thou laid waste) as it is to be
seene this day, for the wickednesse of the house of Israel, and the
house of Iuda.</ab>
<ab n="27">O Lord our God,
thou hast dealt with vs after all thy goodnesse, and according to
all that great mercie of thine.</ab>
<ab n="28">As thou spakest by
thy seruant Moses in the day when thou didst command him to write
thy Law, before the children of Israel, saying,</ab>
<ab n="29">If ye will not
heare my voyce, surely this very great multitude shalbe turned into
a smal [number] among the nations, where I will scatter
them.<note> Leuit. 26. 14. deut.28 15. , Gr. this great swarme.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">For I knew that
they would not heare me: because it is a stiffenecked people: but
in the land of their captiuities, they shall remember
themselues,<note> Or, come to themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And shall know
that I am the Lord their God: For I giue them an heart, and eares
to heare.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they shal
praise me in the land of their captiuitie, and thinke vpon my
name,</ab>
<ab n="33">And returne from
their stiffe neck, and from their wicked deeds: for they shal
remember the way of their fathers which sinned before the
Lord.<note> Gr. backe.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And I will bring
them againe into the land which I promised with an oath vnto their
fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, and they shall bee lords of it,
and I will increase them, and they shall not be diminished.</ab>
<ab n="35">And I will make an
euerlasting couenant with them, to be their God, and they shall be
my people: and I will no more driue my people of Israel out of the
land that I haue giuen them.</ab>



</div>