<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CBaruch_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-51-51-Baruch.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Baruch wrote a booke in Babylon. 5
The Iewes there wept at the reading of it. 7 They sende money and
the booke, to the brethren at Hierusalem.</head>

<ab n="1">And these are
the wordes of the booke, which Baruch the sonne of Nerias, the
sonne of Maasias, the sonne of Sedecias, the sonne of Asadias, the
son of Chelcias, wrote in Babylon,</ab>
<ab n="2">In the fift
yere, and in the seuenth day of the moneth, what time as the
Caldeans tooke Ierusalem, and burnt it with fire.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Baruch
did reade the words of this booke, in the hearing of Iechonias, the
sonne of Ioachim king of Iuda, and in the eares of all the people,
that came to [heare] the booke.<note> Or, Ioacim.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And in the
hearing of the nobles, and of the kings sonnes, and in the hearing
of the Elders, and of all the people from the lowest vnto the
highest, euen of all them that dwelt at Babylon, by the riuer
Sud.</ab>
<ab n="5">Whereupon
they wept, fasted, and prayed before the Lord.<note> Or, and uowed uowes.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">They made
also a collection of money, according to euery mans power.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they sent
it to Ierusalem vnto Ioachim the hie Priest the sonne of Chelcias,
sonne of Salom, and to the Priestes, and to all the people which
were found with him at Ierusalem,<note> Or, Ioacim.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">At the same
time, when he receiued the vessels of the house of the Lord that
were caried out of the Temple, to returne them into the land of
Iuda the tenth day of the moneth Siuan, [namely] siluer vessels,
which Sedecias the sonne of Iosias king of Iuda had made,</ab>
<ab n="9">After that
Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon had caried away Iechonias, and the
Princes, and the captiues, and the mightie men, and the people of
the land from Ierusalem, and brought them vnto Babylon:<note> Or, prisoners.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And they said,
Behold, we haue sent you money, to buy you burnt offerings, and
sinne offerings, and incense, and prepare yee Manna, and offer vpon
the Altar of the Lord our God,<note> Gr. corruptly for Mancha, a meat offring.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And pray for the
life of Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon, and for the life of
Balthasar his sonne, that their dayes may be vpon earth as the
dayes of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the Lord wil
giue vs strength, and lighten our eyes, and we shall liue vnder the
shadow of Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon, and vnder the shadow of
Balthasar his sonne, and wee shall serue them many dayes, and finde
fauour in their sight.</ab>
<ab n="13">Pray for vs also
vnto the Lord our God, (for wee haue sinned against the Lord our
God, and vnto this day the fury of the Lord, and his wrath is not
turned from vs)</ab>
<ab n="14">And yee shall
reade this booke, which we haue sent vnto you, to make confession
in the house of the Lord, vpon the feasts and solemne
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And yee shall say,
To the Lord our God belongeth righteousnesse, but vnto vs the
confusion of faces, as it is come to passe this day vnto them of
Iuda, &amp; to the inhabitants of Ierusalem,<note> Chap. 2.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And to our kings,
and to our princes, and to our Priests, and to our Prophets, and to
our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="17">For wee haue
sinned before the Lord,<note> Dan.9. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And disobeyed him,
and haue not hearkened vnto the voice of the Lord our God, to walke
in the commaundements that he gaue vs openly:</ab>
<ab n="19">Since the day that
the Lorde brought our forefathers out of the land of Egypt, vnto
this present day, wee haue beene disobedient vnto the Lord our God,
and we haue beene negligent in not hearing his voice.</ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore the
euils cleaued vnto vs, and the curse which the Lord appointed by
Moses his seruant, at the time that he brought our fathers out of
the land of Egypt, to giue vs a land that floweth with milke and
honie, like as it is to see this day.<note> Deut. 28. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Neuerthelesse we
haue not hearkened vnto the voice of the Lord our God, according
vnto all the wordes of the Prophets, whom he sent vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="22">But euery man
followed the imagination of his owne wicked heart, to serue strange
gods, and to doe euill in the sight of the Lord our God.</ab>



</div>