<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CBaruch_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-4-5-Letter-of-Jeremiah.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The booke of Commandements, is
that Wisdome which was commended in the former chapter. 25 The
Iewes are mooued to patience, and to hope for the
deliuerance.</head>

<ab n="1">This is the
Booke of the commandements of God: and the Law that endureth for
euer: all they that keepe it shall come to life: but such as leaue
it, shall die.</ab>
<ab n="2">Turne thee, O
Iacob, &amp; take heed of it: walke in the presence of the light
therof, that thou mayest be illuminated.<note> Greeke, to the shining, before the light thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Giue not
thine honour to another, nor the things that are profitable vnto
thee, to a strange nation.</ab>
<ab n="4">O Israel,
happie are wee: for things that are pleasing to God, are made
knowen vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="5">Be of good
cheare, my people, the memoriall of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="6">Ye were sold
to the nations, not for [your] destruction: but because you moued
God to wrath, ye were deliuered vnto the enemies.</ab>
<ab n="7">For yee
prouoked him that made you, by sacrificing vnto deuils, and not to
God.<note> 1.Cor.10. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Ye haue
forgotten the euerlasting God, that brought you vp, and ye haue
grieued Ierusalem that noursed you.</ab>
<ab n="9">For when shee
saw the wrath of God cōming vpon you, she said; Hearken, O ye
that dwell about Sion: God hath brought vpō me great
mourning.</ab>
<ab n="10">For I saw the
captiuitie of my sonnes and daughters, which the euerlasting
brought vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="11">With ioy did I
nourish them: but sent them away with weeping and mourning.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let no man reioyce
ouer me a widow, and forsaken of many, who for the sinnes of my
children, am left desolate: because they departed from the Law of
God.</ab>
<ab n="13">They knew not his
statutes, nor walked in the waies of his Commandements, nor trode
in the pathes of discipline in his righteousnesse.<note> Or, of his discipline in righteousnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Let them that
dwell about Sion come, and remember ye the captiuity of my sonnes
and daughters, which the euerlasting hath brought vpon
them.</ab>
<ab n="15">For he hath
brought a nation vpon them from far: a shamelesse nation, and of a
strange language, who neither reuerenced old man, nor pitied
childe.</ab>
<ab n="16">These haue caried
away the deare beloued children of the widow, and left her that was
alone, desolate without daughters.</ab>
<ab n="17">But what can I
helpe you?</ab>
<ab n="18">For he that
brought these plagues vpon you, will deliuer you from the hands of
your enemies.</ab>
<ab n="19">Goe your way, O my
children, goe your way: for I am left desolate.</ab>
<ab n="20">I haue put off the
clothing of peace, and put vpon me the sackcloth of my prayer. I
will cry vnto the euerlasting in my dayes.<note> Or, prosperitie. , Or, in the time of mine affliction. , Psa.116.2. and 137.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Be of good cheare,
O my children, cry vnto the Lord: &amp; he shal deliuer you from
the power &amp; hand of the enemies.</ab>
<ab n="22">For my hope is in
the Euerlasting that hee will saue you, and ioy is come vnto me
from the Holy one, because of the mercy which shall soone come vnto
you from the euerlasting our Sauiour.</ab>
<ab n="23">For I sent you out
with mourning and weeping: but God will giue you to mee againe,
with ioy and gladnesse for euer.</ab>
<ab n="24">Like as now the
neighbours of Sion haue seene your captiuity: so shall they see
shortly your saluation from our God, which shall come vpon you with
great glory, and brightnesse of the euerlasting.</ab>
<ab n="25">My children,
suffer patiently the wrath that is come vpon you from God: for
thine enemy hath persecuted thee: but shortly thou shalt see his
destruction, &amp; shalt tread vpon his necke.</ab>
<ab n="26">My delicate ones
haue gone rough wayes, and were taken away as a flocke caught of
the enemies.<note> Or, my dearelings.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Be of good
comfort, O my children, and cry vnto God: for you shall be
remembred of him that brought these things vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="28">For as it was your
minde to goe astray from God: so being returned seeke him ten times
more.</ab>
<ab n="29">For he that hath
brought these plagues vpon you, shall bring you euerlasting ioy
againe with your saluation.</ab>
<ab n="30">Take a good heart,
O Ierusalem: for hee that gaue thee that name, will comfort
thee.</ab>
<ab n="31">Miserable are they
that afflicted thee, and reioyced at thy fall.</ab>
<ab n="32">Miserable are the
cities which thy children serued: miserable is she that receiued
thy sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="33">For as shee
reioyced at thy ruine, and was glad of thy fall: so shall she be
grieued for her owne desolation.</ab>
<ab n="34">For I will take
away the reioycing of her great multitude, and her pride shalbe
turned into mourning.</ab>
<ab n="35">For fire shal come
vpon her frō the euerlasting, long to endure: and she shal be
inhabited of deuils for a great time.</ab>
<ab n="36">O Ierusalem, looke
about thee toward the East, and behold the ioy that commeth vnto
thee from God.</ab>
<ab n="37">Loe, thy sonnes
come whom thou sentest away: they come gathered together from the
East to the West, by the word of the holy One, reioycing in the
glory of God.</ab>



</div>