<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CBelDragon_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Susanna-Chapter-1-1b-Bel-and-the-Dragon.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Bel-and-the-Dragon-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Bel-and-the-Dragon-Chapter-1-1b-Prayer-of-Manasseh.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>19 The fraud of Bels Priests, is
discouered by Daniel, 27 and the Dragon slaine, which was
worshipped. 33 Daniel is preserued in the Lions denne. 42 The King
doeth acknowledge the God of Daniel, and casteth his enemies into
the same denne.</head>

<ab n="1">And
King Astyages was gathered to his fathers, and Cyrus of Persia
receiued his kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="2">And
Daniel conuersed with the king, and was honored aboue all his
friends.<note> Or, liued with the King.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now the
Babylonians had an Idol called Bel, and there were spent vpon him
euery day twelue great measures of fine flowre, and fourtie sheepe,
and sixe vessels of wine.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the
king worshipped it, and went daily to adore it: but Daniel
worshipped his owne God. And the king said vnto him, Why doest not
thou worship Bel?</ab>
<ab n="5">Who
answered and said, Because I may not worship idols made with hands,
but the liuing God, who hath created the heauen, and the earth, and
hath soueraigntie ouer all flesh.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then
saide the King vnto him, Thinkest thou not that Bel is a liuing
god? seest thou not how much he eateth and drinketh euery
day?</ab>
<ab n="7">Then
Daniel smiled, and said, O king, be not deceiued: for this is but
clay within, and brasse without, and did neuer eate or drinke any
thing.<note> Ecclus. 30. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">So the
king was wroth, and called for his Priests, and said vnto them, If
yee tell me not who this is that deuoureth these expenses, ye shall
die.</ab>
<ab n="9">But if
ye can certifie me that Bel deuoureth them, then Daniel shall die:
for hee hath spoken blasphemie against Bel. And Daniel sayd vnto
the king, Let it be according to thy word.</ab>
<ab n="10">(Now
the Priests of Bel were threescore and tenne, beside their wiues
and children) and the king went with Daniel into the temple of
Bel.</ab>
<ab n="11">So
Bels Priests said, Loe, wee goe out: but thou, O king, set on the
meate, and make ready the wine, and shut the doore fast, and seale
it with thine owne signet:</ab>
<ab n="12">And to
morrow, when thou commest in, if thou findest not that Bel hath
eaten vp all, wee will suffer death; or else Daniel, that speaketh
falsely against vs.</ab>
<ab n="13">And
they little regarded it: for vnder the table they had made a priuie
entrance, whereby they entred in continually, and consumed those
things.</ab>
<ab n="14">So
when they were gone forth, the king set meates before Bel. Now
Daniel had commanded his seruants to bring ashes, and those they
strewed throughout all the temple, in the presence of the king
alone: then went they out and shut the doore, &amp; sealed it with
the kings signet, and so departed.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now in
the night came the Priests with their wiues and children (as they
were woont to doe) and did eate and drinke vp all.</ab>
<ab n="16">In the
morning betime the king arose, and Daniel with him.</ab>
<ab n="17">And
the king said, Daniel, are the seales whole? And he said, Yea, O
king, they be whole.</ab>
<ab n="18">And
assoone as he had opened the doore, the king looked vpon the table,
and cried with a loude voice, Great art thou, O Bel, and with thee
is no deceit at all.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then
laughed Daniel, and helde the king that he should not goe in, and
sayd, Behold now the pauement, and marke well whose footsteps are
these.</ab>
<ab n="20">And
the king said, I see the footsteps of men, women and children: and
then the king was angry,</ab>
<ab n="21">And
tooke the Priests, with their wiues and children, who shewed him
the priuy doores, where they came in, and consumed such things as
were vpon the table.</ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore
the king slewe them, and deliuered Bel into Daniels power, who
destroyed him and his temple.</ab>
<ab n="23">And in
that same place there was a great Dragon, which they of Babylon
worshipped.<note> Some adde this title: Of the Dragon.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And
the king said vnto Daniel, Wilt thou also say that this is of
brasse? loe, he liueth, he eateth and drinketh, thou canst not say,
that he is no liuing God: therefore worship him.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then
said Daniel vnto the king, I will worship the Lord my God: for he
is the liuing God.</ab>
<ab n="26">But
giue me leaue, O king, and I shall slay this dragon without sword
or staffe. The king sayde, I giue thee leaue.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then
Daniel tooke pitch, fat, and haire, and did seethe them together,
and made lumpes thereof: this hee put in the Dragons mouth, and so
the Dragon burst in sunder: and Daniel said, Loe, these are the
gods you worship.<note> Or, Behold what you worship.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">When
they of Babylon heard that, they tooke great indignation, and
conspired against the king, saying, The king is become a Iew, and
he hath destroyed Bel, he hath slaine the Dragon, and put the
Priests to death.</ab>
<ab n="29">So
they came to the king, and said, Deliuer vs Daniel, or else we will
destroy thee and thine house.</ab>
<ab n="30">Now
when the king sawe that they pressed him sore, being constrained,
he deliuered Daniel vnto them:<note> Dan.6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Who
cast him into the lions den, where he was sixe dayes.</ab>
<ab n="32">And in
the den there were seuen lyons, and they had giuen them euery day
two carkeises, and two sheepe: which then were not giuen to them,
to the intent they might deuoure Daniel.<note> Or, two slaues.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Now
there was in Iury a Prophet called Habacuc, who had made pottage,
&amp; had broken bread in a boule, and was going into the field,
for to bring it to the reapers.<note> Or, sodde.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But
the Angel of the Lord said vnto Habacuc, Goe carrie the dinner that
thou hast into Babylon vnto Daniel, who is in the lions
denne.</ab>
<ab n="35">And
Habacuc said, Lord, I neuer saw Babylon: neither do I know where
the denne is.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then
the Angel of the Lord tooke him by the crown, and bare him by the
haire of his head, and through the vehemencie of his spirit, set
him in Babylon ouer the den.<note> Ezek.8.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And
Habacuc cryed, saying, O Daniel, Daniel, take the dinner which God
hath sent thee.<note> 1.King. 17.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And
Daniel saide, Thou hast remembred mee, O God: neither hast thou
forsaken them that seeke thee, and loue thee.</ab>
<ab n="39">So
Daniel arose and did eate: and the Angel of the Lord set Habacuc in
his owne place againe immediatly.</ab>
<ab n="40">Upon
the seuenth day the king went to bewaile Daniel: and when he came
to the den, he looked in, and behold, Daniel was sitting.</ab>
<ab n="41">Then
cried the king with a loud voyce, saying, Great art thou, O Lord
God of Daniel, and there is none other besides thee.</ab>
<ab n="42">And he
drew him out: and cast those that were the cause of his destruction
into the den: and they were deuoured in a moment before his
face.<note> Ier. 37.17</note></ab>



</div>