<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CColossians_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Colossians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Colossians-Chapter-4-4-1-Thessalonians.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Hee exhorteth them to bee feruent
in prayer, 5 to walke wisely toward them that are not yet come to
the true knowledge of Christ. 10 Hee saluteth them, and wisheth
them all prosperitie.</head>

<ab n="1">Masters, giue
vnto your seruants that which is iust and equall, knowing that yee
also haue a Master in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="2">Continue in
prayer, and watch in the same with thankesgiuing:</ab>
<ab n="3">Withall,
praying also for vs, that God would open vnto vs a doore of
vtterance, to speake the mystery of Christ, for which I am also in
bonds:</ab>
<ab n="4">That I may make
it manifest, as I ought to speake.</ab>
<ab n="5">Walke in
wisdome toward them that are without, redeeming the time.</ab>

<fw>Salutations.</fw>
<ab n="6">Let your speech
bee alway with grace, seasoned with salt, that you may know how yee
ought to answere euery man.</ab>
<ab n="7">All my state
shall Tychicus declare vnto you, who is a beloued brother, and a
faithfull minister, and fellow seruant in the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="8">Whom I haue
sent vnto you for the same purpose, that hee might know your
estate, and comfort your hearts.</ab>
<ab n="9">With Onesimus a
faithfull and beloued brother, who is one of you. They shall make
knowen vnto you all things which are done here.</ab>
<ab n="10">Aristarchus my
fellow prisoner saluteth you, and Marcus sisters sonne to Barnabas,
(touching whome yee receiued commandements; if he come vnto you,
receiue him:)</ab>
<ab n="11">And Iesus,
which is called Iustus, who are of the circumcision. These onely
are my fellow workers vnto the kingdome of God, which haue beene a
comfort vnto me.</ab>

<fw>Effectual faith.</fw>
<ab n="12">Epaphras, who
is one of you, a seruant of Christ, saluteth you, alwaies labouring
feruently for you in praiers, that ye may stand perfect, and
complete in all the will of God.<note> Or, striuing , Or, filled.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For I beare
him record, that hee hath a great zeale for you, and them that are
in Laodicea, and them in Hierapolis.</ab>
<ab n="14">Luke the
beloued physician, and Demas greet you.</ab>
<ab n="15">Salute the
brethren which are in Laodicea, and Nymphas, &amp; the church which
is in his house.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when this
Epistle is read amongst you, cause that it be read also in the
church of the Laodiceans: and that ye likewise reade the Epistle
from Laodicea,</ab>
<ab n="17">And say to
Archippus, Take heede to the ministerie, which thou hast receiued
in the Lord, that thou fulfill it.</ab>
<ab n="18">The salutation
by the hand of me Paul. Remember my bonds. Grace be with you. Amen.
Written from Rome to the Colossians, by Tychicus and
Onesimus.</ab>



</div>