<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CColossians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Colossians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Hee sheweth where wee should seeke
Christ. 5 Hee exhorteth to mortification, 10 to put off the olde
man, and to put on Christ, 12 exhorting to charitie, humilitie, and
other seuerall dueties.</head>

<ab n="1">If yee then bee
risen with Christ, seeke those things which are aboue, where Christ
sitteth on the right hand of God:</ab>
<ab n="2">Set your
affection on things aboue, not on things on the earth.<note> Or, minde.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For yee are
dead, and your life is hid with Christ in God.</ab>
<ab n="4">When Christ,
who is our life, shall appeare, then shall yee also appeare with
him in glorie.</ab>
<ab n="5">Mortifie
therefore your members which are vpon the earth: fornication,
vncleannesse, inordinate affection, euill concupiscence, and
couetousnesse, which is idolatrie:</ab>
<ab n="6">For which
things sake, the wrath of God commeth on the children of
disobedience,</ab>
<ab n="7">In the which
yee also walked sometime, when ye liued in them.</ab>
<ab n="8">But now you
also put off all these, anger, wrath, malice, blasphemie, filthy
communication out of your mouth.</ab>
<ab n="9">Lie not one to
another, seeing that yee haue put off the old man with his
deedes:</ab>
<ab n="10">And haue put
on the new man, which is renued in knowledge, after the image of
him that created him,</ab>
<ab n="11">Where there is
neither Greeke, nor Iew, circumcision, nor vncircumcision,
Barbarian, Scythian, bond, nor free: but Christ is all, and in
all.</ab>
<ab n="12">Put on
therefore (as the elect of God, holy and beloued) bowels of
mercies, kindnesse, humblenesse of minde, meekenesse, long
suffering,</ab>
<ab n="13">Forbearing one
another, and forgiuing one another, if any man haue a quarrell
against any: euen as Christ forgaue you, so also doe
yee.<note> Or, complaint.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And aboue all
these things put on charitie, which is the bond of
perfectnesse.</ab>

<fw>Seuerall dueties.</fw>
<ab n="15">And let the
peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which also yee are called
in one body: and be yee thankefull.</ab>
<ab n="16">Let the word
of Christ dwell in you richly in all wisdome, teaching and
admonishing one another in Psalmes, and Hymnes, and Spirituall
songs, singing with grace in your hearts to the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">And whatsoeuer
yee doe in word or deed, doe all in the Name of the Lord Iesus,
giuing thankes to God and the Father, by him.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wiues, submit
your selues vnto your owne husbands, as it is fit in the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="19">Husbands, loue
your wiues, and be not bitter against them.</ab>
<ab n="20">Children, obey
your parents in all things, for this is well pleasing vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">Fathers,
prouoke not your children to anger, lest they be
discouraged.</ab>
<ab n="22">Seruants, obey
in all things your masters according to the flesh: not with eye
seruice as men pleasers, but in singlenesse of heart, fearing
God:</ab>
<ab n="23">And whatsoeuer
yee doe, doe it heartily, as to the Lord, and not vnto men:</ab>
<ab n="24">Knowing, that
of the Lord yee shall receiue the reward of the inheritance: for ye
serue the Lord Christ.</ab>
<ab n="25">But he that
doeth wrong, shall receiue for the wrong which hee hath done: and
there is no respect of persons.</ab>



</div>