<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CColossians_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Colossians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Colossians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Hee still exhorteth them to bee
constant in Christ, 8 To beware of Philosophie, and vaine
traditions, 18 worshipping of Angels, 20 and Legall Ceremonies,
which are ended in Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">For I would
that ye knew what great conflict I haue for you, and for them at
Laodicea, and for as many as haue not seene my face in the
flesh:<note> Or, feare or care.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">That their
hearts might be comforted, being knit together in loue, and vnto
all riches of the full assurance of vnderstanding, to the
acknowledgement of the mysterie of God, and of the Father, and of
Christ,</ab>
<ab n="3">In whom are hid
all the treasures of wisedome, and knowledge.<note> Or, wherein.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And this I say,
lest any man should beguile you with entising words.</ab>
<ab n="5">For though I
bee absent in the flesh, yet am I with you in the spirit, ioying
and beholding your order, and the stedfastnesse of your faith in
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="6">As yee haue
therefore receiued Christ Iesus the Lord, so walke yee in
him:</ab>

<fw>How to walke in Christ Iesus.</fw>
<ab n="7">Rooted and
built vp in him, and stablished in the faith, as yee haue bene
taught, abounding therein with thankesgiuing.</ab>
<ab n="8">Beware lest any
man spoile you through Philosophie and vaine deceit, after the
tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after
Christ:<note> Or, elements.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For in him
dwelleth all the fulnesse of the Godhead bodily.</ab>
<ab n="10">And ye are
complete in him, which is the head of all principalitie, &amp;
power.</ab>
<ab n="11">In whom also
ye are circumcised with the Circumcision made without handes, in
putting off the body of the sinnes of the flesh, by the
Circumcision of Christ:</ab>
<ab n="12">Buried with
him in Baptisme, wherein also you are risen with him through the
faith of the operation of God, who hath raised him from the
dead.</ab>
<ab n="13">And you being
dead in your sinnes, and the vncircumcision of your flesh, hath hee
quickened together with him, hauing forgiuen you all
trespasses,</ab>
<ab n="14">Blotting out
the handwriting of ordinances, that was against vs, which was
contrary to vs, and tooke it out of the way, nayling it to his
Crosse:</ab>
<ab n="15">And hauing
spoyled principalities and powers, he made a shew of them openly,
triumphing ouer them in it.<note> Or, in himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Let no man
therefore iudge you in meat, or in drinke, or in respect of an Holy
day, or of the New moone, or of the Sabbath dayes:<note> Or, for eating and drinking. , Or, in part.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Which are a
shadow of things to come, but the body is of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="18">Let no man
beguile you of your reward, in a voluntary humilitie, and
worshipping of Angels, intruding into those things which hee hath
not seene, vainely puft vp by his fleshly minde:<note> Or, iudge against you. , Gr. being a voluntary. in humilitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And not
holding the head, from which all the body by ioynts and bands
hauing nourishment ministred, and knit together, increaseth with
the increase of God.</ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore if
yee bee dead with Christ frō the rudiments of the world: why,
as though liuing in the world, are ye subiect to
ordinances?<note> Or, elements.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">(Touch not,
taste not, handle not:</ab>
<ab n="22">Which all are
to perish with the vsing) after the commandements and doctrines of
men:</ab>

<fw>Of mortification.</fw>
<ab n="23">Which things
haue in deed a shew of wisedome in will-worship and humilitie, and
neglecting of the body, not in any honour to the satisfying of the
flesh.<note> Or, punishing, or not sparing.</note></ab>



</div>