<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Iehoiakims captiuitie. 3 Ashpenaz
taketh Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah. 8 They refusing the
Kings portion, doe prosper with pulse and water. 17 Their
excellencie in wisdome.</head>

<ab n="1">In the thirde
yere of the reigne of Iehoiakim King of Iudah, came Nebuchad-nezzar
King of Babylon, vnto Ierusalem, and besieged it.<note> 2.Kings. 24.2. 2. chro.36. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
gaue Iehoiakim king of Iudah into his hand, with part of the
vessels of the house of God, which he caried into the land of
Shinar to the house of his god, and he brought the vessels into the
treasure house of his god.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
the king spake vnto Ashpenaz the master of his Eunuches, that he
should bring certaine of the children of Israel, and of the kings
seed, and of the Princes:</ab>
<ab n="4">Children in
whom was no blemish, but well fauoured, and skilfull in all
wisedome, and cunning in knowledge, and vnderstanding science, and
such as had abilitie in them to stand in the Kings palace, and whom
they might teach the learning, and the tongue of the
Caldeans.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the King
appointed them a daily prouision of the kings meat, and of the wine
which he dranke: so nourishing them three yeeres, that at the ende
thereof they might stand before the king.<note> Hebr. the wine of his drinke.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Now among
these were of the children of Iudah, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and
Azariah:</ab>

<fw>Yong men chosen to serue the
King.</fw>
<ab n="7">Unto whom the
Prince of the Eunuches gaue names: for he gaue vnto Daniel the name
of Belteshazzar; and to Hananiah, of Shadrach; and to Mishael, of
Meshach; and to Azariah of Abednego.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But
Daniel purposed in his heart, that he would not defile himselfe
with the portion of the kings meat, nor with the wine which he
dranke: therefore hee requested of the Prince of the Eunuches, that
hee might not defile himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now God had
brought Daniel into fauour and tender loue with the Prince of the
Eunuches.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the Prince of
the Eunuches said vnto Daniel, I feare my lord the king, who hath
appointed your meat, and your drinke: for why should he see your
faces worse liking then the children which are of your sort? then
shall yee make mee indanger my head to the King.<note> Hebr. sadder. , Or, terme, or continuance.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then said Daniel
to Melzar, whom the Prince of the Eunuches had set ouer Daniel,
Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,<note> Or, the steward.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Proue thy
seruants, I beseech thee, ten dayes, and let them giue pulse to
eat, and water to drinke.<note> Hebr. of pulse. , Hebr. that we may eate, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Then let our
countenances be looked vpon before thee, and the countenance of the
children that eat of the portion of the Kings meate: and as thou
seest, deale with thy seruants.</ab>
<ab n="14">So hee consented
to them in this matter, and proued them ten dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And at the end
often dayes, their countenances appeared fairer, and fatter in
flesh, then all the children, which did eate the portion of the
kings meat.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus Melzar tooke
away the portion of their meat, and the wine that they should
drink: and gaue them pulse.</ab>

<fw>Daniels wisdome.</fw>
<ab n="17">¶ As for
these foure children, God gaue them knowledge, and skil in all
learning and wisedome, and Daniel had vnderstanding in all visions
and dreames.<note> Or, hee made Daniel vnderstand.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Now at the end of
the dayes that the King had said he should bring them in, then the
Prince of the Eunuches brought them in before
Nebuchadnezzar.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the King
communed with them: and among them all was found none like Daniel,
Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: therefore stood they before the
King.</ab>
<ab n="20">And in all matters
of wisedome and vnderstanding that the king enquired of them, hee
found them ten times better then all the Magicians and Astrologers
that were in all his Realme.<note> Heb. wisedome of vnderstanding.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Daniel
continued euen vnto the first yeere of king Cyrus.</ab>



</div>