<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 The ouerthrow of Persia by the
king of Grecia. 5 Leagues and conflicts, betweene the kings of the
South and of the North. 30 The inuasion and tyrannie of the
Romanes.</head>

<ab n="1">Also I, in the
first yeere of Darius the Mede, euen I stood to confirme and to
strengthen him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And now will I
shew thee the trueth. Behold, there shall stand vp yet three Kings
in Persia, &amp; the fourth shalbe farre richer then they all: and
by his strength through his riches he shall stirre vp all against
the realme of Grecia.</ab>
<ab n="3">And a mighty King
shal stand vp, that shall rule with great dominion, and doe
according to his will.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when he shall
stand vp, his kingdome shall be broken, and shall be diuided toward
the foure winds of heauen; and not to his posteritie, nor according
to his dominion which he ruled: for his kingdome shall be pluckt
vp, euen for others besides those.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
King of the South shall be strong, and one of his princes, and he
shall be strong aboue him, and haue dominion: his dominion shall be
a great dominion.</ab>

<fw>Kings of the North and South.</fw>
<ab n="6">And in the end of
yeeres they shall ioyne themselues together: for the Kings daughter
of the South shall come to the King of the North to make an
agreement, but she shall not retaine the power of the arme, neither
shall he stand, nor his arme: but she shall be giuen vp, and they
that brought her, and he that begate her, and he that strengthened
her in these times.<note> Heb. shall associate themselues. , Heb. rights. , Or, whom she brought forth.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But out of a
branch of her rootes shall one stand vp in his estate, which shall
come with an armie, and shall enter into the fortresse of the King
of the North, and shall deale against them, and shall
preuaile:</ab>
<ab n="8">And shall also
carie captiues into Egypt their gods with their princes, and with
their precious vessels of siluer and of gold, and he shall continue
moe yeeres then the King of the North.<note> Heb. vessels of their desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So the King of the
South shall come into his kingdome, and shall returne into his owne
land.</ab>
<ab n="10">But his sonnes
shall be stirred vp, and shall assemble a multitude of great
forces: and one shall certainly come and ouerflow and passe
through: then shall he returne, and be stirred vp euen to his
fortresse.<note> Or, shall warre.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the King of
the South shall be moued with choler, and shall come forth and
fight with him, euen with the King of the North: and hee shall set
forth a great multitude, but the multitude shall be giuen into his
hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when he hath
taken away the multitude, his heart shall be lifted vp: and he
shall cast downe many tenne thousands: but he shall not be
strengthened by it.</ab>
<ab n="13">For the King of
the North shall returne, and shall set forth a multitude greater
then the former, and shall certainly come (after certaine yeeres)
with a great armie &amp; with much riches.<note> Heb. at the end of times of yeeres.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And in those
times there shall many stand vp against the King of the South: also
the robbers of thy people shall exalt themselues to establish the
vision, but they shall fall.<note> Heb. the children of robbers.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">So the King of
the North shall come, and cast vp a mount, and take the most fenced
cities, and the armes of the South shall not withstand, neither his
chosen people, neither shall there be any strength to
withstand.<note> Heb. the citie of munitions. , Heb. the people of his choices.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But he that
commeth against him, shall doe according to his owne will, and none
shall stand before him: and he shall stand in the glorious land,
which by his hand shall be consumed.<note> Or, goodly land. Heb. The land of ornament.</note></ab>

<fw>Kings of the North and South.</fw>
<ab n="17">He shall also set
his face to enter with the strength of his whole kingdome and
vpright ones with him: thus shall he doe, and he shall giue him the
daughter of women corrupting her: but she shall not stand on his
side, neither be for him.<note> Or, much vprightnes: Or equall conditions. , Heb. to corrupt.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">After this shall
he turne his face vnto the yles, and shall take many, but a prince
for his own behalfe shall cause the reproch offred by him to cease
without his owne reproch: he shall cause it to turne vpon
him.<note> Heb. for him. , Heb his reproch.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Then he shall
turne his face towards the fort of his owne lande: but he shall
stumble and fall, and not bee found.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then shall stand
vp in his estate a raiser of taxes in the glory of the kingdome,
but within few dayes he shall be destroyed, neither in anger, nor
in battell.<note> Heb. one that causeth an exactour to passe ouer. , Heb. angers.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And in his estate
shall stand vp a vile person, to whom they shal not giue the honour
of the kingdome: but hee shall come in peaceably, and obtaine the
kingdome by flatteries.</ab>
<ab n="22">And with the
armes of a flood shall they bee ouerflowen from before him, and
shall be broken: yea also the prince of the couenant.</ab>
<ab n="23">And after the
league made with him he shall worke deceitfully, for hee shall come
vp, and shall become strong with a small people.</ab>
<ab n="24">He shall enter
peaceably euen vpon the fattest places of the prouince, and he
shall doe that which his fathers haue not done, nor his fathers
fathers, he shall scatter among them the praye and spoile, and
riches: yea and he shall forecast his deuices against the strong
holdes, euen for a time.<note> Or, into the peaceable or for, &amp;c. , Heb. thinke thoughts.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And he shall
stirre vp his power, and his courage against the king of the South
with a great army, and the king of the South shall bee stirred vp
to battell with a very great and mightie armie: but he shall not
stand: for they shall forecast deuices against him.</ab>
<ab n="26">Yea they that
feede of the portion of his meate, shall destroy him, and his armie
shall ouerflow: and many shall fall downe slaine.</ab>
<ab n="27">And both these
kings hearts shall be to doe mischiefe, and they shall speake lies
at one table: but it shall not prosper: for yet the end shall bee
at the time appointed.<note> Heb. their hearts.</note></ab>

<fw>Kings of the North and South.</fw>
<ab n="28">Then shall hee
returne into his land with great riches, and his heart shall be
against the holy couenant: and he shall doe exploits, and returne
to his owne land.</ab>
<ab n="29">At the time
appointed he shall returne, and come toward the South: but it shall
not be as the former, or as the latter.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ For the
ships of Chittim shall come against him: therefore he shall be
grieued and returne, and haue indignation against the holy
Couenant: so shal he doe, he shall euen returne, and haue
intelligence with them that forsake the holy Couenant.</ab>
<ab n="31">And armes shal
stand on his part, and they shall pollute the Sanctuarie of
strength, and shall take away the daily sacrifice, and they shal
place the abomination that maketh desolate.<note> Or, astonisheth.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And such as doe
wickedly against the couenant, shall he corrupt by flatteries: but
the people that do know their God, shall be strong and doe
exploits.<note> Or, cause to dissemble.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And they that
vnderstand among the people shall instruct many: yet they shall
fall by the sword, and by flame, by captiuitie, and by spoile many
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="34">Now when they
shall fall, they shalbe holpen with a litle help: but many shall
cleaue to them with flatteries.</ab>
<ab n="35">And some of them
of vnderstanding shall fall, to trie them, and to purge, and to
make them white, euen to the time of the end: because it is yet for
a time appointed.<note> Or, by them</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And the king
shall doe according to his will, and he shall exalt himselfe, and
magnifie himselfe aboue euery god, and shall speake marueilous
things against the God of gods, &amp; shall prosper till the
indignation be accomplished: for that that is determined, shall be
done.</ab>
<ab n="37">Neither shall hee
regard the god of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard
any god: for he shall magnifie himselfe aboue all.</ab>
<ab n="38">But in his estate
shall he honour the god of forces: and a God whome his fathers knew
not, shall hee honour with gold, and siluer, and with precious
stones, and pleasant things.<note> Or, munitions. Heb. Mauzzin, or, as for the almighty God in his seate he shall honour, yea he shall honour a God, &amp;c. , Heb. things desired.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Thus shall hee
doe in the most strong holds with a strange god, whom he shall
acknowledge and increase with glory: and he shall cause them to
rule ouer many, and shall diuide the land for gaine.<note> Heb. fortresses of munitions. , Heb. a price</note></ab>

<fw>The resurrection. Of the times.</fw>
<ab n="40">And at the time
of the end shall the king of the South push at him, and the king of
the North shal come against him like a whirlewind with charets, and
with horsemen, and with many ships, and he shall enter into the
countreys, and shall ouerflow and passe ouer.</ab>
<ab n="41">He shall enter
also into the glorious land, and many countreys shall be
ouerthrowen: but these shall escape out of his hand, euen Edom, and
Moab, and the chiefe of the children of Ammon.<note> Or, goodly land. Hebr. land of delight, or ornament.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">He shall stretch
foorth his hand also vpon the countreys, and the land of Egypt
shall not escape.<note> Hebr. send foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">But he shall haue
power ouer the treasures of gold and of siluer, and ouer all the
precious things of Egypt: and the Libyans and the Ethiopians shalbe
at his steps.</ab>
<ab n="44">But tidings out
of the East, and out of the North shall trouble him: therefore he
shall goe foorth with great fury to destroy, and vtterly to make
away many.</ab>
<ab n="45">And hee shall
plant the tabernacles of his palace betweene the seas in the
glorious holy mountaine, yet he shall come to his end, and none
shall helpe him.<note> Or, goodly. Hebr. mountaine of delight of holinesse.</note></ab>



</div>