<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Daniels vision of foure beastes. 9
Of Gods kingdome. 15 The interpretation thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">In the first
yeere of Belshazzar king of Babylon, Daniel had a dreame, and
visions of his head vpon his bed: then he wrote the dreame, and
tolde the summe of the matters.<note> Cald. saw. , Or, words.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Daniel spake,
and said, I saw in my vision by night, &amp; behold, the foure
windes of the heauen stroue vpon the great Sea.</ab>
<ab n="3">And foure
great beastes came vp from the sea, diuers one from
another.</ab>
<ab n="4">The first was
like a Lyon, and had Eagles wings: I beheld till the wings thereof
were pluckt, and it was lifted vp from the earth, and made stand
vpon the feete as a man, and a mans heart was giuen to
it.<note> Or, wherewith.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And behold,
another beast, a second, like to a Beare, and it raised vp it selfe
on one side, and it had three ribbes in the mouth of it betweene
the teeth of it, and they said thus vnto it, Arise, deuoure much
flesh.<note> Or, it raised vp one dominion.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">After this I
beheld, and loe, another like a Leopard, which had vpon the backe
of it foure wings of a foule, the beast had also foure heads, and
dominion was giuen to it.</ab>
<ab n="7">After this I
saw in the night visions, and behold, a fourth beast, dreadfull and
terrible, and strong exceedingly; and it had great yron teeth: it
deuoured and brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with the
feete of it, and it was diuers from all the beasts that were before
it, and it had ten hornes.</ab>
<ab n="8">I considered
the hornes, and behold, there came vp among them another little
horne, before whom there were three of the first hornes pluckt vp
by the roots: and behold, in this horne were eyes like the eyes of
man, and a mouth speaking great things.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ I
beheld till the thrones were cast downe, and the Ancient of dayes
did sit, whose garment was white as snow, and the haire of his head
like the pure wooll: his throne was like the fierie flame, and his
wheeles as burning fire.</ab>

<fw>Christs dominion.</fw>
<ab n="10">A fierie streame
issued, and came foorth from before him: thousand thousands
ministred vnto him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood
before him: the iudgement was set, and the bookes were
opened.<note> Reu.5.11. , Reu.22. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">I beheld then,
because of the voice of the great words which the horne spake: I
beheld euen till the beast was slaine, and his body destroyed, and
giuen to the burning flame.</ab>
<ab n="12">As concerning the
rest of the beasts, they had their dominion taken away: yet their
liues were prolonged for a season and time.<note> Cald. a prolonging in life was giuen them.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">I saw in the night
visions, and behold, one like the sonne of man, came with the
clouds of heauen, and came to the Ancient of daies, and they
brought him neere before him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And there was
giuen him dominion and glory, and a kingdome, that all people,
nations, and languages should serue him: his dominion is an
euerlasting dominion, which shall not passe away; and his kingdome
that, which shall not be destroyed.<note> Chap.2. 44. mic.4. 7. luc.1. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ I Daniel
was grieued in my spirit in the midst of my body, and the visions
of my head troubled me.<note> Cald. sheath.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I came neere vnto
one of them that stood by, and asked him the truth of all this: so
he told mee, and made me know the interpretation of the
things.</ab>
<ab n="17">These great
beasts, which are foure, are foure Kings, which shall arise out of
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">But the Saints of
the most high shall take the kingdome, &amp; possesse the kingdome
for euer, euen for euer &amp; euer.<note> Cald. high ones, i. things or, places.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Then I would know
the truth of the fourth beast, which was diuerse from al the
others, exceeding dreadful, whose teeth were of yron, and his
nailes of brasse, which deuoured, brake in pieces, and stamped the
residue with his feete,<note> Cald. from all those.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And of the ten
hornes that were in his head, and of the other, which came vp, and
before whom three fell, euen of that horne that had eyes, and a
mouth that spake very great things, whose looke was more stout then
his fellowes.</ab>
<ab n="21">I beheld, and the
same horne made warre with the Saints, and preuailed against
them;</ab>
<ab n="22">Untill the Ancient
of daies came, and iudgment was giuen to the Saints of the most
high: and the time came that the Saints possessed the
kingdome.</ab>

<fw>Ten hornes.</fw>
<ab n="23">Thus he said, The
fourth beast shall be the fourth kingdome vpon earth, which shall
be diuerse from all kingdomes, &amp; shall deuoure the whole earth,
and shall tread it downe, and breake it in pieces.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the tenne
hornes out of this kingdome are tenne Kings that shall arise: and
an other shall rise after them, and he shall be diuerse from the
first, and he shall subdue three Kings.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he shall
speake great words against the most high, and shall weare out the
Saints of the most high, and thinke to change times, and lawes: and
they shall be giuen into his hand, vntill a time and times, &amp;
the diuiding of time.</ab>
<ab n="26">But the iudgement
shall sit, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume, and
to destroy it vnto the end.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the kingdome
and dominion, and the greatnesse of the kingdome vnder the whole
heauen, shall be giuen to the people of the Saints of the most
high, whose kingdome is an euerlasting kingdome, and all dominions
shall serue and obey him.<note> Luc.1.33. , Or, rulers.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Hitherto is the
end of the matter. As for me Daniel, my cogitations much troubled
me, and my countenance changed in me: but I kept the matter in my
heart.</ab>



</div>