<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Michael shall deliuer Israel from
their troubles. 5 Daniel is informed of the times.</head>

<ab n="1">And at that time
shall Michael stand vp, the great Prince which standeth for the
children of thy people, and there shalbe a time of trouble, such as
neuer was since there was a nation, euen to that same time: and at
that time thy people shalbe deliuered, euery one that shalbe found
written in the booke.</ab>
<ab n="2">And many of them
that sleepe in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to
euerlasting life, and some to shame and euerlasting
contempt.<note> Matt. 25, 45. ioh.5. 29.</note></ab>

<fw>The resurrection. Of the times.</fw>
<ab n="3">And they that be
wise shall shine as the brightnesse of the firmament, and they that
turne many to righteousnesse, as the starres for euer and
euer.<note> Or, teachers. , Matth.13. 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But thou, O
Daniel, shut vp the wordes, and seale the booke euen to the time of
the ende: many shall runne to and fro, and knowledge shall bee
increased.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then I
Daniel looked, and behold, there stood other two, the one on this
side of the banke of the riuer, and the other on that side of the
banke of the riuer.<note> Hebr. lip.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And one said to
the man clothed in linnen, which was vpon the waters of the riuer;
How long shall it bee to the end of these wonders?<note> Dan.10.5. , Or, from aboue.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And I heard the
man clothed in linnen, which was vpon the waters of the riuer, when
he held vp his right hand, and his left hand vnto heauen, and sware
by him that liueth for euer, that it shalbe for a time, times, and
an halfe: and when hee shall haue accomplished to scatter the power
of the holy people, all these things shall bee
finished.<note> Reuel.10. 5. , Or, part.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I heard, but I
vnderstood not: then said I, O my Lord, what shalbe the end of
these things?</ab>
<ab n="9">And he said, Goe
thy way, Daniel: for the wordes are closed vp and sealed till the
time of the end.</ab>
<ab n="10">Many shalbe
purified, and made white and tried: but the wicked shall doe
wickedly: and none of the wicked shall vnderstand, but the wise
shall vnderstand.</ab>
<ab n="11">And from the time
that the dayly sacrifice shalbe taken away, and the abomination
that maketh desolate set vp, there shalbe a thousand two hundred
and ninetie dayes.<note> Hebr. to set vp the abomination, &amp;c. , Or, astonisheth.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Blessed is he
that waiteth, and commeth to the thousand, three hundred and fiue
and thirtie dayes.</ab>
<ab n="13">But goe thou thy
way till the end be: for thou shalt rest, and stand in the lot at
the end of the dayes.<note> Or, and thou, &amp;c.</note></ab>



</div>