<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Nebuchad-nezzar forgetting his
dreame, requireth it of the Caldeans, by promises and threatnings.
10 They acknowledging their inabilitie, are iudged to die. 14
Daniel obtaining some respite, findeth the dreame. 19 He blesseth
God. 24 He staying the Decree, is brought to the King. 31 The
dreame. 36 The interpretatiō. 46 Daniels
aduancement.</head>

<ab n="1">And in the
second yeere of the reigne of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchad-nezzar
dreamed dreames, wherewith his spirit was troubled, and his sleepe
brake from him.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then the King
commanded to call the Magicians, and the Astrologers, and the
Sorcerers, and the Caldeans, for to shew the King his dreames: so
they came and stood before the king.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the King
said vnto them, I haue dreamed a dreame, and my spirit was troubled
to know the dreame.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then spake
the Caldeans to the King in Syriacke; O king, liue for euer: tell
thy seruants the dreame, and we will shew the
interpretation.<note> Dan. 3.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The King
answered, and said to the Caldeans, The thing is gone from mee: if
ye will not make knowen vnto me the dreame, with the interpretation
thereof, yee shall be cut in pieces, and your houses shalbe made a
dunghill.<note> Dan. 3. 29. , Cald. made pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But if yee
shewe the dreame, and the interpretation thereof, yee shall receiue
of me giftes and rewards, and great honour: therefore shewe me the
dreame, and the interpretation thereof.<note> Or, Fee, Dan.5. 17.</note></ab>

<fw>The Kings fury.</fw>
<ab n="7">They answered
againe, and said, Let the King tell his seruants the dreame, and we
will shew the interpretation of it.</ab>
<ab n="8">The King
answered, and said, I know of certeinty that ye would gaine the
time, because ye see the thing is gone from me.<note> Cald. buy.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But if yee
will not make knowen vnto me the dreame, there is but one decree
for you: for ye haue prepared lying, and corrupt words to speake
before me, till the time be changed: therefore tell me the dreame,
and I shall know that yee can shewe mee the interpretation
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ The
Caldeans answered before the King, and said, There is not a man
vpon the earth that can shew the kings matter: therefore there is
no King, lord, nor ruler, that asked such things at any Magician,
or Astrologer, or Caldean.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it is a rare
thing that the king requireth, and there is none other that can
shew it before the King, except the gods, whose dwelling is not
with flesh.</ab>
<ab n="12">For this cause the
King was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the
wise men of Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the decree
went foorth that the wise men should be slaine, and they sought
Daniel and his fellowes to be slaine.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then Daniel
answered with counsell and wisedome to Arioch the captaine of the
Kings guard, which was gone foorth to slay the wise men of
Babylon.<note> Cald. returned. , Or, chiefe marshall. Cald. chiefe of the executioners or slaughtermen.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hee answered and
said to Arioch the Kings captaine, Why is the decree so hastie from
the King? Then Arioch made the thing knowen to Daniel.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then Daniel went
in and desired of the King, that hee would giue him time, and that
he would shew the king the interpretation.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then Daniel went
to his house, and made the thing knowen to Hananiah, Mishael, and
Azariah his companions:</ab>
<ab n="18">That they would
desire mercies of the God of heauen concerning this secret, that
Daniel and his fellowes should not perish with the rest of the Wise
men of Babylon.<note> Cald. from before God. , Or, that they should not destroy Daniel, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then was
the secret reuealed vnto Daniel in a night vision: then Daniel
blessed the God of heauen.</ab>

<fw>Daniel expoundeth the kings
dreame.</fw>
<ab n="20">Daniel answered
and said; Blessed be the name of God for euer and euer: for
wisedome and might are his:<note> Psal. 113. 2. and 115. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And he changeth
the times and the seasons: he remoueth Kings, and setteth vp Kings:
he giueth wisedome vnto the wise, and knowledge to them that know
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="22">He reuealeth the
deepe and secret things: hee knoweth what is in the darknes, &amp;
the light dwelleth with him.</ab>
<ab n="23">I thanke thee and
praise thee, O thou God of my fathers, who hast giuen me wisedome
and might, and hast made knowen vnto me now what we desired of
thee: for thou hast now made knowen vnto vs the kings
matter.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Therefore
Daniel went in vnto Arioch whom the king had ordained to destroy
the wise men of Babylon: he went and said thus vnto him, Destroy
not the wise men of Babylon: bring me in before the king, and I
will shew vnto the king the interpretation.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then Arioch
brought in Daniel before the king in haste, &amp; said thus vnto
him, I haue found a man of the captiues of Iudah, that will make
knowen vnto the king the interpretation.<note> Cald. that I haue found. , Cald. children of the captiuitie of Iudah.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The King answered
and said to Daniel whose name was Belteshazzar, Art thou able to
make knowen vnto me the dreame which I haue seene, and the
interpretation thereof?</ab>
<ab n="27">Daniel answered in
the presence of the King, and said, The secret which the King hath
demanded, cannot the wise men, the astrologians, the magicians,
þe southsaiers shew vnto the king:</ab>
<ab n="28">But there is a God
in heauen that reuealeth secrets, and maketh knowen to the king
Nebuchad-nezzar, what shalbe in the latter dayes. Thy dreame, and
the visions of thy head vpon thy bed, are these.<note> Cald. hath made knowen.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">As for thee, O
King, thy thoughts came into thy minde vpon thy bed, what should
come to passe hereafter: and he that reuealeth secrets, maketh
knowen to thee, what shall come to passe.<note> Cald. came vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But as for me,
this secret is not reuealed to me, for any wisdome that I haue more
then any liuing, but for their sakes that shall make knowen the
interpretation to the King, and that thou mightest know the
thoughts of thy heart.</ab>

<fw>Daniel expoundeth the kings
dreame.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ Thou, O
King, sawest, and behold a great image: this great image whose
brightnesse was excelleut, stood before thee, and the forme thereof
was terrible.<note> Cald. wass seeing.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">This images head
was of fine gold, his breast and his armes of siluer, his belly and
his thighes of brasse:<note> Or, sides.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">His legs of yron,
his feete part of yron, and part of clay.</ab>
<ab n="34">Thou sawest till
that a stone was cut out without hands, which smote the image vpon
his feete that were of yron and clay, and brake them to
pieces.<note> Or, which was not in hands. As verse 45.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Then was the yron,
the clay, the brasse, the siluer, and the golde broken to pieces
together, and became like the chaffe of the summer threshing
floores, and the wind caried them away, that no place was found for
them: &amp; the stone that smote the image became a great
mountaine, and filled the whole earth.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ This is the
dreame, and we will tell the interpretation thereof before the
King.</ab>
<ab n="37">Thou, O King, art
a king of Kings: for the God of heauen hath giuen thee a kingdome,
power, and strength, and glory.</ab>
<ab n="38">And wheresoeuer
the children of men dwel, the beasts of the field, and the foules
of the heauen hath he giuen into thine hand, and hath made thee
ruler ouer them all: thou art this head of gold.</ab>
<ab n="39">And after thee
shall arise an other kingdome inferiour to thee, and another third
kingdome of brasse, which shall beare rule ouer all the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the fourth
kingdome shall be strong as yron: forasmuch as yron breaketh in
pieces and subdueth all things; and as yron that breaketh all
these, shall it breake in pieces and bruise.</ab>
<ab n="41">And whereas thou
sawest the feete and toes, part of potters clay, and part of yron:
the kingdome shalbe diuided, but there shalbe in it of the strength
of the yron, forasmuch as thou sawest the yron mixt with myrie
clay.</ab>
<ab n="42">And as the toes of
the feete were part of yron, and part of clay; so the kingdome
shall be partly strong, and partly broken.<note> Or, brittle.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And whereas thou
sawest yron mixt with myrie clay, they shall mingle themselues with
the seede of men: but they shall not cleaue one to an other, euen
as yron is not mixed with clay.<note> Cald. this with this.</note></ab>

<fw>An image set vp, and dedicated.</fw>
<ab n="44">And in the daies
of these Kings shall the God of heauen set vp a kingdome, which
shall neuer be destroyed: and the Kingdome shall not be left to
other people, but it shall breake in pieces, and consume all these
kingdomes, and it shall stand for euer.<note> Cald. their dayes. , Chap.4.3, 34. and 6. 27. and 7. 14, 27. mich 4.7. luke 1.33. , Cald. kingdome thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Forasmuch as thou
sawest that the stone was cut out of the mountaine without hands,
and that it brake in pieces the yron, the brasse, the clay, the
siluer, and the gold: the great God hath made knowen to the King
what shall come to passe hereafter, &amp; the dreame is certaine,
and the interpretation thereof sure.<note> Or, which was not in hand. , Cald. after this.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">¶ Then the
King Nebuchadnezzar fell vpon his face, and worshipped Daniel, and
commanded that they should offer an oblation, and sweet odours vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="47">The King answered
vnto Daniel and said, Of a trueth it is, that your God is a God of
gods, and a Lord of Kings, and a reuealer of secrets, seeing thou
couldest reueale this secret.</ab>
<ab n="48">Then the King made
Daniel a great man, and gaue him many great gifts, &amp; made him
ruler ouer the whole prouince of Babylon, and chiefe of the
gouernours ouer all the wise men of Babylon.<note> Chap.4.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">Then Daniel
requested of the King, and he set Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego
ouer the affaires of the prouince of Babylon: but Daniel sate in
the gate of the King.</ab>



</div>