<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Nebuchad-nezzar dedicateth a
golden image in Dura. 8 Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego are accused
for not worshipping the image. 13 They being threatned, make a good
confession. 19 God deliuereth them out of the furnace. 26
Nebuchad-nezzar seeing the miracle, blesseth God.</head>

<ab n="1">Nebuchad-nezzar the
king made an image of gold, whose height was threescore cubits, and
þ<note/> breadth thereof sixe cubites: he set it vp in
the plaine of Dura, in the prouince of Babylon.</ab>

<fw>An image set vp, and dedicated.</fw>
<ab n="2">Then
Nebuchad-nezzar the king sent to gather together the Princes, the
Gouernours, and the Captaines, the Iudges, the Treasurers, the
Counsellers, the Sherifes, and all the rulers of the Prouinces, to
come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchad-nezzar the King
had set vp.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then the
Princes, the Gouernours and Captaines, the Iudges, the Treasurers,
the Counsellers, the Sherifes, and all the rulers of the Prouinces
were gathered together vnto the dedicatiō of the image, that
Nebuchadnezzar the King had set vp, and they stood before the image
that Nebuchadnezzar had set vp.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then an
herauld cryed aloud, To you it is commaunded, O people, nations,
and languages,<note> Cald. with might. , Cald. they command.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">That at what
time yee heare the sound of the cornet, flute, harpe, sackbut,
psalterie, dulcimer, and all kinds of musicke, yee fall downe, and
worship the golden image that Nebuchad-nezzar the King hath set
vp:<note> Or, singing. Cald. Symphonie.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And who so
falleth not down and worshippeth, shall the same houre bee cast
into the middest of a burning fierie furnace.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore at
that time, when all the people heard the sound of the cornet,
flute, harpe, sackbut, psalterie, and all kindes of musicke, all
the people, the nations, and the languages fell downe and
worshipped the golden image, that Nebuchad-nezzar the King had set
vp.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶
Wherefore at that time certaine Caldeans came neere, and accused
the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="9">They spake
and sayd to the King Nebuchad-nezzar, O King, liue for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou, O King, hast
made a decree, that euery man that shal heare the sound of the
cornet, flute, harpe, sackbut, psalterie, and dulcimer, and all
kinds of musicke, shall fall downe and worship the golden
image:</ab>
<ab n="11">And who so falleth
not downe &amp; worshippeth, that he should be cast into the midst
of a burning fierie furnace.</ab>
<ab n="12">There are certain
Iewes whom thou hast set ouer the affaires of the prouince of
Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego: these men, O King, haue
not regarded thee, they serue not thy gods, nor worship the golden
image, which thou hast set vp.<note> Cald. haue set no regard vpon thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then
Nebuchad-nezzar in his rage and furie commaunded to bring Shadrach,
Meshach, and Abednego: then they brought these men before the
King.</ab>

<fw>Deliuerance from the fierie
fornace.</fw>
<ab n="14">Nebuchad-nezzar
spake and said vnto them, Is it true, O Shadrach, Meshach and
Abednego? doe not yee serue my gods, nor worship the golden image
which I haue set vp?<note> Or, of purpose: as Exodus 21. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Now if ye be ready
that at what time yee heare the sound of the cornet, flute, harpe,
sackbut, psalterie, and dulcimer, and all kindes of musicke, ye
fall downe, and worship the image which I haue made, well: but if
yee worship not, ye shall be cast the same houre into the midst of
a fierie furnace, and who is that God that shall deliuer you out of
my handes?</ab>
<ab n="16">Shadrach, Meshach,
and Abednego answered and said to the king; O Nebuchad-nezzar, we
are not carefull to answere thee in this matter.</ab>
<ab n="17">If it be so, our
God whom wee serue, is able to deliuer vs from the burning fierie
furnace, and he will deliuer vs out of thine hand, O king.</ab>
<ab n="18">But if not, bee it
knowen vnto thee, O king, that we will not serue thy gods, nor
worship thy golden image, which thou hast set vp.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then was
Nebuchad-nezzar full of furie, and the forme of his visage was
changed against Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego: therefore he spake
and commanded, that they should heat the furnace one seuen times
more then it was wont to be heat.<note> Cal. filled.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And hee commaunded
the most mighty men that were in his armie, to binde Shadrach,
Meshach and Abednego, and to cast them into the burning fierie
furnace.<note> Cald. mightie of strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Then these men
were bound in their coates, their hosen, and their hats, and their
other garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fierie
furnace.<note> Or, mantle. , Or, turbant.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore because
the Kings commandement was vrgent, and the furnace exceeding hot,
the flame of the fire slew those men that tooke vp Shadrach,
Meshach and Abednego.<note> Cald. word. , Or, sparke.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And these three
men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell downe bound into the
midst of the burning fierie furnace.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then
Nebuchad-nezzar the king was astonied, and rose vp in haste, and
spake and said vnto his counsellers, Did not wee cast three men
bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said vnto the
king; True, O king.<note> Or, gouernours.</note></ab>

<fw>Deliuerance from the fierie
fornace.</fw>
<ab n="25">He answered and
said, Loe, I see foure men loose, walking in the midst of the fire,
and they haue no hurt, and the forme of the fourth is like the
sonne of God.<note> Cal. there is no hurt in them.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Then
Nebuchad-nezzar came neere to the mouth of the burning fierie
furnace, and spake and said, Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, ye
seruants of the most High God, come forth, and come hither. Then
Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego came forth of the midst of the
fire.<note> Cald. doore.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the princes,
gouernours, and captaines, and the kings counsellers, being
gathered together, saw these men, vpon whose bodies the fire had no
power, nor was an haire of their head singed, neither were their
coats changed, nor the smell of fire had passed on them.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then
Nebuchad-nezzar spake and said; Blessed bee the God of Shadrach,
Meshach, and Abednego, who hath sent his Angel, and deliuered his
seruants that trusted in him, and haue changed the Kings word, and
yeelded their bodies, that they might not serue nor worship any
God, except their owne God.</ab>
<ab n="29">Therefore I make a
decree, That euery people, nation, and language, which speake any
thing amisse against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego,
shall be cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill,
because there is no other God, that can deliuer after this
sort.<note> Cald. a decree is made by me. , Cald. errour. , Chap.2.5. , Cald. made pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Then the King
promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego in the prouince of
Babylon.<note> Cald. made to prosper.</note></ab>



</div>