<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Nebuchad-nezzar confesseth Gods
Kingdome, 4 maketh relation of his dreames, which the Magitians
could not interpret. 8 Daniel heareth the dreame. 19 Hee
interpreteth it. 28 The storie of the euent.</head>

<ab n="1">Nebuchad-nezzar the
king, vnto all people, nations, and languages that dwell in all the
earth, Peace be multiplied vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="2">I thought it
good to shew the signes, and wonders, that the high God hath
wrought toward me.<note> Cald. it was seemely before me.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">How great are
his signes? and how mighty are his wonders? his kingdome is an
euerlasting kingdome, and his dominion is frō generation to
generation.<note> Chap.2. 34.</note></ab>

<fw>The Kings dreame is
interpreted.</fw>
<ab n="4">¶ I
Nebuchadnezzar was at rest in mine house, and flourishing in my
palace.</ab>
<ab n="5">I saw a
dreame which made me afraid, and the thoughts vpon my bed, and the
visions of my head troubled me.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore
made I a decree, to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before
mee, that they might make knowen vnto me the interpretation of the
dreame.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then came in
the Magicians, the Astrologers, the Caldeans, and the Southsayers:
and I tolde the dreame before them; but they did not make knowen
vnto mee the interpretation thereof.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But at
the last Daniel came in before me, (whose name was Belteshazzar,
according to the name of my God, and in whom is the spirit of the
holy Gods) &amp; before him I told the dreame, saying,</ab>
<ab n="9">O
Belteshazzar, master of the Magicians, because I know that the
spirit of the holy Gods is in thee, and no secret troubleth thee,
tell me the visions of my dreame that I haue seene, and the
interpretation thereof.<note> Cha. 1.48.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thus were the
visions of mine head in my bed: I saw, and behold, a tree in the
middest of the earth, and the height thereof was great.<note> Cald. I was seeing.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The tree grew, and
was strong, and the height thereof reached vnto heauen, and the
sight thereof to the end of all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="12">The leaues thereof
were faire, and the fruite thereof much, and in it was meate for
all: the beasts of the field had shadow vnder it, and the foules of
the heauen dwelt in the boughes thereof, and all flesh was fed of
it.</ab>
<ab n="13">I sawe in the
visions of my head vpon my bed, &amp; behold, a watcher and an holy
one came downe from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="14">He cryed aloude,
and said thus; Hew downe the tree, and cut off his branches; shake
off his leaues, and scatter his fruite; let the beasts get away
from vnder it, and the foules from his branches.<note> Cald. with might.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Neuerthelesse
leaue the stumpe of his rootes in the earth, euen with a band of
yron and brasse, in the tender grasse of the field, and let it be
wet with the dew of heauen, and let his portion be with the beastes
in the grasse of the earth.</ab>

<fw>The Kings dreame is
interpreted.</fw>
<ab n="16">Let his heart bee
changed from mans, and let a beasts heart be giuen vnto him, and
let seuen times passe ouer him.</ab>
<ab n="17">This matter is by
the decree of the watchers, and the demaund by the word of the Holy
ones: to the intent that the liuing may know, that the most High
ruleth in the kingdome of men, and giueth it to whomsoeuer hee
will, and setteth vp ouer it the basest of men.</ab>
<ab n="18">This dreame, I
king Nebuchadnezzar haue seene: Now thou, O Belteshazzar, declare
the interpretation thereof, forasmuch as all the Wise men of my
kingdome are not able to make knowen vnto mee the interpretation:
but thou art able, for the spirit of the holy Gods is in
thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then Daniel
(whose name was Belteshazzar) was astonied for one houre, and his
thoughts troubled him: The King spake, and said, Belteshazzar, let
not the dreame, or the interpretation thereof trouble thee.
Belteshazzar answered; and said; My lord, the dreame be to them
that hate thee, and the interpretation thereof to thine
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="20">The tree that thou
sawest, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached vnto the
heauen, and the sight thereof to all the earth:</ab>
<ab n="21">Whose leaues were
faire, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meate for all,
vnder which the beasts of the field dwelt, and vpon whose branches
the foules of the heauen had their habitation:</ab>
<ab n="22">It is thou, O
King, that art growen and become strong: for thy greatnesse is
growen and reacheth vnto heauen, and thy dominion to the end of the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="23">And whereas the
King saw a watcher, and an holy one comming downe from heauen, and
saying, Hew the tree downe, and destroy it, yet leaue the stumpe of
the rootes thereof in the earth, euen with a band of yron and
brasse in the tender grasse of the field, and let it be wet with
the dewe of heauen, and let his portion be with the beasts of the
field, till seuen times passe ouer him:</ab>
<ab n="24">This is the
interpretation, O king, &amp; this is the decree of the most Hie,
which is come vpon my lord the king:</ab>

<fw>The kings fall.</fw>
<ab n="25">That they shall
driue thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of
the field, and they shall make thee to eate grasse as oxen, and
they shall wet thee with the dew of heauen, and seuen times shall
passe ouer thee, till thou know that the most high ruleth in the
kingdome of men, and giueth it to whomsoeuer he will.<note> Chap.5. 20. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And whereas they
commanded to leaue the stumpe of the tree rootes; thy kingdome
shall be sure vnto thee, after that thou shalt haue knowen that the
heauens doe rule.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore, O King,
let my counsell be acceptable vnto thee, and breake off thy sinnes
by righteousnesse, and thine iniquities by shewing mercy to the
poore; if it may be a lengthening of thy tranquillitie.<note> Or, an healing of thine errour.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ All this
came vpon the King Nebuchad-nezzar.</ab>
<ab n="29">At the end of
twelue moneths he walked in the palace of the kingdome of
Babylon.<note> Or, vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The King spake,
and said, Is not this great Babylon, that I haue built for the
house of the kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the honour
of my maiestie?</ab>
<ab n="31">While the word was
in the Kings mouth, there fell a voice from heauen, saying, O King
Nebuchad-nezzar, to thee it is spoken; The kingdome is departed
from thee.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they shall
driue thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of
the field; they shall make thee to eate grasse as oxen, and seuen
times shall passe ouer thee, vntill thou know that the most high
ruleth in the kingdome of men, and giueth it to whomsoeuer he
will.</ab>
<ab n="33">The same houre was
the thing fulfilled vpon Nebuchad-nezzar, and he was driuen from
men, and did eate grasse as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew
of heauen, till his haires were growen like Egles feathers, and his
nailes like birds clawes.</ab>
<ab n="34">And at the end of
the dayes, I Nebuchad-nezzar lift vp mine eyes vnto heauen, and
mine vnderstanding returned vnto me, and I blessed the most high,
and I praised, and honoured him that liueth for euer, whose
dominion is an euerlasting dominion, and his kingdome is from
generation to generation.<note> Chap.7 14. mic.4.7 luc.1.33.</note></ab>

<fw>A hand writing.</fw>
<ab n="35">And all the
inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing: and hee doth
according to his will in the armie of heauen, and among the
inhabitants of the earth: and none can stay his hand, or say vnto
him, What doest thou?<note> Iob.9.12. isai.45.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">At the same time
my reason returned vnto me, and for the glory of my kingdome, mine
honour, and brightnes returned vnto me, and my counsellers, and my
Lords sought vnto me, and I was established in my kingdome, and
excellent Maiestie was added vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="37">Now I
Nebuchad-nezzar praise, and extoll and honour the King of heauen,
all whose workes are truth, and his waies iudgement, and those that
walke in pride he is able to abase.</ab>



</div>