<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDaniel_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Daniel-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Daniel considering the time of the
captiuitie, 3 maketh confession of sinnes, 16 and prayeth for the
restauration of Ierusalem. 20 Gabriel informeth him of the seuentie
weekes.</head>

<ab n="1">In the first
yeere of Darius the sonne of Ahasuerus, of the seede of the Medes,
which was made King ouer the realme of the Caldeans,<note> Or, in which he, &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Daniels confession, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="2">In the first
yeere of his reigne, I Daniel vnderstood by bookes the number of
the yeeres, whereof the word of the Lord came to Ieremiah the
Prophet, that he would accomplish seuentie yeeres in the
desolations of Ierusalem.<note> Iere.25. 12. and 29. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And I
set my face vnto the Lord God to seeke by prayer, and
supplications, with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I prayed
vnto the Lord my God, and made my confession, and said; O Lord, the
great and dreadfull God, keeping the couenant, and mercy to them
that loue him, and to them that keepe his
Commandements:<note> Nehe.1.5. deut.7.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">We haue
sinned, and haue committed iniquitie, and haue done wickedly, and
haue rebelled, euen by departing from thy precepts, and from thy
iudgements.<note> Bar.1. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Neither haue
we hearkened vnto thy seruants the Prophets, which spake in thy
Name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the
people of the land.</ab>
<ab n="7">O Lord,
righteousnes belongeth vnto thee, but vnto vs confusion of faces,
as at this day: to the men of Iudah, and to the inhabitants of
Ierusalem, and vnto all Israel that are neere, and that are farre
off, through all the countreys whither thou hast driuen them,
because of their trespasse, that they haue trespassed against
thee.<note> Or, thou hast, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">O Lord, to vs
belongeth confusion of face, to our kings, to our princes, and to
our fathers; because we haue sinned against thee.<note> Bar.1.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">To the Lord
our God belong mercies and forgiuenesses, though we haue rebelled
against him.</ab>
<ab n="10">Neither haue we
obeyed the voice of the Lord our God, to walke in his Lawes which
he set before vs, by his seruants the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="11">Yea, all Israel
haue transgressed thy Law, euen by departing, that they might not
obey thy voice, therefore the curse is powred vpon vs, and the othe
that is written in the Law of Moses the seruant of God, because we
haue sinned against him.<note> Leuit. 26. 14. &amp;c. deu. 28. 15. &amp;c. and 29. 29. &amp;c. and 30. 17, 18. and 31. 17. &amp;c. and 32. 19. &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Daniels confession, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="12">And he hath
confirmed his words which he spake against vs, and against our
Iudges that iudged vs, by bringing vpon vs a great euill: for vnder
the whole heauen hath not bene done, as hath bene done vpon
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="13">As it is written
in the Law of Moses, all this euill is come vpon vs: yet made we
not our prayer before the Lord our God, that we might turne from
our iniquities, and vnderstand thy trueth.<note> Leuit.26. 14. deu.28. 15. lament. 2.17. , Hebr. intreated the face.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore hath the
Lord watched vpon the euil, and brought it vpon vs: for the Lord
our God is righteous in all his workes, which he doeth: for we
obeyed not his voice.</ab>
<ab n="15">And now O Lord our
God, that hast brought thy people forth out of the land of Egypt
with a mighty hand, and hast gotten thee renowne, as at this day,
wee haue sinned, wee haue done wickedly.<note> Exod.14 28. , Heb. made thee a name.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ O Lord,
according to all thy righteousnes, I beseech thee, let thine anger
and thy furie bee turned away from thy citie Ierusalem, thy holy
Mountaine: because for our sinnes, and for the iniquities of our
fathers, Ierusalem and thy people are become a reproch to all that
are about vs.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now therefore, O
our God, heare the prayer of thy seruant, and his supplications,
and cause thy face to shine vpon thy Sanctuary that is desolate,
for the Lords sake.</ab>
<ab n="18">O my God, encline
thine eare and heare: open thine eyes, and behold our desolations,
&amp; the city, which is called by thy name: for we do not present
our supplications before thee for our righteousnesses, but for thy
great mercies.<note> Heb. wherupon thy Name is called. , Heb. cause to fall.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">O Lord heare, O
Lord forgiue, O Lord hearken and doe: deferre not for thine owne
sake, O my God: for thy citie, &amp; thy people are called by thy
Name.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And whiles
I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sinne, and the sinne
of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before the Lord
my God, for the holy Mountaine of my God:</ab>
<ab n="21">Yea whiles I was
speaking in praier, euen the man Gabriel, whom I had seene in the
vision at the beginning, being caused to flie swiftly, touched me
about the time of the euening oblation.<note> Dan.8.16. , Hebr. with wearinesse or flight.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And he informed
mee, and talked with mee, and said; O Daniel, I am now come foorth
to giue thee skill and vnderstanding.<note> Hebr. to make thee skilfull of vnderstanding.</note></ab>

<fw>Daniels vision.</fw>
<ab n="23">At the beginning
of thy supplications the commandement came forth, and I am come to
shew thee: for thou art greatly beloued: therefore vnderstand the
matter, &amp; consider the vision.<note> Heb. word. , Heb. a man of desires.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Seuentie weekes
are determined vpon thy people, and vpon thy holy citie, to finish
the transgression, and to make an ende of sinnes, and to make
reconciliation for iniquitie, and to bring in euerlasting
righteousnes, and to seale vp the vision and prophecie, and to
anoynt the most Holy.<note> Or, to restraine. , Or, to seale vp. , Heb. prophet.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Know therefore and
vnderstand, that from the going foorth of the commandement to
restore and to build Ierusalem, vnto the Messiah the Prince, shall
be seuen weekes; and threescore and two weekes, the street shall be
built againe, and the wall, euen in troublous times.<note> Heb. shall returne and be built. , Or, breach or ditch. , Hebr. in strait of times.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And after
threescore and two weekes, shall Messiah be cut off, but not for
himselfe, and the people of the Prince that shall come, shall
destroy the citie, and the Sanctuarie, and the ende thereof shall
be with a flood, and vnto the ende of the warre desolations are
determined.<note> Or, shall haue nothing. , Or, it shall be cut off by desolations.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And hee shall
confirme the couenant with many for one weeke: and in the midst of
the weeke he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease,
and for the ouerspreading of abominations hee shall make it
desolate, euen vntill the consummation, &amp; that determined,
shalbe powred vpon the desolate.<note> Or, with the abominable armies. , Mat. 24. 15. marke 13.14. luke 21.20.</note></ab>



</div>