<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-29-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 Iacob commeth to the well of
Haran. 9 He taketh acquaintance of Rachel. 13 Laban enterteineth
him. 18 Iacob couenanteth for Rachel. 23 He is deceiued with Leah.
28 He marrieth also Rachel, and serueth for her seuen yeeres more.
32 Leah beareth Reuben, 33 Simeon, 34 Leui, 35 and
Iudah.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iacob went
on his iourney, and came into the land of the people of the
East.<note> Heb. lift up his feet. , Heb. children.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he looked,
and behold, a well in the field, and loe, there were three flocks
of sheepe lying by it: for out of that wel they watered the flocks:
and a great stone was vpon the welles mouth.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thither were
all the flockes gathered, and they rolled the stone from the wels
mouth, &amp; watered the sheepe, and put the stone againe vpon the
wels mouth in his place.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iacob said
vnto them, My brethren, whence be ye? and they saide, Of Haran are
we.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he said vnto
them, Know ye Laban the sonne of Nahor? And they sayde, We knowe
him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he said vnto
them, Is hee well? and they said, He is well: and behold, Rachel
his daughter commeth with the sheepe.<note> Hebr. Is there peace to him?</note></ab>

<fw>He meeteth with Rachel, and marieth
her.</fw>
<ab n="7">And hee said,
Loe, it is yet high day, neither is it time that the cattell should
be gathered together: water yee the sheepe, and goe and feed
them.<note> Heb. yet the day is great.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And they said, We
cannot, vntill all the flockes bee gathered together, and till they
rolle the stone from the welles mouth: then wee water the
sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And while
hee yet spake with them, Rachel came with her fathers sheepe: for
she kept them.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe, when Iacob saw Rachel the daughter of Laban his mothers
brother, and the sheepe of Laban his mothers brother; that Iacob
went neere, and rolled the stone from the wels mouth, and watered
the flocke of Laban his mothers brother.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Iacob kissed
Rachel, and lifted vp his voyce, and wept.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Iacob told
Rachel, that hee was her fathers brother, and that hee was Rebekahs
sonne: and she ranne, and told her father.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it came to
passe, when Laban heard the tidings of Iacob his sisters sonne,
that he ranne to meete him, and imbraced him, and kissed him, &amp;
brought him to his house: and hee tolde Laban all these
things.<note> Heb. hearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Laban said
to him, Surely thou art my bone and my flesh: and he abode with him
the space of a moneth.<note> Hebr. a moneth of daies.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And Laban
said vnto Iacob, Because thou art my brother, shouldest thou
therefore serue me for nought? tell me, what shall thy wages
be?</ab>
<ab n="16">And Laban had
two daughters: the name of the elder was Leah, and the name of the
yonger was Rachel.</ab>
<ab n="17">Leah was tender
eyed: but Rachel was beautiful and well fauoured.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Iacob loued
Rachel, and said, I will serue thee seuen yeeres for Rachel thy
yonger daughter.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Laban said,
It is better that I giue her to thee, then that I should giue her
to another man: abide with mee.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Iacob serued
seuen yeeres for Rachel: and they seemed vnto him but a few dayes,
for the loue hee had to her.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And Iacob
said vnto Laban, Giue me my wife (for my dayes are fulfilled) that
I may goe in vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Laban
gathered together all the men of the place, and made a
feast.</ab>

<fw>He meeteth with Rachel, and marieth
her.</fw>
<ab n="23">And it came to
passe in the euening, that he tooke Leah his daughter, and brought
her to him, and he went in vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Laban gaue
vnto his daughter Leah, Zilpah his mayde, for a handmayd.</ab>
<ab n="25">And it came to
passe, that in the morning, behold it was Leah: and he said to
Laban, What is this thou hast done vnto mee? did not I serue with
thee for Rachel? wherefore then hast thou beguiled me?</ab>
<ab n="26">And Laban said,
It must not be so done in our countrey, to giue the yonger, before
the first borne.<note> Heb. place.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Fulfill her
weeke, and wee will giue thee this also, for the seruice which thou
shalt serue with mee, yet seuen other yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Iacob did
so, and fulfilled her weeke: and he gaue him Rachel his daughter to
wife also.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Laban gaue
to Rachel his daughter, Bilhah his handmayd, to be her
mayd.</ab>
<ab n="30">And hee went in
also vnto Rachel, and he loued also Rachel more then Leah, and
serued with him yet seuen other yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And when
the LORD saw that Leah was hated, hee opened her wombe: but Rachel
was barren.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Leah
conceiued and bare a sonne, and shee called his name Reuben: for
she said, Surely, the LORD hath looked vpon my affliction; now
therefore my husband will loue me.<note> That is, See a sonne.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And shee
conceiued againe, and bare a sonne, and saide, Because the LORD
hath heard that I was hated, hee hath therefore giuen mee this
sonne also, and she called his name Simeon.<note> That is, Hearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And shee
conceiued againe, and bare a sonne, and said, Now this time will my
husband be ioyned vnto me, because I haue borne him three sonnes:
therefore was his name called Leui.<note> That is, ioyned.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And shee
conceiued againe, and bare a sonne: and she said, Now wil I praise
the LORD: therefore she called his name Iudah, and left
bearing.<note> Matth. 1. 2. , That is, Praise. , Hebr. stood from bearing.</note></ab>



</div>