<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-34-34-Joshua.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 Moses from Mount Nebo vieweth the
lande. 5 He dieth there. 6 His buriall. 7 His age. 8 Thirty dayes
mourning for him. 9 Ioshua succeedeth him. 10 The praise of
Moses.</head>

<ab n="1">And Moses
went vp from the plaines of Moab, vnto the mountaine of Nebo, to
the top of Pisgah, that is ouer against Iericho: and the Lord
shewed him all the land of Gilead, vnto Dan,<note> Or, Hill. , Chap.3. 27 2.mac. 2.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And all
Naphtali, and the lande of Ephraim, and Manasseh, and all the land
of Iudah, vnto the vtmost sea.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the
South, and the plaine of the valley of Iericho, the citie of palme
trees vnto Zoar.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
said vnto him, This is the land which I sware vnto Abraham, vnto
Isaac, and vnto Iacob, saying, I will giue it vnto thy seed: I haue
caused thee to see it with thine eyes, but thou shalt not go ouer
thither.<note> Gen. 12.7 and 13.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ So
Moses the seruant of the Lord died there in the land of Moab,
according to the word of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Moses age, death, and
successour.</fw>
<ab n="6">And hee
buried him in a valley in the land of Moab, ouer against Beth-Peor:
but no man knoweth of his Sepulchre vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
Moses was an hundred and twentie yeeres olde when he died: his eye
was not dimme, nor his naturall force abated.<note> Hebr. moisture. , Hebr. fled.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plaines of Moab thirty
dayes: So the dayes of weeping and mourning for Moses were
ended.</ab>

<fw>Moses age, death, and
successour.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Ioshua the sonne of Nun was full of the Spirit of wisedome: for
Moses had layd his handes vpon him, and the children of Israel
hearkened vnto him, and did as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
there arose not a Prophet since in Israel like vnto Moses, whom the
Lord knew face to face:</ab>
<ab n="11">In al the
signes and the wonders which the Lord sent him to doe in the land
of Egypt, to Pharaoh, and to all his seruants, and to all his
land,</ab>
<ab n="12">And in all
that mighty hand, and in all the great terrour, which Moses shewed
in the sight of all Israel.</ab>



</div>