<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The end of the Law is obedience. 3
An exhortation thereto.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are
the Commaundements, the Statutes, &amp; the Iudgements, which the
Lord your God commanded to teach you, that ye might doe them in the
land whither ye goe to possesse it:<note> Hebr. passe ouer.</note></ab>

<fw>Of obedience.</fw>
<ab n="2">That thou
mightest feare the Lord thy God, to keepe all his Statutes, and his
Commandements which I command thee; thou, and thy sonne, and thy
sonnes sonne, all the dayes of thy life: and that thy dayes may be
prolonged.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Heare
therefore, O Israel, and obserue to do it, that it may be wel with
thee, and that ye may increase mightily, as the Lord God of thy
fathers hath promised thee, in the land that floweth with milke and
hony.</ab>
<ab n="4">Heare, O
Israel, the Lord our God is one Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">And thou shalt
loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soule,
and with all thy might.<note> Chap.10. 12. mat.22. 37. mar.12. 30. luke 10. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And these
words which I command thee this day, shall bee in thine
heart.<note> Chap.11. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And thou shalt
teach them diligently vnto thy children, and shalt talke of them
when thou sittest in thine house, and when thou walkest by the way,
and when thou liest downe, and when thou risest vp.<note> Heb. whet or sharpen.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And thou shalt
binde them for a signe vpon thine hand, and they shalbe as
frontlets betweene thine eyes.</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou shalt
write them vpon the posts of thy house, and on thy gates.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it shall
be when the Lord thy God shall haue brought thee into the land
which hee sware vnto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to
Iacob to giue thee, great and goodly cities, which thou buildedst
not,</ab>
<ab n="11">And houses
full of all good things which thou filledst not, and welles digged
which thou diggedst not, vineyards and oliue trees which thou
plantedst not, when thou shalt haue eaten and be full,<note> Chap.8.9, 10, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then beware
lest thou forget the Lord which brought thee forth out of the land
of Egypt, from the house of bondage.<note> Heb. bondmen or seruants.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Thou shalt
feare the Lord thy God, and serue him, &amp; shalt sweare by his
Name.<note> Chap. 10. 12, 20. and 13.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Yee shall not
goe after other gods, of the gods of the people which are round
about you:</ab>
<ab n="15">(For the Lord
thy God is a ielous God among you) lest the anger of the Lord thy
God bee kindled against thee, and destroy thee from off the face of
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Ye
shall not tempt the Lord your God, as yee tempted him in
Massah.<note> Mat.4.7. , Exod.17. 2.</note></ab>

<fw>Exhortations to obedience.</fw>
<ab n="17">You shall
diligently keepe the Commandements of the Lord your God, and his
Testimonies, and his Statutes, which he hath commanded
thee.</ab>
<ab n="18">And thou
shalt doe that which is right and good in the sight of the Lord:
that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest goe in, and
possesse the good land which the Lord sware vnto thy
fathers:</ab>
<ab n="19">To cast out
all thine enemies from before thee, as the Lord hath
spoken.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when thy
sonne asketh thee in time to come, saying, What meane the
Testimonies, &amp; the Statutes, and the Iudgements, which the Lord
our God hath commanded you?<note> Hebr. to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Then thou
shalt say vnto thy sonne, We were Pharaohs bondmen in Egypt, and
the Lord brought vs out of Egypt with a mighty hand.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Lord
shewed signes and wonders, great and sore vpon Egypt, vpon Pharaoh,
and vpon all his houshold, before our eyes:<note> Hebr. euil.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And hee
brought vs out from thence, that hee might bring vs in, to giue vs
the land which hee sware vnto our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the Lord
commanded vs to doe all these Statutes, to feare the Lord our God,
for our good alwayes, that he might preserue vs aliue, as it is at
this day.</ab>
<ab n="25">And it shall
be our righteousnes, if we obserue to doe all these Commandements,
before the Lord our God, as he hath commanded vs.</ab>



</div>