<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Gods mercie in restoring the two
Tables, 6 in continuing the Priesthood, 8 in separating the tribe
of Leui, 10 in hearkening vnto Moses his suit for the people. 12.
An exhortation vnto obedience.</head>

<ab n="1">At that time
the Lord said vnto me, Hew thee two Tables of stone, like vnto the
first, and come vp vnto mee into the mount, and make thee an Arke
of wood.<note> Exod.34. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And I will
write on the Tables the words that were in the first Tables which
thou brakest, and thou shalt put them in the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I made an
Arke of Shittim wood, and hewed two Tables of stone like vnto the
first, and went vp into the mount, hauing the two Tables in mine
hand.</ab>

<fw>Aaron dieth.</fw>
<ab n="4">And he wrote
on the Tables, according to the first writing, the tenne
Commandements, which the Lord spake vnto you in the mount, out of
the midst of the fire, in the day of the assembly: and the Lord
gaue them vnto me.<note> Hebr. words.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And I turned
my selfe and came downe from the mount, and put the Tables in the
Arke which I had made, and there they be, as the Lord commanded
me.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
the children of Israel tooke their iourney from Beeroth, of the
children of Iaakan, to Mosera; there Aaron died, and there he was
buried, and Eleazar his sonne ministred in the Priests office in
his stead.<note> Num. 33. 30. , Num. 20. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">From thence
they iourneyed vnto Gudgodah, and from Gudgodah to Iotbath, a land
of riuers of waters.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ At
that time the Lord separated the tribe of Leui, to beare the Arke
of the Couenant of the Lord, to stand before the Lord, to minister
vnto him, and to blesse in his Name, vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore
Leui hath no part nor inheritance with his brethren: the Lord is
his inheritance, according as the Lord thy God promised
him.<note> Num. 18. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And I stayed
in the mount, according to the first time, fortie dayes, and fortie
nights: and the Lord hearkened vnto mee at that time also, and the
Lord would not destroy thee.<note> Or, fortie dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord
said vnto me, Arise, take thy iourney before the people, that they
may goe in, and possesse the land which I sware vnto their fathers
to giue vnto them.<note> Hebr. goe in iourney.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
now Israel, what doeth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to
feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his waies, and to loue him,
and to serue the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy
soule,</ab>
<ab n="13">To keepe the
Commandements of the Lord, and his Statutes, which I commaund thee
this day for thy good?</ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, the
heauen, &amp; the heauen of heauens is the Lords thy God, the earth
also, with all that therein is.<note> Psal.24.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Onely the
Lord had a delight in thy fathers, to loue them, and hee chose
their seed after them, euen you, aboue all people, as it is this
day.</ab>
<ab n="16">Circumcise
therefore the foreskin of your heart, and bee no more
stiffenecked.</ab>

<fw>Exhortations.</fw>
<ab n="17">For the Lord
your God is God of gods, and Lord of lords, a great God, a mighty,
and a terrible, which regardeth not persons, nor taketh
reward.<note> 2.Chron. 19.7. iob 34.19. acts 10.34. rom. 2.11. galat. 2.6. ephes. 6.9. coloss, 3 25. 1. pet. 1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">He doeth
execute the iudgement of the fatherlesse, and widow, and loueth the
stranger, in giuing him food and raiment.</ab>
<ab n="19">Loue yee
therefore the stranger: for yee were strangers in the land of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou shalt
feare the Lord thy God; him shalt thou serue, and to him shalt thou
cleaue, and sweare by his Name.<note> Chap.6. 13. matt.4 10. luke 4. 8. , Chap. 13. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He is thy
praise, and he is thy God that hath done for thee these great and
terrible things, which thine eyes haue seene.</ab>
<ab n="22">Thy fathers
went downe into Egypt with threescore and ten persons: and now the
Lord thy God hath made thee as the starres of heauen, for
multitude.<note> Gene.46. 27. exod.1. 5. , Gene.15. 5.</note></ab>



</div>