<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Inticers to idolatrie, 6 how neere
soeuer vnto thee, 9 are to be stoned to death. 12 Idolatrous cities
are not to be spared.</head>

<ab n="1">If there
arise among you a prophet, or a dreamer of dreames, and giueth thee
a signe, or a wonder:</ab>
<ab n="2">And the signe
or the wonder come to passe, wherof he spake vnto thee, saying, Let
vs go after other gods (which thou hast not knowen) and let vs
serue them:</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou shalt
not hearken vnto the words of that prophet, or that dreamer of
dreames: for the Lord your God prooueth you, to know whether you
loue the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your
soule.</ab>
<ab n="4">Ye shall
walke after the Lord your God, and feare him, and keepe his
commandements, and obey his voyce, and you shall serue him, and
cleaue vnto him.<note> Chap. 11. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And that
prophet or that dreamer of dreames shalbe put to death (because hee
hath spoken to turne you away from the Lord your God, which brought
you out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed you out of the house of
bondage, to thrust thee out of the way which the Lord thy God
commanded thee to walke in) So shalt thou put the euill away from
the midst of thee.<note> Hebr. spoken reuolt against the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ If thy
brother, the sonne of thy mother, or thy sonne, or thy daughter, or
the wife of thy bosome, or thy friend, which is as thine owne
soule, entise thee secretly, saying, Let vs goe and serue other
gods which thou hast not knowen, thou, nor thy fathers:</ab>
<ab n="7">Namely of the
gods of the people which are round about you, nigh vnto thee, or
farre off from thee, from the one end of the earth, euen vnto the
other end of the earth:</ab>

<fw>Destroy Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="8">Thou shalt
not consent vnto him nor hearken vnto him, neither shall thine eye
pitie him, neither shalt thou spare, neither shalt thou conceale
him.</ab>
<ab n="9">But thou
shalt surely kill him: Thine hand shall be first vpon him, to put
him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the
people.<note> Chap. 17. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And thou
shalt stone him with stones, that hee die: because hee hath sought
to thrust thee away from the Lord thy God, which brought thee out
of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage.<note> Hebr. bondmen.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And all
Israel shall heare, and feare, and shall doe no more any such
wickednesse as this is, among you.<note> Chap. 17. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ If
thou shalt heare say in one of thy cities, which the Lord thy God
hath giuen thee to dwell there, saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Certaine
men, the children of Belial, are gone out from among you, and haue
withdrawen the inhabitants of their citie, saying, Let vs goe &amp;
serue other gods, which ye haue not knowen:<note> Or, naughty men.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Then shalt
thou enquire and make search, and aske diligently: and behold, if
it be trueth, and the thing certaine, that such abomination is
wrought among you:</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou shalt
surely smite the inhabitants of that citie with the edge of the
sword, destroying it vtterly, and all that is therein, and the
cattell thereof, with the edge of the sword.</ab>
<ab n="16">And thou
shalt gather all the spoile of it, into the midst of the street
thereof, and shalt burne with fire the citie, and all the spoile
thereof euery whit, for the Lord thy God: and it shall be an heape
for euer, it shall not bee built againe.</ab>
<ab n="17">And there
shall cleaue nought of the cursed thing to thine hand, that the
Lord may turne from the fiercenesse of his anger, and shew thee
mercy, and haue compassion vpon thee, and multiply thee, as he hath
sworne vnto thy fathers;<note> Or, deuoted.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">When thou
shalt hearken to the voyce of the Lord thy God, to keepe all his
Commaundements which I command thee this day, to doe that which is
right in the eyes of the Lord thy God.</ab>



</div>