<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The story of the conquest of Og
king of Bashan. 11 The bignes of his bed. 12 The distribution of
those lands to the two tribes and halfe. 23 Moses prayer to enter
into the land. 26 He is permitted to see it.</head>

<ab n="1">Then we
turned, and went vp the way to Bashan: and Og the King of Bashan
came out against vs, hee, and all his people to battell at
Edrei.<note> Num. 21. 33, &amp;c. cha. 29.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
said vnto mee, Feare him not: for I will deliuer him, and all his
people, and his land into thy hand, and thou shalt doe vnto him as
thou didst vnto Sihon king of the Amorites, which dwelt at
Heshbon.<note> Num. 21. 24.</note></ab>

<fw>Og is vanquished.</fw>
<ab n="3">So the Lord
our God deliuered into our hands Og also the King of Bashan, and
all his people: and wee smote him vntill none was left to him
remayning.<note> Num. 21. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And we tooke
all his cities at that time, there was not a citie which wee tooke
not from them; threescore cities, all the region of Argob, the
kingdome of Og in Bashan.</ab>
<ab n="5">All these
cities were fenced with high walles, gates and barres, beside
vnwalled townes a great many.</ab>
<ab n="6">And we vtterly
destroyed them, as we did vnto Sihon King of Heshbon, vtterly
destroying the men, women, and children of euery citie.</ab>
<ab n="7">But all the
cattell, and the spoile of the cities, we tooke for a pray to our
selues.</ab>
<ab n="8">And we tooke
at that time out of the hand of the two Kings of the Amorites, the
land that was on this side Iordan, from the riuer of Arnon, vnto
mount Hermon:</ab>
<ab n="9">(Which Hermon
the Sidonians call Syrion: and the Amorites call it
Shenir.)</ab>
<ab n="10">All the
cities of the plaine, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, vnto Salchah,
and Edrei, cities of the kingdome of Og in Bashan.</ab>
<ab n="11">For onely Og
King of Bashan remained of the remnant of giants; behold, his
bedsted was a bedsted of yron: is it not in Rabbath of the children
of Ammon? Nine cubites was the length thereof, and foure cubites
the breadth of it, after the cubite of a man.</ab>
<ab n="12">And this land
which we possessed at that time, from Aroer which is by the riuer
Arnon, and halfe mount Gilead, and the cities thereof, gaue I vnto
the Reubenites, and to the Gadites.<note> Num. 32. 33. iosh. 13. 8. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the rest
of Gilead, and all Bashan, being the kingdome of Og, gaue I vnto
the halfe tribe of Manasseh: All the region of Argob with all
Bashan, which was called the land of Giants.</ab>
<ab n="14">Iair the
sonne of Manasseh tooke all the countrey of Argob, vnto the coastes
of Geshuri, and Maachathi; and called them after his owne name,
Bashan Hauoth Iair, vnto this day.<note> Num. 32. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And I gaue
Gilead vnto Machir.</ab>

<fw>Moses prayer.</fw>
<ab n="16">And vnto the
Reubenites, and vnto the Gadites, I gaue from Gilead, euen vnto the
riuer Arnon, halfe the valley, and the border, euen vnto the riuer
Iabbok, which is the border of the children of Ammon:</ab>
<ab n="17">The plaine
also, and Iordan, and the coast thereof, from Chinnereth, euen vnto
the sea of the plaine, euen the salt sea, vnder Ashdoth Pisgah
Eastward.<note> Or, vnder the springs of Pisgah, or the hill.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And I
commanded you at that time, saying, The Lord your God hath giuen
you this land to possesse it: ye shall passe ouer armed before your
brethren the children of Israel, all that are meet for the
warre.<note> Num. 32. 20. , Heb. sonnes of power.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">But your
wiues, and your little ones, and your cattell (for I know that ye
haue much cattel) shall abide in your cities, which I haue giuen
you:</ab>
<ab n="20">Untill the
Lord haue giuen rest vnto your brethren, as well as vnto you, and
vntill they also possesse the land which the Lord your God hath
giuen them beyond Iordan: and then shall ye returne euery man vnto
his possession, which I haue giuen you.<note> Iosh. 22. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And I
commanded Ioshua at that time, saying, Thine eyes haue seene all
that the Lord your God hath done vnto these two Kings: so shal the
Lord doe vnto all the kingdomes whither thou passest.<note> Num. 27. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Ye shall not
feare them: for the Lord your God, he shal fight for you.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I
besought the Lord at that time, saying,</ab>
<ab n="24">O Lord God,
thou hast begun to shew thy seruant thy greatnesse, and thy mighty
hand: for what God is there in heauen, or in earth, that can do
according to thy workes, and according to thy might?</ab>
<ab n="25">I pray thee
let me goe ouer, and see the good land that is beyond Iordan, that
goodly mountaine and Lebanon.</ab>
<ab n="26">But the Lord
was wroth with me for your sakes, and would not heare mee: and the
Lord said vnto me, Let it suffice thee, speake no more vnto me of
this matter.<note> Num. 20. 12. chap. 1. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Get thee vp
into the top of Pisgah, and lift vp thine eyes Westward, and
Northward, and Southward, and Eastward, and beholde it with thine
eyes: for thou shalt not goe ouer this Iordan.<note> Or, the hill.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">But charge
Ioshua, and encourage him, and strengthen him: for hee shall goe
ouer before this people, and he shall cause them to inherite the
land which thou shalt see.</ab>

<fw>Exhortations to obedience.</fw>
<ab n="29">So we abode
in the valley, ouer against Beth-Peor.</ab>



</div>