<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-32-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 Moses song, which setteth foorth
Gods mercy and vengeance. 46 He exhorteth them to set their hearts
vpon it. 48 God sendeth him vp to mount Nebo, to see the land, and
die.</head>

<ab n="1">Giue eare, O
yee heauens, and I will speake; And heare, O earth, the words of my
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="2">My doctrine
shall drop as the raine: my speech shall distill as the deaw, as
the smal raine vpon the tender herbe, and as the showres vpon the
grasse.</ab>
<ab n="3">Because I wil
publish the Name of the Lord: ascribe yee greatnesse vnto our
God.</ab>
<ab n="4">He is the
rocke, his worke is perfect: for all his wayes are Iudgement: A God
of trueth, and without iniquity, iust and right is he.</ab>
<ab n="5">They haue
corrupted themselues, their spot is not the spot of his children:
they are a peruerse and crooked generation.<note> Hebr. he hath corrupted to himselfe. , Or, that they are not his children, that is their blot.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Doe ye thus
requite the Lord, O foolish people, &amp; vnwise? Is not he thy
Father that hath bought thee? Hath he not made thee, and
established thee?</ab>

<fw>The song of Moses.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶
Remember the dayes of olde, consider the yeeres of many
generations: aske thy father, and he will shewe thee, thy Elders,
and they wil tell thee.<note> Heb. generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">When the most
High diuided to the nations their inheritance, when he separated
the sonnes of Adam, hee set the bounds of the people according to
the number of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="9">For the Lords
portion is his people: Iacob is the lot of his
inheritance.<note> Heb. cord.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">He found him
in a desert land, and in the waste howling wildernesse: Hee ledde
him about, he instructed him, hee kept him as the apple of his
eye.<note> Or, compassed him about,</note></ab>
<ab n="11">As an Eagle
stirreth vp her nest, fluttereth ouer her yong, spreadeth abroad
her wings, taketh them, beareth them on her wings:</ab>
<ab n="12">So the Lord
alone did leade him, and there was no strange God with him.</ab>
<ab n="13">He made him
ride on the high places of the earth, that he might eate the
increase of the fields, and he made him to sucke hony out of the
rocke, and oyle out of the flintie rocke,</ab>
<ab n="14">Butter of
kine, &amp; milke of sheepe, with fat of lambes, and rammes of the
breed of Bashan, &amp; goats, with the fat of kidneis of wheat, and
thou diddest drinke the pure blood of the grape.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ But
Iesurun waxed fat, and kicked: Thou art waxen fat, thou art growen
thicke, thou art couered with fatnes: then he forsooke God which
made him, and lightly esteemed the Rocke of his saluation.</ab>
<ab n="16">They
prouoked him to ielousie with strange gods, with abominations
prouoked they him to anger.</ab>
<ab n="17">They
sacrificed vnto deuils, not to God: to gods whom they knew not, to
new gods, that came newly vp, whom your fathers feared
not.<note> Or, which were not God.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Of the Rocke
that begate thee thou art vnmindfull, and hast forgotten God that
formed thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when the
Lord saw it, he abhorred them, because of the prouoking of his
sonnes, &amp; of his daughters.<note> Or, despised.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And he said,
I will hide my face from them, I will see what their ende shall be:
for they are a very froward generation, children in whom is no
faith.</ab>

<fw>The song of Moses.</fw>
<ab n="21">They haue
mooued me to ielousie with that which is not god, they haue
prouoked me to anger with their vanities: And I will moue them to
ielousie with those which are not a people, I will prouoke them to
anger with a foolish nation.<note> Rom.10.9</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For a fire
is kindled in my anger, and shall burne vnto the lowest hell, and
shall consume the earth with her increase, and set on fire the
foundations of the mountaines.<note> Or, hath burned. , Or, hath consumed.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">I will heape
mischiefes vpon them, I will spend mine arrowes vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="24">They shall
bee burnt with hunger and deuoured with burning heat, and with
bitter destruction: I will also send the teeth of beasts vpon them,
with the poison of serpents of the dust.<note> Heb. burning coales.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The sword
without, and terrour within shall destroy both the yong man, and
the virgin, the suckling also with the man of gray
haires.<note> Heb. from the chambers. , Heb. bereaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">I said, I
would scatter them into corners, I would make the remembrance of
them to cease frō among men:</ab>
<ab n="27">Were it not
that I feared the wrath of the enemie, lest their aduersaries
should behaue themselues strangely, and lest they should say, Our
hande is high, and the Lord hath not done all this.<note> Or, our high hand and not the LORD hath done all this.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For they are
a nation voide of counsel, neither is there any vnderstanding in
them.</ab>
<ab n="29">O that they
were wise, that they vnderstood this, that they would consider
their latter end.</ab>
<ab n="30">How should
one chase a thousand, and two put ten thousand to flight, except
their Rocke had sold them, and the Lord had shut them
vp?<note> Iosh. 23. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For their
rocke is not as our Rocke, euen our enemies themselues being
iudges.</ab>
<ab n="32">For their
vine is of the vine of Sodome, and of the fields of Gomorah: their
grapes are grapes of gall, their clusters are bitter.<note> Or, is worse then the vine of Sodome. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Their wine
is the poison of dragons, and the cruell venime of Aspes.</ab>
<ab n="34">Is not this
laide vp in store with me, and sealed vp among my
treasures?</ab>
<ab n="35">To me
belongeth vengeance, and recompence, their foot shall slide in due
time: for the day of their calamitie is at hand, and the things
that shal come vpon them, make haste.<note> Ecclus.28 1. rom.12. 19. Heb.10. 30.</note></ab>

<fw>Moses song: He may see Canaan.</fw>
<ab n="36">For the Lord
shall iudge his people, and repent himselfe for his seruants, when
he seeth that their power is gone; and there is none shut vp, or
left.<note> Heb. hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And he shall
say, where are their gods? their Rocke in whom they
trusted;</ab>
<ab n="38">Which did
eat the fat of their sacrifices, &amp; dranke the wine of their
drinke offerings? let them rise vp and helpe you, and be your
protection.<note> Hebr. an hiding for you.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">See now,
that I, euen I am he, and there is no god with mee; I kill, and I
make aliue: I wound, and I heale: neither is there any that can
deliuer out of my hand.<note> 1.Sam.2. 6. tob. 13.2. wisd. 16. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">For I lift
vp my hand to heauen, and say, I liue for euer.</ab>
<ab n="41">If I whet my
glittering sword, and mine hand take holde on Iudgement, I will
render vengeance to mine enemies, and will reward them that hate
me.</ab>
<ab n="42">I will make
mine arrowes drunke with blood, (and my sword shal deuoure flesh)
and that with the blood of the slaine, and of the captiues, from
the beginning of reuenges vpon the enemie.</ab>
<ab n="43">Reioyce, O
ye nations with his people, for he will auenge the blood of his
seruants, and will render vengeance to his aduersaries, and wil be
mercifull vnto his land, and to his people.<note> Or, praise his people ye nations. Or, sing ye. , Matt.7.6. rom.15.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ And
Moses came and spake all the wordes of this song in the eares of
the people, he and Hoshea the sonne of Nun.<note> Or, Ioshua.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And Moses
made an end of speaking all these words to all Israel.</ab>
<ab n="46">And hee said
vnto them, Set your hearts vnto all the wordes which I testifie
among you this day, which yee shall commaund your children to
obserue to doe all the wordes of this Law.<note> Chap.6.6. and 11. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">For it is
not a vaine thing for you: because it is your life, and through
this thing yee shall prolong your dayes, in the land whither yee
goe ouer Iordan to possesse it.</ab>
<ab n="48">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses that selfe same day, saying,<note> Num. 27. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">Get thee vp
into this mountaine Abarim, vnto mount Nebo, which is in the land
of Moab, that is ouer against Iericho, and behold the land of
Canaan which I giue vnto the children of Israel for a
possession:</ab>

<fw>Moses song: He may see Canaan.</fw>
<ab n="50">And die in
the mount whither thou goest vp, and bee gathered vnto thy people,
as Aaron thy brother died in mount Hor, and was gathered vnto his
people:<note> Num.20. 25, 28. and 33.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">Because ye
trespassed against me among the children of Israel, at the waters
of Meribah Kadesh, in the wildernesse of Zin: because yee
sanctified mee not in the midst of the children of
Israel.<note> Num. 10. 12, 13. and 27.14. , Or strife at Kadesh.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Yet thou
shalt see the land before thee, but thou shalt not goe thither vnto
the land which I giue the children of Israel.</ab>



</div>