<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The story is continued, that they
were not to meddle with the Edomites, 9 nor with the Moabites, 17
nor with the Ammonites, 24 but Sihon the Amorite was subdued by
them.</head>

<ab n="1">Then we
turned, and tooke our iourney into the wildernesse, by the way of
the Red sea, as the Lord spake vnto mee: and wee compassed mount
Seir many dayes.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
spake vnto me, saying,</ab>

<fw>A repetition of former things.</fw>
<ab n="3">Yee haue
compassed this mountaine long enough: turne you Northward.</ab>
<ab n="4">And commaund
thou the people, saying, Ye are to passe through the coast of your
brethren the children of Esau, which dwell in Seir, and they shall
be afraid of you: take ye good heed vnto your selues
therefore.</ab>
<ab n="5">Meddle not
with them, for I will not giue you of their land, no not so much as
a foote breadth, because I haue giuen mount Seir vnto Esau for a
possession.<note> Hebr. euen to the treading of the sole of the foote. , Gene. 36. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Ye shall buy
meat of them for money, that ye may eat, and yee shall also buy
water of them for money, that yee may drinke.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the Lord
thy God hath blessed thee, in all the workes of thy hand: hee
knoweth thy walking thorow this great wildernesse: these fourtie
yeres the Lord thy God hath bene with thee, thou hast lacked
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when we
passed by from our brethren the children of Esau, which dwelt in
Seir, thorow the way of the plaine from Elath, and from
Ezion-Gaber, wee turned and passed by the way of the wildernesse of
Moab.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the Lord
said vnto mee, Distresse not the Moabites, neither contend with
them in battell: for I wil not giue thee of their land for a
possession, because I haue giuen Ar vnto the children of Lot for a
possession.<note> Or, vse no hostilitie against Moab.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The Emims
dwelt therein in times past, a people great, and many, and tall, as
the Anakims:</ab>
<ab n="11">Which also
were accounted giants, as the Anakims, but the Moabites call them
Emims.</ab>
<ab n="12">The Horims
also dwelt in Seir beforetime, but the children of Esau succeeded
them when they had destroyed them from before them, &amp; dwelt in
their stead, as Israel did vnto the land of his possession, which
the Lord gaue vnto them.<note> Gen. 36. 20. , Hebr. inherited them. , Or, roome.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Now rise vp,
said I, and get you ouer the brooke Zered: and we went ouer the
brooke Zered.<note> Num. 21. 12. , Or, valley.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the space
in which we came from Kadesh Barnea, vntill we were come ouer the
brooke Zered, was thirtie and eight yeeres; vntill all the
generation of the men of warre were wasted out from among the
hoste, as the Lord sware vnto them.</ab>

<fw>King Sihon is ouercome.</fw>
<ab n="15">For indeed
the hand of the Lord was against them, to destroy them from among
the hoste, vntill they were consumed.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ So it
came to passe, when all the men of warre were consumed and dead
from among the people,</ab>
<ab n="17">That the Lord
spake vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">Thou art to
passe ouer thorow Ar, the coast of Moab, this day.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when thou
commest nigh ouer against the children of Ammon, distresse them
not, nor meddle with them: for I will not giue thee of the lande of
the children of Ammon any possession, because I haue giuen it vnto
the children of Lot for a possession:</ab>
<ab n="20">(That also
was accounted a land of Giants: giants dwelt therein in old time,
and the Ammonites call them Zamzummims.</ab>
<ab n="21">A people
great, and many, and tall, as the Anakims: but the Lord destroyed
them before them, and they succeeded them &amp; dwelt in their
stead:)</ab>
<ab n="22">As he did to
the children of Esau which dwelt in Seir, when he destroyed the
Horims from before them, and they succeeded them, and dwelt in
their stead euen vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the Auims
which dwelt in Hazerim, euen vnto Azzah, the Caphtorims which came
foorth out of Caphtor, destroyed them, and dwelt in their
stead.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Rise
ye vp, take your iourney, and passe ouer the riuer Arnon: Behold, I
haue giuen into thy hand Sihon the Amorite king of Heshbon, and his
land: begin to possesse it, and contend with him in
battell.<note> Heb. begin, possesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">This day will
I begin to put the dread of thee, and the feare of thee vpon the
nations, that are vnder the whole heauen, who shall heare report of
thee, and shall tremble, and be in anguish because of thee.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And I
sent messengers out of the wildernesse of Kedemoth, vnto Sihon king
of Heshbon, with wordes of peace, saying,</ab>
<ab n="27">Let me passe
through thy land: I will goe along by the high way, I will neither
turne vnto the right hand, nor to the left.<note> Num. 21. 21, 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Thou shalt
sell me meat for money, that I may eate, and giue me water for
money that I may drinke: Only I will passe through on my
feet:</ab>

<fw>King Sihon is ouercome.</fw>
<ab n="29">As the
children of Esau which dwell in Seir, and the Moabites which dwell
in Ar, did vnto me, vntill I shall passe ouer Iordan, into the land
which the Lord our God giueth vs.</ab>
<ab n="30">But Sihon
King of Heshbon would not let vs passe by him: for the Lord thy God
hardened his spirit, and made his heart obstinate, that hee might
deliuer him into thy hand, as appeareth this day.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the Lord
said vnto mee, Behold, I haue begun to giue Sihon and his land
before thee: begin to possesse, that thou mayest inherit his
land.</ab>
<ab n="32">Then Sihon
came out against vs, he &amp; all his people to fight at
Iahaz.<note> Num. 21. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the Lord
our God deliuered him before vs, and wee smote him, and his sonnes,
and all his people.</ab>
<ab n="34">And we tooke
all his cities at that time, and vtterly destroyed the men, and the
women, and the litle ones of euery citie, we left none to
remaine:<note> Heb. euery citie of men and women and litle ones.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Onely the
cattell wee tooke for a pray vnto our selues, and the spoyle of the
cities, which we tooke:</ab>
<ab n="36">From Aroer,
which is by the brinke of the riuer of Arnon, and from the citie
that is by the riuer euen vnto Gilead, there was not one citie too
strong for vs: the Lord our God deliuered all vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="37">Onely vnto
the land of the children of Ammon thou camest not, nor vnto any
place of the riuer Iabbok, nor vnto the cities in the mountaines,
nor vnto whatsoeuer the Lord our God forbade vs.</ab>



</div>