<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation to obedience in
regard of Gods dealing with them.</head>

<ab n="1">All the
commaundements which I commaund thee this day, shall yee obserue to
doe, that yee may liue, and multiply, and goe in, and possesse the
land which the Lord sware vnto your fathers.</ab>
<ab n="2">And thou shalt
remember all the way which the Lord thy God led thee these fourtie
yeeres in the wildernesse, to humble thee, and to proue thee, to
know what was in thine heart, whether thou wouldest keepe his
commandements, or no.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he humbled
thee, and suffred thee to hunger, and fed thee with Manna, which
thou knewest not, neither did thy fathers know: that he might make
thee know, that man doth not liue by bread onely, but by euery word
that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord doth man
liue.<note> Matt.4.4. luke 4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Thy raiment
waxed not old vpon thee, neither did thy foote swell these fourtie
yeeres.<note> Nehe.9. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou shalt
also consider in thine heart, that as a man chasteneth his son, so
the Lord thy God chasteneth thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore thou
shalt keepe the Commandements of the Lord thy God, to walke in his
wayes, and to feare him.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the Lord
thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a lande of brookes of
water, of fountaines, and depths that spring out of valleys and
hilles,</ab>
<ab n="8">A land of
wheate, and barley, and vines, and fig trees, and pomegranats, a
land of oyle oliue, and hony,<note> Hebr. of oliue tree of oyle.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">A lande
wherein thou shalt eate bread without scarcenes, thou shalt not
lacke any thing in it: a lande whose stones are yron, and out of
whose hils thou mayest digge brasse.</ab>
<ab n="10">When thou
hast eaten and art full, then thou shalt blesse the Lord thy God,
for the good lande which hee hath giuen thee.<note> Chap.6. 12.13.</note></ab>

<fw>Of ingratitude.</fw>
<ab n="11">Beware that
thou forget not the Lord thy God, in not keeping his Commandements,
and his Iudgements, and his Statutes which I command thee this
day:</ab>
<ab n="12">Lest when
thou hast eaten and art full, and hast built goodly houses, and
dwelt therein;</ab>
<ab n="13">And when thy
heards and thy flocks multiply, and thy siluer and thy gold is
multiplied, and all that thou hast is multiplied:</ab>
<ab n="14">Then thine
heart bee lifted vp, and thou forget the Lord thy God (which
brought thee foorth out of the land of Egypt, from the house of
bondage,</ab>
<ab n="15">Who led thee
through that great and terrible wildernesse, wherein were fierie
serpents, and scorpions, &amp; drought, where there was no water,
who brought thee foorth water out of the rocke of
flint,<note> Num.20. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Who fed thee
in the wildernesse with Manna, which thy fathers knew not, that hee
might humble thee, and that hee might prooue thee, to doe thee good
at thy latter end:)<note> Exod.16. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And thou say
in thine heart, My power, and the might of mine hand hath gotten me
this wealth.</ab>
<ab n="18">But thou
shalt remember the Lord thy God: for it is he that giueth thee
power to get wealth, that he may establish his Couenant, which he
sware vnto thy fathers, as it is this day.</ab>
<ab n="19">And it
shalbe, if thou doe at all forget the Lord thy God, and walke after
other gods, and serue them, and worship them; I testifie against
you this day, that ye shall surely perish.</ab>
<ab n="20">As the
nations which the Lord destroyeth before your face, so shall yee
perish; because ye would not be obedient vnto the voice of the Lord
your God.</ab>



</div>