<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Monuments of Idolatrie are to be
destroyed. 5 The place of Gods seruice is to be kept. 15. 23 Blood
is forbidden. 17. 20. 26 Holy things must bee eaten in the Holy
place. 19 The Leuite is not to be forsaken. 29 Idolatrie is not be
inquired after.</head>

<ab n="1">These are the
Statutes, and Iudgements, which ye shal obserue to do, in the land
which the Lord God of thy fathers giueth thee to possesse it, all
the dayes that yee liue vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="2">Yee shall
vtterly destroy all the places, wherein the nations which yee shall
possesse, serued their gods, vpon the high mountaines, and vpon the
hils, and vnder euery greene tree.<note> Chap. 7. 5. , Or, inherite.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And you shall
ouerthrow their altars, and breake their pillars, and burne their
groues with fire, and you shall hew downe the grauen images of
their gods, and destroy the names of them out of that
place.<note> Iudg. 2. 2. , Heb. break downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Yee shall not
doe so vnto the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="5">But vnto the
place which the Lord your God shall chuse out of all your tribes,
to put his name there, euen vnto his habitation shall yee seeke,
and thither thou shalt come:<note> 1. King. 8. 29. 2. chro. 7. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And thither
yee shall bring your burnt offrings, and your sacrifices, and your
tithes, and heaue offrings of your hand, and your vowes, and your
free wil offerings, and the firstlings of your heards, and of your
flocks.</ab>
<ab n="7">And there ye
shall eate before the Lord your God, and yee shall reioyce in all
that you put your hand vnto, ye and your housholds, wherein the
Lord thy God hath blessed thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Ye shall not
do after all the things that we doe here this day, euery man
whatsoeuer is right in his owne eyes.</ab>

<fw>The place of burnt offrings.</fw>
<ab n="9">For yee are
not as yet come to the rest, and to the inheritance which the Lord
your God giueth you.</ab>
<ab n="10">But when yee
goe ouer Iordan, and dwel in the land which the Lord your God
giueth you to inherite, and when he giueth you rest from all your
enemies round about, so that ye dwell in safety:</ab>
<ab n="11">Then there
shall be a place which the Lord your God shall choose to cause his
name to dwell there, thither shall ye bring all that I command you;
your burnt offerings, and your sacrifices, your tithes, and the
heaue offring of your hand, &amp; all your choice vowes, which ye
vow vnto the Lord.<note> Hebr. the choice of your vowes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And yee
shall reioyce before the Lord your God, ye and your sonnes and your
daughters, and your men seruants, and your maid seruants, and the
Leuite that is within your gates, forasmuch as hee hath no part nor
inheritance with you.<note> Chap. 10. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Take heed to
thy selfe, that thou offer not thy burnt offerings in euery place
that thou seest:</ab>
<ab n="14">But in the
place which the Lord shal choose in one of thy tribes, there thou
shalt offer thy burnt offerings, and there thou shalt do all that I
command thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">Notwithstanding,
thou mayest kill and eate flesh in all thy gates, whatsoeuer thy
soule lusteth after, according to the blessing of the Lord thy God
which he hath giuen thee: the vncleane and the cleane may eate
thereof, as of the Roe bucke, and as of the Hart.</ab>
<ab n="16">Onely ye
shall not eat the blood: yee shall powre it vpon the earth as
water.<note> Chap. 15. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Thou
mayest not eate within thy gates the tithe of thy corne, or of thy
wine, or of thy oyle, or the firstlings of thy heards, or of thy
flocke, nor any of thy vowes which thou vowest, nor thy free will
offerings, or heaue offering of thine hand:</ab>
<ab n="18">But thou
must eate them before the Lord thy God, in the place which the Lord
thy God shall choose, thou and thy sonne, and thy daughter, and thy
man seruant, and thy maid seruant, and the Leuite that is within
thy gates: and thou shalt reioyce before the Lord thy God, in all
that thou puttest thine hands vnto.</ab>
<ab n="19">Take heed to
thy selfe, that thou forsake not the Leuite, as long as thou liuest
vpon the earth.<note> Chap. 14 27. ecclus. 7. 31. , Hebr. al thy dayes.</note></ab>

<fw>Eate no blood.</fw>
<ab n="20">¶ When
the Lord thy God shall enlarge thy border, as hee hath promised
thee, and thou shalt say, I will eate flesh (because thy soule
longeth to eat flesh) thou mayest eat flesh whatsoeuer thy soule
lusteth after.<note> Gene. 28. 14. chap. 19.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">If the place
which the Lord thy God hath chosen to put his Name there, be too
farre from thee, then thou shalt kill of thy herd and of thy
flocke, which the Lord hath giuen thee, as I haue commaunded thee,
and thou shalt eate in thy gates, whatsoeuer thy soule lusteth
after.</ab>
<ab n="22">Euen as the
Roe bucke and the Hart is eaten, so thou shalt eate them: the
vncleane and the cleane shall eate of them alike.</ab>
<ab n="23">Onely be
sure that thou eate not the blood: for the blood is the life, and
thou mayest not eate the life with the flesh.<note> Heb. bee strong.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Thou shalt
not eate it; thou shalt powre it vpon the earth as water.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thou shalt
not eate it, that it may goe well with thee, and with thy children
after thee, when thou shalt doe that which is right in the sight of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="26">Onely thy
holy things which thou hast, and thy vowes, thou shalt take, and
goe vnto the place which the Lord shall chuse.</ab>
<ab n="27">And thou
shalt offer thy burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood, vpon the
altar of the Lord thy God: and the blood of thy sacrifices shall be
powred out vpon the altar of the Lord thy God, and thou shalt eat
the flesh.</ab>
<ab n="28">Obserue
&amp; heare all these words which I command thee, that it may go
well with thee, and with thy children after thee for euer, when
thou doest that which is good and right in the sight of the Lord
thy God.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ When
the Lord thy God shall cut off the nations from before thee,
whither thou goest to possesse them, and thou succeedest them, and
dwellest in their land:<note> Heb. inheritest or possessest them.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Take heede
to thy selfe that thou be not snared by following them, after that
they be destroyed from before thee, and that thou enquire not after
their gods, saying, How did these nations serue their gods? euen so
will I doe likewise.<note> Heb. after them.</note></ab>

<fw>Flee idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="31">Thou shalt
not doe so vnto the Lord thy God: for euery abomination to the Lord
which hee hateth, haue they done vnto their gods: for euen their
sonnes and their daughters they haue burnt in the fire to their
gods.<note> Heb. abomination of the.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">What thing
soeuer I command you, obserue to doe it: thou shalt not adde
thereto, nor diminish from it.<note> Chap. 4. 2 iosh. 1. 7. pro. 30. 6. reue. 22. 18.</note></ab>



</div>