<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 The things sacrificed must bee
sound. 2 Idolaters must bee slaine. 8 Hard controuersies are to bee
determined by the Priests and Iudges. 12 The contemner of that
Determination must die. 14 The election, 16 and duetie of a
King.</head>

<ab n="1">Thou shalt
not sacrifice vnto the Lord thy God any bullocke, or sheepe wherein
is blemish, or any euilfauourednes: for that is an abomination vnto
the Lord thy God.<note> Or, goat.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ If
there bee found among you within any of thy gates which the Lord
thy God giueth thee, man or woman that hath wrought wickednes in
the sight of the Lord thy God, in transgressing his
couenant,</ab>
<ab n="3">And hath gone
and serued other gods, and worshipped them, either the Sunne, or
Moone, or any of the hoste of heauen, which I haue not
commanded,</ab>
<ab n="4">And it be
told thee, and thou hast heard of it, and inquired diligently, and
behold, it be true, and the thing certaine, that such abomination
is wrought in Israel:</ab>
<ab n="5">Then shalt
thou bring forth that man, or that woman (which haue committed that
wicked thing) vnto thy gates, euen that man, or that woman, and
shalt stone them with stones till they die.</ab>
<ab n="6">At the mouth
of two witnesses, or three witnesses, shall he that is worthy of
death, be put to death: but at the mouth of one witnesse he shall
not bee put to death.<note> Num. 35. 30. chap. 17. 6. &amp; 19. 15. mat.18.16. iohn 8.17. 2.cor.13.1. Heb.10.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The hands of
the witnesses shall be first vpon him, to put him to death, and
afterward the hands of all the people: so thou shalt put the euil
away from among you.</ab>

<fw>The excercise of the King.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ If
there arise a matter too hard for thee in iudgement, betweene blood
and blood, betweene plea and plea, and betweene stroke and stroke,
being matters of controuersie within thy gates: then shalt thou
arise, and get thee vp into the place, which the Lord thy God shall
choose;</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou
shalt come vnto the Priests the Leuites, &amp; vnto the Iudge that
shal be in those dayes, and enquire; and they shall shew thee the
sentence of Iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou
shalt doe according to the sentence which they of that place (which
the Lord shall choose) shall shew thee, and thou shalt obserue to
do according to all that they enforme thee:</ab>
<ab n="11">According to
the sentence of the Law which they shall teach thee, and according
to the Iudgement which they shall tell thee thou shalt doe: thou
shalt not decline from the Sentence which they shall shew thee, to
the right hand, nor to the left.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the man
that will doe presumptuously, and will not hearken vnto the Priest
(that standeth to minister there before the Lord thy God) or vnto
the Iudge, euen that man shall die, and thou shalt put away the
euill from Israel.<note> Hebr. not to hearken,</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And all the
people shal heare, and feare, and doe no more
presumptuously.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ When
thou art come vnto the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee, and
shalt possesse it, and shalt dwell therein, and shalt say, I will
set a King ouer mee, like as all the nations that are about
me:</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou shalt
in any wise set him King ouer thee, whom the Lord thy God shall
choose. One from among thy brethren shalt thou set King ouer thee:
thou mayest not set a stranger ouer thee, which is not thy
brother.</ab>
<ab n="16">But he shall
not multiply horses to himselfe, nor cause the people to returne to
Egypt, to the ende that hee should multiply horses: for as much as
the Lord hath said vnto you, Yee shall hencefoorth returne no more
that way.</ab>
<ab n="17">Neither
shall he multiply wiues to himselfe, that his heart turne not away:
neither shall hee greatly multiply to himselfe siluer and
gold.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it shall
be when he sitteth vpon the Throne of his kingdome, that he shall
write him a copy of this Law in a booke, out of that which is
before the Priests the Leuites.</ab>

<fw>The excercise of the King.</fw>
<ab n="19">And it shall
be with him, and hee shall reade therein all the dayes of his life,
that hee may learne to feare the Lord his God, to keep all the
words of this Law, and these Statutes, to do them:</ab>
<ab n="20">That his
heart bee not lifted vp aboue his brethren, and that hee turne not
aside from the Commandement, to the right hand, or to the left: to
the end that hee may prolong his dayes in his kingdome, hee, and
his children in the midst of Israel.</ab>



</div>