<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 The confession of him that
offereth the basket of First fruits. 12 The prayer of him that
giueth his third yeere Tithes. 16 The couenant betweene God and the
people.</head>

<ab n="1">And it shall
be when thou art come in vnto the land which the Lord giueth thee
for an inheritance, and possessest it, and dwellest
therein:</ab>

<fw>First fruits.</fw>
<ab n="2">That thou
shalt take of the first of all the fruit of the earth, which thou
shalt bring of thy land that the Lord thy God giueth thee, and
shalt put it in a basket, and shalt goe vnto the place which the
Lord thy God shal choose to place his Name there:</ab>
<ab n="3">And thou
shalt goe vnto the Priest that shall be in those dayes, and say
vnto him, I professe this day vnto the Lord thy God, that I am come
vnto the countrey which the Lord sware vnto our fathers for to giue
vs.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the
Priest shall take the basket out of thine hand, and set it downe
before the Altar of the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="5">And thou
shalt speake and say before the Lord thy God, A Syrian ready to
perish was my father, and hee went downe into Egypt, and soiourned
there with a few, and became there a nation, great, mighty, and
populous.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the
Egyptians euil intreated vs, and afflicted vs, and layd vpon vs
hard bondage.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when wee
cryed vnto the Lord God of our fathers, the Lord heard our voyce,
and looked on our affliction, and our labour, and our
oppression.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the Lord
brought vs foorth out of Egypt with a mightie hand, and with an
out-stretched arme, and with great terriblenesse, and with signes,
and with wonders.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he hath
brought vs into this place, and hath giuen vs this land, euen a
land that floweth with milke and honie.</ab>
<ab n="10">And now
behold, I haue brought the First fruits of the land, which thou, O
Lord, hast giuen mee: and thou shalt set it before the Lord thy
God, and worship before the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="11">And thou
shalt reioyce in euery good thing, which the Lord thy God hath
giuen vnto thee, and vnto thine house, thou, and the Leuite, and
the stranger that is among you.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ When
thou hast made an end of tithing all the tithes of thine increase,
the third yeere, which is the yeere of tything, and hast giuen it
vnto the Leuite, the stranger, the fatherlesse, and the widow, that
they may eate within thy gates, and be filled:<note> Chap.14 28.</note></ab>

<fw>Exhortations to obedience.</fw>
<ab n="13">Then thou
shalt say before the Lord thy God, I haue brought away the hallowed
things out of mine house, and also haue giuen them vnto the Leuite,
and vnto the stranger, to the fatherlesse, and to the widow,
according to all thy commandements, which thou hast commanded me: I
haue not transgressed thy commandements, neither haue I forgotten
them.</ab>
<ab n="14">I haue not
eaten thereof in my mourning, neither haue I taken away ought
thereof for any vncleane vse, nor giuen ought thereof for the dead:
but I haue hearkened to the voyce of the Lord my God, and haue done
according to all that thou hast commaunded me.</ab>
<ab n="15">Looke downe
from thy holy habitation, from heauen, and blesse thy people
Israel, and the land which thou hast giuen vs, as thou swarest vnto
our fathers, a land that floweth with milke and hony.<note> Esa.63.15</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ This
day the Lord thy God hath commanded thee to doe these Statutes and
Iudgements: thou shalt therefore keepe and doe them with all thine
heart, and with all thy soule.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thou hast
auouched the Lord this day to be thy God, and to walke in his
wayes, and to keepe his Statutes, and his Commaundements, and his
Iudgements, and to hearken vnto his voice.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Lord
hath auouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, as he hath
promised thee, and that thou shouldest keepe all his
Commaundements:<note> Chap. 7.6</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And to make
thee high aboue all nations which he hath made, in praise and in
name, and in honour, and that thou mayest be an holy people vnto
the Lord thy God, as he hath spoken.</ab>



</div>