<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 The Maiestie of God. 6 The
blessings of the twelue Tribes. 26 The excellency of
Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">And this is
the blessing, wherewith Moses the man of God blessed the children
of Israel before his death.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said,
The Lord came from Sinai, and rose vp from Seir vnto them, hee
shined foorth from mount Paran, and hee came with ten thousands of
Saints: from his Right hand went a fierie Law for them.<note> Hebr. a fire of law.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Yea hee loued
the people; all his Saints are in thy hand: and they sate downe at
thy feete; euery one shall receiue of thy wordes.</ab>
<ab n="4">Moses
commaunded vs a Law, euen the inheritance of the Congregation of
Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee was
King in Iesurun, when the heads of the people, and the Tribes of
Israel were gathered together.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Let
Reuben liue, and not die, and let not his men be few.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
this is the blessing of Iudah: and he said, Heare, Lord, the voice
of Iudah, and bring him vnto his people: let his hands bee
sufficient for him, and bee thou an helpe to him from his
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And of
Leui hee said, Let thy Thummim and thy Urim be with thy holy one,
whom thou diddest prooue at Massah, &amp; with whom thou didst
striue at the waters of Meribah:<note> Exod. 28. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Who said vnto
his father &amp; to his mother, I haue not seene him, neither did
hee acknowledge his brethren; nor knew his owne children: for they
haue obserued thy word, and kept thy Couenant.</ab>

<fw>Moses blesseth the tribes of
Israel.</fw>
<ab n="10">They shal
teach Iacob thy iudgments, and Israel thy Lawe: they shall put
incense before thee, and whole burnt sacrifice vpon thine
Altar.<note> Or, let them teach, &amp;c. , Or, let them put incense. , Heb. at thy nose.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Blesse,
Lord, his substance, and accept the worke of his handes, smite
thorow the loines of them that rise against him, and of them that
hate him, that they rise not againe.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
of Beniamin he said, The beloued of the Lord shall dwell in safetie
by him, and the Lord shall couer him all the day long, and he shall
dwell betweene his shoulders.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
of Ioseph he said, Blessed of the Lord be his land, for the
precious things of heauen, for the dew, and for the deep that
coucheth beneath;<note> Gen.49. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And for the
precious fruits brought forth by the sunne, and for the precious
things put forth by the moone,<note> Heb. thrust forth. , Hebr. Moones.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And for the
chiefe things of the ancient mountaines, and for the precious
things of the lasting hils,</ab>
<ab n="16">And for the
precious things of the earth, and fulnesse thereof, and for the
good will of him that dwelt in the bush: let the blessing come vpon
the head of Ioseph, and vpon the top of the head of him that was
separated frō his brethren.<note> Gen.49. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">His glory is
like the firstling of his bullocke, &amp; his hornes are like the
hornes of Unicornes: with them he shall push the people together,
to the ends of the earth: and they are the ten thousands of
Ephraim, and they are the thousands of Manasseh.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And
of Zebulun he said, Reioyce, Zebulun, in thy going out; and
Issachar, in thy tents.</ab>
<ab n="19">They shall
call the people vnto the mountaine, there they shal offer
sacrifices of righteousnesse: for they shall sucke of the abundance
of the seas, and of treasures hid in the sand.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
of Gad he said, Blessed be he that enlargeth Gad: he dwelleth as a
lyon, and teareth the arme with the crowne of the head.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he
prouided the first part for himselfe, because there, in a portion
of the lawgiuer was he seated, and hee came with the heads of the
people, he executed the iustice of the Lord, and his iudgments with
Israel.<note> Heb. sieled.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
of Dan he said, Dan is a Lyons whelpe: hee shall leape from
Bashan.</ab>

<fw>Moses blesseth the tribes of
Israel.</fw>
<ab n="23">¶ And
of Naphtali he said, O Naphtali, satisfied with fauour, and full
with the blessing of the Lord: possesse thou the West and the
South.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And
of Asher hee said, let Asher be blessed with children, Let him be
acceptable to his brethren, and let him dip his foot in
oile.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thy shooes
shall bee yron and brasse, and as thy dayes, so shall thy strength
bee.<note> Or, vnder thy shooes shalbe yron.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ There
is none like vnto the God of Iesurun, who rideth vpon the heauen in
thy helpe, and in his excellencie on the skie.</ab>
<ab n="27">The eternall
God is thy refuge, and vnderneath are the euerlasting armes: and he
shall thrust out the enemie from before thee, and shall say,
Destroy them.</ab>
<ab n="28">Israel then
shall dwell in safetie alone: the fountaine of Iacob shalbe vpon a
land of corne and wine, also his heauens shall drop downe
deaw.<note> Ier.23.6</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Happy art
thou, O Israel: Who is like vnto thee, O people! saued by the Lord,
the shield of thy helpe, and who is the sword of thy excellencie:
and thine enemies shal be found liars vnto thee, and thou shalt
tread vpon their high places.<note> Or, shal be subdued.</note></ab>



</div>