<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 Iacobs vision at Mahanaim. 3 His
message to Esau. 6 He is afraid of Esaus comming. 9 He prayeth for
deliuerance. 13 Hee sendeth a present to Esau. 24 He wrestleth with
an Angel at Peniel, where hee is called Israel. 31 He
halteth.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iacob went on
his way, and the Angels of God met him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And when Iacob
saw them, he said, This is Gods hoste: and hee called the name of
that place Mahanaim.<note> That is, two hostes or campes.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Iacob sent
messengers before him, to Esau his brother, vnto the land of Seir,
the countrey of Edom.<note> Heb. Field.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And he commaunded
them, saying, Thus shall ye speake vnto my lord Esau, Thy seruant
Iacob saith thus, I haue soiourned with Laban, and stayed there
vntill now.</ab>
<ab n="5">And I haue oxen,
and asses, flockes, and men seruants and women seruants: and I haue
sent to tell my lord, that I may find grace in thy sight.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
messengers returned to Iacob, saying, Wee came to thy brother Esau,
and also he commeth to meet thee, and foure hundred men with
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then Iacob was
greatly afraid, and distressed, and he diuided the people that was
with him, and the flockes, and herdes, and the camels into two
bands,</ab>
<ab n="8">And said, If Esau
come to the one company, and smite it, then the other company which
is left, shall escape.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Iacob
said, O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Isaac, the
LORD which saidst vnto me, Returne vnto thy countrey, and to thy
kinred, and I will deale well with thee:<note> Chap. 31. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">I am not worthy
of the least of all the mercies, and of all the trueth, which thou
hast shewed vnto thy seruant: for with my staffe I passed ouer this
Iordan, and now I am become two bands.<note> Heb. I am lesse then all &amp;c</note></ab>

<fw>Iacobs present.</fw>
<ab n="11">Deliuer me, I
pray thee, from the hand of my brother, from the hand of Esau: for
I feare him, lest he will come, and smite me, and the mother with
the children.<note> Heb. vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And thou saidst,
I will surely doe thee good, and make thy seed as the sand of the
sea, which cannot be numbred for multitude.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And he
lodged there that same night, and tooke of that which came to his
hand, a present for Esau his brother:</ab>
<ab n="14">Two hundred shee
goats, and twentie hee goats, two hundred ewes, and twentie
rammes,</ab>
<ab n="15">Thirtie milch
camels with their colts, fortie kine, and ten bulles, twenty shee
ashes, and ten foales.</ab>
<ab n="16">And hee
deliuered them into the hand of his seruants, euery droue by
themselues, and said vnto his seruants, Passe ouer before me, and
put a space betwixt droue and droue.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he commanded
the formost, saying, When Esau my brother meeteth thee, and asketh
thee, saying, whose art thou? and whither goest thou? and whose are
these before thee?</ab>
<ab n="18">Then thou shalt
say, They be thy seruant Iacobs: it is a present sent vnto my lord
Esau: and behold also, he is behind vs.</ab>
<ab n="19">And so commanded
he the second, and the third, and all that followed the droues,
saying, On this maner shal you speake vnto Esau, when you find
him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And say ye
moreouer, Beholde, thy seruant Iacob is behind vs: for he said, I
will appease him with the present that goeth before me, and
afterward I will see his face; peraduenture he will accept of
me.<note> Heb. my face.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">So went the
present ouer before him: and himselfe lodged that night in the
company.</ab>
<ab n="22">And hee rose vp
that night, and tooke his two wiues, and his two women seruants,
and his eleuen sonnes, and passed ouer the foord Iabbok.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he tooke
them, and sent them ouer the brooke, and sent ouer that hee
had.<note> Heb. caused to passe.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And Iacob
was left alone: and there wrestled a man with him, vntill the
breaking of the day.<note> Hebr. Ascending of the morning.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And when he saw,
that he preuailed not against him, he touched the hollow of his
thigh: and the hollow of Iacobs thigh was out of ioynt, as hee
wrestled with him.</ab>

<fw>He is named Israel.</fw>
<ab n="26">And he said, Let
me goe, for the day breaketh: and he said, I will not let thee goe,
except thou blesse me.<note> Ose.12.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And he said vnto
him, what is thy name? and he said, Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he said, Thy
name shall be called no more Iacob, but Israel: for as a prince
hast thou power with God, and with men, and hast
preuailed.<note> Chap. 35. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And Iacob asked
him, and saide, Tell me, I pray thee, thy name: and he said,
wherefore is it, that thou doest aske after my name? and he blessed
him there.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Iacob called
the name of the place Peniel: for I haue seene God face to face,
and my life is preserued.<note> That is, The face of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And as he passed
ouer Penuel, the sunne rose vpon him, and he halted vpon his
thigh.</ab>
<ab n="32">Therefore the
children of Israel eate not of the sinewe which shranke, which is
vpon the hollow of the thigh, vnto this day: because hee touched
the hollow of Iacobs thigh, in the sinewe that shranke.</ab>



</div>