<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Of diuorce. 5 A new maried man
goeth not to warre. 6. 10 Of pledges. 7 Of manstealers. 8 Of
leprosie. 14 The hire is to be giuen. 16 Of Iustice. 19 Of
Charitie.</head>

<ab n="1">When a man
hath taken a wife and married her, and it come to passe that shee
find no fauour in his eyes, because hee hath found some
vncleannesse in her: then let him write her a bill of diuorcement,
and giue it in her hand, and send her out of his house.<note> Matt.5. 31. and 19. 7. mar.10.4. , Hebr. matter of nakednesse. , Hebr. cutting off.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And when shee
is departed out of his house, she may goe and be another mans
wife.</ab>
<ab n="3">And if the
latter husband hate her, and write her a bill of diuorcement, and
giueth it in her hand, and sendeth her out of his house: Or if the
latter husband die, which tooke her to be his wife,</ab>
<ab n="4">Her former
husband which sent her away, may not take her againe to be his
wife, after that she is defiled: for that is abomination before the
Lord, and thou shalt not cause the land to sinne, which the Lord
thy God giueth thee for an inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ When a
man hath taken a new wife, he shal not goe out to warre, neither
shall hee be charged with any businesse: but hee shall be free at
home one yeere, and shall cheere vp his wife which he hath
taken.<note> Chap.20. 7. , Hebr. not any thing shall passe vpon him.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ No man
shall take the nether or the vpper milstone to pledge: for hee
taketh a mans life to pledge.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ If a
man bee found stealing any of his brethren of the children of
Israel, and maketh merchandize of him, or selleth him: then that
thiefe shall die, and thou shalt put euill away from among
you.</ab>

<fw>Of lending.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ Take
heede, in the plague of leprosie, that thou obserue diligently, and
doe according to all that the Priests the Leuites shall teach you:
as I commanded them, so ye shall obserue to doe.<note> Leuit.13. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Remember what
the Lord thy God did vnto Miriam by the way, after that yee were
come forth out of Egypt.<note> Num. 12. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ When
thou doest lend thy brother any thing, thou shalt not goe into his
house to fetch his pledge.<note> Heb. lend the loane of any thing to &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Thou shalt
stand abroad, and the man to whome thou doest lend, shall bring out
the pledge abroad vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">And if the
man be poore, thou shalt not sleepe with his pledge:</ab>
<ab n="13">In any case
thou shalt deliuer him the pledge againe when the Sun goeth downe,
that he may sleepe in his owne raiment, and blesse thee: and it
shall be righteousnesse vnto thee before the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Thou
shalt not oppresse an hired seruant that is poore and needy,
whether he be of thy brethren, or of thy strangers that are in thy
lande within thy gates.</ab>
<ab n="15">At his day
thou shalt giue him his hire, neither shall the Sun goe downe vpon
it, for he is poore, and setteth his heart vpon it, lest hee crie
against thee vnto the Lord, and it bee sinne vnto thee.<note> Leuit.19. 13. tob.4. 14. , Heb. hee lifteth his soule vnto it.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The fathers
shall not bee put to death for the children, neither shall the
children be put to death for the fathers: euery man shall be put to
death for his owne sinne.<note> 2. Kings 14.6. 2.chr. 25.4. ier. 31.29.30. ezek.18.20</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Thou
shalt not peruert the iudgement of the stranger, nor of the
fatherles, nor take a widowes raiment to pledge.</ab>
<ab n="18">But thou
shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt, and the Lord thy
God redeemed thee thence: therefore I command thee to doe this
thing.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ When
thou cuttest downe thine haruest in thy field, and hast forgot a
sheafe in the field, thou shalt not go againe to fetch it: it
shalbe for the stranger, for the fatherlesse, and for the widow:
that the Lord thy God may blesse thee in all the worke of thine
hands.<note> Leuit.19. 9. &amp; 23.22.</note></ab>

<fw>Raising seed.</fw>
<ab n="20">When thou
beatest thine oliue tree thou shalt not goe ouer the boughes
againe: it shall be for the stranger, for the fatherlesse, and for
the widow.<note> Heb. thou shalt not bough it after thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">When thou
gatherest the grapes of thy vineyard, thou shalt not gleane it
afterward, it shalbe for the stranger, for the fatherlesse, and for
the widow.<note> Heb. after thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And thou
shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in the land of Egypt:
therfore I command thee to doe this thing.</ab>



</div>