<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 The Priests exhortation to
encourage the people to battell. 5 The officers proclamation who
are to be dismissed from the warre. 10 How to vse the Cities that
accept or refuse the proclamation of peace. 16 What Cities must bee
deuoted. 19 Trees of mans meat must not be destroyed in the
siege.</head>


<fw>Offer peace.</fw>
<ab n="1">When thou
goest out to battell against thine enemies, and seest horses and
charets, and a people more then thou, be not afraid of them: for
the Lord thy God is with thee, which brought thee vp out of the
land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="2">And it shall
bee when ye are come nigh vnto the battell, that the Priest shall
approach and speake vnto the people,</ab>
<ab n="3">And shall say
vnto them, Heare O Israel, you approach this day vnto battell
against your enemies: let not your hearts faint, feare not, and doe
not tremble, neither be ye terrified because of them.<note> Hebr. be tender. , Hebr. make haste.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For the Lord
your God is hee that goeth with you, to fight for you against your
enemies, to saue you.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And
the Officers shall speake vnto the people, saying, What man is
there that hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? let
him goe and returne to his house, lest hee die in the battell, and
an other man dedicate it.</ab>
<ab n="6">And what man
is hee that hath planted a Uineyard, and hath not yet eaten of it?
let him also go and returne vnto his house, lest he die in the
battell, and an other man eate of it.<note> Heb. made it common See Leuit. 19.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And what man
is there that hath betrothed a wife, and hath not taken her? let
him goe and returne vnto his house, lest he die in battell, and
another man take her.<note> Chap.24. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the
Officers shall speake further vnto the people: and they shall say,
What man is there that is fearefull and faint hearted? let him goe
and returne vnto his house, lest his brethrens heart faint as well
as his heart.<note> Iudg. 7.3. , Hebr. melt.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall
be when the Officers haue made an end of speaking vnto the people,
that they shall make Captaines of the armies to leade the
people.<note> Hebr. to be in the head of the people.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ When
thou commest nigh vnto a City to fight against it, then proclaime
peace vnto it.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it shall
be, if it make thee answere of peace, and open vnto thee, then it
shalbe that all the people that is found therein, shall be
tributaries vnto thee, and they shall serue thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">And if it
will make no peace with thee, but will make warre against thee,
then thou shalt besiege it.</ab>

<fw>Of murder that is not knowen.</fw>
<ab n="13">And when the
Lord thy God hath deliuered it into thine hands, thou shalt smite
euery male thereof with the edge of the sword.</ab>
<ab n="14">But the
women, and the litle ones, and the cattell, and all that is in the
citie, euen all the spoile thereof, shalt thou take vnto thy selfe,
and thou shalt eate the spoile of thine enemies, which the Lord thy
God hath giuen thee.<note> Iosh.8.2. , Heb. spoile</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thus shalt
thou doe vnto all the cities which are very far off from thee,
which are not of the cities of these nations.</ab>
<ab n="16">But of the
cities of these people which the Lord thy God doth giue thee for an
inheritance, thou shalt saue aliue nothing that breatheth:</ab>
<ab n="17">But thou
shalt vtterly destroy them, namely, the Hittites, and the Amorites,
the Canaanites, and the Perizzites, the Hiuites, and the Iebusites,
as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee:</ab>
<ab n="18">That they
teach you not to do after all their abominations, which they haue
done vnto their gods, so should ye sinne against the Lord your
God.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ When
thou shalt besiege a citie a long time, in making warre against it
to take it, thou shalt not destroy the trees thereof, by forcing an
axe against them: for thou mayest eate of them, and thou shalt not
cut them downe ( for the tree of the field is mans life) to employ
them in the siege.<note> Or, for, O man the tree of the field is to be employed in the siege. , Heb. to goe from before thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Only the
trees which thou knowest that they be not trees for meate, thou
shalt destroy, and cut them downe, and thou shalt build bulwarkes
against the city that maketh warre with thee, vntil it be
subdued.<note> Hebr. it come downe.</note></ab>



</div>