<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 The people are commanded to write
the Law vpon stones, 5 and to build an Altar of whole stones. 11
The Tribes diuided on Gerizzim and Ebal. 14 The curses pronounced
on mount Ebal.</head>

<ab n="1">And Moses
with the Elders of Israel commaunded the people, saying, Keepe all
the Commandements which I command you this day.</ab>

<fw>Exhortations to obedience.</fw>
<ab n="2">And it shall
be on the day when you shall passe ouer Iordan, vnto the land which
the Lord thy God giueth thee, that thou shalt set thee vp great
stones, and plaister them with plaister.<note> Iosh. 4.1</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And thou
shalt write vpon them all the words of this Law when thou art
passed ouer, that thou mayest goe in vnto the land which the Lord
thy God giueth thee, a land that floweth with milke and hony, as
the Lord God of thy fathers hath promised thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore it
shall be when ye bee gone ouer Iordan, that yee shall set vp these
stones, which I command you this day, in mount Ebal, and thou shalt
plaister them with plaister.</ab>
<ab n="5">And there
shalt thou build an Altar vnto the Lord thy God, an altar of
stones: thou shalt not lift vp any yron toole vpon
them.<note> Exod.20. 25. iosh.8.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou shalt
build the Altar of the Lord thy God of whole stones: and thou shalt
offer burnt offerings theron vnto the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thou
shalt offer peace offerings, and shalt eate there, and reioyce
before the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou
shalt write vpon the stones all the words of this Law very
plainely.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Moses, and the Priestes the Leuites, spake vnto all Israel, saying,
Take heed, and hearken O Israel, this day thou art become the
people of the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou shalt
therefore obey the voyce of the Lord thy God, and doe his
Commandements, and his Statutes which I command thee this
day.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
Moses charged the people the same day, saying,</ab>
<ab n="12">These shall
stand vpon mount Gerizzim to blesse the people, when yee are come
ouer Iordan: Simeon, and Leui, and Iudah, and Issachar, and Ioseph,
and Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="13">And these
shall stand vpon mount Ebal to curse: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and
Zebulun, Dan, &amp; Naphtali.<note> Hebr. for a cursing.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
the Leuites shal speake, and say vnto all the men of Israel with a
loud voyce:<note> Dan.9.11</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Cursed be
the man that maketh any grauen or molten image, an abomination vnto
the Lord, the worke of the handes of the craftesman, and putteth it
in a secret place: and all the people shall answere and say,
Amen.</ab>
<ab n="16">Cursed be he
that setteth light by his father or his mother: and all the people
shall say, Amen.</ab>

<fw>Blessings for the obedient.</fw>
<ab n="17">Cursed be he
that remooueth his neighbours land-marke: and all the people shall
say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="18">Cursed be
hee that maketh the blinde to wander out of the way: and all the
people shall say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="19">Cursed be
hee that peruerteth the iudgement of the stranger, fatherlesse, and
widow: and all the people shall say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="20">Cursed be
hee that lieth with his fathers wife, because he vncouereth his
fathers skirt: and all the people shall say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="21">Cursed be
hee that lieth with any maner of beast: and all the people shall
say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="22">Cursed be
hee that lieth with his sister, the daughter of his father, or the
daughter of his mother: and all the people shall say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="23">Cursed be
hee that lieth with his mother in law: and all the people shall
say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="24">Cursed be
hee that smiteth his neighbour secretly: and all the people shall
say, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="25">Cursed be he
that taketh reward to slay an innocent person: and all the people
shall say, Amen.<note> Ezech. 22. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Cursed be
hee that confirmeth not all the words of this Law to doe them: and
al the people shal say, Amen.<note> Gal.3.10.</note></ab>



</div>