<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Moses disswadeth them from the
opinion of their owne righteousnesse, by rehearsing their seuerall
rebellions.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare, O
Israel, thou art to passe ouer Iordan this day, to goe in, to
possesse nations greater &amp; mightier then thy selfe, Cities
great, and fenced vp to heauen,</ab>

<fw>God, a fire.</fw>
<ab n="2">A people great
and tall, the children of the Anakims, whom thou knowest, and of
whom thou hast heard say, Who can stand before the children of
Anak?<note> Num.13 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Understand
therefore this day, that the Lord thy God is he, which goeth ouer
before thee, as a consuming fire: he shall destroy them, and he
shall bring them downe before thy face: So shalt thou driue them
out, and destroy them quickly, as the Lord hath said vnto
thee.<note> Chap.4. 24. Hebr.12. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Speake not
thou in thine heart, after that the Lord thy God hath cast them out
from before thee, saying, For my righteousnesse the Lord hath
brought mee in to possesse this land: but for the wickednesse of
these nations, the Lord doeth driue them out from before
thee.</ab>
<ab n="5">Not for thy
righteousnesse, or for the vprightnesse of thine heart, doest thou
goe to possesse their land: But for the wickednesse of these
nations the Lord thy God doeth driue them out from before thee, and
that he may performe the word which the Lord sware vnto thy
fathers, Abraham, Isaac and Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="6">Understand
therefore, that the Lord thy God giueth thee not this good land to
possesse it, for thy righteousnesse; for thou art a stiffe-necked
people.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶
Remember and forget not, how thou prouokedst the Lord thy God to
wrath in the wildernesse: from the day that thou didst depart out
of the land of Egypt, vntill ye came vnto this place, yee haue bene
rebellious against the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">Also in Horeb
yee prouoked the Lord to wrath, so that the Lord was angry with
you, to haue destroyed you.</ab>
<ab n="9">When I was
gone vp into the mount, to receiue the Tables of stone, euen the
Tables of the Couenant which the Lord made with you, then I abode
in the mount fortie dayes, and fortie nights, I neither did eate
bread, nor drinke water:<note> Exod. 24. 18.and.34 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the Lord
deliuered vnto me two Tables of stone, written with the finger of
God, and on them was written according to all the words which the
Lord spake with you in the mount, out of the midst of fire, in the
day of the assembly.<note> Exod. 31. 18.</note></ab>

<fw>The Tables broken, are renewed.</fw>
<ab n="11">And it came
to passe at the end of fortie dayes, and fortie nights, that the
Lord gaue mee the two Tables of stone, euen the Tables of the
Couenant.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the Lord
said vnto mee, Arise, get thee downe quickly from hence; for thy
people which thou hast brought foorth out of Egypt, haue corrupted
themselues: they are quickly turned aside out of the way which I
commanded them; they haue made them a molten image.<note> Exod.32. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Furthermore,
the Lord spake vnto me, saying, I haue seene this people, and
behold, it is a stifnecked people.</ab>
<ab n="14">Let me alone,
that I may destroy them, and blot out their name from vnder heauen:
and I will make of thee a nation mightier and greater then
they.</ab>
<ab n="15">So I turned
and came downe from the mount, and the mount burned with fire: and
the two Tables of the Couenant were in my two hands.</ab>
<ab n="16">And I looked,
and behold, ye had sinned against the Lord your God, and had made
you a molten calfe: ye had turned aside quickly out of the way
which the Lord had commanded you.</ab>
<ab n="17">And I tooke
the two Tables, and cast them out of my two hands, and brake them
before your eyes.</ab>
<ab n="18">And I fell
downe before the Lord, as at the first, fortie dayes and fortie
nights, I did neither eate bread nor drinke water, because of all
your sinnes which ye sinned, in doing wickedly in the sight of the
Lord, to prouoke him to anger.</ab>
<ab n="19">(For I was
afraid of the anger, and whot displeasure wherewith the Lord was
wroth against you, to destroy you.) But the Lord hearkned vnto me
at that time also.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord
was very angry with Aaron, to haue destroyed him: And I prayed for
Aaron also the same time.</ab>
<ab n="21">And I tooke
your sinne, the calfe which ye had made, and burnt it with fire,
and stamped it, and ground it very small, euen vntill it was as
small as dust: and I cast the dust therof into the brooke that
descended out of the mount.</ab>
<ab n="22">And at
Taberah, and at Massah, and at Kibroth-Hattaauah, ye prouoked the
Lord to wrath.<note> Num.11. 1, 3. , Exod.17. 7. , Num. 11. 34.</note></ab>

<fw>The Tables broken, are renewed.</fw>
<ab n="23">Likewise when
the Lord sent you from Kadesh Barnea, saying, Goe vp and possesse
the land which I haue giuen you, then you rebelled against the
commandement of the Lord your God, and ye beleeued him not, nor
hearkened to his voyce.</ab>
<ab n="24">You haue bin
rebellious against the Lord, from the day that I knew you.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thus I fell
downe before the Lord fourtie dayes, and fourtie nights, as I fel
downe at the first, because the Lord had said, he would destroy
you.</ab>
<ab n="26">I prayed
therefore vnto the Lord, and said, O Lord God, destroy not thy
people, and thine inheritance, which thou hast redeemed through thy
greatnes, which thou hast brought foorth out of Egypt, with a
mightie hand.</ab>
<ab n="27">Remember thy
seruants, Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, looke not vnto the
stubburnnesse of this people, nor to their wickednes, nor to their
sinne:</ab>
<ab n="28">Lest the land
whence thou broughtest vs out, say, Because the Lord was not able
to bring them into the land which hee promised them, and because
hee hated them, hee hath brought them out, to slay them in the
wildernesse.<note> Num.14. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Yet they are
thy people, and thine inheritance which thou broughtest out by thy
mightie power, and by thy stretched out arme.</ab>



</div>