<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 Great mercies promised vnto the
repentant. 11 The Commaundement is manifest. 15 Death and life are
set before them.</head>

<ab n="1">And it shall
come to passe when all these things are come vpon thee, the
blessing, and the curse, which I haue set before thee, and thou
shalt call them to minde among all the nations whither the Lord thy
God hath driuen thee,</ab>
<ab n="2">And shalt
returne vnto the Lord thy God, and shalt obey his voyce according
to all that I command thee this day, thou and thy children with al
thine heart, and with all thy soule:</ab>

<fw>Mercie to the repentant.</fw>
<ab n="3">That then the
Lord thy God will turne thy captiuitie, and haue compassion vpon
thee, and wil returne and gather thee from all the nations whither
the Lord thy God hath scattered thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">If any of
thine be driuen out vnto the outmost parts of heauen, from thence
will the Lord thy God gather thee, and from thence will he fetch
thee.<note> Nehe.1. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the Lord
thy God will bring thee into the land which thy fathers possessed,
and thou shalt possesse it: and he will doe thee good, and multiply
thee aboue thy fathers.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Lord
thy God will circumcise thine heart, and the heart of thy seed, to
loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy soule,
that thou mayest liue.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the Lord
thy God will put all these curses vpon thine enemies, and on them
that hate thee, which persecuted thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou
shalt returne and obey the voice of the Lord, and doe all his
Commandements which I command thee this day.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the Lord
thy God will make thee plenteous in euery worke of thine hand, in
the fruit of thy body, and in the fruit of thy cattell, and in the
fruit of thy land, for good: for the Lord will againe reioyce ouer
thee for good, as he reioyced ouer thy fathers:<note> Chap.28. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">If thou
shalt hearken vnto the voyce of the Lord thy God to keepe his
Commandements, and his Statutes which are written in this booke of
the Law, and if thou turne vnto the Lord thy God with all thine
heart, and with all thy soule.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ For
this Commaundement which I command thee this day, it is not hidden
from thee, neither is it farre off.</ab>
<ab n="12">It is not in
heauen, that thou shouldest say, Who shal goe vp for vs to heauen,
and bring it vnto vs, that wee may heare it, and doe
it?<note> Rom. 10. 6. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Neither is
it beyond the sea, that thou shouldest say, Who shall goe ouer the
sea for vs, and bring it vnto vs, that we may heare it, and doe
it?</ab>
<ab n="14">But the word
is very nigh vnto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou
mayest doe it.</ab>

<fw>Life and death.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ See,
I haue set before thee this day, life and good, and death, and
euill:</ab>
<ab n="16">In that I
command thee this day to loue the Lord thy God, to walke in his
wayes, and to keepe his Commandements, and his Statutes, and his
Iudgements, that thou maiest liue and multiply: and the Lord thy
God shall blesse thee in the land, whither thou goest to possesse
it.</ab>
<ab n="17">But if thine
heart turne away, so that thou wilt not heare, but shalt bee drawen
away, and worship other gods and serue them:</ab>
<ab n="18">I denounce
vnto you this day, that ye shall surely perish, and that yee shall
not prolong your dayes vpon the land, whither thou passest ouer
Iordan, to goe to possesse it.</ab>
<ab n="19">I call
heauen and earth to record this day against you, that I haue set
before you life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose
life, that both thou and thy seed may liue:<note> Chap.4. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">That thou
maiest loue the Lord thy God, and that thou mayest obey his voyce,
and that thou mayest cleaue vnto him: for he is thy life, and the
length of thy dayes, that thou mayest dwell in the land, which the
Lord sware vnto thy fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Iacob, to
giue them.</ab>



</div>