<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Of humanitie toward brethren. 5
The sexe is to bee distinguished by apparell. 6 The dam is not to
be taken with her yong ones. 8 The house must haue battlements. 9
Confusion is to be auoyded. 12 Fringes vpon the vesture. 13 The
punishment of him that slandereth his wife. 20.22 Of adulterie, 25
of rape, 28 and of fornication. 30 Incest.</head>

<ab n="1">Thou shalt
not see thy brothers oxe, or his sheepe go astray, and hide thy
selfe from them: thou shalt in any case bring them againe vnto thy
brother.<note> Exod. 23. 4.</note></ab>

<fw>Apparell.</fw>
<ab n="2">And if thy
brother be not nigh vnto thee, or if thou know him not, then thou
shalt bring it vnto thine owne house, and it shall be with thee,
vntil thy brother seeke after it, and thou shalt restore it to him
againe.</ab>
<ab n="3">In like maner
shalt thou do with his asse, and so shalt thou doe with his
raiment: and with all lost thing of thy brothers which he hath
lost, and thou hast found, shalt thou do likewise: thou mayest not
hide thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Thou
shalt not see thy brothers asse or his oxe fall downe by the way,
and hide thy selfe from them: thou shalt surely helpe him to lift
them vp againe.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ The
woman shall not weare that which pertaineth vnto a man, neither
shall a man put on a womans garment: for all that doe so, are
abomination vnto the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ If a
birds nest chance to be before thee in the way in any tree, or on
the ground, whether they be yong ones, or egges, and the damme
sitting vpon the yong, or vpon the egges, thou shalt not take the
damme with the yong.</ab>
<ab n="7">But thou
shalt in any wise let the damme goe, and take the yong to thee,
that it may be well with thee, and that thou mayest prolong thy
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ When
thou buildest a new house, then thou shalt make a battlement for
thy roofe, that thou bring not blood vpon thine house, if any man
fall from thence.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Thou
shalt not sow thy vineyard with diuers seeds: lest the fruit of thy
seed which thou hast sowen, and the fruit of thy Uineyard be
defiled.<note> Hebr. fulnesse of the seed.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Thou
shalt not plow with an oxe and an asse together.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Thou
shalt not weare a garment of diuers sorts, as of woollen, and
linnen together.<note> Leuit. 19.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Thou
shalt make thee fringes vpon the foure quarters of thy vesture,
wherewith thou couerest thy selfe.<note> Num. 15. 38. , Hebr. wings.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ If
any man take a wife, and go in vnto her, and hate her,</ab>
<ab n="14">And giue
occasions of speach against her, and bring vp an euill name vpon
her, and say, I tooke this woman, and when I came to her, I found
her not a mayd:</ab>

<fw>The punishment of whoredome.</fw>
<ab n="15">Then shal
the father of the damosell, and her mother take, and bring forth
the tokens of the damosels virginitie, vnto the Elders of the citie
in the gate.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the
damosels father shall say vnto the Elders, I gaue my daughter vnto
this man to wife, &amp; he hateth her:</ab>
<ab n="17">And loe, he
hath giuen occasions of speech against her, saying, I found not thy
daughter a maid: and yet these are the tokens of my daughters
virginity; and they shall spread the cloth before the Elders of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
Elders of that citie shall take that man, and chastise him.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they
shall amearse him in an hundred shekels of siluer, and giue them
vnto the father of the damosell, because he hath brought vp an
euill name vpon a virgine of Israel: and she shall be his wife, hee
may not put her away all his dayes.</ab>
<ab n="20">But if this
thing be true, and the tokens of virginitie be not found for the
damosel:</ab>
<ab n="21">Then they
shall bring out the damosell to the doore of her fathers house, and
the men of her city shal stone her with stones that she die,
because she hath wrought folly in Israel, to play the whore in her
fathers house: so shalt thou put euill away from among you.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ If a
man be found lying with a woman married to an husband, then they
shall both of them die, both the man that lay with the woman, and
the woman: so shalt thou put away euill from Israel.<note> Leuit. 20. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ If a
damosell that is a virgin be betrothed vnto an husband, and a man
find her in the citie, and lie with her:</ab>
<ab n="24">Then yee
shall bring them both out vnto the gate of that citie, and yee
shall stone them with stones that they die; the damosel, because
shee cried not, being in the citie; and the man, because he hath
humbled his neighbours wife: so thou shalt put away euill from
among you.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ But
if a man find a betrothed damosel in the field, and the man force
her, and lie with her: then the man only that lay with her, shall
die.<note> Or, take strong hold of her.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But vnto the
damosel thou shalt doe nothing, there is in the damosel no sinne
worthy of death: for as when a man riseth against his neighbour,
and slayeth him, euen so is this matter.</ab>
<ab n="27">For he found
her in the field, and the betrothed damosel cried, and there was
none to saue her.</ab>

<fw>The punishment of whoredome.</fw>
<ab n="28">¶ If a
man finde a damosel that is a virgin, which is not betrothed, and
lay hold on her, and lie with her, and they be found:<note> Exod.22. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Then the man
that lay with her, shall giue vnto the damosels father fifty
shekels of siluer, and she shalbe his wife, because he hath humbled
her: he may not put her away all his dayes.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ A man
shall not take his fathers wife, nor discouer his fathers
skirt.<note> Leuit.18. 8.</note></ab>



</div>