<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-28-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-28-28b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 The blessings for Obedience. 15
The curses for disobedience.</head>

<ab n="1">And it shall
come to passe, if thou shalt hearken diligently vnto the voyce of
the Lord thy God, to obserue and to doe all his Commandements which
I command thee this day; that the Lord thy God will set thee on
high aboue all nations of the earth.<note> Leuit.26. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And all these
blessings shall come on thee, and ouertake thee, if thou shalt
hearken vnto the voice of the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="3">Blessed shalt
thou bee in the citie, and blessed shalt thou be in the
field.</ab>
<ab n="4">Blessed shall
be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the
fruit of thy cattell, the increase of thy kine, and the flocks of
thy sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="5">Blessed shall
be thy basket and thy store.<note> Or, dough, or, kneading troughes.</note></ab>

<fw>Blessings for the obedient.</fw>
<ab n="6">Blessed shalt
thou bee when thou commest in, and blessed shalt thou bee when thou
goest out.</ab>
<ab n="7">The Lord
shall cause thine enemies that rise vp against thee, to bee smitten
before thy face: they shall come out against thee one way, and flee
before thee seuen wayes.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord
shall command the blessing vpon thee in thy store-houses, and in
all that thou settest thine hand vnto, and he shall blesse thee in
the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee.<note> Or, barnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The Lord
shall establish thee an holy people vnto himselfe, as hee hath
sworne vnto thee, if thou shalt keepe the Commaundements of the
Lord thy God, and walke in his wayes.</ab>
<ab n="10">And all
people of the earth shall see, that thou art called by the Name of
the Lord, and they shall bee afraid of thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord
shal make thee plenteous in goods, in the fruit of thy body, and in
the fruit of thy cattell, and in the fruit of thy ground, in the
land which the Lord sware vnto thy fathers to giue
thee.<note> Chap. 30. 9.etc. , Or, for good. , Hebr. belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The Lord
shal open vnto thee his good treasure, the heauen to giue the raine
vnto thy land in his season, and to blesse all the worke of thine
hand: and thou shalt lend vnto many nations, and thou shalt not
borrow.<note> Chap.15. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord
shall make thee the head, and not the taile, and thou shalt be
aboue onely, and thou shalt not be beneath: if that thou hearken
vnto the Commandements of the Lord thy God, which I command thee
this day, to obserue, and to doe them:</ab>
<ab n="14">And thou
shalt not go aside from any of the wordes which I command thee this
day, to the right hand, or to the left, to goe after other gods, to
serue them.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ But
it shal come to passe, if thou wilt not hearken vnto the voyce of
the Lord thy God, to obserue to doe all his Commandements and his
Statutes, which I command thee this day, that all these curses
shall come vpon thee, and ouertake thee.<note> Leuit.26.14. lament. 2.17. mala. 2.2. baruc. 1.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Cursed shalt
thou be in the city, and cursed shalt thou be in the field.</ab>
<ab n="17">Cursed shall
be thy basket and thy store.</ab>

<fw>Curses for disobedience.</fw>
<ab n="18">Cursed
shalbe the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, the
increase of thy kine, and the flocks of thy sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="19">Cursed shalt
thou bee when thou commest in, and cursed shalt thou bee when thou
goest out.</ab>
<ab n="20">The Lord
shall send vpon thee cursing, vexation, and rebuke, in all that
thou settest thine hand vnto, for to doe, vntill thou be destroyed,
and vntill thou perish quickely, because of the wickednesse of thy
doings, whereby thou hast forsaken me.<note> Heb. which thou wouldest doe.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The Lord
shall make the pestilence cleaue vnto thee, vntill he haue consumed
thee from off the land, whither thou goest to possesse it.</ab>
<ab n="22">The Lord
shall smite thee with a consumption, and with a feuer, and with an
inflammation, &amp; with an extreme burning, and with the sword,
and with blasting, and with mildewe: and they shall pursue thee
vntill thou perish.<note> Leuit. 26. 16. , Or, drought</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the
heauen that is ouer thy head shall be brasse, and the earth that is
vnder thee shall be yron.</ab>
<ab n="24">The Lord
shall make the raine of thy land powder &amp; dust: from heauen
shall it come downe vpon thee, vntill thou be destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="25">The Lord
shall cause thee to be smitten before thine enemies: thou shalt go
out one way against them, and flee seuen wayes before them, and
shalt be remoued into all the kingdomes of the earth.<note> Heb. for a remouing.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And thy
carkeise shalbe meat vnto all foules of the aire, and vnto the
beasts of the earth, and no man shall fray them away.</ab>
<ab n="27">The Lord wil
smite thee with the botch of Egypt, and with the emerods, and with
the scabbe, and with the itch, whereof thou canst not bee
healed.</ab>
<ab n="28">The Lord
shall smite thee with madnesse, and blindnesse, and astonishment of
heart.</ab>
<ab n="29">And thou
shalt grope at noone dayes, as the blind gropeth in darknes, and
thou shalt not prosper in thy waies: and thou shalt be onely
oppressed, and spoiled euermore, and no man shal saue thee.</ab>

<fw>Curses for disobedience.</fw>
<ab n="30">Thou shalt
betrothe a wife, and another man shall lie with her: thou shalt
build an house, and thou shalt not dwell therein: thou shalt plant
a vineyard, and shalt not gather the grapes thereof.<note> Deut.20. 6. , Hebr. prophane, or vse it as common meat.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Thine oxe
shall be slaine before thine eyes, and thou shalt not eat thereof:
thine asse shall be violently taken away from before thy face, and
shal not be restored to thee: thy sheepe shall bee giuen vnto thine
enemies, and thou shalt haue none to rescue them.<note> Heb. shall not returne to thee, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Thy sonnes,
and thy daughters shall be giuen vnto another people, and thine
eyes shal looke, and faile with longing for them al the day long:
and there shall be no might in thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="33">The fruit of
thy land, and all thy labours, shall a nation which thou knowest
not, eate vp: and thou shalt be onely oppressed and crushed
alway:</ab>
<ab n="34">So that thou
shalt bee mad, for the sight of thine eyes which thou shalt
see.</ab>
<ab n="35">The Lord
shall smite thee in the knees, and in the legges with a sore botch
that cannot bee healed, from the sole of thy foot, vnto the top of
thy head.</ab>
<ab n="36">The Lord
shal bring thee, and thy king which thou shalt set ouer thee, vnto
a nation which neither thou, nor thy fathers haue knowen, and there
shalt thou serue other gods, wood and stone.</ab>
<ab n="37">And thou
shalt become an astonishment, a prouerbe, and a by-worde, among all
nations whither the Lord shall leade thee.<note> 1.King.9 7. ier. 24.9. and 25.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Thou shalt
carie much seede out into the field, and shalt gather but litle in:
for the locust shall consume it.<note> Mica. 6. 15. agge. 1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Thou shalt
plant vineyards and dresse them, but shalt neither drinke of the
wine, nor gather the grapes: for the wormes shall eate
them.</ab>
<ab n="40">Thou shalt
haue Oliue trees throughout al thy coasts, but thou shalt not
anoint thy selfe with the oyle: for thine Oliue shall cast his
fruit.</ab>
<ab n="41">Thou shalt
beget sonnes and daughters, but thou shalt not enioy them: for they
shall goe into captiuitie.<note> Hebr. they shall not be thine.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">All thy
trees and fruit of thy land shall the locusts consume.<note> Or, possesse</note></ab>
<ab n="43">The stranger
that is within thee shall get vp aboue thee very high: and thou
shalt come downe very low.</ab>
<ab n="44">He shall
lend to thee, and thou shalt not lend to him: he shall bee the
head, and thou shalt be the taile.</ab>

<fw>Plagues and threatenings.</fw>
<ab n="45">Moreouer,
all these curses shall come vpon thee, and shall pursue thee, and
ouertake thee, til thou be destroied: because thou hearkenedst not
vnto the voice of the Lord thy God, to keepe his Commandements, and
his Statutes which he commanded thee.</ab>
<ab n="46">And they
shall be vpon thee for a signe, and for a wonder, and vpon thy seed
for euer:</ab>
<ab n="47">Because thou
seruedst not the Lord thy God with ioyfulnesse, and with gladnesse
of heart, for the aboundance of all things.</ab>
<ab n="48">Therefore
shalt thou serue thine enemies, which the Lord shall send against
thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakednesse, and in want of
all things: and he shall put a yoke of iron vpon thy necke, vntill
he haue destroyed thee.</ab>
<ab n="49">The Lord
shall bring a nation against thee from farre, from the end of the
earth, as swift as the Eagle fleeth, a nation whose tongue thou
shalt not vnderstand:<note> Heb. heare.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">A nation of
fierce countenance, which shal not regard the person of the old,
nor shew fauour to the yong:<note> Heb. strong of face.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And hee
shall eat the fruit of thy cattell, and the fruit of thy land,
vntill thou be destroyed: which also shall not leaue thee either
corne, wine, or oyle, or the increase of thy kine, or flockes of
thy sheepe, vntill he haue destroyed thee.</ab>
<ab n="52">And he shall
besiege thee in all thy gates, vntill thy high and fenced walles
come downe wherein thou trustedst throughout all thy land: and hee
shall besiege thee in all thy gates, throughout all thy land which
the Lord thy God hath giuen thee.</ab>
<ab n="53">And thou
shalt eate the fruit of thine owne body, the flesh of thy sonnes,
and of thy daughters (which the Lord thy God hath giuen thee) in
the siege, and in the straitnesse wherewith thine enemies shall
distresse thee.<note> Leuit. 26. 29. 2.king. 6.29. lam. 4.10. baruc.2.3. , Hebr. belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">So that the
man that is tender among you, and very delicate, his eye shalbe
euill toward his brother, and toward the wife of his bosome, and
towards the remnant of his children which he shall leaue:</ab>
<ab n="55">So that he
wil not giue to any of them of the flesh of his children whom he
shall eate: because hee hath nothing left him in the siege, and in
the straitnesse wherewith thine enemies shal distresse thee, in all
thy gates.</ab>

<fw>Plagues and threatenings.</fw>
<ab n="56">The tender
and delicate woman among you, which would not aduenture to set the
sole of her foote vpon the ground, for delicatenesse and
tendernesse, her eye shall be euill towards the husband of her
bosome, and towards her sonne, and towards her daughter,</ab>
<ab n="57">And towards
her yong one that commeth out from betweene her feete, and towards
her children which shee shall beare: for shee shall eate them for
want of all things secretly in the siege and straitnes, wherewith
thine enemie shall distresse thee in thy gates.<note> Hebr. after-birth.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">If thou wilt
not obserue to doe all the wordes of this Law that are written in
this booke, that thou mayest feare this glorious and fearefull
Name, The Lord thy God:</ab>
<ab n="59">Then the
Lord wil make thy plagues wonderfull, and the plagues of thy seed,
euen great plagues, and of long continuance, and sore sicknesses,
and of long continuance.</ab>
<ab n="60">Moreouer,
hee will bring vpon thee all the diseases of Egypt, which thou wast
afraid of, and they shal cleaue vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="61">Also euery
sickenesse, and euery plague which is not written in the booke of
this Law, them will the Lord bring vpon thee, vntill thou be
destroyed.<note> Hebr. cause to ascend.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">And ye shall
be left few in number, whereas ye were as the starres of heauen for
multitude: because thou wouldest not obey the voyce of the Lord thy
God.<note> Chap. 10. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">And it shall
come to passe, that as the Lord reioyced ouer you to doe you good,
and to multiply you; so the Lord will reioyce ouer you to destroy
you, and to bring you to nought; and ye shalbe plucked from off the
land whither thou goest to possesse it.</ab>
<ab n="64">And the Lord
shall scatter thee among all people, from the one end of the earth,
euen vnto the other: and there thou shalt serue other gods, which
neither thou nor thy fathers haue knowen, euen wood and
stone.</ab>
<ab n="65">And among
these nations shalt thou finde no ease, neither shall the sole of
thy foote haue rest: but the Lord shall giue thee there a trembling
heart, and failing of eyes, &amp; sorrow of minde.</ab>
<ab n="66">And thy life
shall hang in doubt before thee, and thou shalt feare day and
night, and shalt haue none assurance of thy life.</ab>

<fw>Sihon and Og.</fw>
<ab n="67">In the
morning thou shalt say, Would God it were Euen: and at Euen thou
shalt say, Would God it were morning, for the feare of thine heart
wherewith thou shalt feare, and for the sight of thine eyes which
thou shalt see.</ab>
<ab n="68">And the Lord
shall bring thee into Egypt againe, with ships, by the way whereof
I spake vnto thee, Thou shalt see it no more againe: and there ye
shall bee sold vnto your enemies for bondmen, and bondwomen, and no
man shall buy you.</ab>



</div>