<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Stripes must not exceed fortie. 4
The Oxe is not to be musled. 5 Of raising seed vnto a brother. 11
Of the immodest woman. 13 Of vniust weights. 17 The memorie of
Amalek is to be blotted out.</head>

<ab n="1">If there bee
a controuersie betweene men, and they come vnto iudgment, that the
Iudges may iudge them, then they shall iustifie the righteous, and
condemne the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="2">And it shall
be, if the wicked man be worthy to be beaten, that the Iudge shall
cause him to lie downe, and to bee beaten before his face,
according to his fault, by a certaine number.</ab>
<ab n="3">Fourtie
stripes he may giue him, and not exceed: lest if he should exceede,
and beate him aboue these, with many stripes, then thy brother
should seeme vile vnto thee.<note> 2.Cor.11. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Thou
shalt not mussell the oxe when he treadeth out the
corne.<note> 1.Cor.9.9. 1. tim.5.18 , Hebr. thresheth.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ If
brethren dwell together, and one of them die, and haue no child,
the wife of the dead shall not marrie without, vnto a stranger: her
husbands brother shall go in vnto her, and take her to him to wife,
and performe the duetie of an husbands brother vnto
her.<note> Matt.22. 24. mar.12. 19. luk. 20. 28. , Or, next kinseman.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And it shall
be, that the first borne which she beareth, shall succeede in the
name of his brother which is dead, that his name be not put out of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">And if the
man like not to take his brothers wife, then let his brothers wife
go vp to the gate, vnto the Elders, and say, My husbands brother
refuseth to raise vp vnto his brother a name in Israel: he will not
performe the dutie of my husbands brother.<note> Or, next kinsemans wife. , Ruth 3.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then the
Elders of his citie shall call him and speake vnto him: and if he
stand to it, and say, I like not to take her:</ab>

<fw>Iust weights &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="9">Then shal his
brothers wife come vnto him in the presence of the Elders, and
loose his shooe from off his foote, and spit in his face, and shall
answere, and say, So shall it bee done vnto that man that will not
build vp his brothers house.</ab>
<ab n="10">And his name
shall bee called in Israel, the house of him that hath his shooe
loosed.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ When
men striue together one with another, and the wife of the one
draweth neere, for to deliuer her husband out of the hand of him
that smiteth him, and putteth foorth her hand and taketh him by the
secrets:</ab>
<ab n="12">Then thou
shalt cut off her hand, thine eye shall not pitie her.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Thou
shalt not haue in thy bagge diuers weights, a great, and a
small.<note> Hebr. a stone and a stone.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thou shalt
not haue in thine house diuers measures, a great, and a
small.<note> Hebr. an Ephah, and an Ephah.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But thou
shalt haue a perfect and iust weight, a perfect and iust measure
shalt thou haue: that thy dayes may bee lengthened in the land
which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">For all that
doe such things, and all that doe vnrighteously, are an abomination
vnto the Lord thy God.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶
Remember what Amalek did vnto thee by the way, when ye were come
foorth out of Egypt:<note> Exod. 17. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">How he met
thee by the way, and smote the hindmost of thee, euen all that were
feeble behinde thee, when thou wast faint and weary; and he feared
not God.</ab>
<ab n="19">Therefore it
shall bee when the Lord thy God hath giuen thee rest from all thine
enemies round about, in the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee
for an inheritance to possesse it; that thou shalt blot out the
remembrance of Amalek from vnder heauen: thou shalt not forget
it.</ab>



</div>