<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The feast of the Passeouer, 9 of
Weekes, 13 of Tabernacles. 16 Euery male must offer, as he is able,
at these three Feasts. 18 Of Iudges and Iustice. 22 Groues and
Images are forbidden.</head>

<ab n="1">Obserue the
moneth of Abib, and keepe the Passeouer vuto the Lord thy God: for
in the moneth of Abib the Lord thy God brought thee foorth out of
Egypt by night.<note> Exod. 12. 2. &amp;c. , Exod. 13. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thou shalt
therefore sacrifice the Passeouer vnto the Lord thy God, of the
flocke and the heard, in the place which the Lord shall choose to
place his name there.<note> Chap.12. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thou shalt
eat no leauened bread with it: seuen dayes shalt thou eat
vnleauened bread therewith, euen the bread of affliction, (for thou
camest forth out of the land of Egypt in haste) that thou mayest
remember the day when thou camest foorth out of the land of Egypt,
all the dayes of thy life.<note> Exod. 12. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And there
shall bee no leauened bread seene with thee in all thy coasts seuen
dayes, neither shall there any thing of the flesh, which thou
sacrificedst the first day at Euen, remaine all night, vntill the
morning.<note> Exod. 34. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou mayest
not sacrifice the Passeouer within any of the gates, which the Lord
thy God giueth thee.<note> Or, kill.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But at the
place which the Lord thy God shall choose to place his Name in,
there thou shalt sacrifice the Passeouer at Euen, at the going
downe of the Sunne, at the season that thou camest foorth out of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thou
shalt roste and eate it in the place which the Lord thy God shall
choose, and thou shalt turne in the morning, and goe vnto thy
tents.</ab>
<ab n="8">Sixe dayes
thou shalt eate vnleauened bread, and on the seuenth day shall be a
solemne assembly to the Lord thy God: thou shalt doe no worke
therein.<note> Hebr. restraint.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Seuen
weekes shalt thou number vnto thee: beginne to number the seuen
weekes, from such time as thou beginnest to put the sickle to the
corne.<note> Leuit. 23. 15.</note></ab>

<fw>Iudges and Officers.</fw>
<ab n="10">And thou
shalt keepe the feast of weekes vnto the Lord thy God with a
tribute of a free will offering of thine hand, which thou shalt
giue vnto the Lord thy God, according as the Lord thy God hath
blessed thee.<note> Or, sufficiencie.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And thou
shalt reioyce before the Lord thy God, thou, and thy sonne, and thy
daughter, and thy man seruant and thy maid seruant, and the Leuite
that is within thy gates, and the stranger, and the fatherlesse,
and the widow, that are among you, in the place which the Lord thy
God hath chosen to place his Name there.</ab>
<ab n="12">And thou
shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt: and thou shalt
obserue &amp; do these Statutes.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Thou
shalt obserue the feast of Tabernacles seuen dayes, after that thou
hast gathered in thy corne, and thy wine.<note> Heb. floore and thy wine presse.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And thou
shalt reioice in thy feast, thou, and thy sonne, and thy daughter,
and thy man seruant, and thy maid seruant, and the Leuite, the
stranger, and the fatherlesse, and the widow, that are within thy
gates.</ab>
<ab n="15">Seuen dayes
shalt thou keepe a solemne feast vnto the Lord thy God, in the
place which the Lord shall chuse: because the Lord thy God shall
blesse thee in all thy increase, and in all the workes of thine
handes, therefore thou shalt surely reioyce.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Three
times in a yeere shal all thy males appeare before the Lord thy
God, in the place which hee shall chuse: in the feast of Unleauened
bread, and in the feast of Weekes, and in the feast of Tabernacles:
and they shal not appeare before the Lord emptie.<note> Exod. 23. 14. and 34. 23. , Ecclus. 35.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Euery man
shall giue as hee is able, according to the blessing of the Lord
thy God, which he hath giuen thee.<note> Heb. according to the gift of his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶
Iudges and officers shalt thou make thee in all thy gates which the
Lord thy God giueth thee throughout thy tribes: and they shall
iudge the people with iust iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thou shalt
not wrest iudgement, thou shalt not respect persons, neither take a
gift: for a gift doth blind the eyes of the wise, and peruert the
wordes of the righteous.<note> Exod. 23. 8. , Or, matters</note></ab>

<fw>Of idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="20">That which
is altogether iust shalt thou followe, that thou mayest liue, and
inherite the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee.<note> Heb. iustice, iustice.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Thou
shalt not plant thee a groue of any trees neere vnto the Altar of
the Lord thy God, which thou shalt make thee:</ab>
<ab n="22">Neither
shalt thou set thee vp any image, which the Lord thy God
hateth.<note> Leuit. 26. 1. , Or, statue, or pillar.</note></ab>



</div>