<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CDeuteronomy_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 All communion with the Nations is
forbidden, 4 for feare of Idolatrie, 6 for the holinesse of the
people, 9 for the nature of God in his Mercie and Iustice, 17 for
the assurednesse of victorie which God will giue ouer
them.</head>

<ab n="1">When the Lord
thy God shall bring thee into the land whither thou goest to
possesse it, and hath cast out many nations before thee, the
Hittites, and the Girgashites, and the Amorites, and the
Canaanites, and the Perizzites, and the Hiuites, and the Iebusites,
seuen nations greater and mightier then thou:<note> Chap.31. 3.</note></ab>

<fw>Exhortations to obedience.</fw>
<ab n="2">And when the
Lord thy God shall deliuer them before thee, thou shalt smite them,
and vtterly destroy them, thou shalt make no couenant with them,
nor shew mercy vnto them.<note> Exod. 23. 32.and 34. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Neither shalt
thou make marriages with them: thy daughter thou shalt not giue
vnto his sonne, nor his daughter shalt thou take vnto thy
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="4">For they will
turne away thy sonne from following mee, that they may serue other
gods: so will the anger of the Lord be kindled against you, and
destroy thee suddenly.</ab>
<ab n="5">But thus shal
ye deale with them; ye shall destroy their altars, and breake downe
their images, and cut downe their groues, and burne their grauen
images with fire.<note> Hebr. statues, or pillars.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For thou art
an holy people vnto the Lord thy God: the Lord thy God hath chosen
thee to be a special people vnto himselfe, aboue all people that
are vpon the face of the earth.<note> Chap.14. 2. and 26, 19. , Exod.19. 5. 1.pet.2. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The Lord did
not set his loue vpon you, nor choose you, because yee were moe in
number then any people: (for ye were the fewest of all
people,)</ab>
<ab n="8">But because
the Lord loued you, and because hee would keepe the othe which hee
had sworne vnto your fathers, hath the Lord brought you out with a
mighty hand, and redeemed you out of the house of bondmen, from the
hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="9">Know therefore
that the Lord thy God, he is God, the faithfull God, which keepeth
Couenant and Mercy with them that loue him, and keepe his
Commandements, to a thousand generations;</ab>
<ab n="10">And repaieth
them that hate him to their face, to destroy them: he wil not be
slacke to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his
face.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thou shalt
therefore keepe the Commandements, and the Statutes, and the
Iudgements, which I command thee this day, to doe them.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶
Wherefore it shal come to passe, if ye hearken to these iudgements,
and keepe and do them: That the Lord thy God shall keepe vnto thee
the Couenant and the Mercy which he sware vnto thy
fathers.<note> Hebr. because.</note></ab>

<fw>To auoid all Idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="13">And hee will
loue thee, and blesse thee, and multiply thee: Hee will also blesse
the fruit of thy wombe, and the fruit of thy land, thy corne, and
thy wine, and thine oile, the encrease of thy kine, and the flockes
of thy sheepe, in the land which hee sware vnto thy fathers to giue
thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Thou shalt
bee blessed aboue all people: there shall not bee male or female
barren among you or among your cattell.<note> Exod.23. 26, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the Lord
will take away from thee all sickenesse, and will put none of the
euill diseases of Egypt (which thou knowest) vpon thee: but will
lay them vpon all them that hate thee.<note> Exod.9. 14. &amp;15. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And thou
shalt consume all the people which the Lord thy God shall deliuer
thee: thine eye shall haue no pitie vpon them, neither shalt thou
serue their gods, for that will be a snare vnto thee.<note> Exod.23. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">If thou shalt
say in thine heart, These nations are moe then I, howe can I
dispossesse them?</ab>
<ab n="18">Thou shalt
not be afraid of them: but shalt well remember, what the Lord thy
God did vnto Pharaoh, and vnto all Egypt,</ab>
<ab n="19">The great
temptations which thine eyes sawe, and the signes and the wonders,
and the mightie hand, and the stretched out arme, whereby the Lord
thy God brought thee out: so shall the Lord thy God doe vnto all
the people of whom thou art afraid.</ab>
<ab n="20">Moreouer, the
Lord thy God will send the hornet among them, vntill they that are
left and hide themselues from thee, be destroyed.<note> Exod.23. 28. iosh.24 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Thou shalt
not bee affrighted at them: for the Lord thy God is among you, a
mightie God, and terrible.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Lord
thy God will put out those nations before thee by litle and litle:
thou mayest not consume them at once, lest the beastes of the field
increase vpon thee.<note> Hebr. plucke off.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But the Lord
thy God shall deliuer them vnto thee, and shall destroy them with a
mightie destruction, vntill they be destroyed.<note> Hebr. before thy face.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And he shall
deliuer their kings into thine hand, and thou shalt destroy their
name from vnder heauen: There shal no man be able to stand before
thee, vntil thou haue destroyed them.</ab>

<fw>To auoid all Idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="25">The grauen
images of their gods shall yee burne with fire: thou shalt not
desire the siluer or golde that is on them, nor take it vnto thee,
lest thou bee snared therein: for it is an abomination to the Lord
thy God.<note> Chap. 12. 3. , Iosh.7.1, 21. 2. mac. 12.40.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Neither shalt
thou bring an abomination into thine house, lest thou bee a cursed
thing like it: but thou shalt vtterly detest it, and thou shalt
vtterly abhorre it, for it is a cursed thing.<note> Chap.13. 17.</note></ab>



</div>