<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-26-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Of sinnes in selling and buying. 7
Our speach will tell what is in vs. 16 A friend is lost by
discouering his secrets. 25 Hee that diggeth a pit shall fall into
it.</head>

<ab n="1">Many haue
sinned for a smal matter: &amp; he that seeketh for abundance will
turne his eies away.<note> Prou.28. 21. , Or, a thing indifferent.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">As a naile
sticketh fast betweene the ioynings of the stones: so doth sinne
sticke close betweene buying and selling.<note> Prou.23. 4. 1.tim.6. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Unlesse a
man hold himselfe diligently in the feare of the Lord, his house
shall soone be ouerthrowen.</ab>
<ab n="4">As when
one sifteth with a sieue, the refuse remaineth, so the filth of man
in his talke.<note> Or, thought</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The
furnace prooueth the potters vessell: so the triall of man is in
his reasoning.<note> Prou. 27. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The fruite
declareth if the tree haue beene dressed: so is the vtterance of a
conceit in the heart of man.<note> Matth.7. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Praise no
man before thou hearest him speake, for this is the triall of
men.</ab>
<ab n="8">If thou
followest righteousnesse, thou shalt obtaine her, and put her on,
as a glorious long robe.</ab>
<ab n="9">The birds
will resort vnto their like, so will truth returne vnto them that
practise in her.</ab>
<ab n="10">As the
Lyon lieth in waite for the pray: so sinne for them that worke
iniquity.</ab>
<ab n="11">The
discourse of a godly man is alwaies with wisedome: but a foole
changeth as the Moone.</ab>
<ab n="12">If thou
be among the vndiscreet, obserue the time: but be continually among
men of vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="13">The
discourse of fooles is irksome, and their sport is in the
wantonnesse of sinne.</ab>
<ab n="14">The talke
of him that sweareth much, maketh the haire stand vpright: and
their braules make one stop his eares.</ab>
<ab n="15">The
strife of the proud is blood-shedding, and their reuilings are
grieuous to the eare.</ab>
<ab n="16">Who so
discouereth secrets, looseth his credit: and shall neuer find
friend to his minde.</ab>
<ab n="17">Loue thy
friend, and be faithfull vnto him: but if thou bewrayest his
secrets, follow no more after him.</ab>
<ab n="18">For as a
man hath destroyed his enemie: so hast thou lost the loue of thy
neighbour.</ab>
<ab n="19">As one
that letteth a bird goe out of his hand, so hast thou let thy
neighbour goe; and shalt not get him againe.</ab>
<ab n="20">Follow
after him no more, for he is too far off, he is as a roe escaped
out of the snare.</ab>
<ab n="21">As for a
wound it may be bound vp, and after reuiling there may be
reconcilement: but he that bewrayeth secrets is without
hope.</ab>
<ab n="22">He that
winketh with the eies worketh euil, and he that knoweth him will
depart from him.<note> Prou. 10. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">When thou
art present he will speake sweetly, and will admire thy words: but
at the last he will writhe his mouth, and slander thy
sayings.<note> Or, alter his speach.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">I haue
hated many things, but nothing like him, for the Lord will hate
him.</ab>
<ab n="25">Who so
casteth a stone on high, casteth it on his owne head, and a
deceitfull stroke shall make wounds.</ab>
<ab n="26">Who so
diggeth a pit shall fall therein: and he that setteth a trap shall
be taken therein.<note> Psal.7.15. prou.26. 27. ecclesi. 8.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">He that
worketh mischiefe, it shall fall vpon him, and he shall not know
whence it commeth.</ab>
<ab n="28">Mockery
and reproach are from the proud: but vengeance as a Lyon shall lie
in waite for them.<note> Deut.32. 35. rom.12. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">They that
reioyce at the fall of the righteous shalbe taken in the snare, and
anguish shall consume them before they die.</ab>
<ab n="30">Malice
and wrath, euen these are abhominations, and the sinfull man shall
haue them both.</ab>



</div>