<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Like things happen to good and
bad. 4 There is a necessitie of death vnto men. 7 Comfort is all
their portion in this life. 11 Gods prouidence ruleth ouer all. 13
Wisdome is better then strength.</head>

<ab n="1">For all this
I considered in my heart, euen to declare all this, that the
righteous, and the wise, and their workes, are in the hand of God:
no man knoweth either loue, or hatred, by all that is before
them.<note> Hebr. I gaue, or set to my heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">All things
come alike to all: there is one euent to the righteous and to the
wicked, to the good and to the cleane, and to the vncleane; to him
that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not: as is the good,
so is the sinner, and hee that sweareth, as he that feareth an
oath.<note> Mala. 3. 14. psal. 73. 2. &amp; 12. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">This is an
euill among all things that are done vnder the Sunne, that there is
one euent vnto all: yea also the heart of the sonnes of men is full
of euill, and madnesse is in their heart while they liue, and after
that they goe to the dead.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ For to
him that is ioyned to all the liuing, there is hope: for a liuing
dogge is better then a dead Lion.</ab>
<ab n="5">For the
liuing know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing,
neither haue they any more a reward, for the memorie of them is
forgotten.</ab>
<ab n="6">Also their
loue, and their hatred, and their enuy is now perished; neither
haue they any more a portion for euer in any thing that is done
vnder the Sunne.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Goe
thy way, eate thy bread with ioy, and drinke thy wine with a merry
heart; for God now accepteth thy workes.</ab>

<fw>Wisdome despised.</fw>
<ab n="8">Let thy
garments bee alwayes white; and let thy head lacke no
oyntment.</ab>
<ab n="9">Liue ioyfully
with the wife, whom thou louest, all the dayes of the life of thy
vanitie, which he hath giuen thee vnder the Sunne, all the dayes of
thy vanitie: for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy
labour which thou takest vnder the Sunne.<note> Hebr. see, or enioy life. , Chap.2. 24. and 3. 13. and 5. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Whatsoeuer
thy hand findeth to doe, doe it with thy might: for there is no
worke, nor deuice, nor knowledge, nor wisedome in the graue,
whither thou goest.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ I
returned, and saw vnder the Sunne, That the race is not to the
swift, nor the battell to the strong, neither yet bread to the
wise, nor yet riches to men of vnderstanding, nor yet fauour to men
of skil; but time and chance happeneth to them all.</ab>
<ab n="12">For man also
knoweth not his time, as the fishes that are taken in an euil net,
and as the birds that are caught in the snare; so are the sonnes of
men snared in an euill time, when it falleth suddenly vpon
them.<note> Prou.29. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ This
wisedome haue I seene also vnder the Sunne, and it seemed great
vnto me:</ab>
<ab n="14">There was a
little citie, and few men within it; and there came a great King
against it, and besieged it, &amp; built great bulwarks against
it:</ab>
<ab n="15">Now there
was found in it a poore wise man, and hee by his wisedome deliuered
the citie; yet no man remembred that same poore man.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then said I,
Wisedome is better then strength: neuerthelesse, the poore mans
wisedome is despised, and his words are not heard.<note> Prou. 21. 22.chap.7. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The words of
wise men are heard in quiet, more then the cry of him that ruleth
among fooles.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wisedome is
better then weapons of warre: but one sinner destroyeth much
good.</ab>



</div>