<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Wee are exhorted from sinne, 4
from ambition, 8 presumption, 10 and fainting in prayer: 12 from
lying and backebiting, 18 and how to esteeme a friend: 19 A good
wife: 20 a seruant: 22 our cattell: 23 our children and parents: 31
the Lord and his Priests: 32 the poore and those that
mourne.</head>

<ab n="1">Doe no
euill, so shall no harme come vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">Depart from
the vniust, and iniquitie shall turne away from thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">My sonne,
sow not vpon the furrowes of vnrighteousnesse, and thou shalt not
reape them seuen folde.</ab>
<ab n="4">Seeke not
of the Lord preheminence, neither of the King the seate of
honour.</ab>
<ab n="5">Iustifie
not thy selfe before the Lord, and boast not of thy wisedome before
the king.<note> Psal.142. 2. eccles.7. 17. iob9. 20. luke 18.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Seeke not
to be iudge, being not able to take away iniquitie, lest at any
time thou feare the person of the mightie, and lay a stumbling
blocke in the way of thy vprightnesse.</ab>
<ab n="7">Offend not
against the multitude of a city, and then thou shalt not cast thy
selfe downe among the people.</ab>
<ab n="8">Bind not
one sinne vpon another, for in one thou shalt not be
vnpunished.</ab>
<ab n="9">Say not,
God wil looke vpon the multitude of my oblations, and when I offer
to the most High God, he will accept it.</ab>
<ab n="10">Be not
faint hearted when thou makest thy prayer, and neglect not to giue
almes.</ab>
<ab n="11">Laugh no
man to scorne in the bitternesse of his soule: for there is one
which humbleth and exalteth.</ab>
<ab n="12">Deuise not
a lie against thy brother: neither doe the like to thy
friend.<note> Gre. plough not.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Use not to
make any maner of lie: for the custome thereof is not good.</ab>
<ab n="14">Use not
many words in a multitude of Elders, and make not much babling when
thou prayest.<note> Mat.6.5,7 , Or, vaine repetition.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hate not
laborious worke, neither husbandrie, which the most High hath
ordeined.<note> Gre. created.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Number not
thy selfe among the multitude of sinners, but remember that wrath
will not tary long.</ab>
<ab n="17">Humble thy
soule greatly: for the vengeance of the vngodly is fire and
wormes.</ab>
<ab n="18">Change not
a friend for any good by no meanes: neither a faithfull brother for
the gold of Ophir.</ab>
<ab n="19">Forgoe not
a wise and good woman: for her grace is aboue gold.</ab>
<ab n="20">Whereas
thy seruant worketh truely, entreate him not euill, nor the
hireling that bestoweth himselfe wholly for thee.<note> Leuit.19. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Let thy
soule loue a good seruant, and defraud him not of liberty.</ab>
<ab n="22">Hast thou
cattell? haue an eye to them, and if they be for thy profit, keepe
them with thee.<note> Deu.25.4</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Hast thou
children? instruct them, and bow downe their necke from their
youth.</ab>
<ab n="24">Hast thou
daughters? haue care of their body, and shewe not thy selfe
cheerefull toward them.</ab>
<ab n="25">Marrie thy
daughter, and so shalt thou haue performed a weightie matter: but
giue her to a man of vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="26">Hast thou
a wife after thy minde? forsake her not, but giue not thy selfe
ouer to a light woman.<note> Or, hateful</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Honour thy
father with thy whole heart, and forget not the sorrowes of thy
mother.</ab>
<ab n="28">Remember
that thou wast begot of them, and how canst thou recompense them
the things that they haue done for thee?</ab>
<ab n="29">Feare the
Lord with all thy soule, and reuerence his priests.</ab>
<ab n="30">Loue him
that made thee with all thy strength, and forsake not his
ministers.</ab>
<ab n="31">Feare the
Lord, and honour the priest: and giue him his portion, as it is
commanded thee, the first fruits, and the trespasse offering, &amp;
the gift of the shoulders, and the sacrifice of sanctification, and
the first fruits of the holy things.</ab>
<ab n="32">And
stretch thine hand vnto the poore, that thy blessing may be
perfected<note> Deut. 15. 10. , Or, thy liberality.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">A gift
hath grace in the sight of euery man liuing, and for the dead
deteine it not.</ab>
<ab n="34">Faile not
to bee with them that weepe, and mourne with them that
mourne.</ab>
<ab n="35">Be not
slow to visit the sicke: for that shall make thee to be
beloued.</ab>
<ab n="36">Whatsoeuer
thou takest in hand, remember the end, and thou shalt neuer doe
amisse.</ab>



</div>