<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>2 Doe not extoll thy owne conceit, 7
But make choise of a friend. 18 Seeke wisedome betimes: 20 It is
grieuous to some, 28 yet the fruits thereof are pleasant. 35 Be
ready to heare wise men.</head>

<ab n="1">In stead of
a friend, become not an enemie; for [thereby] thou shalt inherite
an ill name, shame, and reproch: euen so shall a sinner that hath a
double tongue.</ab>
<ab n="2">Extoll not
thy selfe in the counsell of thine owne heart, that thy soule bee
not torne in pieces as a bull [straying alone.]</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou shalt
eat vp thy leaues, and loose thy fruit, and leaue thy selfe as a
dry tree.</ab>
<ab n="4">A wicked
soule shall destroy him that hath it, and shall make him to be
laughed to scorne of his enemies.</ab>
<ab n="5">Sweet
language will multiply friends: and a faire speaking tongue will
increase kinde greetings.<note> Greeke, a sweet throat.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Be in peace
with many: neuerthelesse haue but one counseller of a
thousand.</ab>
<ab n="7">If thou
wouldst get a friend, proue him first, and be not hasty to credit
him.<note> Or, get him in the time of trouble.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For some
man is a friend for his owne occasion, and will not abide in the
day of thy trouble.</ab>
<ab n="9">And there
is a friend, who being turned to enmitie, and strife, will discouer
thy reproch.</ab>
<ab n="10">Againe
some friend is a companion at the table, and will not continue in
the day of thy affliction.<note> Cha.37.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But in thy
prosperitie hee will be as thy selfe, and will be bould ouer thy
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="12">If thou be
brought low, he will be against thee, and will hide himselfe from
thy face.</ab>
<ab n="13">Separate
thy selfe from thine enemies, and take heed of thy friends.</ab>
<ab n="14">A
faithfull friend is a strong defence: and hee that hath found such
an one, hath found a treasure.</ab>
<ab n="15">Nothing
doeth counteruaile a faithful friend, and his excellencie is
vnualuable.</ab>
<ab n="16">A
faithfull friend is the medicine of life, and they that feare the
Lord shal finde him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Who so
feareth the Lord shall direct his friendship aright, for as he is,
so shall his neighbour be also.</ab>
<ab n="18">My sonne,
gather instruction from thy youth vp: so shalt thou finde wisedome
till thine old age.</ab>
<ab n="19">Come vnto
her as one that ploweth, and soweth, and wait for her good fruits,
for thou shalt not toile much in labouring about her, but thou
shalt eat of her fruits right soone.</ab>
<ab n="20">She is
very vnpleasant to the vnlearned: he that is without vnderstanding,
will not remaine with her.<note> Or, heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">She wil
lye vpon him as a mightie stone of triall, and hee will cast her
from him ere it be long.<note> Zech.12.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For
wisedome is according to her name, and she is not manifest vnto
many.</ab>
<ab n="23">Giue eare,
my sonne, receiue my aduice, and refuse not my counsell,</ab>
<ab n="24">And put
thy feet into her fetters, and thy necke into her
chaine.<note> Or, coller.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Bow downe
thy shoulder, and beare her, and be not grieued with her
bonds.<note> Mat.11. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Come vnto
her with thy whole heart, and keepe her wayes with all thy
power.</ab>
<ab n="27">Search and
seeke, and shee shall bee made knowen vnto thee, and when thou hast
got hold of her, let her not goe.</ab>
<ab n="28">For at the
last thou shalt finde her rest, and that shalbe turned to thy
ioy.</ab>
<ab n="29">Then shall
her fetters be a strong defence for thee, and her chaines a robe of
glory.</ab>
<ab n="30">For there
is a golden ornament vpon her, and her bandes are purple
lace.<note> Or, a ribband of blew silke, Numb. 15.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Thou shalt
put her on as a robe of honour: and shalt put her about thee as a
crowne of ioy.</ab>
<ab n="32">My sonne,
if thou wilt, thou shalt bee taught: and if thou wilt apply thy
minde, thou shalt be prudent.</ab>
<ab n="33">If thou
loue to heare, thou shalt receiue vnderstanding: and if thou bow
thine eare, thou shalt be wise.</ab>
<ab n="34">Stand in
the multitude of the elders, and cleaue vnto him that is
wise.<note> Ecclus.8.9</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Be willing
to heare euery godly discourse, and let not the parables of
vnderstanding escape thee.</ab>
<ab n="36">And if
thou seest a man of vnderstanding, get thee betimes vnto him, and
let thy foote weare the steps of his doore.</ab>
<ab n="37">Let thy
minde be vpon the ordinances of the Lord, &amp; meditate
continually in his commandements: he shal establish thine heart,
and giue thee wisedome at thine owne desire.<note> Psal.1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>