<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 By the necessary change of times,
vanitie is added to humane trauaile. 11 There is an excellencie in
Gods workes: 16 But as for man, God shall iudge his workes there,
and here he shalbe like a beast.</head>


<fw>A time for all.</fw>
<ab n="1">To euery
thing there is a season, and a time to euery purpose vnder the
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="2">A time to be
borne, and a time to die: a time to plant, and a time to pluck vp
that which is planted.<note> Heb. to beare.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">A time to
kill, and a time to heale: a time to breake downe, and a time to
build vp.</ab>
<ab n="4">A time to
weepe, and a time to laugh: a time to mourne, and a time to
dance.</ab>
<ab n="5">A time to
cast away stones, and a time to gather stones together: a time to
imbrace, and a time to refraine from imbracing.<note> Heb. to be farre from.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">A time to
get, and a time to lose: a time to keepe, and a time to cast
away.<note> Or, seeke.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">A time to
rent, and a time to sow: a time to keepe silence, and a time to
speake.</ab>
<ab n="8">A time to
loue, and a time to hate: a time of warre, and a time of
peace.</ab>
<ab n="9">What profite
hath hee that worketh, in that wherein he laboureth?<note> Chap. 1. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">I haue seene
the trauaile which God hath giuen to the sonnes of men, to be
exercised in it.</ab>
<ab n="11">He hath made
euery thing beautifull in his time: also hee hath set the world in
their heart, so that no man can finde out the worke that God maketh
from the beginning to the end.</ab>
<ab n="12">I know that
there is no good in them, but for a man to reioyce, and to doe good
in his life.</ab>
<ab n="13">And also
that euery man should eate and drinke, and enioy the good of all
his labour: it is the gift of God.</ab>
<ab n="14">I know that
whatsoeuer God doeth, it shalbe for euer: nothing can be put to it,
nor any thing taken from it: and God doth it, that men should feare
before him.</ab>
<ab n="15">That which
hath beene, is now: and that which is to be, hath alreadie beene,
and God requireth that which is past.<note> Cha.1.9. , Heb. that which is driuen away.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
moreouer, I sawe vnder the Sunne the place of iudgement, that
wickednesse was there; and the place of righteousnesse, that
iniquitie was there.</ab>
<ab n="17">I said in
mine heart, God shall iudge the righteous and the wicked: for there
is a time there, for euery purpose and for euery worke.<note> Vers. 1.</note></ab>

<fw>Man and beast.</fw>
<ab n="18">I said in my
heart concerning the estate of the sonnes of men, that God might
manifest them, and that they might see that they themselues are
beasts.<note> Or, that they might deare God, and see, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For that
which befalleth the sonnes of men, befalleth beastes, euen one
thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea
they haue all one breath, so that a man hath no preheminence aboue
a beast; for all is vanitie.<note> Psal.49. 21. chap. 2.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">All goe vnto
one place, all are of the dust, and all turne to dust
againe.</ab>
<ab n="21">Who knoweth
the spirit of man that goeth vpward; and the spirit of the beast
that goeth downeward to the earth?<note> Heb. of the sons of man. , Heb. is ascending.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Wherefore I
perceiue that there is nothing better, then that a man should
reioyce in his owne workes: for that is his portion; for who shall
bring him to see what shalbe after him?<note> Cha.2.24. and 5.17.</note></ab>



</div>