<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_38" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-38-38.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Honour due to the Phisitian, and
why. 16 How to weepe and mourne for the dead. 24 The wisedome of
the learned man, and of the Labourer and Artificer: with the vse of
them both.</head>

<ab n="1">Honour a
Phisitian with the honour due vnto him, for the vses which you may
haue of him: for the Lord hath created him.</ab>
<ab n="2">For of the
most High commeth healing, and he shall receiue honour of the
King.<note> Or, a gift</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The skill
of the Phisitian shall lift vp his head: and in the sight of great
men he shalbe in admiration.</ab>
<ab n="4">The Lord
hath created medicines out of the earth; and he that is wise will
not abhorre them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Was not
the water made sweet with wood, that the vertue thereof might be
knowen?<note> Exod. 15. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he
hath giuen men skill, that hee might be honoured in his marueilous
workes.</ab>
<ab n="7">With such
doeth he heale [men,] and taketh away their paines.</ab>
<ab n="8">Of such
doeth the Apothecarie make a confection; and of his workes there is
no end, and from him is peace ouer all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="9">My sonne,
in thy sickenesse be not negligent: but pray vnto the Lord, and he
will make thee whole.<note> Esay.38.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Leaue off
from sinne, and order thy hands aright, and cleanse thy heart from
all wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">Giue a
sweet sauour, and a memoriall of fine flowre: and make a fat
offering, as not being.<note> Or, as a deadman.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then giue
place to the phisitian, for the Lord hath created him: let him not
go from thee, for thou hast need of him.</ab>
<ab n="13">There is
a time when in their hands there is good successe.</ab>
<ab n="14">For they
shall also pray vnto the Lord, that hee would prosper that, which
they giue, for ease and remedy to prolong life.<note> Or, curing.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">He that
sinneth before his maker, let him fal into the hand of the
Phisitian.</ab>
<ab n="16">My sonne,
let teares fall downe ouer the dead, and begin to lament, as if
thou hadst suffered great harme thy selfe: and then couer his body
according to the custome, &amp; neglect not his buriall.</ab>
<ab n="17">Weepe
bitterly, and make great moane, and vse lamentation, as hee is
worthy, and that a day or two, lest thou be euill spoken of: and
then comfort thy selfe for thy heauinesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">For of
heauinesse commeth death, and the heauinesse of the heart, breaketh
strength.<note> Prou.15. 13. and 17. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">In
affliction also sorrow remaineth: and the life of the poore, is the
curse of the heart.</ab>
<ab n="20">Take no
heauines to heart: driue it away, and remember the last
end.</ab>
<ab n="21">Forget it
not, for there is no turning againe: thou shalt not doe him good,
but hurt thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="22">Remember
my iudgement: for thine also shall be so; yesterday for me, and to
day for thee.<note> Or, the sentence vpon him.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">When the
dead is at rest, let his remembrance rest, &amp; be comforted for
him, when his spirit is departed from him.<note> 2.Sam.12. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The
wisedome of a learned man cōmeth by opportunitie of leasure:
&amp; he that hath litle busines shal become wise.</ab>
<ab n="25">How can
he get wisdome that holdeth the plough, and that glorieth in the
goad; that driueth oxen, and is occupied in their labours, and
whose talke is of bullocks?<note> Greeke, of the breed of bullocks.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He giueth
his minde to make furrowes: and is diligent to giue the kine
fodder.</ab>
<ab n="27">So euery
carpenter, and workemaster, that laboureth night and day: and they
that cut and graue seales, and are diligent to make great variety,
and giue themselues to counterfait imagerie, and watch to finish a
worke.</ab>
<ab n="28">The smith
also sitting by the anuill, &amp; considering the iron worke; the
vapour of the fire wasteth his flesh, and he fighteth with the heat
of the furnace: the noise of the hammer &amp; the anuill is euer in
his eares, and his eies looke still vpon the patterne of the thing
that he maketh, he setteth his mind to finish his worke, &amp;
watcheth to polish it perfitly.</ab>
<ab n="29">So doeth
the potter sitting at his worke, and turning the wheele about with
his feet, who is alway carefully set at his worke: and maketh all
his worke by number.</ab>
<ab n="30">He
fashioneth the clay with his arme, and boweth downe his strength
before his feet: he applieth himselfe to lead it ouer; and he is
diligent to make cleane the furnace.<note> Or, tempereth it with his feet.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">All these
trust to their hands: and euery one is wise in his worke.</ab>
<ab n="32">Without
these cannot a citie be inhabited: and they shall not dwell where
they will, nor goe vp and downe.</ab>
<ab n="33">They
shall not be sought for in publike counsaile; nor sit high in the
congregation: they shal not sit on the Iudges seate, nor vnderstand
the sentence of iudgement: they cannot declare iustice, and
iudgement, and they shall not be found where parables are
spoken.</ab>
<ab n="34">But they
will maintaine the state of the world, and [all] their desire is in
the worke of their craft.</ab>



</div>