<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Directions for charitie. 7 Death
in life, 9 and the day of iudgement in the dayes of youth are to be
thought on.</head>

<ab n="1">Cast thy
bread vpon the waters: for thou shalt find it after many
dayes.<note> Heb. vpon the face of the waters. , Deut. 15. 10. Mat.10 42. prou.19 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Giue a
portion to seuen and also to eight; for thou knowest noc what euill
shall be vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="3">If the
clouds be full of raine, they emptie themselues vpon the earth: and
if the tree fall toward the South, or toward the North, in the
place where the tree falleth, there it shall be.</ab>
<ab n="4">He that
obserueth the wind, shall not sow: and hee that regardeth the
clouds, shall not reape.</ab>
<ab n="5">As thou
knowest not what is the way of the spirit, nor how the bones doe
growe in the wombe of her that is with child: euen so thou knowest
not the workes of God who maketh all.</ab>
<ab n="6">In the
morning sowe thy seede, and in the euening withhold not thine hand:
for thou knowest not whether shall prosper, either this or that, or
whether they both shall be alike good.<note> Heb. shall be right.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Truly
the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing is it for the eyes to
behold the sunne.</ab>
<ab n="8">But if a man
liue many yeeres, and reioyce in them all; yet let him remember the
dayes of darkenesse, for they shall be many. All that commeth is
vanitie.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶
Reioyce, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheere thee
in the dayes of thy youth, and walke in the wayes of thine heart,
and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these
things, God will bring thee into iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore
remoue sorrow from thy heart, and put away euill from thy flesh;
for child-hood &amp; youth are vanitie.<note> Or, anger.</note></ab>



</div>