<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>4 Wee may not vaunt or set foorth
our selues, 8 Nor answere rashly, 10 Nor meddle with many matters.
14 Wealth and all things else, are from God. 14 Bragge not of thy
wealth, 29 Nor bring euery man into thy house.</head>

<ab n="1">Wisedome
lifteth vp the head of him that is of low degree, and maketh him to
sit among great men.<note> Or, of the lowly. , Gen.40. 40. dan.6.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Commend
not a man for his beautie, neither abhorre a man for his outward
appearance.</ab>
<ab n="3">The Bee is
little among such as flie, but her fruite is the chiefe of sweete
things.</ab>
<ab n="4">Boast not
of thy cloathing and raiment, and exalt not thy selfe in the day of
honour: for the workes of the Lord are wonderfull, and his workes
among men are hidden.<note> Act.12.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Many kings
haue sit downe vpon the ground, and one that was neuer thought of,
hath worne the crowne.<note> Gr. tyrants.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Many
mightie men haue beene greatly disgraced: and the honourable
deliuered into other mens hands.<note> 1.Kin.15. 28 hest 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Blame not
before thou hast examined the trueth: vnderstand first, and then
rebuke.<note> Deut.12. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Answere
not, before thou hast heard the cause: neither interrupt men in the
midst of their talke.<note> Pro..8.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Striue not
in a matter that concerneth thee not: and sit not in iudgement with
sinners.<note> Or, in the iudgement of sinners.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">My sonne,
meddle not with many matters: for if thou meddle much, thou shalt
not be innocent: and if thou follow after, thou shalt not obtaine,
neither shalt thou escape by flying.<note> Or, escape hurt.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">There is
one that laboureth and taketh paines, and maketh haste, and is so
much the more behinde.<note> Mat.19. 12. 1.tim. 6.9 prou. 10.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Againe,
there is another that is slow, and hath neede of helpe, wanting
abilitie, and full of pouertie, yet the eye of the Lord looked vpon
him for good, and set him vp from his low estate,<note> Iob 1.12. ezek. 28.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And
lifted vp his head from miserie, so that many that saw it,
marueiled at him.</ab>
<ab n="14">Prosperitie
and aduersitie, life and death, pouerty and riches, come of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wisedome,
knowledge, and vnderstanding of the Lawe, are of the Lord: loue,
&amp; the way of good workes, are from him.</ab>
<ab n="16">Errour
and darkenesse had their beginning together with sinners: and euill
shall waxe old with them that glory therein.</ab>
<ab n="17">The gift
of the Lord remaineth with the godly, and his fauour bringeth
prosperitie for euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">There is
that waxeth rich by his warinesse, and pinching, and this is the
portion of his reward:</ab>
<ab n="19">Whereas
he sayth, I haue found rest, and now will eate continually of my
goods, and yet hee knoweth not what time shall come vpon him, and
that hee must leaue those things to others, and die.<note> Luke 12. 19. , Or, passe.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Be
stedfast in thy couenant, and be conuersant therein, and waxe olde
in thy worke.<note> Matt.10. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Marueile
not at the workes of sinners, but trust in the Lord, and abide in
thy labour: for it is an easie thing in the sight of the Lord, on
the sudden to make a poore man rich.</ab>
<ab n="22">The
blessing of the Lord is in the reward of the godly, and suddenly he
maketh his blessing to flourish.<note> Or, for a reward.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Say not,
what profit is there of my seruice? and what good things shal I
haue hereafter?<note> Mal.3.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Againe,
say not, I haue enough, and possesse many things; and what euill
can come to me hereafter?</ab>
<ab n="25">In the
day of prosperitie, there is a forgetfulnesse of affliction: and in
the day of affliction, there is no remembrance of
prosperitie.</ab>
<ab n="26">For it is
an easie thing vnto the Lord in the day of death, to reward a man
according to his wayes.</ab>
<ab n="27">The
affliction of an houre, maketh a man forget pleasure: and in his
end, his deeds shalbe discouered.</ab>
<ab n="28">Iudge
none blessed before his death: for a man shall bee knowen in his
children.</ab>
<ab n="29">Bring not
euery man into thine house, for the deceitfull man hath many
traines.</ab>
<ab n="30">Like as a
Partrich taken [and kept] in a cage, so is the heart of the proud;
and like as a spie, watcheth hee for thy fall.</ab>
<ab n="31">For hee
lieth in wait, and turneth good into euill, and in things worthy
praise, will lay blame vpon thee.</ab>
<ab n="32">Of a
sparke of fire, a heape of coales is kindled: and a sinnefull man
layeth waite for blood.</ab>
<ab n="33">Take heed
of a mischieuous man, (for hee worketh wickednesse) lest hee bring
vpon thee a perpetuall blot.</ab>
<ab n="34">Receiue a
stranger into thine house, and hee will disturbe thee, and turne
thee out of thine owne.</ab>



</div>