<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Remedies against vanitie, are a
good name, 2 Mortification, 7 Patience, 11 Wisedome. 23 The
difficultie of wisedome.</head>


<fw>A fooles laughter.</fw>
<ab n="1">A Good name
is better then precious ointment: and the day of death, then the
day of ones birth.<note> Prou.23.1 and 15.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ It is
better to goe to the house of mourning, then to goe to the house of
feasting: for that is the end of all men, and the liuing will lay
it to his heart.</ab>
<ab n="3">Sorrow is
better then laughter: for by the sadnesse of the countenance the
heart is made better.<note> Or, anger.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The heart of
the wise is in the house of mourning: but the heart of fooles is in
the house of mirth.</ab>
<ab n="5">It is better
to heare the rebuke of the wise, then for a man to heare the song
of fooles.<note> Pro.13.18 &amp; 15.31.32</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For as the
crackling of thornes vnder a pot, so is the laughter of the foole:
this also is vanitie.<note> Heb. sound</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Surely
oppression maketh a wise man mad: and a gift destroyeth the
heart.<note> Deut.16. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Better is the
ende of a thing then the beginning thereof: and the patient in
spirit is better then the proude in spirit.</ab>
<ab n="9">Be not hastie
in thy spirit to bee angry: for anger resteth in the bosome of
fooles.<note> Pro.14.17 and 16.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Say not
thou, What is the cause that the former dayes were better then
these? For thou doest not enquire wisely concerning
this.<note> Heb. out of wisedome.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶
Wisedome is good with an inheritance: and by it there is profite to
them that see the sunne.<note> Or, as good as an inheritance, yea, better too.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For wisedome
is a defence, and money is a defence: but the excellencie of
knowledge is, that wisedome giueth life to them that haue
it.<note> Hebr. shadowe.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Consider the
worke of God: for who can make that straight, which hee hath made
crooked?<note> Chap. 1. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">In the day
of prosperitie be ioyfull, but in the day of aduersitie consider:
God also hath set the one ouer against the other, to the end that
man should find nothing after him.<note> Heb. made.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">All things
haue I seene in the dayes of my vanitie: there is a iust man that
perisheth in his righteousnes, and there is a wicked man that
prolongeth his life in his wickednes.</ab>
<ab n="16">Be not
righteous ouer much, neither make thy selfe ouer wise: why
shouldest thou destroy thy selfe?<note> Heb. be desolate?</note></ab>

<fw>None is iust.</fw>
<ab n="17">Be not
ouermuch wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die
before thy time?<note> Heb. not in thy time?</note></ab>
<ab n="18">It is good
that thou shouldest take holde of this, yea also from this withdraw
not thine hand: for hee that feareth God, shall come foorth of them
all.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wisedome
strengtheneth the wise, more then ten mightie men which are in the
citie.<note> Prou.21. 22. and 24. 5. cha.9.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For there is
not a iust man vpon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth
not.<note> Prou.20.9 1.kin. 8.46. 1.ioh.1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Also take no
heede vnto all words that are spoken; lest thou heare thy seruant
curse thee.<note> Heb. giue not thine heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For often
times also thine owne heart knoweth, that thou thy selfe likewise
hast cursed others.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ All
this haue I prooued by wisedome: I said, I will be wise, but it was
farre from me.</ab>
<ab n="24">That which
is farre off, and exceeding deepe, who can finde it out?</ab>
<ab n="25">I applyed
mine heart to know, and to search, and to seeke out wisdome, and
the reason of things, aud to know the wickednes of folly, euen of
foolishnesse and madnesse.<note> Heb. I and mine heart compassed.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And I finde
more bitter then death, the woman whose heart is snares &amp; nets,
and her handes as bands: who so pleaseth God, shall escape from
her, but the sinner shall be taken by her.<note> Prou.22. 14. , He that is good before God.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Behold, this
haue I found (saith the Preacher) counting one by one to finde out
the account:<note> Or, weighing one thing after another to finde out the reason.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Which yet my
soule seeketh, but I finde not: one man among a thousand haue I
found, but a woman among all those haue I not found.</ab>
<ab n="29">Loe, this
onely haue I found, that God hath made man vpright: but they haue
sought out many inuentions.<note> Gen.1.27.</note></ab>



</div>