<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>3 Children must honour, and helpe
both their parents. 21 We may not desire to knowe all things 26 The
incorrigible must needes perish. 30 Almes are
rewarded.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare mee
your father, O children, and doe thereafter, that ye may be
safe.</ab>
<ab n="2">For the
Lord hath giuen the father honour ouer the children, and hath
confirmed the authoritie of the mother ouer the sonnes.<note> Exo.20.6. deut. 5. 10. , Or, iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Who so
honoureth his father, maketh an atonement for his sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And he that
honoureth his mother, is as one that layeth vp treasure.</ab>
<ab n="5">Who so
honoureth his father, shal haue ioy of his owne children, and when
he maketh his prayer, hee shall bee heard.</ab>
<ab n="6">He that
honoureth his father, shal haue a long life, and he that is
obedient vnto the Lord, shall bee a comfort to his mother.</ab>
<ab n="7">He that
feareth the Lord, will honour his father, and will doe seruice vnto
his parents, as to his masters.</ab>
<ab n="8">Honour thy
father and mother, both in word and deed, that a blessing may come
vpon thee from them.<note> Exod.20. 12. deut. 5. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For the
blessing of the father establisheth the houses of children, but the
curse of the mother rooteth out foundations.<note> Gene.27. 27. deu.33. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Glory not
in the dishonour of thy father, for thy fathers dishonour is no
glory vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the
glory of a man, is from the honour of his father, and a mother in
dishonour, is a reproch to the children.</ab>
<ab n="12">My sonne,
helpe thy father in his age, and grieue him not as long as hee
liueth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And if his
vnderstanding faile, haue patience with him, and despise him not,
when thou art in thy ful strength.<note> Or, in all thine habilitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the
relieuing of thy father shall not be forgotten: and in stead of
sinnes it shall be added to build thee vp.</ab>
<ab n="15">In the day
of thine affliction it shall be remembred, thy sinnes also shal
melt away, as the yce in þ<note/> faire warme
weather.</ab>
<ab n="16">He that
forsaketh his father, is as a blasphemer, and he that angreth his
mother, is cursed of God.</ab>
<ab n="17">My sonne,
goe on with thy businesse in meekenesse, so shalt thou be beloued
of him that is approued.</ab>
<ab n="18">The
greater thou art, the more humble thy selfe, and thou shalt find
fauour before the Lord.<note> Phil.2.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Many are
in high place and of renowne: but mysteries are reueiled vnto the
meeke.<note> Psal.25. 9,14.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For the
power of the Lord is great, and hee is honoured of the
lowly.</ab>
<ab n="21">Seeke not
out the things that are too hard for thee, neither search the
things that are aboue thy strength.<note> Prou.25. 27. rom.12. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But what
is commaunded thee, thinke thereupon with reuerence, for it is not
needfull for thee, to see with thine eyes, the things that are in
secret.</ab>
<ab n="23">Be not
curious in vnnecessarie matters: for moe things are shewed vnto
thee, then men vnderstand.</ab>
<ab n="24">For many
are deceiued by their owne vaine opinion, and an euill suspition
hath ouerthrowen their iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="25">Without
eyes thou shalt want light: professe not the knowledge therfore
that thou hast not.</ab>
<ab n="26">A
stubborne heart shall fare euill at the last, and he that loueth
danger shall perish therein.</ab>
<ab n="27">An
obstinate heart shall be laden with sorrowes, and the wicked man
shall heape sinne vpon sinne.</ab>
<ab n="28">In the
punishment of the proud there is no remedie: for the plant of
wickednesse hath taken roote in him.<note> Or, the proud man is not healed by his punishment.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The heart
of the prudent will vnderstand a parable, and an attentiue eare is
the desire of a wise man.</ab>
<ab n="30">Water will
quench a flaming fire, and almes maketh an attonement for
sinnes.<note> Psal.40.2. dan.4.24. matth.5. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And hee
that requiteth good turnes, is mindfull of that which may come
heereafter: and when he falleth he shall find a stay.</ab>



</div>