<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Of silence and speaking. 10 Of
gifts, and gaine. 18 Of slipping by the tongue. 24 Of lying. 27 Of
diuers aduertisements.</head>

<ab n="1">There is a
reproofe that is not comely: againe some man holdeth his tongue,
and he is wise.<note> Or, seasonable.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">It is much
better to reprooue, then to be angry secretly, and he that
confesseth his fault, shall be preserued from hurt.</ab>
<ab n="3">How good
is it when thou art reproued, to shew repentance? for so shalt thou
escape wilfull sinne.</ab>
<ab n="4">As is the
lust of an Eunuch to defloure a virgine; so is he that executeth
iudgement with violence.<note> Chap. 30. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">There is
one that keepeth silence and is found wise: and another by much
babling becommeth hatefull.</ab>
<ab n="6">Some man
holdeth his tongue, because hee hath not to answere, and some
keepeth silence, knowing his time.<note> Eccle.3.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">A wise man
wil hold his tongue till he see opportunitie: but a babler and a
foole will regard no time.<note> Cha.32.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He that
vseth many words shalbe abhorred; and hee that taketh to himselfe
authoritie therein, shalbe hated.</ab>
<ab n="9">There is a
sinner that hath good successe in euill things; and there is a
gaine that turneth to losse.</ab>
<ab n="10">There is
a gift that shall not profit thee; and there is a gift whose
recompence is double.</ab>
<ab n="11">There is
an abasement because of glory; and there is that lifteth vp his
head from a low estate.</ab>
<ab n="12">There is
that buyeth much for a little, and repayeth it seuen fold.</ab>
<ab n="13">A wise
man by his words maketh himselfe beloued: but the graces of fooles
shalbe powred out.<note> Chap.6.5. , Or, pleasant conceits. , Lost, or spilt.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The gift
of a foole shall doe thee no good when thou hast it; neither yet of
the enuious for his necessitie: for hee looketh to receiue many
things for one.<note> Gr. for, his eyes are many for one to receiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hee
giueth little and vpbraideth much; hee openeth his mouth like a
crier; to day he lendeth, and to morrow will he aske it againe:
such an one is to be hated of God and man.</ab>
<ab n="16">The foole
saith, I haue no friends, I haue no thanke for all my good deeds:
and they that eate my bread speake euill of me.</ab>
<ab n="17">How oft,
and of how many shall he be laughed to scorne? for hee knoweth not
aright what it is to haue; and it is all one vnto him, as if he had
it not.</ab>
<ab n="18">To slip
vpon a pauement, is better then to slip with the tongue: so, the
fall of the wicked shall come speedily.</ab>
<ab n="19">An
vnseasonable tale will alwayes be in the mouth of the
vnwise.<note> Or, an vnpleasant fellow.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">A wise
sentence shall be reiected when it commeth out of a fools mouth:
for he will not speake it in due season.</ab>
<ab n="21">There is
that is hindred from sinning through want: and when hee taketh
rest, he shall not be troubled.<note> Gr. shall not be pricked.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">There is
that destroyeth his owne soule through bashfulnesse, and by
accepting of persons ouerthroweth himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="23">There is
that for bashfulnes promiseth to his friend, and maketh him his
enemy for nothing.</ab>
<ab n="24">A lie is
a foule blot in a man, yet it is continually in the mouth of the
vntaught.<note> Cha.25.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">A thiefe
is better then a man that is accustomed to lie: but they both shall
haue destruction to heritage.</ab>
<ab n="26">The
disposition of a liar is dishonourable, and his shame is euer with
him.<note> Or, igno-minde.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">A wise
man shall promote himselfe to honour with his words: and hee that
hath vnderstanding, will please great men.</ab>
<ab n="28">He that
tilleth his land, shall increase his heape: and he that pleaseth
great men, shal get pardon for iniquity.<note> Prou.12. 11. and 28. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Presents
and gifts blind the eyes of the wise, and stoppe vp his mouth that
he cannot reprooue.<note> Exo.23.8. deu. 16.19. , Or, as a muzzle in the mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Wisedome
that is hidde, and treasure that is hoarded vp, what profit is in
them both?</ab>
<ab n="31">Better is
he that hideth his folly, then a man that hideth his
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="32">Necessary
patience in seeking the Lord, is better then he that leadeth his
life without a guide.</ab>



</div>