<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 What things are beautifull, and
what hatefull. 6 What is the crowne of age. 7 What things make men
happy. 13 Nothing worse then a wicked woman.</head>

<ab n="1">In three
things I was beautified, and stoode vp beautiful, both before God
and men: the vnitie of brethren, the loue of neighbours, a man and
a wife that agree together.<note> Or, gloried. , Gen.13. 2,5. rom. 12.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Three
sorts of men my soule hateth, and I am greatly offended at their
life: a poore man that is proud, a rich man that is a lyar, and an
olde adulterer that doteth.</ab>
<ab n="3">If thou
hast gathered nothing in thy youth, how canst thou finde any thing
in thine age?</ab>
<ab n="4">Oh how
comely a thing is iudgement for gray haires, and for ancient men to
know counsell?</ab>
<ab n="5">Oh how
comely is the wisedome of olde men, and vnderstanding and counsell
to men of honour?</ab>
<ab n="6">Much
experience is the crowne of olde men, and the feare of God is their
glory.</ab>
<ab n="7">There be
nine things which I haue iudged in mine heart to be happy, and the
tenth I will vtter with my tongue: a man that hath ioy of his
children, and he that liueth to see the fall of his enemie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Well is
him that dwelleth with a wife of vnderstanding, and that hath not
slipped with his tongue, and that hath not serued a man more
vnworthy then himselfe.<note> Cha.14.1. and 19.16. iam.3.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Well is
him that hath found prudence, and he that speaketh in the eares of
him that will heare.<note> Or, a friend</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Oh how
great is he that findeth wisedome! yet is there none aboue him that
feareth the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="11">But the
loue of the Lord passeth all things for illumination: he that
holdeth it, whereto shall he be likened?<note> Or, to whom.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The feare
of the Lord is the beginning of his loue: and faith is the
beginning of cleauing vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="13">[Giue
mee] any plague, but the plague of the heart: and any wickednesse,
but the wickednesse of a woman.</ab>
<ab n="14">And any
affliction, but the affliction from them that hate me: and any
reuenge, but the reuenge of enemies.</ab>
<ab n="15">There is
no head aboue the head of a serpent, and there is no wrath aboue
the wrath of an enemie.</ab>
<ab n="16">I had
rather dwell with a lyon and a dragon, then to keepe house with a
wicked woman.<note> Pro,21.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The
wickednesse of a woman changeth her face, and darkeneth her
countenance like sackecloth.<note> Or, like a Beare.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Her
husband shall sit among his neighbours: and when hee heareth it,
shall sigh bitterly.</ab>
<ab n="19">All
wickednesse is but little to the wickednesse of a woman: let the
portion of a sinner fall vpon her.</ab>
<ab n="20">As the
climbing vp a sandie way is to the feete of the aged, so is a wife
full of words to a quiet man.<note> Or, scolding.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Stumble
not at the beautie of a woman, and desire her not for
pleasure.<note> 2.Sam. 11. 2 chap. 42.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">A woman,
if shee maintaine her husband, is full of anger, impudencie, and
much reproch.</ab>
<ab n="23">A wicked
woman abateth the courage, maketh a heauie countenance, and a
wounded heart: a woman that will not comfort her husband in
distresse maketh weake hands, and feeble knees.</ab>
<ab n="24">Of the
woman came the beginning of sinne, &amp; through her wee all
die.<note> Gen. 3. 6. 1.tim.2.14</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Giue the
water no passage: neither a wicked woman libertie to gad
abroad.</ab>
<ab n="26">If she
goe not as thou wouldest haue her, cut her off from thy flesh, and
giue her a bill of diuorce, and let her goe.</ab>



</div>