<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>1 A description of him that is
truely wise. 12 An exhortation to praise God for his workes, which
are good to the good, and euill to them that are
euill.</head>

<ab n="1">But hee
that giueth his minde to the Law of the most high, and is occupied
in the meditation thereof, wil seeke out the wisdome of all the
ancient, and be occupied in prophecies.</ab>
<ab n="2">Hee will
keepe the sayings of the renowmed men: and where subtile parables
are, he will be there also.</ab>
<ab n="3">Hee will
seeke out the secrets of graue sentences, and be conuersant in
darke parables.</ab>
<ab n="4">He shall
serue among great men, and appeare before princes: he will trauaile
through strange countreys, for hee hath tried the good, and the
euill among men.</ab>
<ab n="5">Hee will
giue his heart to resort early to the Lord that made him, and will
pray before the most high, and will open his mouth in prayer, and
make supplication for his sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="6">When the
great Lord will, he shall bee filled with the spirit of
vnderstanding: he shal powre out wise sentences, and giue thankes
vnto the Lord in his prayer.</ab>
<ab n="7">Hee shall
direct his counsell and knowledge, and in his secrets shall hee
meditate.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hee shall
shew foorth that which he hath learned, and shall glory in the Law
of the couenant of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">Many shall
commend his vnderstanding, and so long as the world endureth, it
shall not be blotted out, his memoriall shall not depart away, and
his name shall liue from generation to generation.</ab>
<ab n="10">Nations
shall shewe foorth his wisedome, and the congregation shall declare
his praise.<note> Chap. 44. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">If hee
die, he shall leaue a greater name then a thousand: and if he liue,
he shall increase it.<note> Or, gaine vnto it.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Yet I
haue more to say which I haue thought vpon, for I am filled as the
Moone at the full.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hearken
vnto me, ye holy children, and budde foorth as a rose growing by
the brooke of the field:<note> Or, riuers of water.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And giue
yee a sweete sauour as frankincense, and flourish as a lilly, send
foorth a smell, and sing a song of praise, blesse the Lord in all
his workes.</ab>
<ab n="15">Magnifie
his Name, and shewe foorth his praise with the songs of your lips,
and with harpes, and in praising him you shall say after this
maner:</ab>
<ab n="16">Al the
works of the Lord are exceeding good, &amp; whatsoeuer hee
commandeth, shalbe accomplished in due season.<note> Gen.1.31. mark.7.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And none
may say, What is this? wherefore is that? for at time conuenient
they shall all be sought out: at his commaundement the waters stood
as an heape, &amp; at the wordes of his mouth the receptacles of
waters.</ab>
<ab n="18">At his
commandement is done whatsoeuer pleaseth him, and none can hinder
when he will saue.</ab>
<ab n="19">The
workes of all flesh are before him, &amp; nothing can be hid from
his eyes.</ab>
<ab n="20">He seeth
from euerlasting to euerlasting, and there is nothing wonderfull
before him.</ab>
<ab n="21">A man
neede not to say, What is this? wherefore is that? for hee hath
made all things for their vses.</ab>
<ab n="22">His
blessing couered the dry land as a riuer, and watered it as a
flood.</ab>
<ab n="23">As hee
hath turned the waters into saltnesse: so shall the heathen
inherite his wrath.</ab>
<ab n="24">As his
wayes are plaine vnto the holy, so are they stumbling blockes vnto
the wicked.<note> Ose 14.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For the
good, are good things created from the beginning: so euill things
for sinners.</ab>
<ab n="26">The
principall things for the whole vse of mans life, are water, fire,
yron, and salt, floure of wheate, honie, milke, and the blood of
the grape, and oyle, and clothing.</ab>
<ab n="27">All these
things are for good to the godly: so to the sinners they are turned
into euill.</ab>
<ab n="28">There be
spirits that are created for vengeance, which in their furie lay on
sore strokes, in the time of destruction they powre out their
force, and appease the wrath of him that made them.</ab>
<ab n="29">Fire, and
haile, and famine, and death: all these were created for
vengeance:</ab>
<ab n="30">Teeth of
wild beasts, and scorpions, serpents, &amp; the sword, punishing
the wicked to destruction.<note> Or, vipers.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">They
shall reioice in his commandement, and they shall bee ready vpon
earth when neede is, and when their time is come, they shall not
transgresse his word.</ab>
<ab n="32">Therefore
from the beginning I was resolued, and thought vpon these things,
and haue left them in writing.</ab>
<ab n="33">All the
workes of the Lord are good: and he will giue euery needefull thing
in due season.</ab>
<ab n="34">So that a
man cannot say, This is worse then that: for in time they shall all
be well approued.</ab>
<ab n="35">And
therefore praise ye the Lord with the whole heart and mouth, and
blesse the Name of the Lord.</ab>



</div>