<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_41" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-41-43.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLI.</head>
<head>1 The remembrance of Death. 3 Death
is not to be feared. 5 The vngodly shall be accursed. 11 Of an
euill and a good name. 14 Wisedome is to be vttered. 16 Of what
things we should be ashamed.</head>

<ab n="1">O death,
how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that liueth at rest
in his possessions, vnto the man that hath nothing to vexe him, and
that hath prosperity in all things: yea vnto him that is yet able
to receiue meate?</ab>
<ab n="2">O death,
acceptable is thy sentence vnto the needy, and vnto him whose
strength faileth, that is now in the last age, and is vexed with
all things, and to him that despaireth and hath lost
patience.<note> Or, to whom euery thing is troublesome.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Feare not
the sentence of death, remember them that haue beene before thee,
and that come after, for this is the sentence of the Lord ouer all
flesh.</ab>
<ab n="4">And why
art thou against the pleasure of the most High? there is no
inquisition in the graue, whether thou haue liued ten, or a
hundred, or a thousand yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="5">The
children of sinners, are abhominable children: and they that are
conuersant in the dwelling of the vngodly.</ab>
<ab n="6">The
inheritance of sinners children shal perish, and their posterity
shal haue a perpetuall reproch.</ab>
<ab n="7">The
children will complaine of an vngodly father, because they shall be
reproched for his sake.</ab>
<ab n="8">Woe be
vnto you vngodly men which haue forsaken the law of the most high
God: for if you encrease, it shall be to your destruction.</ab>
<ab n="9">And if you
be borne, you shall be borne to a curse: and if you die, a curse
shall be your portion.</ab>
<ab n="10">All that
are of the earth shall turne to earth againe: so the vngodly shall
goe from a curse to destruction.<note> Chap. 40. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The
mourning of men is about their bodies: but an ill name of sinners
shall be blotted out.</ab>
<ab n="12">Haue
regard to thy name: for that shall continue with thee aboue a
thousand great treasures of gold.</ab>
<ab n="13">A good
life hath but few daies: but a good name endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="14">My
children, keepe discipline in peace: for wisedome that is hid, and
a treasure that is not seene, what profit is in them both?</ab>
<ab n="15">A man
that hideth his foolishnesse is better then a man that hideth his
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore
be shamefast according to my word: for it is not good to retaine
all shamefastnesse, neither is it altogether approoued in euery
thing.</ab>
<ab n="17">Be
ashamed of whoredome before father and mother, and of a lie before
a prince and a mighty man:</ab>
<ab n="18">Of an
offence before a iudge and ruler, of iniquitie before a
congregation and people, of vniust dealing before thy partner and
friend:</ab>
<ab n="19">And of
theft in regard of the place where thou soiournest, and in regard
of the trueth of God and his couenant, and to leane with thine
elbow vpon the meate, and of scorning to giue and take:</ab>
<ab n="20">And of
silence before them that salute thee, and to look vpon an
harlot:</ab>
<ab n="21">And to
turne away thy face from thy kinsman, or to take away a portion or
a gift, or to gaze vpon another mans wife,</ab>
<ab n="22">Or to bee
ouerbusie with his maide, and come not neere her bed, or of
vpbraiding speaches before friends; and after thou hast giuen,
vpbraide not:</ab>
<ab n="23">Or of
iterating and speaking againe that which thou hast heard, and of
reuealing of secrets.</ab>
<ab n="24">So shalt
thou be truely shamefast, and finde fauour before all men.</ab>



</div>