<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_37" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVII.</head>
<head>1 How to know friends and
counsellers. 12 The discretion and wisedome of a godly man blesseth
him. 27 Learne to refraine thine appetite.</head>

<ab n="1">Euery
friend saieth, I am his friend also: but there is a friend which is
onely a friend in name.</ab>
<ab n="2">Is it not
a griefe vnto death, when a companion and friend is turned to an
enemie?</ab>
<ab n="3">O wicked
imagination, whence camest thou in to couer the earth with
deceit?</ab>
<ab n="4">There is a
companion, which reioyceth in the prosperity of a friend: but in
the time of trouble will be against him.</ab>
<ab n="5">There is a
companion which helpeth his friend for the belly, and taketh vp the
buckler against the enemie.<note> Or, in presence of the enemie.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Forget not
thy friend in thy minde, and be not vnmindfull of him in thy
riches.</ab>
<ab n="7">Euery
counseller extolleth counsell; but there is some that counselleth
for himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="8">Beware of
a counseller, and know before what neede he hath (for he will
counsell for himselfe) lest hee cast the lot vpon thee:<note> Or, what vse there is of him.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And say
vnto thee, Thy way is good: and afterward he stand on the other
side, to see what shall befall thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">Consult
not with one that suspecteth thee: and hide thy counsell from such
as enuie thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">Neither
consult with a woman touching her of whom she is iealous; neither
with a coward in matters of warre, nor with a merchant concerning
exchange; nor with a buyer of selling; nor with an enuious man of
thankfulnesse; nor with an vnmercifull man touching kindnesse; nor
with the slouthfull for any worke; nor with an hireling for a
yeere, of finishing worke; nor with an idle seruant of much
businesse: Hearken not vnto these in any matter of
counsell.</ab>
<ab n="12">But be
continually with a godly man, whom thou knowest to keepe the
commandements of the Lord, whose minde is according to thy minde,
and will sorrow with thee, if thou shalt miscarry.</ab>
<ab n="13">And let
the counsell of thine owne heart stand: for there is no man more
faithfull vnto thee then it.</ab>
<ab n="14">For a
mans minde is sometime wont to tell him more then seuen watchmen,
that sit aboue in an high towre.</ab>
<ab n="15">And aboue
all this pray to the most high, that he will direct thy way in
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="16">Let
reason goe before euery enterprise, &amp; counsell before euery
action.</ab>
<ab n="17">The
countenance is a signe of changing of the heart.</ab>
<ab n="18">Foure
maner of things appeare: good and euill, life and death: but the
tongue ruleth ouer them continually.</ab>
<ab n="19">There is
one that is wise and teacheth many, and yet is vnprofitable to
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="20">There is
one that sheweth wisedome in words, and is hated: he shall be
destitute of all foode.<note> Or, wisedome.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For grace
is not giuen him from the Lord: because he is depriued of all
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="22">Another
is wise to himselfe: and the fruits of vnderstanding are
commendable in his mouth.</ab>
<ab n="23">A wise
man instructeth his people, and the fruits of his vnderstanding
faile not.</ab>
<ab n="24">A wise
man shall be filled with blessing, and all they that see him, shall
count him happy.</ab>
<ab n="25">The daies
of the life of man may be numbred: but the daies of Israel are
innumerable.</ab>
<ab n="26">A wise
man shall inherite glory among his people, and his name shalbe
perpetuall.<note> Or, credit.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">My sonne
prooue thy soule in thy life, and see what is euill for it, and
giue not that vnto it.</ab>
<ab n="28">For all
things are not profitable for all men, neither hath euery soule
pleasure in euery thing.</ab>
<ab n="29">Be not
vnsatiable in any dainty thing: nor too greedy vpon meates.</ab>
<ab n="30">For
excesse of meates, bringeth sicknesse, and surfetting will turne
into choler.<note> Or, varietie of meates.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">By
surfetting haue many perished, but hee that taketh heed, prolongeth
his life.</ab>



</div>