<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Gods seruants must looke for
trouble, 7 and be patient, and trust in him. 12 For woe to them
that doe not so. 15 But they that feare the Lord, will doe
so.</head>

<ab n="1">My sonne,
if thou come to serue the Lorde, prepare thy soule for
temptation.<note> Mat.4.11. 2.tim.3.12. 1.pet.4.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Set thy
heart aright, and constantly endure, and make not haste in time of
trouble.<note> Or, haste not.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Cleaue vnto
him, and depart not away, that thou mayest be increased at thy last
end.</ab>
<ab n="4">Whatsoeuer
is brought vpon thee, take cheerefully, and bee patient when thou
art changed to a lowe estate.</ab>
<ab n="5">For gold is
tried in the fire, and acceptable men in the furnace of
aduersitie.<note> Wisd.3.6 pro. 17.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Beleeue in
him, and he will helpe thee, order thy way aright, and trust in
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Ye that
feare the Lord, waite for his mercie, and goe not aside, lest ye
fall.</ab>
<ab n="8">Yee that
feare the Lord, beleeue him, and your reward shall not
faile.</ab>
<ab n="9">Ye that
feare the Lord, hope for good, and for euerlasting ioy and
mercy.</ab>
<ab n="10">Looke at
the generations of old, and see, did euer any trust in the Lord,
and was confounded? or did any abide in his feare, &amp; was
forsaken? or whom did hee euer despise, that called vpon
him?</ab>
<ab n="11">For the
Lord is full of compassion, and mercie, longsuffering, and very
pitifull, and forgiueth sinnes, and saueth in time of
affliction.<note> Psal.37.25</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Woe be to
fearefull hearts, and faint hands, and the sinner that goeth two
wayes.</ab>
<ab n="13">Woe vnto
him that is faint hearted, for he beleeueth not, therefore shall he
not be defended.</ab>
<ab n="14">Woe vnto
you that haue lost patience: and what will ye doe when the Lord
shall visite you?</ab>
<ab n="15">They that
feare the Lord, will not disobey his word, and they that loue him,
will keepe his wayes.<note> Ioh.14.20</note></ab>
<ab n="16">They that
feare the Lord, will seeke that which is well pleasing vnto him,
and they that loue him, shall bee filled with the Law.</ab>
<ab n="17">They that
feare the Lord, will prepare their hearts, and humble their soules
in his sight:</ab>
<ab n="18">Saying, We
will fal into the hands of the Lord, and not into the hands of men:
for as his maiestie is, so is his mercie.</ab>



</div>