<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_50" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-48-50.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-50-51.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. L.</head>
<head>1 Of Simon the sonne of Onias. 22
How the people were taught to praise God, and pray. 27 The
conclusion.</head>

<ab n="1">Simon the
high priest the sonne of Onias, who in his life repaired the house
againe, and in his dayes fortified the Temple:<note> 2.Mac.3,4</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And by him
was built from the foundation the double height, the high fortresse
of the wall about the Temple.</ab>
<ab n="3">In his
dayes the cisterne to receiue water being in compasse as the sea,
was couered with plates of brasse.<note> 1.King.7. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">He tooke
care of the Temple that it should not fall, and fortified the citie
against besieging.</ab>
<ab n="5">How was he
honoured in the midst of the people, in his comming out of the
Sanctuarie?<note> Gr. the house of the vaile.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He was as
the morning starre in the midst of a cloud: and as the moone at the
full.</ab>
<ab n="7">As the
Sunne shining vpon the Temple of the most High, and as the rainebow
giuing light in the bright cloudes.</ab>
<ab n="8">And as the
flowre of roses in the spring of the yeere, as lillies by the
riuers of waters, and as the branches of the frankincense tree in
the time of summer.</ab>
<ab n="9">As fire
and incense in the censer, and as a vessell of beaten gold set with
all maner of precious stones,</ab>
<ab n="10">And as a
faire oliue tree budding forth fruit, and as a Cypresse tree which
groweth vp to the cloudes.</ab>
<ab n="11">When he
put on the robe of honour, and was clothed with the perfection of
glory, when he went vp to the holy altar, he made the garment of
holinesse honourable.</ab>
<ab n="12">When he
tooke the portions out of the priests hands, hee himselfe stood by
the hearth of the altar, compassed with his brethren round about,
as a yong cedar in Libanus, and as palme trees compassed they him
round about.</ab>
<ab n="13">So were
all the sonnes of Aaron in their glory, and the oblations of the
Lord in their hands, before all the congregation of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">And
finishing the seruice at the altar, that he might adorne the
offring of the most high Almighty,</ab>
<ab n="15">He
stretched out his hand to the cup, and powred of the blood of the
grape, he powred out at the foote of the altar, a sweet smelling
sauour vnto the most high King of all.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then
shouted the sonnes of Aaron, and sounded the siluer trumpets, and
made a great noise to be heard, for a remembrance before the most
High.<note> Or, trumpets beaten forth with the hammer.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Then all
the people together hasted, and fell downe to the earth vpon their
faces to worship their Lord God almighty the most High.</ab>
<ab n="18">The
singers also sang praises with their voices, with great variety of
sounds was there made sweete melodie.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
people besought the Lord the most High by prayer before him that is
mercifull, till the solemnity of the Lord was ended, and they had
finished his seruice.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then he
went downe, and lifted vp his hands ouer the whole congregation of
the children of Israel, to giue the blessing of the Lord with his
lips, and to reioyce in his name.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they
bowed themselues downe to worship the second time, that they might
receiue a blessing from the most High.</ab>
<ab n="22">Now
therefore blesse yee the God of all, which onely doth wonderous
things euery where, which exalteth our daies from the wombe, and
dealeth with vs according to his mercy.</ab>
<ab n="23">He grant
vs ioyfulnesse of heart, and that peace may be in our daies in
Israel for euer.</ab>
<ab n="24">That hee
would confirme his mercy with vs, and deliuer vs at his
time.</ab>
<ab n="25">There be
two maner of nations which my heart abhorreth, and the third is no
nation.</ab>
<ab n="26">They that
sit vpon the mountaine of Samaria, and they that dwell amongst the
Philistines, and that foolish people that dwell in Sichem.</ab>
<ab n="27">Iesus the
sonne of Sirach of Hierusalem hath written in this booke, the
instruction of vnderstanding and knowledge, who out of his heart
powred forth wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="28">Blessed
is he that shall be exercised in these things, and hee that layeth
them vp in his heart, shall become wise.</ab>
<ab n="29">For if he
doe them, hee shall be strong to all things, for the light of the
Lord leadeth him, who giueth wisedome to the godly: blessed be the
Lord for euer. Amen. Amen.</ab>



</div>