<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_43" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-41-43.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIII.</head>
<head>1 The workes of God in heauen, and
in earth, and in the sea, are exceeding glorious and wonderfull. 29
Yet God himselfe in his power and wisedome is aboue
all.</head>

<ab n="1">The pride
of the height, the cleare firmament, the beautie of heauen, with
his glorious shew;</ab>
<ab n="2">The Sunne
when it appeareth, declaring at his rising, a marueilous
instrument, the worke of the most High.<note> Or, vessell.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">At noone
it parcheth the country, and who can abide the burning heate
thereof?</ab>
<ab n="4">A man
blowing a furnace is in works of heat, but the Sunne burneth the
mountaines three times more; breathing out fiery vapours, and
sending foorth bright beames, it dimmeth the eyes.</ab>
<ab n="5">Great is
the Lord that made it, and at his commandement it runneth
hastily.<note> Gr, hee stayed his course.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He made
the Moone also to serue in her season, for a declaration of times,
and a signe of the world.<note> Gen.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">From the
Moone is the signe of Feasts, a light that decreaseth in her
perfection.<note> Exo. 12.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The moneth
is called after her name, encreasing wonderfully in her changing,
being an instrument of the armies aboue, shining in the firmament
of heauen,</ab>
<ab n="9">The
beautie of heauen, the glory of the starres, an ornament giuing
light in the highest places of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">At the
commandement of the holy One, they will stand in their order, and
neuer faint in their watches.</ab>
<ab n="11">Looke
vpon the rainebow, and praise him that made it, very beautifull it
is in the brightnesse thereof.<note> Gen.9.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">It
compasseth the heauen about with a glorious circle, and the hands
of the most high haue bended it.<note> Esa.40.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">By his
commandement hee maketh the snow to fall apace, and sendeth swiftly
the lightnings of his iudgment.</ab>
<ab n="14">Through
this the treasures are opened, and clouds flie forth as
foules.</ab>
<ab n="15">By his
great power hee maketh the cloudes firme, and the hailestones are
broken small.</ab>
<ab n="16">At his
sight the mountaines are shaken, and at his will the South wind
bloweth.</ab>
<ab n="17">The noise
of the thunder maketh the earth to tremble: so doth the Northren
storme, and the whirlewinde: as birds flying he scattereth the
snow, and the falling downe thereof, is as the lighting of
grashoppers.<note> Or, to grone as a woman in her trauaile.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The eye
marueileth at the beauty of the whitenesse thereof, and the heart
is astonished at the raining of it.</ab>
<ab n="19">The hoare
frost also as salt hee powreth on the earth, and being congealed,
it lieth on the toppe of sharpe stakes.<note> Or, it is as the point of sharp stakes.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Wheu the
colde North-winde bloweth, and the water is congealed into yce, it
abideth vpon euery gathering together of water, and clotheth the
water as with a brestplate.</ab>
<ab n="21">It
deuoureth the mountaines, and burneth the wildernesse, and
consumeth the grasse as fire.</ab>
<ab n="22">A present
remedy of all is a miste comming speedily: a dew comming after
heate, refresheth.<note> Or, vpon the heat.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">By his
counsell he appeaseth the deepe, and planteth Ilands
therein.</ab>
<ab n="24">They that
saile on the Sea, tell of the danger thereof, and when wee heare it
with our eares, wee marueile thereat.</ab>
<ab n="25">For
therein be strange and wonderous workes, varietie of all kindes of
beasts, and whales created.<note> Psal.107. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">By him
the ende of them hath prosperous successe, and by his word all
things consist.</ab>
<ab n="27">We may
speake much, &amp; yet come short: wherefore in summe, he is
all.</ab>
<ab n="28">How shall
wee be able to magnifie him? for hee is great aboue all his
workes.</ab>
<ab n="29">The Lord
is terrible and very great, and marueilous is his
power.<note> Psal.96.42</note></ab>
<ab n="30">When you
glorifie the Lord exalt him as much as you can: for euen yet wil he
farre exceed, and when you exalt him, put foorth all your strength,
and be not weary: for you can neuer goe farre enough.</ab>
<ab n="31">Who hath
seene him, that hee might tell vs? and who can magnifie him as he
is?<note> Psal.106.2 ioh.1.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">There are
yet hid greater things then these be, for wee haue seene but a few
of his workes:</ab>
<ab n="33">For the
Lord hath made all things, and to the godly hath hee giuen
wisedome.</ab>



</div>