<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_44" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-44-45.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIV.</head>
<head>1 The praise of certaine holy men:
16 Of Enoch, 17 Noah, 19 Abraham, 22 Isaac, 23 and
Iacob.</head>

<ab n="1">Let vs now
praise famous men, and our Fathers that begat vs.<note> The praise of the fathers.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The Lorde
hath wrought great glory by them, through his great power from the
beginning.</ab>
<ab n="3">Such as
did beare rule in their kingdomes, men renowmed for their power,
giuing counsell by their vnderstanding, and declaring
prophecies:</ab>
<ab n="4">Leaders of
the people by their counsels, and learning meet for the people,
wise and eloquent in their instructions.</ab>
<ab n="5">Such as
found out musical tunes, and reiected verses in
writing.<note> Or, ditties.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Rich men
furnished with abilitie, liuing peaceably in their
habitations.</ab>
<ab n="7">All these
were honoured in their generations, and were the glory of their
times.</ab>
<ab n="8">There be
of them, that haue left a name behind them, that their praises
might be reported.</ab>
<ab n="9">And some
there be, which haue no memorial, who are perished as though they
had neuer bene, and are become as though they had neuer bene borne,
and their children after them.<note> Gen.7.22</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But these
were mercifull men, whose righteousnesse hath not beene
forgotten.</ab>
<ab n="11">With
their seed shall continually remaine a good inheritance, and their
children are within the couenant.</ab>
<ab n="12">Their
seed stands fast, and their children for their sakes.<note> Or, after them.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Their
seed shall remaine for euer, and their glory shall not be blotted
out.</ab>
<ab n="14">Their
bodies are buried in peace, but their name liueth for
euermore.</ab>
<ab n="15">The
people will tell of their wisdome, and the congregation will shew
forth their praise.<note> Chap. 39. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Enoch
pleased the Lord, and was translated, being an example of
repentance, to all generations.<note> Gen.5. 24 heb.11.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Noah was
found perfect and righteous, in the time of wrath, he was taken in
exchange (for the world) therefore was he left as a remnant vnto
the earth, when the flood came.<note> Gen.6.9. and 7.1. heb.11.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">An
euerlasting Couenant was made with him, that all flesh should
perish no more by the flood.<note> Gen.9.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Abraham
was a great father of many people: in glory was there none like
vnto him:<note> Gen.12.3 and 15.5. and 17.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Who kept
the Law of the most High, and was in couenant with him, hee
established the Couenant in his flesh, and when he was proued, he
was found faithfull.<note> Gen.21.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Therefore
he assured him by an othe, that he would blesse the nations in his
seed, and that he would multiply him, as the dust of the earth, and
exalt his seed as the starres, and cause them to inherit from Sea
to Sea, &amp; from the riuer vnto the vtmost part of the
land.<note> Gen.22. 16,17,18. gal.3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">With
Isaac did he establish likewise [for Abraham his fathers sake] the
blessing of all men and the couenant,<note> Gen.27. 28. and 28. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And made
it rest vpon the head of Iacob. Hee acknowledged him in his
blessing, and gaue him an heritage, and diuided his portions, among
the twelue tribes did he part them.</ab>



</div>