<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 A prayer for grace to flee sinne.
9 We may not vse swearing: 14 But remember our parents. 16 Of three
sorts of sinne. 23 The adultresse wife sinneth many
waies.</head>

<ab n="1">O Lord,
father and gouernour of all my whole life, leaue me not to their
counsels, and let me not fall by them.</ab>
<ab n="2">Who will
set scourges ouer my thoughts, and the discipline of wisedome ouer
mine heart? that they spare me not for mine ignorances and it passe
not by my sinnes:</ab>
<ab n="3">Least mine
ignorances increase, and my sinnes abound to my destruction, and I
fall before mine aduersaries, and mine enemie reioyce ouer mee,
whose hope is farre from thy mercy.</ab>
<ab n="4">O Lord,
father and God of my life, giue me not a proud looke, but turne
away from thy seruants alwaies a haughty minde:<note> Or, a giant like.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Turne away
from mee vaine hopes, and concupiscence, and thou shalt hold him vp
that is desirous alwaies to serue thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">Let not
the greedinesse of the belly, nor lust of the flesh take hold of
me, and giue not ouer me thy seruant into an impudent
minde.</ab>
<ab n="7">Heare, O
yee children, the discipline of the mouth: He that keepeth it,
shall neuer be taken in his lippes.</ab>
<ab n="8">The sinner
shall be left in his foolishnesse: both the euill speaker and the
proud shall fall thereby.</ab>
<ab n="9">Accustome
not thy mouth to swearing: neither vse thy selfe to the naming of
the holy one.<note> Exod. 20. 7. chap. 27. 15. math.5. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For as a
seruant that is continually beaten, shall not be without a blew
marke: so hee that sweareth and nameth God continually, shal not be
faultlesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">A man
that vseth much swearing shall be filled with iniquity, and the
plague shall neuer depart from his house: If he shall offend, his
sinne shall be vpon him: and if he acknowledge not his sinne, hee
maketh a double offence, and if he sweare in vaine, he shall not be
innocent, but his house shall be full of calamities.<note> Gre. iustified.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">There is
a word that is clothed about with death: God graunt that it be not
found in the heritage of Iacob, for all such things shall be farre
from the godly, and they shall not wallow in their sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="13">Use not
thy mouth to vntemperate swearing, for therein is the word of
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="14">Remember
thy father and thy mother, when thou sittest among great men. Be
not forgetfull before them, and so thou by thy custome become a
foole, and wish that thou hadst not beene borne, and curse the day
of thy natiuitie.</ab>
<ab n="15">The man
that is accustomed to opprobrious words, will neuer be reformed all
the daies of his life.<note> 2.Sam.16. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Two sorts
of men multiply sinne, and the third will bring wrath: a hot minde
is as a burning fire, it will neuer be quenched till it be
consumed: a fornicatour in the body of his flesh, will neuer cease
till he hath kindled a fire.</ab>
<ab n="17">All bread
is sweete to a whoremonger, he will not leaue off till he
die.<note> Prou.9. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">A man
that breaketh wedlocke, saying thus in his heart, Who seeth me? I
am compassed about with darknesse: the walles couer me; &amp; no
body seeth me, what neede I to feare? The most high wil not
remember my sinnes:<note> Isai.29. 15. iob. 24. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Such a
man only feareth the eies of men, and knoweth not that the eies of
the Lord are tenne thousand times brighter then the Sunne,
beholding all the waies of men, and considering the most secret
parts.</ab>
<ab n="20">He knew
all things ere euer they were created, so also after they were
perfited, he looked vpon them all:</ab>
<ab n="21">This man
shall bee punished in the streets of the citie, and where he
suspecteth not, he shall be taken.<note> Leuit.20. 10. deut. 22.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Thus
shall it goe also with the wife, that leaueth her husband, and
bringeth in an heire by another:<note> Or, a stranger.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For first
she hath disobeyed the Law of the most High: and secondly, she hath
trespassed against her owne husband, and thirdly, she hath played
the whore in adultery, and brought children by another
man.<note> Exod. 20. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Shee
shall be brought out into the congregation, and inquisition shalbe
made of her children.<note> Or, visitation.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Her
children shall not take root, and her branches shall bring foorth
no fruit.<note> Wisd.4.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">She shall
leaue her memorie to be cursed, and her reproch shall not be
blotted out.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they
that remaine, shall know that there is nothing better then the
feare of the Lord, and that there is nothing sweeter then to take
heed vnto the Commandement of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="28">It is
great glory to follow the Lord, &amp; to be receiued of him is long
life.</ab>



</div>