<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>4 Gods workes are to be wondred at.
9 Mans life is short. 11 God is mercifull. 15 Doe not blemish thy
good deeds with ill wordes. 22 Deferre not to bee iustified. 30
Followe not thy lustes.</head>

<ab n="1">Hee that
liueth for euer, created all things in generall.<note> Gen. 1. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord
onely is righteous, and there is none other but he.</ab>
<ab n="3">Who
gouerneth the world with the palme of his hand, and all things obey
his will, for he is the king of all, by his power diuiding holy
things among them from prophane.<note> Leuit.10. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">To whom
hath he giuen power to declare his works? and who shall finde out
his noble actes?<note> Psal. 105.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Who shall
number the strength of his maiestie? and who shall also tel out his
mercies?</ab>
<ab n="6">As for the
wonderous workes of the Lord, there may nothing bee taken from
them, neither may any thing bee put vnto them, neither can the
ground of them be found out.</ab>
<ab n="7">When a man
hath done, then he beginneth, and when hee leaueth off, then he
shall be doubtfull.</ab>
<ab n="8">What is
man, and whereto serueth he? what is his good, &amp; what is his
euil?</ab>
<ab n="9">The number
of a mans dayes at the most are an hundred yeeres.<note> Psal.90.10</note></ab>
<ab n="10">As a drop
of water vnto the Sea, and a grauell stone in comparison of the
sand, so are a thousand yeeres to the dayes of
eternitie.<note> 2.Pet.3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Therfore
is God patient with them, &amp; powreth forth his mercy vpon
them.</ab>
<ab n="12">He saw
and perceiued their end to be euill, therefore he multiplied his
compassion.</ab>
<ab n="13">The mercy
of man is toward his neighbour, but the mercy of the Lord is vpon
all flesh: he reprooueth and nurtureth, and teacheth, &amp;
bringeth againe as a shepheard his flocke.</ab>
<ab n="14">He hath
mercy on them that receiue discipline, and that diligently seeke
after his iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="15">My sonne,
blemish not thy good deeds, neither vse vncomfortable words when
thou giuest any thing.<note> Chap.41. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Shall not
the deaw asswage the heate? so is a word better then a
gift.</ab>
<ab n="17">Loe is
not a word better then a gift? but both are with a gracious
man.</ab>
<ab n="18">A foole
will vpbraide churlishly, and a gift of the enuious consumeth the
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="19">Learne
before thou speake, and vse phisicke, or euer thou be
sicke.</ab>
<ab n="20">Before
iudgement examine thy selfe, and in the day of visitation thou
shalt find mercy.<note> 1.Cor.11. 28.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Humble
thy selfe before thou be sicke, and in the time of sinnes shew
repentance.</ab>
<ab n="22">Let
nothing hinder thee to pay thy vowe in due time, and deferre not
vntill death to be iustified.</ab>
<ab n="23">Before
thou prayest, prepare thy selfe, and be not as one that tempteth
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">Thinke
vpon the wrath that shall be at the end; and the time of vengeance
when he shall turne away his face.<note> Chap.7. 17,36.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">When thou
hast enough remember the time of hunger, and when thou art rich
thinke vpon pouerty and need.</ab>
<ab n="26">From the
morning vntill the euening the time is changed, and all things are
soone done before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="27">A wise
man will feare in euery thing, and in the day of sinning he will
beware of offence: but a foole will not obserue time.<note> Prou. 28. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Euery man
of vnderstanding knoweth wisedome, and wil giue praise vnto him
that found her.</ab>
<ab n="29">They that
were of vnderstanding in sayings, became also wise themselues, and
powred forth exquisite parables.</ab>
<ab n="30">Goe not
after thy lustes, but refraine thy selfe from thine
appetites.<note> Rom.6.6. and 13.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">If thou
giuest thy soule the desires that please her, she will make thee a
laughing stocke to thine enemies, that maligne thee.</ab>
<ab n="32">Take not
pleasure in much good cheere, neither be tyed to the expence
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="33">Be not
made a begger by banquetting vpon borrowing, when thou hast nothing
in thy purse, for thou shalt lie in waite for thy owne life: and be
talked on.</ab>



</div>