<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-31-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 Of the desire of riches. 12 Of
moderation and excesse in eating, or drinking wine.</head>

<ab n="1">Watching
for riches, consumeth the flesh, and the care therof driueth away
sleepe.<note> 1.Tim.6. 9,10.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Watching
care will not let a man slumber, as a sore disease breaketh
sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="3">The rich
hath great labour in gathering riches together, and when he
resteth, he is filled with his delicates.</ab>
<ab n="4">The poore
laboureth in his poore estate, and when he leaueth off, hee is
still needie.</ab>
<ab n="5">He that
loueth gold shall not bee iustified, and he that followeth
corruption, shall haue enough thereof.</ab>
<ab n="6">Gold hath
bin the ruine of many, and their destruction was
present.<note> Chap.8.2</note></ab>
<ab n="7">It is a
stumbling block vnto them that sacrifice vnto it, and euery foole
shall be taken therewith.</ab>
<ab n="8">Blessed is
the rich that is found without blemish, and hath not gone after
gold:<note> Luke 6. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Who is he?
and we will call him blessed: for wonderfull things hath hee done
among his people.</ab>
<ab n="10">Who hath
bene tried thereby, and found perfit? then let him glory. Who might
offend and hath not offended, or done euill, and hath not done
it?</ab>
<ab n="11">His goods
shall be established, and the congregatiō shall declare his
almes.</ab>
<ab n="12">If thou
sit at a bountifull table, bee not greedy vpon it, and say not,
There is much meate on it.<note> Psa.111.9 pro.23.1. , Gr. open not thy throat vpon it.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Remember
that a wicked eye is an euill thing: and what is created more
wicked then an eye? therefore it weepeth vpon euery
occasion.<note> Or, before euery thing that is presented.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Stretch
not thine hand whithersoeuer it looketh, and thrust it not with him
into the dish.</ab>
<ab n="15">Iudge of
thy neighbour by thy selfe: and be discreet in euery point.</ab>
<ab n="16">Eate as
it becommeth a man those things which are set before thee: and
deuoure not, lest thou be hated.</ab>
<ab n="17">Leaue off
first for maners sake, and be not vnsatiable, lest thou
offend.</ab>
<ab n="18">When thou
sittest among many, reach not thine hand out first of
all.<note> Chap. 37. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">A very
litle is sufficient for a man well nurtured, and he fetcheth not
his wind short vpon his bed.<note> Or, &amp; lieth not pussing and blowing.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Sound
sleepe commeth of moderate eating: he riseth early, and his wits
are with him, but the paine of watching and choller, and pangs of
the bellie are with an vnsatiable man.</ab>
<ab n="21">And if
thou hast bin forced to eate, arise, goe forth, vomit, and thou
shalt haue rest.</ab>
<ab n="22">My sonne,
heare me, and despise me not, and at the last thou shalt finde as I
told thee: in all thy workes bee quicke, so shall there no
sickenesse come vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">Who so is
liberall of his meat, men shall speake well of him, and the report
of his good housekeeping will be beleeued.<note> Prou.22. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But
against him that is a niggard of his meate, the whole citie shall
murmure; and the testimonies of his niggardnesse shall not be
doubted of.</ab>
<ab n="25">Shew not
thy valiantnesse in wine, for wine hath destroyed many.<note> Isai.5.22. iudet.13.8</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The
furnace prooueth the edge by dipping: so doth wine the hearts of
the proud by drunkennesse.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wine is
as good as life to a man if it be drunke moderatly: what life is
then to a man that is without wine? for it was made to make men
glad.</ab>
<ab n="28">Wine
measurably drunke, and in season, bringeth gladnesse of the heart
and cheerefulnesse of the minde.</ab>
<ab n="29">But wine
drunken with excesse, maketh bitternesse of the minde, with
brawling and quarreling.</ab>
<ab n="30">Drunkennesse
increaseth the rage of a foole till he offend, it diminisheth
strength, and maketh wounds.</ab>
<ab n="31">Rebuke
not thy neighbour at the wine, and despise him not in his mirth:
giue him no despitefull words, and presse not vpon him with vrging
him (to drinke.)</ab>



</div>