<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-31-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 The safety of him that feareth the
Lord. 2 The wise and the foolish. 7 Times and seasons are of God.
10 Men are in his hands, as clay in the hands of the potter. 18
Cheefely regard thy selfe. 24 Of seruants.</head>

<ab n="1">There
shall no euill happen vnto him that feareth the Lord, but in
temptation euen againe he will deliuer him.</ab>
<ab n="2">A wise man
hateth not the Law, but he that is an hypocrite therein, is as a
ship in a storme.</ab>
<ab n="3">A man of
vnderstanding trusteth in the Law, and the Law is faithfull vnto
him, as an oracle.<note> Or, as the asking of Vrim.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Prepare
what to say, and so thou shalt be heard, and binde vp instruction,
and then make answere.</ab>
<ab n="5">The heart
of the foolish is like a cartwheele: and his thoughts are like a
rolling axeltree.<note> Greeke, bowels. , Chap. 21. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">A stallion
horse is as a mocking friend, hee neigheth vnder euery one that
sitteth vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Why doth
one day excell another? when as all the light of euery day in the
yeere is of the Sunne.</ab>
<ab n="8">By the
knowledge of the Lord they were distinguished: and he altered
seasons and feasts.</ab>
<ab n="9">Some of
them hath hee made high dayes, and hallowed them, and some of them
hath hee made ordinary dayes.<note> Or, ordained for the number of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And all
men are from the ground, and Adam was created of earth.<note> Gen. 1. 27. and 2.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">In much
knowledge the Lord hath diuided them, and made their wayes
diuers.</ab>
<ab n="12">Some of
them hath hee blessed, and exalted, and some of them hath hee
sanctified, and set neere himselfe: but some of them hath hee
cursed, and brought low, and turned out of their
places.<note> Or, standings.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">As the
clay is in the potters hand to fashion it at his pleasure: so man
is in the hand of him that made him, to render to them as liketh
him best.<note> Esay 45.9. rom.9.20, 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Good is
set against euill, and life against death: so is the godly against
the sinner, and the sinner against the godly.</ab>
<ab n="15">So looke
vpon all the workes of the most High, and there are two and two,
one against another.</ab>
<ab n="16">I awaked
vp last of all, as one that gathereth after the grape-gatherers: by
the blessing of the Lord I profited, and filled my wine-presse,
like a gatherer of grapes.<note> Or, gleaneth.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Consider
that I laboured not for my selfe onely, but for all them that seeke
learning;<note> Chap. 24. 39.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Heare me,
O ye great men of the people, and hearken with your eares ye rulers
of the Congregation:</ab>
<ab n="19">Giue not
thy sonne, and wife, thy brother and friend power ouer thee while
thou liuest, and giue not thy goods to another, lest it repent
thee: and thou intreat for the same againe.</ab>
<ab n="20">As long
as thou liuest and hast breath in thee, giue not thy selfe ouer to
any.<note> Or, sell not.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For
better it is that thy children should seeke to thee, then that thou
shouldst stand to their courtesie.<note> Or, looke to their hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">In all
thy workes keepe to thy selfe the preheminence, leaue not a staine
in thine honour.</ab>
<ab n="23">At the
time when thou shalt end thy dayes, and finish thy life, distribute
thine inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="24">Fodder, a
wand, and burdens, are for the asse: and bread, correction, and
worke for a seruant.<note> Of seruants.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">If thou
set thy seruant to labour, thou shalt finde rest: but if thou let
him goe idle, he shall seeke libertie.</ab>
<ab n="26">A yoke
and a collar doe bow the necke: so are tortures and torments for an
euill seruant.</ab>
<ab n="27">Sende him
to labour that hee be not idle: for idlenesse teacheth much
euill.</ab>
<ab n="28">Set him
to worke, as is fit for him; if he be not obedient, put on more
heauy fetters.</ab>
<ab n="29">But be
not excessiue toward any, and without discretion doe
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="30">If thou
haue a seruant, let him bee vnto thee as thy selfe, because thou
hast bought him with a price.<note> Chap.7. 20. , Greeke, in blood.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">If thou
haue a seruant, intreate him as a brother: for thou hast neede of
him, as of thine owne soule: if thou intreate him euill, and he
runne from thee, which way wilt thou goe to seeke him?</ab>



</div>