<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 We may not despise the poore or
fatherlesse, 11 but seeke for Wisedome, 20 and not be ashamed of
some things, nor gainsay the trueth, 30 nor be as lyons in our
houses.</head>

<ab n="1">My sonne,
defraude not the poore of his liuing, and make not the needy eies
to waite long.</ab>
<ab n="2">Make not an
hungry soule sorrowfull, neither prouoke a man in his
distresse.</ab>
<ab n="3">Adde not
more trouble to an heart that is vexed, and deferre not to giue to
him that is in neede.</ab>
<ab n="4">Reiect not
the supplication of the afflicted, neither turne away thy face from
a poore man.</ab>
<ab n="5">Turne not
away thine eye from the needy, and giue him none occasion to curse
thee:<note> Or, him that asketh.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For if he
curse thee in the bitternesse of his soule, his prayer shall be
heard of him that made him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Get thy
selfe the loue of the congregation, and bow thy head to a great
man.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let it not
grieue thee to bowe downe thine eare to the poore, and giue him a
friendly answere with meekenesse.</ab>
<ab n="9">Deliuer him
that suffreth wrong, from the hand of the oppressour, and be not
faint hearted when thou sittest in iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="10">Be as a
father vnto the fatherlesse, and in stead of a husband vnto their
mother, so shalt thou be as the sonne of the most high, and he
shall loue thee more then thy mother doeth.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wisedome
exalteth her children, and layeth hold of them that seeke
her.</ab>
<ab n="12">He that
loueth her, loueth life, and they that seeke to her earely, shall
be filled with ioy.</ab>
<ab n="13">He that
holdeth her fast shall inherit glory, and wheresoeuer she entreth,
the Lord will blesse.</ab>
<ab n="14">They that
serue her shall minister to the Holy one, and them that loue her,
the Lord doth loue.<note> Or, in the sanctuary.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Who so
giueth eare vnto her, shall iudge the nations, and he that
attendeth vnto her, shall dwell securely.</ab>
<ab n="16">If a man
commit himselfe vnto her, he shall inherite her, and his generation
shall hold her in possession.</ab>
<ab n="17">For at the
first she will walke with him by crooked wayes, and bring feare and
dread vpon him, and torment him with her discipline, vntill she may
trust his soule, and try him by her Lawes.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then wil
she returne the straight way vnto him, and comfort him, and shew
him her secrets.</ab>
<ab n="19">But if he
goe wrong, she will forsake him, and giue him ouer to his owne
ruine.</ab>
<ab n="20">Obserue
the opportunitie, and beware of euill, and be not ashamed when it
concerneth thy soule.</ab>
<ab n="21">For there
is a shame that bringeth sinne, and there is a shame which is
glorie and grace.</ab>
<ab n="22">Accept no
person against thy soule, and let not the reuerence of any man
cause thee to fall:</ab>
<ab n="23">And
refraine not to speake, when there is occasion to doe good, and
hide not thy wisedome in her beautie.<note> Greeke, in time of sauing.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For by
speach wisedome shall be knowen, and learning by the word of the
tongue.</ab>
<ab n="25">In no wise
speake against the trueth, but be abashed of the errour of thine
ignorance.</ab>
<ab n="26">Bee not
ashamed to confesse thy sinnes, and force not the course of the
riuer.<note> Or, and striue not against the streame.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Make not
thy selfe an vnderling to a foolish man, neither accept the person
of the mighty.</ab>
<ab n="28">Striue for
the trueth vnto death, and the Lord shall fight for thee.</ab>
<ab n="29">Be not
hastie in thy tongue, and in thy deeds slacke and remisse.</ab>
<ab n="30">Bee not as
a Lion in thy house, nor franticke among thy seruants.</ab>
<ab n="31">Let not
thine hand bee stretched out to receiue, and shut when thou
shouldest repay.<note> Or, giue.</note></ab>



</div>