<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>2 Wisedome embraceth those that
feare God. 7 The wicked shall not get her. 11 We may not charge God
with our faults: 14 For he made, and left vs to our
selues.</head>

<ab n="1">He that
feareth the Lord will doe good, and he that hath the knowledge of
the Law shal obtaine her.</ab>
<ab n="2">And as a
mother shall she meet him, and receiue him as a wife maried of a
virgin.</ab>
<ab n="3">With the
bread of vnderstanding shall she feed him, and giue him the water
of wisedome to drinke.</ab>
<ab n="4">Hee shall
be stayed vpon her, and shall not be moued, and shall rely vpon
her, and shall not be confounded.</ab>
<ab n="5">Shee shall
exalt him aboue his neighbours, and in the midst of the
congregation shall she open his mouth.</ab>
<ab n="6">He shall
finde ioy, and a crowne of gladnesse, and she shall cause him to
inherit an euerlasting name.</ab>
<ab n="7">But
foolish men shall not attaine vnto her, and sinners shall not see
her.</ab>
<ab n="8">For she is
farre from pride, and men that are liers cannot remember
her.</ab>
<ab n="9">Praise is
not seemly in the mouth of a sinner, for it was not sent him of the
Lord:<note> Or, a parable. , Or, he was not sent of, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For
praise shalbe vttered in wisdome, and the Lord wil prosper
it.<note> Or, rather a parable.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Say not
thou, It is through the Lord, that I fell away, for thou oughtest
not to doe the things that he hateth.</ab>
<ab n="12">Say not
thou, He hath caused mee to erre, for hee hath no need of the
sinfull man.</ab>
<ab n="13">The Lord
hateth all abomination, and they that feare God loue it
not.</ab>
<ab n="14">Hee
himselfe made man from the beginning, and left him in the hand of
his counsell,<note> Gene.1. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">If thou
wilt, to keepe the Commandements, and to performe acceptable
faithfulnesse.</ab>
<ab n="16">He hath
set fire and water before thee: stretch forth thy hand vnto whether
thou wilt.</ab>
<ab n="17">Before
man is life and death, and whether him liketh shalbe giuen
him.<note> Iere.21.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For the
wisedome of the Lord is great, and he is mighty in power, and
beholdeth all things,</ab>
<ab n="19">And his
eyes are vpon them that feare him, &amp; hee knoweth euery worke of
man.<note> Psal.33. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Hee hath
commanded no man to do wickedly, neither hath he giuen any man
license to sinne.</ab>



</div>