<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The commodities of a wise ruler. 4
God setteth him vp. 7 The inconueniences of pride, iniustice, and
couetousnesse. 14 What God hath done to the proud. 19 Who shall be
honored, 29 And who not.</head>

<ab n="1">A wise
iudge will instruct his people, &amp; the gouernement of a prudent
man is well ordered.</ab>
<ab n="2">As the
iudge of the people is himselfe, so are his officers, and what
maner of man the ruler of the citie is, such are all they that
dwell therein.<note> Prou.29. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">An vnwise
king destroyeth his people, but through the prudence of them which
are in authoritie, the citie shalbe inhabited.</ab>
<ab n="4">The power
of the earth is in the hand of the Lord, and in due time hee will
set ouer it one that is profitable.</ab>
<ab n="5">In the
hand of God is the prosperitie of man: and vpon the person of the
scribe shall he lay his honour.<note> Or, face.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Beare not
hatred to thy neighbour for euery wrong, and do nothing at all by
iniurious practises.<note> Leuit. 19. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Pride is
hatefull before God, and man: and by both doeth one commit
iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Because of
vnrighteous dealings, iniuries, and riches got by deceit, the
kingdome is translated from one people to another.</ab>
<ab n="9">Why is
earth and ashes proude? There is not a more wicked thing, then a
couetous man: for such an one setteth his owne soule to sale,
because while he liueth, he casteth away his bowels.</ab>
<ab n="10">The
Phisition cutteth off a long disease, and he that is to day a King,
to morrow shall die.</ab>
<ab n="11">For when
a man is dead, hee shall inherite creeping things, beastes and
wormes.</ab>
<ab n="12">The
beginning of pride is, when one departeth from God, and his heart
is turned away from his maker.</ab>
<ab n="13">For pride
is the beginning of sinne, and hee that hath it, shall powre out
abomination: and therefore the Lord brought vpon them strange
calamities, and ouerthrew them vtterly.</ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord
hath cast downe the thrones of proud Princes, and set vp the meeke
in their stead.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Lord
hath plucked vp the rootes of the proud nations: and planted the
lowly in their place.</ab>
<ab n="16">The Lord
ouerthrew countreys of the heathen: and destroyed them to the
foundations of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">He tooke
some of them away, and destroyed them, and hath made their
memoriall to cease from the earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">Pride was
not made for men, nor furious anger for them that are borne of a
woman.</ab>
<ab n="19">They that
feare the Lord are a sure seed, and they that loue him, an
honourable plant: they that regard not the Law, are a dishonourable
seed, they that transgresse the commandements, are a deceiuable
seed.<note> Or, vnstable generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Among
brethren he that is chiefe is honourable, so are they that feare
the Lord in his eyes.</ab>
<ab n="21">The feare
of the Lord goeth before the obtayning of authoritie: but
roughnesse and pride, is the loosing thereof.<note> Or, principalitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Whether
hee bee rich, noble, or poore, their glorie is the feare of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">It is not
meet to despise the poore man that hath vnderstanding, neither is
it conuenient to magnifie a sinnefull man.</ab>
<ab n="24">Great
men, and Iudges, and Potentates shall bee honoured, yet is there
none of them greater then he that feareth the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">Unto the
seruant that is wise, shall they that are free doe seruice: and hee
that hath knowledge, will not grudge when he is
reformed.<note> Pro. 17.2. 2.Sam.12. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Be not
ouerwise in doing thy busines, and boast not thy selfe in the time
of thy distresse.</ab>
<ab n="27">Better is
he that laboureth and aboundeth in all things, then hee that
boasteth himselfe, and wanteth bread.<note> Pro.12.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">My sonne,
glorifie thy soule in meekenesse, and giue it honour according to
the dignitie thereof.</ab>
<ab n="29">Who wil
iustifie him that sinneth against his owne soule? and who will
honour him that dishonoureth his owne life?</ab>
<ab n="30">The poore
man is honoured for his skill, and the rich man is honoured for his
riches.</ab>
<ab n="31">Hee that
is honoured in pouertie, how much more in riches? And he that is
dishonourable in riches, how much more in pouertie?</ab>



</div>