<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>2 Wisdome doeth praise herselfe,
shew her beginning, 4 Her dwelling, 13 Her glory, 17 Her fruit, 26
Her increase, and perfection.</head>

<ab n="1">Wisedome
shall praise her selfe, and shall glory in the midst of her
people.<note> The praise of wisedome.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">In the
Congregation of the most high, shall she open her mouth, and
triumph before his power.</ab>
<ab n="3">I came out
of the mouth of the most High, and couered the earth as a
cloud.<note> Or, a miste.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I dwelt in
high places, and my throne is in a cloudy pillar.<note> Iob.22. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">I alone
compassed the circuit of heauen, and walked in the bottome of the
deepe.</ab>
<ab n="6">In the
waues of the sea, and in all the earth, and in euery people, and
nation, I got a possession.</ab>
<ab n="7">With all
these I sought rest: and in whose inheritance shall I
abide?</ab>
<ab n="8">So the
creatour of all things gaue mee a commandement, and hee that made
me, caused my tabernacle to rest: and said, Let thy dwelling be in
Iacob, and thine inheritance in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="9">Hee
created mee from the beginning before the world, and I shall neuer
faile.<note> Pro.8.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">In the
holy Tabernacle I serued before him: and so was I established in
Sion.<note> Exod.31. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Likewise
in the beloued citie he gaue mee rest, and in Ierusalem was my
power.<note> Psal. 132. 8. , Or, holy.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And I
tooke roote in an honourable people, euen in the portion of the
Lords inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="13">I was
exalted like a Cedar in Libanus, and as a Cypresse tree vpon the
mountaines of Hermon.</ab>
<ab n="14">I was
exalted like a palme tree in Engaddi, and as a rose-plant in
Iericho, as a faire oliue tree in a pleasant fielde, and grew vp as
a planetree by the water.<note> Or, Cades. , Or, in the water.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">I gaue a
sweete smell like cinamon, and aspalathus, and I yeelded a pleasant
odour like the best mirrhe, as Galbanum and Onix, and sweet Storax,
and as the sume of franckincense in the Tabernacle.<note> Exod.30. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">As the
Turpentine tree, I stretched out my branches, and my branches are
the branches of honour and grace.</ab>
<ab n="17">As the
Uine brought I foorth pleasant sauour, and my flowers are the fruit
of honour and riches.<note> Ioh. 15.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">I am the
mother of faire loue, and feare, and knowledge, and holy hope, I
therefore being eternall, am giuen to all my children which are
named of him.<note> Or, chosen.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Come vnto
me all ye that be desirous of mee, and fill your selues with my
fruits.</ab>
<ab n="20">For my
memorial is sweeter then hony, and mine inheritance then the hony
combe.<note> Psal.19. 10,11.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">They that
eate mee shall yet be hungry, and they that drinke me shall yet be
thirstie.</ab>
<ab n="22">He that
obeyeth me, shall neuer be confounded, and they that worke by me,
shall not doe amisse.</ab>
<ab n="23">All these
things are the booke of the Couenant of the most high God, euen the
Law which Moses commanded for an heritage vnto the Congregations of
Iacob.<note> Exod. 20. 1. and 24. 1. deut.4.1. and 29.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Faint not
to bee strong in the Lord; that he may confirme you, cleaue vnto
him: for the Lord Almightie is God alone, and besides him there is
no other Sauiour.</ab>
<ab n="25">He
filleth all things with his wisdome, as Physon, and as Tigris in
the time of the new fruits.<note> Gen.2.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He maketh
the vnderstanding to abound like Euphrates, and as Iorden in the
time of the haruest.<note> Iosh.3.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">He maketh
the doctrine of knowledge appeare as the light, and as Geon in the
time of vintage.</ab>
<ab n="28">The first
man knew her not perfectly: no more shall the last finde her
out.</ab>
<ab n="29">For her
thoughts are more then the Sea, and her counsels profounder then
the great deepe.</ab>
<ab n="30">I also
came out as a brooke from a riuer, and as a conduit into a
garden.<note> Or, draine or ditch.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">I said, I
will water my best garden, and will water abundantly my garden
bedde: and loe, my brooke became a riuer, and my riuer became a
sea.</ab>
<ab n="32">I will
yet make doctrine to shine as the morning, and will send forth her
light afarre off.</ab>
<ab n="33">I will
yet powre out doctrine as prophecie, and leaue it to all ages for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="34">Behold
that I haue not laboured for my selfe onely, but for all them that
seeke wisedome.<note> Chap. 33. 16.</note></ab>



</div>