<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Keepe not companie with the
proude, or a mightier then thy selfe. 15 Like will to like. 21 The
difference betweene the rich and the poore. 25 A mans heart will
change his countenance.</head>

<ab n="1">He that
toucheth pitch, shal be defiled therewith, and hee that hath
fellowship with a proude man, shall be like vnto him.<note> Deu.7.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Burthen
not thy selfe aboue thy power, while thou liuest, and haue no
fellowship with one that is mightier, and richer then thy selfe.
For how agree the kettle and the earthen pot together? for if the
one be smitten against the other, it shall be broken.<note> Gre. this shal smite against it, and be broken.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The rich
man hath done wrong, and yet he threatneth withall: the poore is
wronged, and he must intreat also.</ab>
<ab n="4">If thou be
for his profit, he will vse thee: but if thou haue nothing, he will
forsake thee.</ab>
<ab n="5">If thou
haue any thing, he will liue with thee, yea he will make thee bare,
and will not be sorie for it.</ab>
<ab n="6">If he haue
need of thee, hee will deceiue thee, and smile vpon thee, and put
thee in hope, he will speake thee faire, and say, What wantest
thou?</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee
will shame thee by his meates, vntill he haue drawen thee drie
twice or thrice, and at the last hee will laugh thee to scorne:
afterward when he seeth thee, he will forsake thee, and shake his
head at thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Beware
that thou bee not deceiued, and brought downe in thy
iolitie.<note> Or, by thy simplicitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">If thou be
inuited of a mighty man, withdraw thy selfe, and so much the more
will he inuite thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">Presse
thou not vpon him, lest thou be put backe, stand not farre off,
lest thou be forgotten.</ab>
<ab n="11">Affect
not to be made equall vnto him in talke, and beleeue not his many
words: for with much communication will he tempt thee, and smiling
vpon thee will get out thy secrets.<note> Or, forbeare not. , Or, but.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But
cruelly he will lay vp thy words, and will not spare to doe thee
hurt, and to put thee in prison.</ab>
<ab n="13">Obserue
and take good heed, for thou walkest in peril of thy ouerthrowing:
when thou hearest these things, awake in thy sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="14">Loue the
Lord all thy life, and call vpon him for thy saluation.</ab>
<ab n="15">Euery
beast loueth his like, and euery man loueth his neighbour.</ab>
<ab n="16">All flesh
consorteth according to kind, and a man will cleaue to his
like:</ab>
<ab n="17">What
fellowship hath the wolfe with the lambe? so the sinner with the
godly.</ab>
<ab n="18">What
agreement is there betweene the Hyena and a dogge? and what peace
betweene the rich and the poore?</ab>
<ab n="19">As the
wilde asse is the lyons pray in the wildernesse: so the rich eate
vp the poore.</ab>
<ab n="20">As the
proud hate humilitie: so doth the rich abhorre the poore.</ab>
<ab n="21">A rich
man beginning to fall, is held vp of his friends: but a poore man
being downe, is thrust also away by his friends.</ab>
<ab n="22">When a
rich man is fallen, he hath many helpers: he speaketh things not to
be spoken, and yet men iustifie him: the poore man slipt, and yet
they rebuked him too: he spake wisely, and could haue no
place.</ab>
<ab n="23">When a
rich man speaketh, euery man holdeth his tongue, and looke what hee
sayeth, they extoll it to the clouds: but if the poore man speake,
they say, What fellow is this? and if he stumble, they will helpe
to ouerthrowe him.</ab>
<ab n="24">Riches
are good vnto him that hath no sinne, and pouerty is euill in the
mouth of the vngodly.</ab>
<ab n="25">The heart
of a man changeth his countenance, whether it be for good or euill:
and a merry heart maketh a cheerefull countenance.</ab>
<ab n="26">A
cheerefull countenance is a token of a heart that is in prosperity,
and the finding out of parables, is a wearisome labour of the
minde.</ab>



</div>