<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 A prayer for the Church against
the enemies thereof. 18 A good heart and a froward. 21 Of a good
wife.</head>

<ab n="1">Haue
mercie vpon vs, O Lord God of all, and behold vs:</ab>
<ab n="2">And send
thy feare vpon all the nations that seeke not after thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">Lift vp
thy hand against the strange nations, and let them see thy
power.<note> Ier.10.25 , Or, vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">As thou
wast sanctified in vs before them: so be thou magnified among them
before vs.</ab>
<ab n="5">And let
them know thee, as we haue knowen thee, that there is no God, but
onely thou, O God.</ab>
<ab n="6">Shew new
signes, and make other strange wonders: glorifie thy hand and thy
right arme, that they may set forth thy wonderous workes.</ab>
<ab n="7">Raise vp
indignation, and powre out wrath: take away the aduersarie and
destroy the enemie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Make the
time short, remember the couenant, and let them declare thy
wonderfull works.<note> Gre, othe.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Let him
that escapeth, be consumed by the rage of the fire, and let them
perish that oppresse the people.</ab>
<ab n="10">Smite in
sunder the heads of the rulers of the heathen, that say, There is
none other but we.</ab>
<ab n="11">Gather
all the tribes of Iacob together, and inherit thou them, as from
the beginning.</ab>
<ab n="12">O Lord
haue mercie vpon the people, that is called by thy name, and vpon
Israel, whom thou hast named thy first borne.<note> Exo.4.22</note></ab>
<ab n="13">O bee
mercifull vnto Ierusalem thy holy citie, the place of thy
rest.</ab>
<ab n="14">Fill Sion
with thine vnspeakable oracles, and thy people with thy
glory.<note> Or, that it may magnifie thine oracles.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Giue
testimonie vnto those that thou hast possessed from the beginning,
and raise vp prophets that haue bin in thy name.<note> Or, prophecies.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Reward
them that wait for thee, and let thy prophets be found
faithfull.</ab>
<ab n="17">O Lord
heare the prayer of thy seruants, according to the blessing of
Aaron ouer thy people, that all they which dwel vpon the earth, may
know that thou art the Lord, the eternall God.<note> Or, suppliants. , Num.6. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The belly
deuoureth all meates, yet is one meat better then another.</ab>
<ab n="19">As the
palate tasteth diuers kinds of venison: so doth an heart of
vnderstanding false speeches.<note> Iob 34.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">A froward
heart causeth heauinesse: but a man of experience will recompense
him.</ab>
<ab n="21">A woman
will receiue euery man, yet is one daughter better then
another</ab>
<ab n="22">The
beautie of a woman cheareth the countenance, and a man loueth
nothing better.</ab>
<ab n="23">If there
be kindnesse, meekenes, and comfort in her tongue, then is not her
husband like other men.<note> Or, common.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">He that
getteth a wife, beginneth a possession, a helpe like vnto himselfe,
and a pillar of rest.<note> Or, to thriue.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Where no
hedge is, there the possession is spoiled: and he that hath no wife
will wander vp and downe mourning.</ab>
<ab n="26">Who will
trust a thiefe well appointed, that skippeth from citie to citie?
so [who will beleeue] a man that hath no house? and lodgeth
wheresoeuer the night taketh him?</ab>



</div>