<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_49" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-48-50.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIX.</head>
<head>1 The praise of Iosias, 4 Of Dauid
and Ezekias, 6 Of Ieremie, 8 Of Ezechiel, 11 Zorobabel, 12 Iesus
the sonne of Iosedec. 13 Of Nehemiah, Enoch, Seth, Sem, and
Adam.</head>

<ab n="1">The
remembrance of Iosias is like the composition of the perfume
þe is made by the arte of the Apothecarie: it is
sweete as hony in all mouthes, and as musicke at a banquet of
wine.<note> 2.King. 22 1. and 23.2. 2. chr.3.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He behaued
himselfe vprightly in the conuersion of the people, and tooke away
the abominations of iniquitie.<note> Or, prospered.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">He
directed his heart vnto the Lord, and in the time of the vngodly he
established the worship of God.<note> 2.Kin.23. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">All,
except Dauid and Ezechias, and Iosias, were defectiue: for they
forsooke the Law of the most High, (euen) the kings of Iudah
failed:</ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore
he gaue their power vnto others, &amp; their glory to a strange
nation.<note> Or, horne.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">They burnt
the chosen citie of the Sanctuarie, and made the streets desolate
according to the prophecie of Ieremias:<note> 2.King. 25.9. , Or, by the hand of Ieremie.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For they
entreated him euil, who neuerthelesse was a prophet sanctified in
his mothers wombe, that he might root out and afflict &amp;
destroy, and that he might build vp also and plant.<note> Ier.38.6. , Ier.1.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">It was
Ezechiel who sawe the glorious vision, which was shewed him vpon
the chariot of the Cherubims<note> Eze.1.3, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For he
made mention of the enemies vnder [the figure of] the raine, and
directed them that went right.<note> Eze.13. 11 and 38. 11, 16. &amp; 46.12 hag.2.24 ezr.3.2. , Or, did good.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And of
the twelue prophets let the memorial be blessed, and let their
bones flourish againe out of their place: for they comforted Iacob,
and deliuered them by assured hope.<note> Ezek. 13. 13. &amp; 38.22</note></ab>
<ab n="11">How shall
we magnifie Zorobabel? euen he was as a signet on the right
hand.<note> Zach.3.1. ezr.3.2 hag 1 12 and 2. 3</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So was
Iesus the sonne of Iosedec: who in their time builded the house,
and set vp an holy Temple to the Lord, which was prepared for
euerlasting glory.<note> Nehe.7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And among
the elect was Neemias whose renowme is great, who raised vp for vs,
the walles that were fallen, and set vp the gates &amp; the barres,
and raised vp our ruines againe.<note> Gen.5.24 heb.11.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But vpon
the earth was no man created like Enoch, for he was taken from the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="15">Neither
was there a man borne like vnto Ioseph, a gouernour of his
brethren, a stay of the people, whose bones were regarded of the
Lord.<note> Gen.41. 44. and 42. 6. &amp; 45.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Sem and
Seth were in great honour among men, and so was Adam aboue euery
liuing thing in the creation.<note> Gen.5.3. and 11.10.</note></ab>



</div>