<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_45" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-44-45.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-45-46.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLV.</head>
<head>1 The praise of Moses, 6 Of Aaron,
23 and of Phinees.</head>

<ab n="1">And he
brought out of him a mercifull man, which found fauour in the sight
of all flesh, euen Moses beloued of God and men, whose memoriall is
blessed:<note> Exo.11.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He made
him like to the glorious Saints, and magnified him, so that his
enemies stood in feare of him.</ab>
<ab n="3">By his
words he caused the wonders to cease, and he made him glorious in
the sight of kings, and gaue him a commaundement for his people,
and shewed him part of his glory.<note> Exod.6. 7,8,9.chap.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">He
sanctified him in his faithfulnesse, and meekenesse, and chose him
out of all men.<note> Num.12.3</note></ab>
<ab n="5">He made
him to heare his voyce, and brought him into the darke cloud, and
gaue him commandements before his face, euen the law of life and
knowledge, that hee might teach Iacob his Couenants, and Israel his
iudgments.<note> Exo.17.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He exalted
Aaron an holy man like vnto him, euen his brother, of the tribe of
Leui.<note> Exo.4.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">An
euerlasting couenant he made with him, and gaue him the priesthood
among the people, he beautified him with comely ornaments, and
clothed him with a robe of glory.<note> Gr. he blessed.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Hee put
vpon him perfect glory: and strengthened him with rich garments,
with breeches, with a long robe, and the Ephod:<note> Greeke, vessels or instruments.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And he
compassed him with pomegranates, and with many golden bels round
about, that as he went, there might be a sound, and a noise made
that might be heard in the Temple, for a memoriall to the children
of his people.<note> Exod. 28. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">With an
holy garment, with gold and blew silke, and purple the worke of the
embroiderer; with a brestplate of iudgement, and with Urim &amp;
Thummim.</ab>
<ab n="11">With
twisted scarlet, the worke of the cunning workeman, with precious
stones grauen like seales, and set in gold, the worke of the
Ieweller, with a writing engraued for a memoriall, after the number
of the tribes of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">He set a
crowne of gold vpon the miter, wherein was engraued holinesse an
ornament of honour, a costly worke, the desires of the eies goodly
&amp; beautiful.</ab>
<ab n="13">Before
him there were none such, neither did euer any stranger put them
on, but onely his children, and his childrens children
perpetually.</ab>
<ab n="14">Their
sacrifices shall be wholy consumed euery day twise
continually.</ab>
<ab n="15">Moises
consecrated him, and annointed him with holy oile, this was
appointed vnto him by an euerlasting couenant, and to his seed so
long as the heauens should remaine, that they should minister vnto
him, and execute the office of the priesthood, and blesse the
people in his name.</ab>
<ab n="16">He chose
him out of all men liuing to offer sacrifices to the Lord, incense
and a sweet sauour, for a memoriall, to make reconciliation for his
people.</ab>
<ab n="17">He gaue
vnto him his commandements, and authority in the statutes of
iudgements, that he should teach Iacob the testimonies, and informe
Israel in his lawes.<note> Deut. 17. 10. and 21. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Strangers
conspired together against him, and maligned him in the
wildernesse, euen the men that were of Dathans, and Abirons side,
and the congregation of Core with fury and wrath.<note> Num. 16. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">This the
Lord saw and it displeased him, and in his wrathfull indignation,
were they consumed: he did wonders vpon them, to consume them with
the fiery flame.</ab>
<ab n="20">But he
made Aaron more honourable, and gaue him an heritage, and diuided
vnto him the first fruits of the encrease, especially he prepared
bread in abundance:<note> Num. 17. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For they
eate of the sacrifices of the Lord, which he gaue vnto him and his
seed:</ab>
<ab n="22">Howbeit
in the land of the people he had no inheritance, neither had he any
portion among the people, for the Lord himselfe is his portion and
inheritance.<note> Deut. 12. 12. and 18. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The third
in glory is Phinees the sonne of Eleazar, because he had zeale in
the feare of the Lord, and stood vp with good courage of heart,
when the people were turned backe, and made reconciliation for
Israel.<note> Num 25. 12,13.1. mac.2.54.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Therfore
was there a couenant of peace made with him, that he should be the
cheefe of the sanctuary, and of his people, and that he, and his
posteritie should haue the dignitie of the Priesthood for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="25">According
to the couenant made with Dauid sonne of Iesse, of the tribe of
Iuda, that the inheritance of the king should be to his posterity
alone: so the inheritance of Aaron should also be vnto his
seed.</ab>
<ab n="26">God giue
you wisedome in your heart to iudge his people in righteousnesse,
that their good things be not abolished, and that their glory may
endure for euer.</ab>



</div>