<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 Of dreames. 13 The praise and
blessing of them that feare the Lord. 18 The offering of the
ancient, and praier of the poore innocent.</head>

<ab n="1">The hopes
of a man voyd of vnderstanding are vaine, and false: and dreames
lift vp fooles.<note> Of dreames.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Who so
regardeth dreames, is like him that catcheth at a shadow, and
followeth after the winde.<note> Or, hath his minde vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The vision
of dreames is the resemblance of one thing to another, euen as the
likenesse of a face to a face.<note> Prou.27. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Of an
vncleane thing, what can be cleansed? and from that thing which is
false, what trueth can come?<note> Iob 14.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Diuinations,
and soothsayings, and dreames are vaine: and the heart fancieth as
a womans heart in trauell.</ab>
<ab n="6">If they be
not sent from the most high in thy visitation, set not thy heart
vpon them.<note> Or, regard them not.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For
dreames haue deceiued many, and they haue failed that put their
trust in them.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Law
shall be found perfect without lies: and wisedome is perfection to
a faithfull mouth.</ab>
<ab n="9">A man that
hath trauailed knoweth many things: and hee that hath much
experience, wil declare wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="10">He that
hath no experience, knoweth little: but he that hath trauailed, is
full of prudence.</ab>
<ab n="11">When I
trauailed, I saw many things: and I vnderstand more, then I can
expresse.</ab>
<ab n="12">I was oft
times in danger of death, yet I was deliuered because of these
things.</ab>
<ab n="13">The
spirit of those that feare the Lord shall liue, for their hope is
in him that saueth them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Who so
feareth the Lord, shall not feare nor be afraid, for hee is his
hope.</ab>
<ab n="15">Blessed
is the soule of him that feareth the Lord: to whom doeth hee looke?
and who is his strength?</ab>
<ab n="16">For the
eyes of the Lord are vpon them that loue him, he is their mightie
protection, and strong stay, a defence from heat, and a couer from
the Sunne at noone, a preseruation from stumbling, and a helpe from
falling.<note> psal.33. 18. and 61. 1,2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">He
raiseth vp the soule, and lighteneth the eyes: hee giueth health,
life, and blessing.</ab>
<ab n="18">Hee that
sacrificeth of a thing wrongfully gotten, his offering is
ridiculous, and the giftes of vniust men are not
accepted.<note> Prou.21. 27. , Or, the mockeries.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The most
high is not pleased with the offerings of the wicked, neither is he
pacified for sinne by the multitude of sacrifices.<note> Pro. 15.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Who so
bringeth an offering of the goods of the poore, doeth as one that
killeth the sonne before his fathers eyes.</ab>
<ab n="21">The bread
of the needie, is their life: he that defraudeth him thereof, is a
man of blood.</ab>
<ab n="22">Hee that
taketh away his neighbours liuing, slayeth him: and hee that
defraudeth the labourer of his hire, is a bloodshedder.<note> Deut.24. 14,15. cha. 7.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">When one
buildeth, and another pulleth downe, what profite haue they then
but labour?</ab>
<ab n="24">When one
prayeth, and another curseth, whose voice will the Lorde
heare?</ab>
<ab n="25">He that
washeth himselfe after the touching of a dead body, if he touch it
againe, what auaileth his washing?<note> Num. 19. 11,12.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">So is it
with a man that fasteth for his sinnes, and goeth againe and doeth
the same: who will heare his prayer, or what doeth his humbling
profit him?</ab>



</div>