<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_47" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-46-47.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVII.</head>
<head>1 The praise of Nathan, 2 Of Dauid,
12 Of Solomon his glory, and infirmities. 23 Of his end and
punishment.</head>

<ab n="1">And after
him rose vp Nathan to prophesie in the time of Dauid.<note> 2.Sam.12. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">As is the
fat taken away from the peace offering, so was Dauid chosen out of
the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">Hee played
with Lions as with kids, and with beares as with lambs.<note> Or, he smote Lions. , 1.Sam.17. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Slew he
not a gyant when hee was yet but yong? and did he not take away
reproch from the people, when he lifted vp his hand with the stone
in the sling, and beat downe the boasting of Goliah?<note> 1.Sam.17. 49,50,51.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For he
called vpon the most high Lord, and he gaue him strength in his
right hand to slay that mighty warriour, and set vp the horne of
his people:</ab>
<ab n="6">So the
people honoured him with ten thousands, and praised him in the
blessings of the Lord, in that hee gaue him a crowne of
glory.<note> 1.Sam.18. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For hee
destroyed the enemies on euery side, and brought to nought the
Philistines his aduersaries, and brake their horne in sunder vnto
this day.<note> 2.Sam.5. 7. , Or, contemned.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">In all his
workes hee praised the holy one most High, with words of glory,
with his whole heart he sung songs, and loued him that made
him.</ab>
<ab n="9">He set
singers also before the Altar, that by their voyces they might make
sweet melody, and daily sing praises in their songs.<note> 1.Chr. 16. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">He
beautified their feasts, and set in order the solemne times, vntill
the ende, that they might praise his holy Name, and that the Temple
might sound from morning.<note> Or, perfectly.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord
tooke away his sinnes, and exalted his horne for euer: he gaue him
a couenant of kings, and a throne of glory in Israel.<note> 1.Sam.12. 13. , Or, of a kingdome.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">After him
rose vp a wise sonne, and for his sake he dwelt at large.</ab>
<ab n="13">Salomon
reigned in a peaceable time, and was honoured; for God made all
quiet round about him, that hee might build an house in his Name,
and prepare his Sanctuary for euer.<note> 1.King.4. 21,24.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">How wise
wast thou in thy youth, &amp; as a flood filled with
vnderstanding.<note> 1.King.4. 29,30.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thy soule
couered the whole earth, and thou filledst it with dark
parables.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thy name
went farre vnto the Ilands, and for thy peace thou wast
beloued.</ab>
<ab n="17">The
countreys marueiled at thee for thy Songs, and Prouerbs, and
Parables, and interpretations.<note> 1.King.4. 31,32.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">By the
Name of the Lord God, which is called the Lord God of Israel, thou
didst gather gold as tinne, and didst multiply siluer as
lead.<note> 1.Kin.10. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Thou
didst bow thy loines vnto women, and by thy body thou wast brought
into subiection.<note> 1.King. 11.1. , Or, in.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Thou dist
staine thy honour, and pollute thy seed, so that thou broughtest
wrath vpon thy children, and wast grieued for thy folly.</ab>
<ab n="21">So the
kingdome was diuided, and out of Ephraim ruled a rebellious
kingdome.<note> 1.Kin.12 15,16,17.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But the
Lord will neuer leaue off his mercy, neither shall any of his
workes perish, neither will hee abolish the posterity of his elect,
and the seed of him that loueth him he will not take away:
wherefore he gaue a remnant vnto Iacob, and out of him a roote vnto
Dauid.<note> 2 Sam.7.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Thus
rested Solomon with his fathers, and of his seede he left behinde
him Roboam, euen the foolishnesse of the people, and one that had
no vnderstanding; who turned away the people through his counsell:
there was also Ieroboam the sonne of Nabat, who caused Israel to
sinne, and shewed Ephraim the way of sinne:<note> 1.Kin.12. 10,11,13, 14. , 1.Kin.12. 28,30.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And their
sinnes were multiplied exceedingly, that they were driuen out of
the land.</ab>
<ab n="25">For they
sought out all wickednes, till the vengeance came vpon
them.</ab>



</div>