<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_48" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-48-50.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVIII.</head>
<head>1 The praise of Elias, 12 of
Elizeus, 17 and of Ezekias.</head>

<ab n="1">Then stood
vp Elias the Prophet as fire, and his word burnt like a
lampe.<note> 1.King. 17.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He brought
a sore famine vpon them, and by his zeale he diminished their
number.</ab>
<ab n="3">By the
word of the Lord he shut vp the heauen, and also three times
brought downe fire.<note> Or, made heauen to holde vp. , 1.Kin. 18. 38. 2.king. 1.10,12.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">O Elias,
how wast thou honoured in thy wondrous deedes! and who may glory
like vnto thee!</ab>
<ab n="5">Who didst
raise vp a dead man from death, &amp; his soule from the place of
the dead by the word of the most Hie.<note> 1.Kin.17. 21,22. , Or, graue.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Who
broughtest kings to destruction, and honourable men from their
bedde.<note> 2.Kings 1.16. , Or, seate.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Who
heardest the rebuke of the Lord in Sinai, and in Horeb the iudgment
of vengeance.<note> 1.Kings 19.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Who
anointed kings to take reuenge, &amp; Prophets to succeed after
him:<note> 1.Kin. 19. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Who wast
taken vp in a whirlewinde of fire, and in a charet of fierie
horses:<note> 2.King.2. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Who wast
ordained for reproofes in their times, to pacifie the wrath of the
Lordes iudgement before it brake foorth into fury, and to turne the
heart of the father vnto the sonne, and to restore the tribes of
Iacob.<note> Or, written of. , Mal.4.3. , Or, establish.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Blessed
are they that saw thee, and slept in loue, for we shal surely
liue.<note> Or, were adorned with loue.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Elias it
was, who was couered with a whirlewinde: and Elizeus was filled
with his spirit: whilest he liued he was not mooued [with the
presence] of any prince, neither could any bring him into
subiection.<note> 2.King.2. 11,15.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">No word
could ouercome him, &amp; after his death his body
prophecied.<note> Or, Nothing. , 2.King. 13.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">He did
wonders in his life, and at his death were his works
marueilous.</ab>
<ab n="15">For all
this the people repented not, neither departed they from their
sinnes, till they were spoiled and caried out of their land, and
were scattered through all the earth: yet there remained a small
people, and a ruler in the house of Dauid:<note> 2.Kin.18. 11,12.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Of whom,
some did that which was pleasing to God, and some multiplied
sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="17">Ezekias
fortified his citie, and brought in water into the midst thereof:
he digged the hard rocke with yron, and made welles for
waters.<note> 2.King. 18.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">In his
time Sennacherib came vp, and sent Rabsaces, and lift vp his hand
against Sion, &amp; boasted proudly.<note> 2.King. 18.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Then
trembled their hearts and handes, and they were in paine as women
in trauell.</ab>
<ab n="20">But they
called vpon the Lord which is mercifull, and stretched out their
hands towards him, and immediatly the holy One heard them out of
heauen, and deliuered them by the ministery of Esay.<note> Or, hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He smote
the hoste of the Assyrians, and his Angel destroyed
them.<note> 2.Kin. 19. 35. isa.37. 36. tob.1. 18. 1.mac. 7.41. 2.mac. 8.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For
Ezekias had done the thing that pleased the Lord, and was strong in
the wayes of Dauid his father, as Esay the Prophet, who was great
and faithfull in his vision, had commaunded him.</ab>
<ab n="23">In his
time the Sunne went backeward, and hee lengthened the kings
life.<note> 2.King. 20.10. isa. 38.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Hee sawe
by an excellent spirit what should come to passe at the last, and
hee comforted them that mourned in Sion.</ab>
<ab n="25">He shewed
what should come to passe for euer, and secret things or euer they
came.</ab>



</div>