<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 It is better to haue none then
many lewd children. 6 The wicked are not spared for their number.
12 Both the wrath and the mercy of the Lord are great. 17 The
wicked cannot be hid. 20 Gods workes are vnsearchable.</head>

<ab n="1">Desire not
a multitude of vnprofitable children, neither delight in vngodly
sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="2">Though
they multiply, reioyce not in them, except the feare of the Lord be
with them.</ab>
<ab n="3">Trust not
thou in their life, neither respect their multitude: for one that
is iust, is better then a thousand, and better it is to die without
children, then to haue them that are vngodly.</ab>
<ab n="4">For by one
that hath vnderstanding, shall the city be replenished, but the
kindred of the wicked, shall speedily become desolate.<note> Or, tribe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Many such
things haue I seene with mine eyes, and mine eare hath heard
greater things then these.</ab>
<ab n="6">In the
congregation of the vngodly, shall a fire be kindled, and in a
rebellious nation, wrath is set on fire.<note> Chap.21. 10. , Or, hath bene.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Hee was
not pacified towards the olde giants, who fell away in the strength
of their foolishnesse.<note> Gen.6.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Neither
spared he the place where Lot soiourned, but abhorred them for
their pride.<note> Gen.19. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Hee pitied
not the people of perdition, who were taken away in their
sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="10">Nor the
sixe hundreth thousand footmen, who were gathered together in the
hardnesse of their hearts.<note> Num.14. 15. and 16. 20. and 20. 51.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And if
there be one stiffe-necked among the people, it is marueile, if he
escape vnpunished; for mercy and wrath are with him, hee is mighty
to forgiue, and to powre out displeasure.<note> Chap.5.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">As his
mercy is great, so is his correction also: he iudgeth a man
according to his workes.</ab>
<ab n="13">The
sinner shall not escape with his spoiles, and the patience of the
godly shall not be frustrate.</ab>
<ab n="14">Make way
for euery worke of mercy: for euery man shall finde according to
his workes.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Lord
hardened Pharaoh, that hee should not know him, that his powerfull
workes might be knowen to the world.</ab>
<ab n="16">His mercy
is manifest to euery creature, and hee hath separated his light
from the darkenesse with an Adamant.<note> Or, strong partition.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Say not
thou, I will hide my selfe from the Lord: shall any remember me
from aboue? I shall not be remembred among so many people: for what
is my soule among such an infinite number of creatures?</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold,
the heauen, and the heauen of heauens, the deepe and the earth, and
all that therein is, shall be mooued when he shall
visit.<note> 1.King.8. 17. 2. chron. 6.18. 2.pet. 3.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The
mountaines also, and foundations of the earth shall bee shaken with
trembling, when the Lord looketh vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="20">No heart
can thinke vpon these things worthily: and who is able to conceiue
his wayes?</ab>
<ab n="21">It is a
tempest, which no man can see: for the most part of his workes are
hidde.</ab>
<ab n="22">Who can
declare the workes of his iustice? or who can endure them? for his
Couenant is afarre off, and the triall of all things is in the
ende.</ab>
<ab n="23">He that
wanteth vnderstanding, will thinke vpon vaine things: and a foolish
man erring, imagineth follies.</ab>
<ab n="24">My sonne,
hearken vnto mee, and learne knowledge, and marke my words with thy
heart.</ab>
<ab n="25">I will
shewe foorth doctrine in weight, and declare his knowledge
exactly.</ab>
<ab n="26">The works
of the Lord are done in iudgement from the beginning: and from the
time he made them, hee disposed the parts thereof.</ab>
<ab n="27">Hee
garnished his workes for euer, and in his hand are the chiefe of
them vnto all generations: they neither labour, nor are weary, nor
cease from their workes.<note> Or, beginnings.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">None of
them hindreth another, and they shall neuer disobey his
word.</ab>
<ab n="29">After
this, the Lord looked vpon the earth, and filled it with his
blessings.</ab>
<ab n="30">With all
maner of liuing things hath hee couered the face thereof, and they
shall returne into it againe.</ab>



</div>