<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-12-12-Song-of-Solomon.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The Creator is to be remembred in
due time. 8 The Preachers care to edifie. 13 The feare of God is
the chiefe Antidote of vanitie.</head>


<fw>Repent betime.</fw>
<ab n="1">Remember now
thy Creatour in the dayes of thy youth, while the euil daies come
not, nor the yeeres drawe nigh, when thou shalt say, I haue no
pleasure in them:<note> Prou.22.6</note></ab>
<ab n="2">While the
Sunne, or the light, or the moone, or the starres be not darkened,
nor the cloudes returne after the raine:</ab>
<ab n="3">In the day
when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men
shall bowe themselues, and the grinders cease, because they are
fewe, and those that looke out of the windowes be
darkened:<note> Or, the grinders faile, because they grind litle.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the
doores shal be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding
is low, and he shall rise vp at the voice of the bird, and all the
daughters of musicke shall be brought low.</ab>
<ab n="5">Also when
they shalbe afraid of that which is high, and feares shall bee in
the way, and the Almond tree shall flourish, and the grashopper
shall be a burden, and desire shall faile: because man goeth to his
long home, and the mourners goe about the streets:</ab>

<fw>The end of all.</fw>
<ab n="6">Or euer the
siluer corde be loosed, or the golden bowle be broken, or the
pitcher be broken at the fountaine, or the wheele broken at the
cisterne.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then shall
the dust returne to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall
returne vnto God who gaue it.<note> Gen.3.19</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶
Uanitie of vanities (saith the preacher) all is
vanitie.<note> Chap.1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And moreouer
because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people
knowledge, yea he gaue good heed, and sought out, and set in order
many prouerbes.<note> Or, the more wise the Preacher was, &amp;c. , 1.King.4. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The
preacher sought to finde out acceptable words, and that which was
written was vpright, euen wordes of trueth.<note> Heb. words of delight.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The wordes
of the wise are as goads, and as nailes fastened by the masters of
assemblies, which are giuen from one shepheard.</ab>
<ab n="12">And
further, by these, my sonne, be admonished: of making many bookes
there is no end, and much studie is a wearinesse of the
flesh.<note> Or, reading.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Let
vs heare the conclusion of the whole matter: Feare God, and keepe
his commandements, for this is the whole duetie of man.<note> Or, the end of the matter, euen all that hath bene heard, is.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For God
shal bring euery worke into iudgement, with euer secret thing,
whether it bee good, or whether it bee euill.<note> Rom.2.16 and 14.10. 1.cor.5.10.</note></ab>



</div>