<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Vanitie is encreased vnto men by
oppression, 4 By enuie, 5 By idlenesse, 7 By couetousnesse, 9 By
solitarinesse, 13 By wilfulnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">So I
returned, and considered all the oppressions that are done vnder
the sunne; &amp; behold the teares of such as were oppressed, and
they had no comforter: and on the side of their oppressours there
was power, but they had no comforter.<note> Chap.5.7. &amp;c. , Heb. hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore I
praised the dead which are already dead, more then the liuing which
are yet aliue.<note> Iob 3.17. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Yea better is
he then both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not seene the
euill worke that is done vnder the Sunne.<note> Iob 3.11, 16,21.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Againe
I considered all trauaile, and euery right worke, that for this a
man is enuied of his neighbour: this is also vanitie, and vexation
of spirit.<note> Heb. all the rightnes of worke. , Heb. this is the enuie of a man from his neighbour.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The foole
foldeth his hands together, and eateth his owne flesh.<note> Prou.6.10 and 24.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Better is an
handfull with quietnesse, then both the hands full with trauell and
vexation of spirit.<note> Prou. 15. 16. and 16. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Then I
returned, and I saw vanitie vnder the Sunne.</ab>

<fw>Mans societie.</fw>
<ab n="8">There is one
alone, and there is not a second; yea, he hath neither childe nor
brother: yet is there no end of all his labour, neither is his eye
satisfied with riches, neither sayth hee, For whom doe I labour,
and bereaue my soule of good? this is also vanitie, yea it is a
sore trauell.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Two
are better then one; because they haue a good reward for their
labour.</ab>
<ab n="10">For if they
fall, the one will lift vp his fellow; but woe to him that is
alone, when he falleth: for he hath not another to helpe him
vp.</ab>
<ab n="11">Againe, if
two lye together, then they haue heate; but howe can one be warme
alone?</ab>
<ab n="12">And if one
preuaile against him, two shall withstand him; and a threefold
coard is not quickly broken.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶
Better is a poore and a wise child, then an old and foolish king
who will no more be admonished.<note> Heb. who knoweth not to be admonished.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For out of
prison hee commeth to raigne, whereas also he that is borne in his
kingdome, becommeth poore.</ab>
<ab n="15">I considered
all the liuing which walke vnder the sunne, with the second child
that shall stand vp in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="16">There is no
end of all the people, euen of all that haue beene before them:
they also that come after, shall not reioyce in him: surely this
also is vanitie, and vexation of spirit.</ab>



</div>