<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Of the slouthfull man, 3 and a
foolish daughter. 11 Weepe rather for fooles, then for the dead. 13
Meddle not with them. 16 The wise mans heart will not shrinke. 20
What will lose a friend.</head>

<ab n="1">A
slouthful man is compared to a filthy stone, and euery one will
hisse him out to his disgrace.</ab>
<ab n="2">A
slouthfull man is compared to the filth of a dunghill: euery man
that takes it vp, will shake his hand.</ab>
<ab n="3">An euill
nurtured sonne is the dishonour of his father that begate him: and
a [foolish] daughter is borne to his losse.</ab>
<ab n="4">A wise
daughter shall bring an inheritance to her husband: but shee that
liueth dishonestly, is her fathers heauinesse.<note> Prou.13. 22. , Or, shalbe the heire of her husband</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Shee that
is bold, dishonoureth both her father and her husband, but they
both shall despise her.</ab>
<ab n="6">A tale out
of season [is as] musick in mourning: but stripes and correction of
wisedome are neuer out of time.</ab>
<ab n="7">Who so
teacheth a foole, is as one that gleweth a potsheard together, and
as hee that waketh one from a sound sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hee that
telleth a tale to a foole, speaketh to one in a slumber: when hee
hath told his tale, he will say, What is the matter?</ab>
<ab n="9">If
children liue honestly, and haue wherwithall, they shall couer the
basenesse of their parents.<note> Or an art.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But
children being haughtie through disdaine, and want of nurture, doe
staine the nobilitie of their kinred.</ab>
<ab n="11">Weepe for
the dead, for hee hath lost the light: and weepe for the foole, for
he wanteth vnderstanding: make litle weeping for the dead, for hee
is at rest: but the life of the foole is worse then
death.<note> Chap.38. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Seuen
dayes doe men mourne for him that is dead; but for a foole, and an
vngodly man, all the dayes of his life.</ab>
<ab n="13">Talke not
much with a foole, and goe not to him that hath no vnderstanding,
beware of him lest thou haue trouble, and thou shalt neuer be
defiled with his fooleries: depart from him, and thou shalt find
rest, and neuer bee disquieted with madnesse.<note> Cha.12.12 , Or, when he shakes off his filth. , Or, wearied</note></ab>
<ab n="14">What is
heauier then lead? and what is the name thereof, but a
foole?</ab>
<ab n="15">Sand, and
salt, and a masse of yron is easier to beare then a man without
vnderstanding.<note> Pro.27.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">As timber
girt and bound together in a building, cannot be loosed with
shaking: so the heart that is stablished by aduised counsel, shal
feare at no time.</ab>
<ab n="17">A heart
setled vpon a thought of vnderstanding, is as a faire plaistering
on the wall of a gallerie.<note> Or, of a polished wall</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Pales set
on an high place will neuer stand against the wind: so a feareful
heart in the imagination of a foole, can not stand against any
feare.</ab>
<ab n="19">He that
pricketh the eye, wil make teares to fall: and he that pricketh the
heart, maketh it to shewe her knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="20">Who so
casteth a stone at the birds, frayeth them away, and he that
vpbraideth his friend, breaketh friendship.</ab>
<ab n="21">Though
thou drewest a sword at thy friend, yet despaire not, for there way
be a returning (to fauour.)</ab>
<ab n="22">If thou
hast opened thy mouth against thy friend, feare not, for there may
be a reconciliation: except for vpbraiding, or pride, or disclosing
of secrets, or a treacherous wound, for, for these things euery
friend will depart.</ab>
<ab n="23">Be
faithfull to thy neighbour in his pouertie, that thou mayest
reioyce in his prosperitie: abide stedfast vnto him in the time of
his trouble, that thou mayest bee heire with him in his heritage:
for a meane estate is not alwayes to be contemned, nor the rich
that is foolish, to be had in admiration.</ab>
<ab n="24">As the
vapour and smoke of a furnace goeth before the fire: so reuiling
before blood.</ab>
<ab n="25">I will
not be ashamed to defend a friend: neither will I hide my selfe
from him.</ab>
<ab n="26">And if
any euill happen vnto me by him, euery one that heareth it will
beware of him.</ab>
<ab n="27">Who shall
set a watch before my mouth, and a seale of wisedome vpon my
lippes, that I fall not suddenly by them, &amp; that my tongue
destroy me not?<note> Psal.141. 3.</note></ab>



</div>