<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 How God created and furnished man.
14 Auoid all sinne: 19 For God seeth all things. 25 Turne to him
while thou liuest.</head>

<ab n="1">The Lord
created man of the earth, and turned him into it
againe.<note> Gen. 1.27 and 5.2. wisd.2.23. and 7.1,6. 1.cor.11.7. col.3.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He gaue
them few dayes, and a short time, and power also ouer the things
therein.<note> Gen. 1.26. 1.cor.11.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">He endued
them with strength by themselues, and made them according to his
image,</ab>
<ab n="4">And put
the feare of man vpon all flesh, and gaue him dominion ouer beasts
and foules.<note> Or, of him.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">[They
receiued the vse of the fiue operations of the Lord, and in the
sixt place he imparted them vnderstanding, and in the seuenth,
speech, an interpreter of the cogitations thereof.]</ab>
<ab n="6">Counsell,
and a tongue, and eyes, eares, and a heart, gaue he them to
vnderstand.</ab>
<ab n="7">Withall,
hee filled them with the knowledge of vnderstanding, &amp; shewed
them good and euill.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hee set
his eye vpon their hearts, that he might shew them the greatnesse
of his workes.</ab>
<ab n="9">He gaue
them to glory in his marueilous actes for euer, that they might
declare his works with vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
elect shall praise his holy Name.</ab>
<ab n="11">Beside
this he gaue them knowledge, and the law of life for an
heritage.</ab>
<ab n="12">He made
an euerlasting couenant with them, and shewed them his
iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="13">Their
eyes saw the maiestie of his glory, and their eares heard his
glorious voyce.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he
said vnto them, Beware of all vnrighteousnes, and he gaue euery man
commandement concerning his neighbour,<note> Exod. 20. 16. &amp;. 22. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Their
wayes are euer before him, and shall not be hid from his
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="16">Euery man
from his youth is giuen to euil, neither could they make to
themselues fleshie hearts for stonie.</ab>
<ab n="17">For in
the diuision of the nations of the whole earth, he set a ruler ouer
euery people, but Israel is the Lords portion.<note> Deu.32.8. rom.13.1. , Deu.4.20 and 10.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Whom
being his first borne, hee nourisheth with discipline, and giuing
him the light of his loue, doth not forsake him.</ab>
<ab n="19">Therefore
all their workes are as the Sunne before him, and his eyes are
continually vpon their wayes.</ab>
<ab n="20">None of
their vnrighteous deeds are hid from him, but all their sinnes are
before the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="21">But the
Lord being gracious, and knowing his workemanship, neither left nor
forsooke them, but spared them.</ab>
<ab n="22">The almes
of a man is as a signet with him, and he will keep the good deedes
of man, as the apple of the eye, and giue repentance to his sonnes
and daughters.<note> Cha.29.13</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Afterward
he will rise vp and reward them, and render their recompense vpon
their heads.<note> Mat.25. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But vnto
them that repent, he granted them returne, and comforted those that
faile in patience.<note> Acts 3.19</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Returne
vnto the Lord, and forsake thy sinnes, make thy prayer before his
face, and offend lesse.<note> Iere.3. 12 , Or, lessen thy offence.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Turne
againe to the most High, and turne away from iniquitie: for he will
leade thee out of darkenesse into the light of health, and hate
thou abomination vehemently.<note> Or, illumination.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Who shall
praise the most High in the graue, in stead of them which liue and
giue thanks?<note> Psal.6.6. isa.38.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Thankesgiuing
perisheth from the dead, as from one that is not: the liuing and
sound in heart, shall praise the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">How great
is the louing kindnes of the Lord our God, and his compassion vnto
such as turne vnto him in holinesse?</ab>
<ab n="30">For all
things cannot bee in men, because þe sonne of man
is not immortal.</ab>
<ab n="31">What is
brighter then the Sun? yet the light thereof faileth: and flesh and
blood will imagine euill.<note> Iob 25. 4,5.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Hee
vieweth the power of the height of heauen, and all men are but
earth and ashes.</ab>



</div>