<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-31-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 Of his duty that is cheefe or
master in a feast. 14 Of the feare of God. 18 Of counsell. 20 Of a
ragged and a smooth way. 23 Trust not to any but to thy selfe and
to God.</head>

<ab n="1">If thou be
made the master (of the feast) lift not thy selfe vp, but bee among
them as one of the rest, take diligent care for them, and so sit
downe.</ab>
<ab n="2">And when
thou hast done all thy office, take thy place that thou mayest be
merry with them, and receiue a crowne for thy well ordering of the
feast.</ab>
<ab n="3">Speake
thou that art the elder, for it becometh thee, but with sound
iudgement, and hinder not musicke.</ab>
<ab n="4">Powre not
out words where there is a musitian, and shew not forth wisedome
out of time.<note> Eccle.3.7. chap.20. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">A consort
of musicke in a banket of wine, is as a signet of Carbuncle set in
gold.</ab>
<ab n="6">As a
signet of an Emeraud set in a worke of gold, so is the melodie of
musicke with pleasant wine.</ab>
<ab n="7">Speake
yong man, if there be need of thee: and yet scarsely when thou art
twise asked:</ab>
<ab n="8">Let thy
speach be short, comprehending much in few words, be as one that
knoweth, and yet holdeth his tongue.</ab>
<ab n="9">If thou be
among great men, make not thy selfe equall with them, and when
ancient men are in place, vse not many words.<note> Iob.33.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Before
the thunder goeth lightening: and before a shamefast man shall goe
fauour.</ab>
<ab n="11">Rise vp
betimes, and be not the last: but get thee home without
delay.</ab>
<ab n="12">There
take thy pastime, &amp; do what thou wilt: but sinne not by proud
speach</ab>
<ab n="13">And for
these things blesse him that made thee, and hath replenished thee
with his good things.</ab>
<ab n="14">Who so
feareth the Lord, will receiue his discipline, and they that seeke
him early, shall find fauour.</ab>
<ab n="15">He that
seeketh the law, shall be filled therewith: but the hypocrite will
be offended thereat.</ab>
<ab n="16">They that
feare the Lord shall find iudgement, and shall kindle iustice as a
light.</ab>
<ab n="17">A sinfull
man will not be reproued, but findeth an excuse according to his
will.</ab>
<ab n="18">A man of
counsell will be considerate, but a strange and proud man is not
daunted with feare, euen when of himselfe he hath done without
counsell.</ab>
<ab n="19">Doe
nothing without aduice, and when thou hast once done, repent
not.</ab>
<ab n="20">Goe not
in a way wherein thou maiest fall, and stumble not among the
stones.</ab>
<ab n="21">Be not
confident in a plaine way.</ab>
<ab n="22">And
beware of thine owne children.</ab>
<ab n="23">In euery
good worke trust thy owne soule: for this is the keeping of the
commandements.<note> Rom.14. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">He that
beleeueth in the Lord, taketh heed to the commandement, and he that
trusted in him, shall fare neuer the worse.<note> Or, shall not be hurt.</note></ab>



</div>