<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 We are aduised how to vse our
wiues. 3 What women to auoide. 10 And not to change an old friend.
13 Not to be familiar with men in authority, 14 But to knowe our
neighbours, 15 And to conuerse with wise men.</head>

<ab n="1">Be not
iealous ouer the wife of thy bosome, and teach her not an euil
lesson against thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="2">Giue not
thy soule vnto a woman, to set her foot vpon thy substance.</ab>
<ab n="3">Meete not
with an harlot, least thou fall into her snares.</ab>
<ab n="4">Use not
much the companie of a woman that is a singer, least thou be taken
with her attempts.<note> Or, playeth vpon instruments.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Gaze not on
a maide, that thou fall not by those things, that are pretious in
her.</ab>
<ab n="6">Giue not
thy soule vnto harlots, that thou loose not thine
inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="7">Looke not
round about thee, in the streets of the citie, neither wander thou
in the solitary places thereof.</ab>
<ab n="8">Turne away
thine eye from a beautifull woman, and looke not vpon anothers
beautie: for many haue beene deceiued by the beautie of a woman,
for heerewith loue is kindled as a fire.<note> Gen.34. 22. 2.sam. 11.2. iudg. 10.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Sit not at
all with another mans wife, nor sit downe with her in thine armes,
and spend not thy money with her at the wine, least thine heart
incline vnto her, and so thorough thy desire thou fall into
destruction.</ab>
<ab n="10">Forsake
not an old friend, for the new is not comparable to him: a new
friend is as new wine: when it is old, thou shalt drinke it with
pleasure.</ab>
<ab n="11">Enuy not
the glory of a sinner: for thou knowest not what shall be his
end.</ab>
<ab n="12">Delight
not in the thing that the vngodly haue pleasure in, but remember
they shall not goe vnpunished vnto their graue.</ab>
<ab n="13">Keepe thee
farre from the man that hath power to kill, so shalt thou not doubt
the feare of death: and if thou come vnto him, make no fault, least
he take away thy life presently: remember that thou goest in the
midst of snares, and that thou walkest vpon the battlements of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="14">As neere
as thou canst, ghesse at thy neighbour, and consult with the
wise.</ab>
<ab n="15">Let thy
talke be with the wise, and all thy communication in the law of the
most high.</ab>
<ab n="16">And let
iust men eate and drinke with thee, and let thy glorying be in the
feare of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">For the
hand of the artificer, the worke shall be commended: and the wise
ruler of the people, for his speech.</ab>
<ab n="18">A man of
an ill tongue is dangerous in his citie, and he that is rash in his
talke shall be hated.</ab>




</div>