<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 Sacrifices pleasing God. 14 The
prayer of the fatherlesse, of the widow, and of the humble in
spirit. 20 Acceptable mercy.</head>

<ab n="1">Hee that
keepeth the law, bringeth offerings enow: he that taketh heed to
the commandement, offereth a peace offering.<note> 1.Sam. 15. 22. iere.7. 3,5,6,7.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He that
requiteth a good turne, offereth fine floure: and he that giueth
almes, sacrificeth praise.</ab>
<ab n="3">To depart
from wickednesse is a thing pleasing to the Lord: and to forsake
vnrighteousnesse, is a propitiation.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou shalt
not appeare emptie before the Lord:<note> Exod. 23. 15. deut. 16.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For all
these things [are to bee done] because of the commandement.</ab>
<ab n="6">The
offering of the righteous maketh the Altar fat, and the sweete
sauour thereof is before the most high.</ab>
<ab n="7">The
sacrifice of a iust man is acceptable, and the memoriall thereof
shall neuer be forgotten.</ab>
<ab n="8">Giue the
Lord his honour with a good eye, and diminish not the first fruits
of thine hands.</ab>
<ab n="9">In all thy
gifts shew a cheerefull countenance, and dedicate thy tithes with
gladnesse.<note> 2.Cor.9.7. , Or, set apart.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Giue vnto
the most high, according as hee hath enriched thee, and as thou
hast gotten, giue with a cheerefull eye.<note> Tob.4.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For the
Lord recompenseth, and will giue thee seuen times as much.</ab>
<ab n="12">Doe not
thinke to corrupt with gifts, for such he will not receiue: and
trust not to vnrighteous sacrifices, for the Lord is iudge, and
with him is no respect of persons.<note> Or, diminish nothing of thy offerings. , Leuit. 22. 21,22. deu. 15.21. , Deut.10. 17. 2.chr.19 7. iob 34.19 wisd.6.7. acts 10.34. rom.2.11. gal.2.6. eph.6.9. colos.3.25. 1.pet.1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Hee will
not accept any person against a poore man: but will heare the
prayer of the oppressed.</ab>
<ab n="14">He will
not despise the supplication of the fatherlesse: nor the widowe
when she powreth out her complaint.</ab>
<ab n="15">Doeth not
the teares run downe the widowes cheeks? and is not her crie
against him that causeth them to fall?</ab>
<ab n="16">He that
serueth the Lord, shall be accepted with fauour, and his prayer
shall reach vnto the cloudes.</ab>
<ab n="17">The
prayer of the humble pierceth the clouds: and till it come nigh he
will not be comforted: and will not depart till the most High shall
beholde to iudge righteously, and execute iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the
Lord wil not be slacke, neither will the mightie be patient towards
them, till he hath smitten in sunder the loines of the vnmercifull,
and repaid vengeance to the heathen: till he haue taken away the
multitude of the proud, and broken the scepter of the
vnrighteous:<note> Or, cruell oppressours.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Till he
haue rendred to euery man according to his deeds, and to the works
of men according to their deuises, till he haue iudged the cause of
his people: and made them to reioyce in his mercie,</ab>
<ab n="20">Mercie is
seasonable in the time of affliction, as cloudes of raine in the
time of drought.<note> Gre. faire.</note></ab>



</div>