<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Obseruations of Wisedome and
folly. 16 Of Riot, 18 Slouthfulnesse, 19 and Money. 20 Mens
thoughts of Kings ought to bee reuerend.</head>


<fw>Folly esteemed.</fw>
<ab n="1">Dead flies
cause the oyntment of the Apothecarie to send foorth a stinking
sauour: so doeth a little folly him that is in reputation for
wisedome and honour.<note> Hebr. flies of death.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">A wise mans
heart is at his right hand: but a fooles heart at his left.</ab>
<ab n="3">Yea also
when hee that is a foole walketh by the way, his wisedome faileth
him, and hee saith to euery one that he is a foole.<note> Heb. his heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">If the
spirit of the ruler rise vp against thee, leaue not thy place; for
yeelding pacifieth great offences.</ab>
<ab n="5">There is an
euill which I haue seene vnder the Sunne, as an errour, which
proceedeth from the ruler.<note> Heb. from before.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Folly is set
in great dignitie; and the rich sit in lowe place.<note> Heb. in great heights.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">I haue seene
seruants vpon horses, and princes walking as seruants vpon the
earth.<note> Prou. 30. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He that
diggeth a pit, shall fall into it; and who so breaketh an hedge, a
serpent shall bite him.<note> Psal.7.16. prou.26.27</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Who so
remoueth stones, shall be hurt therewith: and hee that cleaueth
wood, shalbe endangered thereby.</ab>
<ab n="10">If the yron
be blunt, and he doe not whet the edge, then must he put to more
strength: but wisedome is profitable to direct.</ab>
<ab n="11">Surely the
serpent will bite without inchauntment, and a babbler is no
better.<note> Heb. the master of the tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The words
of a wise mans mouth are gratious: but the lips of a foole will
swallow vp himselfe.<note> Prou.10. 32. and 12. 13. , Heb. grace.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The
beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishnesse: and the end of
his talke is mischieuous madnesse.<note> Heb. his mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">A foole
also is full of words; a man cannot tell what shall be; and what
shall bee after him who can tell him?<note> Prou. 15. 2. , Heb. multiplieth words. , Chap.3. 21. and 6. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The labour
of the foolish wearyeth euery one of them; because hee knoweth not
how to goe to the citie.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Woe
to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eate in
the morning.<note> Isa.3.3,4.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Blessed art
thou, O land, when thy king is the sonne of nobles, and thy princes
eate in due season, for strength, and not for drunkennesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ By
much slouthfulnesse the building decayeth; and through idlenesse of
the hands the house droppeth through.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ A
feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh merry: but money
answereth all things.<note> Psal.104. 15. , Heb. maketh glad the life.</note></ab>

<fw>God iudgeth all.</fw>
<ab n="20">¶
Curse not the king, no not in thy thought, and curse not the rich
in thy bed-chamber: for a bird of the aire shall carry the voyce,
and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.<note> Exod.22. 28. , Or, conscience.</note></ab>



</div>