<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Vanities in Diuine seruice, 8 in
murmuring against oppression, 9 and in Riches. 18 Ioy in riches is
the gift of God.</head>

<ab n="1">Kepe thy
foote when thou goest to the house of God, and be more ready to
heare, then to giue the sacrifice of fooles: for they consider not
that they doe euill.<note> 1.Sam.15 22. psal.50. 8. prou.15. 8. &amp; 21.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Be not rash
with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be hasty to vtter any thing
before God: for God is in heauen, and thou vpon earth: therefore
let thy words be few.<note> Or, word. , Mat.6.7. prou.10.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For a dreame
commeth through the multitude of businesse, and a fooles voyce is
knowen by multitude of words.</ab>
<ab n="4">When thou
vowest a vow vnto God, deferre not to pay it: for he hath no
pleasure in fooles; pay that which thou hast vowed.<note> Deut.23. 21. , Psal.66. 13,14.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Better is it
that thou shouldest not vowe, then that thou shouldest vowe and not
pay.</ab>

<fw>How riches are miserable.</fw>
<ab n="6">Suffer not
thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sinne, neither say thou before the
Angel, that it was an errour: wherefore should God be angrie at thy
voyce, and destroy the worke of thine hands?</ab>
<ab n="7">For in the
multitude of dreames and many words, there are also diuers
vanities: but feare thou God.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ If
thou seest the oppression of the poore, and violent peruerting of
iudgement, and iustice in a prouince, maruell not at the matter:
for he that is higher then the highest, regardeth, and there be
higher then they.<note> Heb. at the will or purpose.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶
Moreouer the profit of the earth is for all: the king himselfe is
serued by the field.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee that
loueth siluer shall not be satisfied with siluer; nor he that
loueth abundance, with increase: this is also vanitie.</ab>
<ab n="11">When goods
increase, they are increased that eate them: and what good is there
to the owners thereof, sauing the beholding of them with their
eyes?</ab>
<ab n="12">The sleepe
of a labouring man is sweete, whether he eate little or much: but
the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="13">There is a
sore euill which I haue seene vnder the Sun, namely riches kept for
the owners therof to their hurt.</ab>
<ab n="14">But those
riches perish by euill trauell; and he begetteth a sonne, and there
is nothing in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="15">As he came
forth of his mothers wombe, naked shall he returne to goe as he
came, and shall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away
in his hand.<note> Iob.1. 21. 1.tim.6.7. psal. 49.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And this
also is a sore euill, that in all points as he came, so shall hee
goe: and what profit hath he that hath laboured for the
winde?<note> Chap.1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">All his
dayes also hee eateth in darkenesse, and he hath much sorrowe, and
wrath with his sicknesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶
Behold that which I haue seene: It is good and comely for one to
eate and to drinke, and to enioy the good of all his labour that he
taketh vnder the sunne, all the dayes of his life, which God giueth
him: for it is his portion.<note> Chap.2. 24 and 3. 12. , Heb. there is a good which is comely, &amp;c. , Heb. the number of the dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Euery man
also to whom God hath giuen riches and wealth, and hath giuen him
power to eate thereof, and to take his portion, and to reioyce in
his labour; this is the gift of God.</ab>
<ab n="20">For he shall
not much remember the dayes of his life: because God answereth him
in the ioy of his heart.<note> Or, though he giue not much, yet he remembred &amp;c.</note></ab>



</div>