<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The vanitie of riches without vse.
3 Of children, 6 and old age without riches. 9 The vanitie of sight
and wandring desires. 11 The conclusion of vanities.</head>

<ab n="1">There is an
euill which I haue seen vnder the Sun, and it is common among
men:</ab>
<ab n="2">A man to whom
God hath giuen riches, wealth and honour, so that he wanteth
nothing for his soule of all that he desireth, yet God giueth him
not power to eate thereof, but a stranger eateth it: This is
vanitie, and it is an euill disease.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ If a
man beget an hundred children, and liue many yeeres, so that the
dayes of his yeeres bee many: and his soule be not filled with
good, and also that he haue no buriall, I say, that an vntimely
birth is better then he.</ab>
<ab n="4">For he
commeth in with vanitie, and departeth in darkenesse, and his name
shall be couered with darkenesse.</ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer hee
hath not seene the Sunne, nor knowen any thing: this hath more rest
then the other.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Yea
though he liue a thousand yeeres twice told, yet hath he seene no
good: Doe not all goe to one place?</ab>
<ab n="7">All the
labour of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not
filled.<note> Heb. soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For what hath
the wise more then the foole? what hath the poore, that knoweth to
walke before the liuing?</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Better
is the sight of the eyes, then the wandering of the desire: this is
also vanitie and vexation of spirit.<note> Heb. then the walking of the soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">That which
hath bene, is named already, and it is knowen that it is man:
neither may he contend with him that is mightier then he.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶
Seeing there be many things that increase vanitie, what is man the
better?</ab>
<ab n="12">For who
knoweth what is good for man in this life, all the dayes of his
vaine life, which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man
what shal be after him vnder the sunne?<note> Heb. the number of the dayes of the life of his vanitie. , Psal. 144. 4.</note></ab>



</div>