<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-26-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 A good wife, 4 and a good
conscience doe glad men. 6 A wicked wife is a feareful thing. 13 Of
good and bad wiues. 28 Of three things that are grieuous. 29
Merchants and hucksters are not without sinne.</head>

<ab n="1">Blessed is
the man that hath a vertuous wife, for the number of his dayes
shall be double.</ab>
<ab n="2">A vertuous
woman reioyceth her husband, and he shall fulfill the yeeres of his
life in peace.</ab>
<ab n="3">A good
wife is a good portion, which shall be giuen in the portion of them
that feare the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">Whether a
man be rich or poore, if he haue a good heart towards the Lord, he
shall at all times reioyce with a cheerefull countenance.</ab>
<ab n="5">There bee
three things that mine heart feareth: and for the fourth I was sore
afraid: the slander of a citie, the gathering together of an vnruly
multitude, and a false accusation: all these are worse then
death.<note> Gr. an euill report.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But a
griefe of heart and sorrow, is a woman that is ielous ouer another
woman, and a scourge of the tongue which communicateth
withall.</ab>
<ab n="7">An euil
wife is a yoke shaken to and fro: he that hath hold of her, is as
though he held a scorpion.<note> Or, a yoke of oxen.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">A drunken
woman and a gadder abroad, causeth great anger, and shee will not
couer her owne shame.</ab>
<ab n="9">The
whordome of a woman may be knowen in her haughtie lookes, and eye
lids.</ab>
<ab n="10">If thy
daughter be shamelesse, keepe her in straitly: lest she abuse her
selfe through ouermuch libertie.<note> Chap. 44. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Watch
ouer an impudent eye: and marueile not, if shee trespasse against
thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Shee will
open her mouth as a thirstie traueiler, when he hath found a
fountaine: and drinke of euery water neere her: by euery hedge will
she sit downe, and open her quiuer against euery arrow.<note> Or stake.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The grace
of a wife delighteth her husband, and her discretion will fat his
bones.</ab>
<ab n="14">A silent
and louing woman is a gift of the Lord, and there is nothing so
much worth, as a mind well instructed.</ab>
<ab n="15">A
shamefast and faithfull woman is a double grace, and her continent
mind cannot be valued.</ab>
<ab n="16">As the
Sunne when it ariseth in the high heauen: so is the beautie of a
good wife in the ordering of her house.<note> Gre. in the highest places of the Lord. , Or, ornament.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">As the
cleare light is vpon the holy candlesticke: so is the beautie of
the face in ripe age.<note> Or, in constant age.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">As the
golden pillars are vpon the sockets of siluer: so are the faire
feete with a constant heart.<note> Or, comely. , Or, brest.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">My sonne,
keepe the flowre of thine age sound: and giue not thy strength to
strangers.</ab>
<ab n="20">When thou
hast gotten a fruitfull possession through all the field: sowe it
with thine owne seede, trusting in the goodnesse of thy
stocke.</ab>
<ab n="21">So thy
race which thou leauest shalbe magnified, hauing the confidence of
their good descent.</ab>
<ab n="22">An harlot
shall bee accounted as spittle: but a maried woman is a towre
against death to her husband.<note> Or, a swine.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">A wicked
woman is giuen as a portion to a wicked man: but a godly woman is
giuen to him that feareth the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">A
dishonest woman contemneth shame, but an honest woman will
reuerence her husband.</ab>
<ab n="25">A
shamelesse woman shalbe counted as a dog: but she that is shamefast
will feare the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="26">A woman
that honoureth her husband, shall bee iudged wise of all: but she
that dishonoureth him in her pride, shall be counted vngodly of
all.</ab>
<ab n="27">A loude
crying woman, and a scolde, shall be sought out to driue away the
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="28">There be
two things that grieue my heart: and the third maketh me angry: a
man of warre that suffereth pouerty, and men of vnderstanding that
are not set by: and one that returneth from righteousnesse to
sinne: the Lord prepareth such a one for the sword.</ab>
<ab n="29">A
merchant shall hardly keepe himselfe from doing wrong: and an
huckster shall not be freed from sinne.</ab>



</div>