<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 It is good to correct our
children, 7 and not to cocker them. 14 Health is better then
wealth. 22 Health and life are shortened by griefe.</head>

<ab n="1">Hee that
loueth his sonne, causeth him oft to feele the rodde, that hee may
haue ioy of him in the end.<note> Prou.13. 24. and 23. 13. , Of children.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He that
chastiseth his sonne, shall haue ioy in him, and shall reioyce of
him among his acquaintance.<note> Or, good by him. , Or, kinsefolke.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">He that
teacheth his sonne, grieueth the enemie: and before his friends he
shall reioyce of him.<note> Deut. 6.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Though his
father die, yet he is as though hee were not dead: for hee hath
left one behinde him that is like himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="5">While he
liued, he saw and reioyced in him: and when he died hee was not
sorrowfull.<note> Psal. 128.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He left
behinde him an auenger against his enemies, and one that shall
requite kindnesse to his friends.</ab>
<ab n="7">He that
maketh too much of his sonne, shall binde vp his wounds, and his
bowels wil be troubled at euery cry.</ab>
<ab n="8">An horse
not broken becommeth headstrong: and a childe left to himselfe will
be wilfull.</ab>
<ab n="9">Cocker thy
childe, and hee shall make thee afraid: play with him, and he will
bring thee to heauinesse.<note> Or, astonished.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Laugh not
with him, lest thou haue sorrow with him, and lest thou gnash thy
teeth in the end.</ab>
<ab n="11">Giue him
no liberty in his youth, and winke not at his follies.<note> Chap.7.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Bow downe
his necke while hee is young, and beate him on the sides while he
is a childe, lest hee waxe stubborne, and be disobedient vnto thee,
and so bring sorrow to thine heart.</ab>
<ab n="13">Chastise
thy sonne, and hold him to labour, lest his lewd behauiour be an
offence vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Better is
the poore being sound and strong of constitution, then a rich man
that is afflicted in his body.<note> Of health.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Health
and good state of body are aboue all gold, and a strong body aboue
infinite wealth.</ab>
<ab n="16">There is
no riches aboue a sound body, and no ioy aboue the ioy of the
heart.</ab>
<ab n="17">Death is
better then a bitter life, or continuall sickenesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">Delicates
powred vpon a mouth shut vp, are as messes of meat set vpon a
graue.</ab>
<ab n="19">What good
doth the offering vnto an idole? for neither can it eat nor smell:
so is he that is persecuted of the Lord.<note> Or, afflicted.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Hee seeth
with his eyes and groneth, as an Eunuch that embraceth a virgine,
and sigheth.</ab>
<ab n="21">Giue not
ouer thy mind to heauinesse, and afflict not thy selfe in thine
owne counsell.<note> Pro.12. 25 &amp; 15. 13. and 17. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The
gladnesse of the heart is the life of man, and the ioyfulnes of a
man prolongeth his dayes.<note> Or, exultation.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Loue
thine owne soule, and comfort thy heart, remoue sorrow far from
thee: for sorrow hath killed many, and there is no profit
therein.</ab>
<ab n="24">Enuie and
wrath shorten the life, and carefulnesse bringeth age before the
time.</ab>
<ab n="25">A
cherefull and good heart will haue a care of his meat and
diet.<note> Or, a noble.</note></ab>



</div>