<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Flee from sinne as from a serpent.
4 His oppression will vndoe the rich. 9 The ende of the vniust
shall be naught. 12 The differences betweene the foole and the
wise.</head>

<ab n="1">My sonne,
hast thou sinned? doe so no more, but aske pardon for thy former
sinnes.<note> Psal.41.4. luk. 15.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Flee from
sinne as from the face of a Serpent: for if thou commest too neere
it, it will bite thee: the teeth thereof, are as the teeth of a
lyon, slaying the soules of men.</ab>
<ab n="3">All
iniquitie is as a two edged sword, the wounds whereof cannot be
healed.</ab>
<ab n="4">To
terrifie and doe wrong, will waste riches: thus the house of proude
men shalbe made desolate.</ab>
<ab n="5">A prayer
out of a poore mans mouth reacheth to the eares of God, and his
iudgement commeth speedily.<note> Exod.3.9. and 22.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He that
hateth to be reprooued, is in the way of sinners: but hee that
feareth the Lord, will repent from his heart.<note> Gr. be conuerted.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">An
eloquent man is knowen farre and neere, but a man of vnderstanding
knoweth when he slippeth.</ab>
<ab n="8">He that
buildeth his house with other mens money, is like one that
gathereth himselfe stones for the tombe of his buriall.</ab>
<ab n="9">The
congregation of the wicked is like tow wrapped together: and the
end of them is a flame of fire to destroy them.<note> Chap. 16. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The way
of sinners is made plaine with stones, but at the ende thereof is
the pit of hell.</ab>
<ab n="11">Hee that
keepeth the Law of the Lord, getteth the vnderstanding thereof: and
the perfection of the feare of the Lord, is wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="12">He that
is not wise, will not be taught: but there is a wisedome which
multiplieth bitternesse.<note> Eccles.1. 18. , Or, wittie. , Or, subtiltie.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The
knowledge of a wise man shall abound like a flood: and his counsell
is like a pure fountaine of life.</ab>
<ab n="14">The inner
parts of a foole, are like a broken vessell, and he will holde no
knowledge as long as he liueth.<note> Cha.33.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">If a
skilfull man heare a wise word, hee will commend it, and adde vnto
it: but assoone as one of no vnderstanding heareth it, it
displeaseth him, and he casteth it behinde his backe.<note> Pro.9.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The
talking of a foole is like a burden in the way: but grace shall be
found in the lips of the wise.</ab>
<ab n="17">They
inquire at the mouth of the wise man in the congregation, and they
shall ponder his words in their heart.</ab>
<ab n="18">As is a
house that is destroyed, so is wisedome to a foole: and the
knowledge of the vnwise, is as talke without sense.<note> Or, not to be enquired after.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Doctrine
vnto fooles, is as fetters on the feete, and like manacles on the
right hand.</ab>
<ab n="20">A foole
lifteth vp his voyce with laughter, but a wise man doeth scarce
smile a litle.<note> Chap.19. 27,28.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Learning
is vnto a wise man, as an ornament of gold, and like a bracelet
vpon his right arme.</ab>
<ab n="22">A foolish
mans foote is soone in his [neighbours] house: but a man of
experience is ashamed of him.</ab>
<ab n="23">A foole
will peepe in at the doore into the house, but he that is well
nurtured, will stand without.</ab>
<ab n="24">It is the
rudenesse of a man to hearken at the doore: but a wise man will be
grieued with the disgrace.</ab>
<ab n="25">The lips
of talkers will bee telling such things as pertaine not vnto them:
but the words of such as haue vnderstanding, are weighed in the
ballance.</ab>
<ab n="26">The heart
of fooles is in their mouth, but the mouth of the wise is in their
heart.</ab>
<ab n="27">When the
vngodly curseth Satan, he curseth his owne soule.</ab>
<ab n="28">A
whisperer defileth his owne soule, and is hated wheresoeuer hee
dwelleth.<note> Chap.28. 13.</note></ab>



</div>