<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_42" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-41-43.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLII.</head>
<head>1 Whereof we should not be ashamed.
9 Be carefull of thy daughter. 12 Beware of a woman. 15 The workes
and greatnes of God.</head>

<ab n="1">Of these
things be not thou ashamed, and accept no person to sinne
thereby.</ab>
<ab n="2">Of the Law
of the most High, and his Couenant, and of iudgement to iustifie
the vngodly:</ab>
<ab n="3">Of
reckoning with thy partners, and traueilers: or of the gift of the
heritage of friends:<note> Or, of thy partners speech. , Or, companions. , Or, of the giuing.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Of
exactnesse of ballance, and waights: or of getting much or
little:</ab>
<ab n="5">And of
merchants indifferent selling, of much correction of children, and
to make the side of an euill seruant to bleed.<note> Or, without profit.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Sure
keeping is good where an euill wife is, and shut vp where many
hands are.</ab>
<ab n="7">Deliuer
all things in number and waight, and put al in writing that thou
giuest out, or receiuest in.<note> Or, dealest for.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Be not
ashamed to informe the vnwise and foolish, and the extreeme aged
that contendeth with those that are yong, thus shalt thou bee
truely learned and approued of all men liuing.<note> Or, rebuke. , Or, that is accused of fornication.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The father
waketh for the daughter when no man knoweth, and the care for her
taketh away sleepe; when shee is yong lest shee passe away the
flowre of her age, and being married, lest she should be
hated:</ab>
<ab n="10">In her
virginitie lest she should be defiled, and gotten with childe in
her fathers house; and hauing an husband, lest she should misbehaue
herselfe: and when shee is married, lest shee should be
barren.</ab>
<ab n="11">Keepe a
sure watch ouer a shamelesse daughter, lest shee make thee a
laughing stocke to thine enemies, and a by-word in the citie, and a
reproch among the people, and make thee ashamed before the
multitude.</ab>
<ab n="12">Behold
not euery bodies beauty, and sit not in the midst of
women.<note> Chap.25. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For from
garments commeth a moth, and from women wickednesse.<note> Gene.3.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Better is
the churlishnesse of a man, then a courteous woman, a woman I say,
which bringeth shame and reproch.<note> Or, wickednesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">I will
now remember the works of the Lord, and declare the things that I
haue seene: in the words of the Lord are his workes.</ab>
<ab n="16">The Sunne
that giueth light, looketh vpon all things: and the worke thereof
is full of the glory of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">The Lord
hath not giuen power to the Saints to declare all his marueilous
workes, which the Almightie Lord firmely setled, that whatsoeuer
is, might be established for his glory.</ab>
<ab n="18">He
seeketh out the deepe and the heart, and considereth their crafty
deuices: for the Lord knoweth all that may be knowen, and he
beholdeth the signes of the world.<note> Or, the highest.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Hee
declareth the things that are past, and for to come, and reueileth
the steps of hidden things.</ab>
<ab n="20">No
thought escapeth him, neither any word is hidden from
him.<note> Iob 41.4. esay 21. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Hee hath
garnished the excellent workes of his wisedome, and hee is from
euerlasting to euerlasting, vnto him may nothing be added, neither
can he be diminished, and he hath no need of any
counseller.</ab>
<ab n="22">O how
desireable are all his workes: and that a man may see euen to a
sparke.</ab>
<ab n="23">All these
things liue and remaine for euer, for all vses, and they are all
obedient.</ab>
<ab n="24">All
things are double one against another: and hee hath made nothing
vnperfit.</ab>
<ab n="25">One thing
establisheth the good of another: and who shalbe filled with
beholding his glory?</ab>



</div>