<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Wee must not presume of our wealth
and strength, 6 Nor of the mercie of God to sinne. 9 We must not be
double tongued, 12 Nor answere without knowledge.</head>

<ab n="1">Set not thy
heart vpon thy goods, and say not, I haue ynough for my
life.<note> Luke 12. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Folow not
thine owne minde, and thy strength, to walke in the wayes of thy
heart:</ab>
<ab n="3">And say
not, Who shall controll mee for my workes? for the Lord will surely
reuenge thy pride.</ab>
<ab n="4">Say not, I
haue sinned, and what harme hath happened vnto mee? for the Lord is
long suffering, he wil in no wise let thee goe.</ab>
<ab n="5">Concerning
propitiation, bee not without feare to adde sinne vnto
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="6">And say
not, His mercy is great, hee will be pacified for the multitude of
my sinnes: for mercy and wrath come from him, and his indignation
resteth vpon sinners.<note> Ecclus.21. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Make no
tarying to turne to the Lord, and put not off from day to day: for
suddenly shal the wrath of the Lord come foorth, and in thy
securitie thou shalt be destroyed, and perish in the day of
vengeance.<note> Chap.16. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Set not thy
heart vpon goods vniustly gotten: for they shall not profit thee in
the day of calamitie.<note> Pro.10.2. and 11.4. ezek.7.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Winnow not
with euery winde, and goe not into euery way: for so doth the
sinner that hath a double tongue.</ab>
<ab n="10">Be
stedfast in thy vnderstanding, and let thy word be the
same.</ab>
<ab n="11">Be swift
to heare, and let thy life be sincere, &amp; with patience giue
answere.<note> Iam.1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If thou
hast vnderstanding, answer thy neighbour, if not, lay thy hand vpon
thy mouth.</ab>
<ab n="13">Honour and
shame is in talke; and the tongue of man is his fall.</ab>
<ab n="14">Be not
called a whisperer, and lye not in wait with thy tongue: for a
foule shame is vpon the thiefe, and an euill condemnation vpon the
double tongue.</ab>
<ab n="15">Be not
ignorant of any thing, in a great matter or a small.</ab>



</div>