<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Whom we may not striue with, 8 nor
despise, 10 nor prouoke, 15 nor haue to doe with.</head>

<ab n="1">Striue not
with a mighty man, lest thou fall into his hands.</ab>
<ab n="2">Bee not at
variance with a rich man, lest he ouerweigh thee: for gold hath
destroyed many, and peruerted the hearts of kings.<note> Mat.5.25. chap.31.6</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Striue not
with a man that is full of tongue, and heape not wood vpon his
fire.<note> Or, of an euill tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Iest not
with a rude man, lest thy ancestours be disgraced.</ab>
<ab n="5">Reproch not
a man that turneth from sinne, but remember that we are all worthy
of punishment.<note> Gal.6.2. 1.cor.2.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Dishonour
not a man in his old age: for euen some of vs waxe old.<note> Leuit. 19. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Reioice not
ouer thy greatest enemie being dead, but remember that we die
all.</ab>
<ab n="8">Despise not
the discourse of the wise, but acquaint thy selfe with their
prouerbs; for of them thou shalt learne instruction, &amp; how to
serue great men with ease.</ab>
<ab n="9">Misse not
the discourse of the Elders: for they also learned of their
fathers, and of them thou shalt learne vnderstanding, and to giue
answere as need requireth.</ab>
<ab n="10">Kindle not
the coales of a sinner, lest thou be burnt with the flame of his
fire.</ab>
<ab n="11">Rise not
vp (in anger) at the presence of an iniurious person, least he lie
in waite to entrap thee in thy words.<note> Or, for thy mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Lend not
vnto him that is mightier then thy selfe; for if thou lendest him,
count it but lost.</ab>
<ab n="13">Be not
surety aboue thy power: for if thou be surety, take care to pay
it.</ab>
<ab n="14">Goe not to
law with a iudge, for they will iudge for him according to his
honour.<note> Or, opinion.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Trauaile
not by the way with a bold fellow, least he become grieuous vnto
thee: for he will doe according to his owne will, and thou shalt
perish with him through his folly.<note> Gene.4.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Striue not
with an angry man, and goe not with him into a solitary place: for
blood is as nothing in his sight, and where there is no helpe, he
will ouerthrow thee.<note> Prou.22. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Consult
not with a foole; for he cannot keepe counsell.</ab>
<ab n="18">Doe no
secret thing before a stranger, for thou knowest not what he will
bring forth.</ab>
<ab n="19">Open not
thine heart to euery man, least he requite thee with a shrewd
turne.</ab>



</div>