<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_51" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-50-51.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-51-51-Baruch.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. LI.</head>
<opener>A prayer of Jesus the sonne of Sirach</opener>
<ab n="1">I will
thanke thee, O Lord and king, and praise thee O God my Sauiour, I
doe giue praise vnto thy name:</ab>
<ab n="2">For thou
art my defeuder, and helper, and hast preserued my body from
destruction, and from the snare of the slanderous tongue, and from
the lippes that forge lies, and hast beene my helper against mine
aduersaries.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hast
deliuered me according to the multitude of thy mercies, and
greatnesse of thy name, from the teeth of them that were ready to
deuoure me, and out of the hands of such as sought after my life,
and from the manifold afflictions which I had:<note> Gre. the gnashing of the teeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">From the
choking of fire on euery side, and from the mids of the fire, which
I kindled not:</ab>
<ab n="5">From the
depth of the belly of hel, from an vncleane tongue, and from lying
words.</ab>
<ab n="6">By an
accusation to the king from an vnrighteous tongue, my soule drew
neere euen vnto death, my life was neere to the hell
beneath:</ab>
<ab n="7">They
compassed me on euery side, and there was no man to helpe me: I
looked for the succour of men, but there was none:</ab>
<ab n="8">Then
thought I vpon thy mercy, O Lord, and vpon thy acts of old, how
thou deliuerest such as waite for thee, and sauest them out of the
hands of the enemies:</ab>
<ab n="9">Then
lifted I vp my supplication from the earth, and prayed for
deliuerance from death.</ab>
<ab n="10">I called
vpon the Lord the father of my Lord, that he would not leaue me in
the dayes of my trouble, &amp; in the time of the proud when there
was no helpe.</ab>
<ab n="11">I will
praise thy Name continually, and will sing praise with
thankesgiuing, and so my prayer was heard:</ab>
<ab n="12">For thou
sauedst me from destruction, and deliuerest mee from the euill
time: therefore will I giue thankes and praise thee, and blesse thy
Name, O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">When I
was yet yong, or euer I went abroad, I desired wisedome openly in
my prayer.<note> Or, went astray.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I prayed
for her before the Temple, &amp; will seeke her out euen to the
end:</ab>
<ab n="15">Euen from
the flowre till the grape was ripe, hath my heart delighted in her,
my foot went the right way, from my youth vp sought I after
her.</ab>
<ab n="16">I bowed
downe mine eare a litle and receiued her, &amp; gate much
learning.</ab>
<ab n="17">I
profited therein, [therefore] will I ascribe the glory vnto him
that giueth me wisedome:</ab>
<ab n="18">For I
purposed to doe after her, and earnestly I followed that which is
good, so shall I not be confounded:</ab>
<ab n="19">My soule
hath wrestled with her, and in my doings I was exact, I stretched
foorth my hands to the heauen aboue, &amp; bewailed my ignorances
of her.</ab>
<ab n="20">I
directed my soule vnto her, and I found her in purenesse, I haue
had my heart ioyned with her from the beginning, therefore shall I
not bee forsaken.<note> Or, I got vnderstanding.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">My heart
was troubled in seeking her: therefore haue I gotten a good
possession.<note> Or, bowels.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The Lord
hath giuen mee a tongue for my reward, and I wil praise him
therewith.</ab>
<ab n="23">Draw
neere vnto me you vnlearned, and dwell in the house of
learning.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore
are you slow, and what say you of these things, seeing your soules
are very thirstie?</ab>
<ab n="25">I opened
my mouth, and said, buy her for your selues without
money.<note> Esay 55.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Put your
necke vnder the yoke, and let your soule receiue instruction, she
is hard at hand to finde.</ab>
<ab n="27">Behold
with your eies, how that I haue had but little labour, and haue
gotten vnto me much rest.<note> Chap. 6. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Get
learning with a great summe of money, and get much gold by
her.</ab>
<ab n="29">Let your
soule reioyce in his mercy, and be not ashamed of his
praise.</ab>
<ab n="30">Worke
your worke betimes, &amp; in his time he will giue you your
reward.</ab>



</div>