<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 A good conscience maketh men
happie. 5 The niggard doth good to none. 13 But doe thou good. 10
Men are happy that draw neere to wisedome.</head>

<ab n="1">Blessed is
the man that hath not slipt with his mouth, and is not pricked with
the multitude of sinnes.<note> Chap. 19. 16. and 25 8. iam.3.2. , Or, sorrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Blessed is
hee whose conscience hath not condemned him, and who is not fallen
from his hope in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">Riches are
not comely for a niggard: and what should an enuious man doe with
money?</ab>
<ab n="4">He that
gathereth by defrauding his owne soule, gathereth for others, that
shall spend his goods riotously.</ab>
<ab n="5">Hee that
is euill to himselfe, to whom will he be good? he shall not take
pleasure in his goods.</ab>
<ab n="6">There is
none worse then he that enuieth himselfe; and this is a recompence
of his wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="7">And if he
doth good, he doth it vnwillingly, and at the last he will declare
his wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">The
enuious man hath a wicked eye, he turneth away his face and
despiseth men.</ab>
<ab n="9">A couetous
mans eye is not satisfied with his portion, and the iniquity of the
wicked dryeth vp his soule.<note> Prou.17. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">A wicked
eye enuieth [his] bread, and he is a niggard at his table.</ab>
<ab n="11">My sonne,
according to thy habilitie doe good to thy selfe, and giue the Lord
his due offering.</ab>
<ab n="12">Remember
that death will not be long in comming, and that the couenant of
the graue is not shewed vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">Doe good
vnto thy friend before thou die, and according to thy abilitie,
stretch out thy hand and giue to him.<note> Tobit.4.7. luc.14.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Defraud
not thy selfe of the good day, and let not the part of a good
desire ouerpasse thee.<note> Or, the feast day.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Shalt
thou not leaue thy trauailes vnto another? and thy labours to be
diuided by lot?</ab>
<ab n="16">Giue, and
take, and sanctifie thy soule, for there is no seeking of dainties
in the graue.</ab>
<ab n="17">All flesh
waxeth old as a garment: for the couenant from the beginning is;
thou shalt die the death.<note> Isa.40.5. iam.1.10. 1.pet.1.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">As of the
greene leaues on a thicke tree, some fall, and some grow; so is the
generation of flesh and blood, one commeth to an end, and another
is borne.</ab>
<ab n="19">Euery
worke rotteth and consumeth away, and the worker therof shal goe
withall.</ab>
<ab n="20">Blessed
is the man that doeth meditate good things in wisdome, and that
reasoneth of holy things by his vnderstanding.<note> Psal.1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He that
considereth her wayes in his heart, shall also haue vnderstanding
in her secrets.</ab>
<ab n="22">Goe after
her as one that traceth, and lie in wait in her wayes.</ab>
<ab n="23">Hee that
prieth in at her windowes, shal also hearken at her doores.</ab>
<ab n="24">Hee that
doeth lodge neere her house, shall also fasten a pin in her
walles.<note> Or, stake.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">He shall
pitch his tent nigh vnto her, and shall lodge in a lodging where
good things are.</ab>
<ab n="26">He shal
set his children vnder her shelter, and shall lodge vnder her
branches.</ab>
<ab n="27">By her he
shall be couered from heat, and in her glory shall he
dwell.</ab>



</div>