<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiastes_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiastes-Chapter-1-2-Ecclesiastes.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The Preacher sheweth that all
humane courses are vaine: 4 Because the creatures are restlesse in
their courses, 9 They bring foorth nothing newe, and all olde
things are forgotten, 12 And because he hath found it so in the
studies of wisedome.</head>

<ab n="1">The wordes of
the Preacher, the son of Dauid, King in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="2">Uanitie of
vanities, saith the Preacher, vanitie of vanities, all is
vanitie.<note> Chap.12.9 psal.144.4. psal.36.6. and 62.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">What profite
hath a man of all his labour which hee taketh vnder the
Sunne?<note> Cha.2.22. and 3.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">One
generation passeth away, and another generation commeth: but the
earth abideth for euer.<note> Psal.104.5 &amp; 119.90.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The Sunne
also ariseth, and the Sunne goeth downe, and hasteth to the place
where he arose.<note> Heb. panteth.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The winde
goeth toward the South, and turneth about vnto the North; it
whirleth about continually, and the winde returneth againe
according to his circuits.</ab>
<ab n="7">All the
riuers runne into the sea, yet the Sea is not full: vnto the place
from whence the riuers come, thither they returne
againe.<note> Psal. 104. 9, 10. iob 38. 10. , Heb. returne to goe.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">All things
are full of labour, man cannot vtter it: the eye is not satisfied
with seeing, nor the eare filled with hearing.</ab>
<ab n="9">The thing
that hath beene, it is that which shall be: and that which is done,
is that which shall be done; and there is no new thing vnder the
sunne.<note> Cha. 3. 15.</note></ab>

<fw>The vanitie of worldly things.</fw>
<ab n="10">Is there any
thing, whereof it may be sayd, See, this is new? it hath beene
already of olde time, which was before vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">There is no
remembrance of former things; neither shall there bee any
remembrance of things that are to come, with those that shall come
after.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ I the
Preacher was king ouer Israel in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="13">And I gaue
my heart to seeke and search out by wisedome, concerning all things
that are done vnder heauen: this sore trauell hath God giuen to the
sonnes of man, to be exercised therewith.<note> Or, to afflict them.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I haue seene
all the workes that are done vnder the Sunne, and behold, all is
vanitie, and vexation of spirit.</ab>
<ab n="15">That which
is crooked, cannot be made straight: and that which is wanting
cannot be numbred.<note> Cha.7.13. , Heb. defect.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I communed
with mine owne heart, saying, Loe, I am come to great estate, and
haue gotten more wisedome then all they that haue beene before me
in Ierusalem: yea my heart had great experience of wisedome &amp;
knowledge.<note> 1.King.4. 30. and 10. 7, 23. , Heb. had seene much.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And I gaue
my heart to know wisedome, and to know madnesse and folly: I
perceiued that this also is vexation of spirit.<note> Cha.2.12. and 7.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For in much
wisedome is much griefe: and hee that increaseth knowledge,
increaseth sorrow.</ab>



</div>