<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEcclesiasticus_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ecclesiasticus-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>2 Wine and women seduce wise men. 7
Say not all thou hearest. 17 Reproue thy friend without anger. 22
There is no wisedome in wickednesse.</head>

<ab n="1">A
labouring man that is giuen to drunkennesse shal not be rich, and
hee that contemneth small things shall fall by little &amp;
little.</ab>
<ab n="2">Wine and
women will make men of vnderstanding to fall away, and he that
cleaueth to harlots will become impudent.</ab>
<ab n="3">Mothes and
wormes shall haue him to heritage, and a bold man shall be taken
away.</ab>
<ab n="4">He that is
hasty to giue credit is light minded, and he that sinneth shall
offend against his owne soule.<note> Iosh.22. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Who so
taketh pleasure in wickednesse shall be condemned, but he that
resisteth pleasures, crowneth his life.</ab>
<ab n="6">He that
can rule his tongue shall liue without strife, and he that hateth
babbling, shall haue lesse euill.</ab>
<ab n="7">Rehearse
not vnto another that which is told vnto thee, and thou shalt fare
neuer the worse.</ab>
<ab n="8">Whether it
be to friend or foe, talk not of other mens liues, and if thou
canst without offence reueale them not.<note> Or, of friend or foe.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For he
heard and obserued thee, and when time commeth he will hate
thee.<note> Or, shewe his hatred.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">If thou
hast heard a word, let it die with thee, and be bold it will not
burst thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">A foole
trauaileth with a word, as a woman in labour of a child.</ab>
<ab n="12">As an
arrowe that sticketh in a mans thigh, so is a word within a fooles
belly.<note> Or, heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Admonish
a friend, it may be he hath not done it, and if he haue [done it]
that he doe it no more.<note> Leuit.19. 17. matth. 18.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Admonish
thy friend, it may be he hath not said it, and if he haue, that he
speake it not againe.<note> Or, reproue.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Admonish
a friend: for many times it is a slander, &amp; beleeue not euery
tale.</ab>
<ab n="16">There is
one that slippeth in his speach, but not from his heart, and who is
he that hath not offended with his tongue?<note> Or, willingly. , Iam.3. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Admonish
thy neighbour before thou threaten him, and not being angry giue
place to the Law of the most high.<note> Or, reproue.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The feare
of the Lord is the first step to be accepted [of him,] and wisedome
obtaineth his loue.<note> Or, of receiuing him.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The
knowledge of the Commandements of the Lord, is the doctrine of
life, and they that do things that please him, shall receiue the
fruit of the tree of immortalitie.</ab>
<ab n="20">The feare
of the Lord is all wisedome, and in all wisedome is the performance
of the Law, and the knowledge of his omnipotencie.</ab>
<ab n="21">If a
seruant say to his master, I will not doe as it pleaseth thee,
though afterward hee doe it, hee angereth him that nourisheth
him.</ab>
<ab n="22">The
knowledge of wickednes is not wisedome, neither at any time the
counsell of sinners, prudence.</ab>
<ab n="23">There is
a wickednesse, and the same an abomination, and there is a foole
wanting in wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="24">He that
hath smal vnderstanding and feareth God, is better then one that
hath much wisedome, and transgresseth the Law of the most
High.</ab>
<ab n="25">There is
an exquisite subtilty, and the same is vniust, and there is one
that turneth aside to make iudgement appeare: and there is a wise
man that iustifieth in iudgement.<note> Or, iudgeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">There is
a wicked man that hangeth downe his head sadly; but inwardly he is
full of deceit,<note> Or, in blacke.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Casting
downe his countenance, and making as if he heard not: where he is
not knowen, he will do thee a mischiefe before thou be
aware.</ab>
<ab n="28">And if
for want of power hee be hindered from sinning, yet when he findeth
opportunitie he wil doe euil.</ab>
<ab n="29">A man may
bee knowen by his looke, and one that hath vnderstanding, by his
countenance, when thou meetest him.</ab>
<ab n="30">A mans
attire, and excessiue laughter, and gate, shew what he is.</ab>



</div>