<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEphesians_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The duetie of children towards
their parents, 5 Of seruants towards their masters. 10 Our life is
a warfare, 12 Not onely against flesh and blood, but also spiritual
enemies. 13 The complete armor of a Christian, 18 and how it ought
to be vsed. 21 Tychicus is cōmended.</head>

<ab n="1">Children, obey
your parents in the Lord: for this is right.</ab>
<ab n="2">Honour thy
father and mother, (which is the first commandement with
promise,)</ab>
<ab n="3">That it may bee
well with thee, and thou maiest liue long on the earth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And yee fathers,
prouoke not your children to wrath: but bring them vp in the
nourture and admonition of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">Seruants, bee
obedient to them that are your masters according to the flesh, with
feare and trembling, in singlenesse of your heart, as vnto
Christ:</ab>
<ab n="6">Not with eye
seruice as men pleasers, but as the seruants of Christ, doing the
will of God from the heart:</ab>

<fw>The armour of Christians.</fw>
<ab n="7">With good will
doing seruice, as to the Lord, and not to men,</ab>
<ab n="8">Knowing that
whatsoeuer good thing any man doeth, the same shall he receiue of
the Lord, whether he be bond or free.</ab>
<ab n="9">And ye masters,
do the same things vnto them, forbearing threatning: knowing that
your master also is in heauen, neither is there respect of persons
with him.<note> Or, moderating. , Some reade, both your, and their master.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Finally, my
brethren, be strong in the Lord, &amp; in the power of his
might.</ab>
<ab n="11">Put on the
whole armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles
of the deuill.</ab>
<ab n="12">For wee wrestle
not against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against
powers, against the rulers of the darknes of this world, against
spirituall wickednes in high places.<note> Or, wicked spirits. , Or, heauenly.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Wherfore take
vnto you the whole armour of God, that yee may be able to withstand
in the euill day, and hauing done all, to stand.<note> Or, hauing ouercome all.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Stand
therefore, hauing your loynes girt about with trueth, and hauing on
the breast-plate of righteousnesse:</ab>
<ab n="15">And your feete
shod with the preparation of the Gospel of peace.</ab>

<fw>The armour of Christians.</fw>
<ab n="16">Aboue all,
taking the shielde of Faith, wherewith yee shall bee able to quench
all the fierie dartes of the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="17">And take the
helmet of saluation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word
of God:</ab>
<ab n="18">Praying alwayes
with all prayer and supplication in the spirit, and watching
thereunto with all perseuerance, and supplication for all
Saints,</ab>
<ab n="19">And for mee,
that vtterance may be giuen vnto me, that I may open my mouth
boldly, to make knowen the mysterie of the Gospel:</ab>
<ab n="20">For which I am
an ambassador in bonds, that therein I may speake boldly, as I
ought to speake.<note> Or, in a chaine. , Or, thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But that yee
also may know my affaires, and how I doe, Tychicus a beloued
brother, and faithfull minister in the Lord, shall make knowen to
you all things.</ab>
<ab n="22">Whom I haue
sent vnto you for the same purpose, that yee might know our
affaires, and that he might comfort your hearts.</ab>
<ab n="23">Peace be to the
brethren, and loue, with faith from God the Father, and the Lord
Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="24">Grace be with
all them that loue our Lord Iesus Christ in sinceritie. Written
from Rome vnto the Ephesians by Tychicus.<note> Or, with incorruption.</note></ab>



</div>