<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEphesians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>5 The hidden mysterie, 6 that the
Gentiles should be saued, 3 was made knowen to Paul by reuelation:
8 And to him was that grace giuen, that 9 he should preach it. 13
He desireth them not to faint for his tribulation, 14 and praieth,
19 that they may perceiue the great loue of Christ toward
them.</head>

<ab n="1">For this cause I
Paul, the prisoner of Iesus Christ for you Gentiles,</ab>
<ab n="2">If ye haue heard
of the dispensation of the grace of God, which is giuen me to
youward:</ab>
<ab n="3">How that by
reuelation hee made knowen vnto me the mysterie, (as I wrote afore
in few words,<note> Or, a little before.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Whereby when ye
reade, ye may vnderstand my knowledge in the mysterie of
Christ.)</ab>
<ab n="5">Which in other
ages was not made knowen vnto the sonnes of men, as it is now
reueiled vnto his holy Apostles and Prophets by the Spirit,</ab>
<ab n="6">That the
Gentiles should be fellow heires, and of the same body, and
partakers of his promise in Christ, by the Gospel:</ab>
<ab n="7">Whereof I was
made a Minister, according to the gift of the grace of God giuen
vnto mee, by the effectuall working of his power.</ab>
<ab n="8">Unto mee, who am
lesse then the least of all Saints, is this grace giuen, that I
should preach among the Gentiles the vnsearchable riches of
Christ,</ab>
<ab n="9">And to make all
men see, what is the fellowship of the mysterie, which from the
beginning of the world, hath bene hid in God, who created all
things by Iesus Christ:</ab>
<ab n="10">To the intent
that now vnto the principalities and powers in heauenly places,
might be knowen by the church, the manifold wisedome of
God,</ab>

<fw>Grace giuen to the Gentiles.</fw>
<ab n="11">According to
the eternall purpose which he purposed in Christ Iesus our
Lord:</ab>
<ab n="12">In whom we haue
boldnesse and accesse, with confidence, by the faith of
him.</ab>
<ab n="13">Wherefore I
desire that yee faint not at my tribulations for you, which is your
glory.</ab>
<ab n="14">For this cause
I bow my knees vnto the Father of our Lord Iesus Christ,</ab>
<ab n="15">Of whom the
whole family in heauen and earth is named,</ab>
<ab n="16">That he would
grant you according to the riches of his glory, to bee strengthened
with might, by his Spirit in the inner man,</ab>
<ab n="17">That Christ may
dwell in your hearts by faith, that yee being rooted and grounded
in loue,</ab>
<ab n="18">May be able to
comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and
depth, and height:</ab>
<ab n="19">And to know the
loue of Christ, which passeth knowledge, that yee might bee filled
with all the fulnesse of God.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now vnto him
that is able to do exceeding abundantly aboue all that wee aske or
thinke, according to the power that worketh in vs,</ab>
<ab n="21">Unto him be
glory in the Church by Christ Iesus, throughout all ages, world
without end. Amen.</ab>



</div>