<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEphesians_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 By comparing what we were by 3
nature, with what we are 5 by grace: 10 He declareth, that wee are
made for good workes; and 13 beeing brought neere by Christ, should
not liue as 11 Gentiles, and 12 forreiners in time past, but as 19
citizens with the Saints, and the family of God.</head>

<ab n="1">And you hath hee
quickned who were dead in trespasses, and sinnes,</ab>
<ab n="2">Wherein in time
past ye walked according to the course of this world, according to
the prince of the power of the aire, the spirit that now worketh in
the children of disobedience,</ab>

<fw>Christ our peace.</fw>
<ab n="3">Among whom also
we all had our conuersation in times past, in the lusts of our
flesh, fulfilling the desires of the flesh, and of the minde, and
were by nature the children of wrath, euen as others:<note> Gr. the wills.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But God who is
rich in mercie, for his great loue wherewith hee loued vs,</ab>
<ab n="5">Euen when wee
were dead in sinnes, hath quickned vs together with Christ, (by
grace ye are saued)</ab>
<ab n="6">And hath raised
vs vp together, and made vs sit together in heauenly places in
Christ Iesus:</ab>
<ab n="7">That in the ages
to come, hee might shew the exceeding riches of his grace, in his
kindenesse towards vs, through Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="8">For by grace are
ye saued, through faith, and that not of your selues: it is the
gift of God:</ab>
<ab n="9">Not of workes,
lest any man should boast.</ab>
<ab n="10">For wee are his
workemanship, created in Christ Iesus vnto good workes, which God
hath before ordeined, that we should walke in them.<note> Or, prepared.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore
remember that ye being in time passed Gentiles in the flesh, who
are called vncircumcision by that which is called the Circumcision
in the flesh made by hands,</ab>
<ab n="12">That at that
time yee were without Christ, being aliens from the common wealth
of Israel, and strangers from the couenants of promise, hauing no
hope, &amp; without God in the world.</ab>
<ab n="13">But now in
Christ Iesus, ye who sometimes were far off, are made nigh by the
blood of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="14">For hee is our
peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken downe the middle
wall of partition betweene vs:</ab>
<ab n="15">Hauing
abolished in his flesh the enmitie, euen the Lawe of Commandements
conteined in Ordinances, for to make in himselfe, of twaine, one
newe man, so making peace.</ab>
<ab n="16">And that he
might reconcile both vnto God in one body by the crosse, hauing
slaine the enmitie thereby,<note> Or, in himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And came, and
preached peace to you, which were afarre off, and to them that were
nigh.</ab>
<ab n="18">For through him
wee both haue an accesse by one Spirit vnto the Father.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now therefore
yee are no more strangers and forreiners; but fellow citizens with
the Saints, and of the houshold of God,</ab>

<fw>Grace giuen to the Gentiles.</fw>
<ab n="20">And are built
vpon the foundation of the Apostles and Prophets, Iesus Christ
himselfe being the chiefe corner stone,</ab>
<ab n="21">In whom all the
building fitly framed together, groweth vnto an holy Temple in the
Lord:</ab>
<ab n="22">In whom you
also are builded together for an habitation of God thorow the
Spirit.</ab>



</div>