<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEphesians_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-6-6-Ephesians.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 After the salutation, 3 and
thankesgiuing for the Ephesians, 4 he treateth of our Election, 6
and Adoption by grace, 11 which is the true and proper fountaine of
mans saluation. 13 And because the height of this mysterie cannot
easily be atteined vnto, 16 he praieth that they may come 18 to the
full knowledge, and 20 possession thereof in Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul an Apostle
of Iesus Christ by the will of God, to the Saincts which are at
Ephesus, and to the faithfull in Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="2">Grace be to you,
and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="3">Blessed be the
God and Father of our Lord Iesus Christ, who hath blessed vs with
all spirituall blessings in heauenly places in Christ:<note> Or, things</note></ab>
<ab n="4">According as he
hath chosen vs in him, before the foundation of the world, that wee
should bee holy, and without blame before him in loue:</ab>

<fw>The election of the Saints.</fw>
<ab n="5">Hauing
predestinated vs vnto the adoption of children by Iesus Christ to
himselfe, according to the good pleasure of his will:</ab>
<ab n="6">To the praise of
the glorie of his grace, wherein he hath made vs accepted in the
beloued:</ab>
<ab n="7">In whom wee haue
redemption through his blood, the forgiuenesse of sinnes, according
to the riches of his grace,</ab>
<ab n="8">Wherein hee hath
abounded toward vs in all wisedome and prudence:</ab>
<ab n="9">Hauing made
knowen vnto vs the mysterie of his will, according to his good
pleasure, which he had purposed in himselfe,</ab>
<ab n="10">That in the
dispensation of the fulnesse of times, he might gather together in
one all things in Christ, both which are in heauen, and which are
on earth, euen in him:<note> Gr. the heauens.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">In whom also we
haue obteined an inheritance, being predestinated according to the
purpose of him who worketh all things after the counsell of his
owne will:</ab>
<ab n="12">That we should
be to the praise of his glorie, who first trusted in
Christ.<note> Or, hoped.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">In whom ye also
trusted, after that ye heard the word of trueth, the Gospel of your
saluation: in whom also after that yee beleeued, yee were sealed
with that holy Spirit of promise,</ab>

<fw>Christs power.</fw>
<ab n="14">Which is the
earnest of our inheritance, vntill the redemption of the purchased
possession, vnto the praise of his glorie.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wherefore I
also, after I heard of your faith in the Lord Iesus, and loue vnto
all the Saints,</ab>
<ab n="16">Cease not to
giue thankes for you, making mention of you in my prayers,</ab>
<ab n="17">That the God of
our Lord Iesus Christ the Father of glorie, may giue vnto you the
Spirit of wisedome and reuelation in the knowledge of
him:<note> Or, for the acknowledgment.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The eyes of
your vnderstanding being inlightned: that yee may know what is the
hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glorie of his
inheritance in the Saints:</ab>
<ab n="19">And what is the
exceeding greatnesse of his power to vs-ward who beleeue, according
to the working of his mightie power:<note> Gr. of the might of his power.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Which he
wrought in Christ when he raised him from the dead, and set him at
his owne right hand in the heauenly places,</ab>
<ab n="21">Farre aboue all
principalitie, and power, and might, and dominion, and euery name
that is named, not onely in this world, but also in that which is
to come:</ab>
<ab n="22">And hath put
all things vnder his feete, and gaue him to be the head ouer all
things to the Church,</ab>
<ab n="23">Which is his
body, the fulnesse of him that filleth all in all.</ab>



</div>