<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEphesians_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 He exhorteth to vnitie, 7 and
declareth that God therefore giueth diuers 11 gifts vnto men, that
his Church might be. 13 edified, and 16 growen vp in Christ. 18 He
calleth them from the impuritie of the Gentiles. 24 To put on the
new man. 25 To cast of lying, and 29 corrupt
communication.</head>

<ab n="1">I therefore the
prisoner of the Lord, beseech you that yee walke worthy of the
vocation wherewith ye are called,<note> Or, in the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">With all
lowlinesse and meekenesse, with long suffering, forbearing one
another in loue.</ab>
<ab n="3">Endeuouring to
keepe the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</ab>
<ab n="4">There is one
body, and one spirit, euen as yee are called in one hope of your
calling.</ab>
<ab n="5">One Lord, one
Faith, one Baptisme,</ab>

<fw>Christes gifts.</fw>
<ab n="6">One God and
Father of all, who is aboue all, &amp; through all, &amp; in you
all.</ab>
<ab n="7">But vnto euery
one of vs is giuen grace, according to the measure of the gift of
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="8">Wherefore he
saith: When he ascended vp on high, he led captiuitie captiue, and
gaue gifts vnto men.<note> Psal. 68. 18. , Or, a multitude of captiues.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">(Now that he
ascended, what is it but that hee also descended first into the
lower parts of the earth?</ab>
<ab n="10">He that
descended, is the same also that ascended vp far aboue all heauens,
that he might fill all things.)<note> Or, fulfill.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And he gaue
some, Apostles: and some, Prophets: and some, Euangelists: and
some, Pastors, and teachers:<note> 1.Cor.12. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For the
perfecting of the Saints, for the worke of the ministerie, for the
edifying of the body of Christ:</ab>
<ab n="13">Till we all
come in the vnitie of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Sonne
of God, vnto a perfect man, vnto the measure of the stature of the
fulnesse of Christ:<note> Or, into the vnitie. , Or, age.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">That we
hencefoorth be no more children, tossed to and fro, and caried
about with euery winde of doctrine, by the sleight of men, and
cunning craftinesse, whereby they lye in waite to deceiue:</ab>
<ab n="15">But speaking
the trueth in loue, may grow vp into him in all things which is the
head, euen Christ:<note> Or, being sincere.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">From whom the
whole body fitly ioyned together, and compacted by that which euery
ioynt supplyeth, according to the effectuall working in the measure
of euery part, maketh increase of the body, vnto the edifying of it
selfe in loue.<note> Col.2.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">This I say
therefore and testifie in the Lord, that yee henceforth walke not
as other Gentiles walke in the vanitie of their minde,</ab>
<ab n="18">Hauing the
vnderstanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God,
through the ignorance that is in them, because of the blindnesse of
their heart:<note> Rom.1.21 , Or, hardnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Who being past
feeling, haue giuen themselues ouer vnto lasciuiousnesse, to worke
all vncleannesse with greedinesse.</ab>
<ab n="20">But ye haue not
so learned Christ:</ab>
<ab n="21">If so be that
ye haue heard him, and haue bene taught by him, as the trueth is in
Iesus,</ab>

<fw>The new man.</fw>
<ab n="22">That yee put
off concerning the former conuersation, the olde man, which is
corrupt according to the deceitfull lusts:</ab>
<ab n="23">And bee renewed
in the spirit of your minde:</ab>
<ab n="24">And that yee
put on that new man, which after God is created in righteousnesse,
and true holinesse.<note> Or, holines of trueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Wherefore
putting away lying, speake euery man truth with his neighbour: for
we are members one of another.</ab>
<ab n="26">Be ye angry and
sinne not, let not the Sunne go down vpon your wrath:</ab>
<ab n="27">Neither giue
place to the deuill.</ab>
<ab n="28">Let him that
stole, steale no more: but rather let him labour, working with his
handes the thing which is good, that he may haue to giue to him
that needeth.<note> Or, to distribute.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Let no corrupt
communication proceede out of your mouth, but that which is good to
the vse of edifying, that it may minister grace vnto the
hearers.<note> Or, to edifie profitably.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And grieue not
the holy Sririt of God, whereby yee are sealed vnto the day of
redemption.</ab>
<ab n="31">Let all
bitternes, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and euill speaking,
be put away from you, with all malice,</ab>
<ab n="32">And bee ye
kinde one to another. tender hearted, forgiuing one another, euen
as God for Christs sake hath forgiuen you.<note> 2.Cor.2. 10.</note></ab>



</div>