<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEphesians_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ephesians-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>2 After generall exhortations, to
loue, 3 to flie fornication, 4 and all vncleannesse, 7 not to
conuerse with the wicked, 15 to walke warily, and to be 18 filled
with the spirit, 22 he descendeth to the particular dueties, how
wiues ought to obey their husbands, 25 and husbands ought to loue
their wiues, 32 euen as Christ doth his Church.</head>

<ab n="1">Be ye therefore
followers of God, as deare children.</ab>
<ab n="2">And walke in
loue, as Christ also hath loued vs, and hath giuen himselfe for vs,
an offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweet smelling
sauour;</ab>
<ab n="3">But fornication
and all vncleannesse, or couetousnesse, let it not be once named
amongst you, as becommeth Saints:</ab>

<fw>Awake from sleepe.</fw>
<ab n="4">Neither
filthinesse, nor foolish talking, nor iesting, which are not
conuenient: but rather giuing of thankes.</ab>
<ab n="5">For this ye
know, that no whoremonger, nor vncleane person, nor couetous man
who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the kingdome of Christ,
and of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">Let no man
deceiue you with vaine words: for because of these things commeth
the wrath of God vpon the children of disobedience.<note> Or, vnbeliefe.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Bee not yee
therefore partakers with them.</ab>
<ab n="8">For yee were
sometimes darkenesse, but now are yee light in the Lord: walke as
children of light,</ab>
<ab n="9">(For the fruite
of the spirit is in all goodnesse and righteousnesse &amp;
trueth.)</ab>
<ab n="10">Proouing what
is acceptable vnto the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="11">And haue no
fellowship with the vnfruitfull workes of darkenesse, but rather
reproue them.</ab>
<ab n="12">For it is a
shame euen to speake of those things which are done of them in
secret.</ab>
<ab n="13">But all things
that are reprooued, are made manifest by the light: for whatsoeuer
doth make manifest, is light.<note> Or, discouered.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Wherfore hee
saith: Awake thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and
Christ shall giue thee light.<note> Esai.60.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">See then that
yee walke circumspectly, not as fooles, but as wise,<note> Col.4.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Redeming the
time, because the dayes are euill.</ab>
<ab n="17">Wherefore be ye
not vnwise, but vnderstanding what the will of the Lord is.</ab>
<ab n="18">And bee not
drunke with wine, wherein is excesse: but bee filled with the
Spirit:</ab>
<ab n="19">Speaking to
your selues, in Psalmes, and Hymnes, and Spirituall songs, singing
and making melodie in your heart to the Lord,</ab>
<ab n="20">Giuing thankes
alwayes for all things vnto God, and the Father, in the Name of our
Lord Iesus Christ,</ab>
<ab n="21">Submitting your
selues one to another in the feare of God.</ab>
<ab n="22">Wiues, submit
your selues vnto your own husbands, as vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">For the husband
is the head of the wife, euen as Christ is the head of the Church:
and he is the sauiour of the body.</ab>

<fw>Seuerall duties.</fw>
<ab n="24">Therefore as
the Church is subiect vnto Christ, so let the wiues bee to their
owne husbands in euery thing.</ab>
<ab n="25">Husbands, loue
your wiues, euen as Christ also loued the Church, and gaue himselfe
for it:</ab>
<ab n="26">That he might
sanctifie &amp; cleanse it with the washing of water, by the
word,</ab>
<ab n="27">That hee might
present it to himselfe a glorious Church, not hauing spot or
wrinckle, or any such thing: but that it should bee holy and
without blemish.</ab>
<ab n="28">So ought men to
loue their wiues, as their owne bodies: hee that loueth his wife,
loueth himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="29">For no man euer
yet hated his owne flesh: but nourisheth and cherisheth it, euen as
the Lord the Church:</ab>
<ab n="30">For we are
members of his body, of his flesh, and of his bones.</ab>
<ab n="31">For this cause
shall a man leaue his father and mother, and shall be ioyned vnto
his wife, and they two shalbe one flesh.</ab>
<ab n="32">This is a great
mysterie: but I speake concerning Christ and the Church.</ab>
<ab n="33">Neuerthelesse,
let euery one of you in particular, so loue his wife euen as
himselfe, and the wife see that she reuerence her husband.</ab>



</div>