<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEsther_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The waters asswage. 4 The Arke
resteth on Ararat. 7 The rauen and the doue. 15 Noah, being
commanded, 18 goeth forth of the Arke. 20 He buildeth an Altar, and
offereth sacrifice, 21 which God accepteth, and promiseth to curse
the earth no more.</head>


<fw>The Arke resteth.</fw>
<ab n="1">And God remembred
Noah, and euery liuing thing, and all the cattell that was with him
in the Arke: and God made a winde to passe ouer the earth, and the
waters asswaged.</ab>
<ab n="2">The fountaines
also of the deepe, and the windowes of heauen were stopped, and the
raine from heauen was restrained.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the waters
returned from off the earth, continually: and after the end of the
hundred and fiftie dayes, the waters were abated.<note> Hebr. in going and returning.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the Arke
rested in the seuenth moneth, on the seuenteenth day of the moneth,
vpon the mountaines of Ararat.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the waters
decreased continually vntill the tenth moneth: in the tenth moneth,
on the first day of the moneth, were the tops of the mountaines
seene.<note> Hebr. were in going and decreasing.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And it came
to passe at the end of forty dayes, that Noah opened the window of
the Arke which he had made.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he sent forth
a Rauen, which went foorth to and fro, vntill the waters were dried
vp from off the earth.<note> Hebr. in going foorth, and returning.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Also hee sent
foorth a doue from him, to see if the waters were abated from off
the face of the ground.</ab>
<ab n="9">But the doue found
no rest for the sole of her foote, and she returned vnto him into
the Arke: for the waters were on the face of the whole earth. Then
he put foorth his hand, and tooke her, and pulled her in vnto him,
into the Arke.<note> Hebr. caused her to come.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And hee stayed
yet other seuen dayes; and againe hee sent foorth the doue out of
the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the doue came
in to him in the euening, and loe, in her mouth was an Oliue leafe
pluckt off: So Noah knew that the waters were abated from off the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee stayed
yet other seuen dayes, and sent forth the doue, which returned not
againe vnto him any more.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And it
came to passe in the sixe hundredth and one yeere, in the first
moneth, the first day of the moneth, the waters were dryed vp from
off the earth: and Noah remooued the couering of the Arke, and
looked, and behold, the face of the ground was drie.</ab>
<ab n="14">And in the second
moneth, on the seuen and twentieth day of the moneth, was the earth
dried.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And God
spake vnto Noah, saying,</ab>

<fw>Noah sacrificeth.</fw>
<ab n="16">Goe foorth of the
Arke, thou, and thy wife, and thy sonnes, and thy sonnes wiues with
thee:</ab>
<ab n="17">Bring foorth with
thee euery liuing thing that is with thee, of all flesh, both of
fowle, and of cattell, and of euery creeping thing that creepeth
vpon the earth, that they may breed abundantly in the earth, and be
fruitfull, and multiply vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Noah went
foorth, and his sonnes, and his wife, and his sonnes wiues with
him:</ab>
<ab n="19">Euery beast,
euery creeping thing, and euery fowle, and whatsoeuer creepeth vpon
the earth, after their kinds, went foorth out of the
Arke.<note> Hebr. families.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And Noah
builded an Altar vnto the LORD, and tooke of euery cleane beast,
and of euery cleane fowle, and offred burnt offrings on the
Altar.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the LORD
smelled a sweete sauour, and the LORD said in his heart, I will not
againe curse the ground any more for mans sake; for the imagination
of mans heart is euil from his youth: neither will I againe smite
any more euery thing liuing, as I haue done.<note> Hebr. a sauour of rest. , Chap.6. 5. matt.15. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">While the earth
remaineth, seed-time and haruest, and cold, and heat, and Summer,
and Winter, and day and night, shall not cease.<note> Heb. as yet all the dayes of the earth.</note></ab>



</div>