<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEsther_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Ahasuerus maketh royall feasts. 10
Vasthi, sent for, refuseth to come. 13 Ahasuerus, by the counsell
of Memucan, maketh the decree of mens soueraigntie.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came
to passe in the dayes of Ahasuerus, (this is Ahasuerus which
reigned from India, euen vnto Ethiopia, ouer an hundred, and seuen
and twentie prouinces.)</ab>
<ab n="2">That in those
dayes, when the King Ahasuerus sate on the throne of his kingdome,
which was in Shushan the palace:</ab>
<ab n="3">In the third
yeere of his reigne, he made a feast vnto all his Princes, and his
seruants, the power of Persia and Media, the Nobles and Princes of
the prouinces being before him.</ab>
<ab n="4">When he
shewed the riches of his glorious kingdome, and the honour of his
excellent maiestie, many dayes, euen an hundred and fourescore
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when
these dayes were expired, the king made a feast vnto all the people
that were present in Shushan the palace, both vnto great and small,
seuen dayes, in the court of the garden of the kings
palace,<note> Hebr. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Where were
white, greene and blew hangings, fastened with cords of fine
linnen, and purple, to siluer rings, and pillers of marble: the
beds were of gold and siluer, vpon a pauement of red, and blewe,
and white, and blacke marble.<note> Or, violet. , Or, of porphyre, and marble, and alabaster, and stone of blew colour.</note></ab>

<fw>The Kings, and Queenes feasts.</fw>
<ab n="7">And they gaue
them drinke in vessels of gold, (the vessels being diuers one from
another) and royall wine in abundance, according to the state of
the king.<note> Hebr. wine of the kingdome. , Heb. according to the hand of the king.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the
drinking was according to the law, none did compell: for the king
had appointed to all the officers of his house, that they should
doe according to euery mans pleasure.</ab>
<ab n="9">Also Uasthi
the Queene made a feast for the women, in the royall house which
belonged to king Ahasuerus.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ On the
seuenth day, when the heart of the King was merry with wine, he
commanded Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, and Abagtha, Zethar,
and Carcas, the seuen chamberlens that serued in the presence of
Ahasuerus the king,<note> Or, Eunuches.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">To bring Uasthi
the Queene before the king, with the Crowne royall, to shew the
people, and the Princes her beautie: for she was faire to looke
on.<note> Hebr. good of countenance.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But the Queene
Uasthi refused to come at the Kings commandement by his
chamberlens: therefore was the King very wroth, and his anger
burned in him.<note> Hebr. which was by the hand of his Eunuches.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then the
king saide to the wise men, which knew the times (for so was the
Kings maner towards all that knew law, and iudgement:</ab>
<ab n="14">And the next vnto
him, was Carshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshis, Meres, Marsena, and
Memucan, the seuen Princes of Persia, and Media, which saw the
Kings face, and which sate the first in the kingdome.)<note> Ezra.7.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">What shall wee doe
vnto the Queene Uasthi, according to law, because she hath not
performed the commandement of the king Ahasuerus, by the
chamberlens?<note> Hebr. what to doe?</note></ab>

<fw>Vasthi put away.</fw>
<ab n="16">And Memucan
answered before the king and the Princes; Uasthi the Queene hath
not done wrong to the king onely, but also to all the Princes, and
to all the people that are in all the prouinces of the king
Ahasuerus.</ab>
<ab n="17">For this deed of
the queene shall come abroad vnto all women, so that they shal
despise their husbands in their eyes, when it shall bee reported;
The king Ahasuerus commanded Uasthi the queene to be brought in
before him, but she came not.</ab>
<ab n="18">Likewise shall the
Ladies of Persia and Media say this day vnto all the kings princes,
which haue heard of the deed of the Queene. Thus shall there arise
too much contempt and wrath.</ab>
<ab n="19">If it please the
king, let there go a royall commandement from him, and let it bee
written among the lawes of the Persians, and the Medes, that it be
not altered, that Uasthi come no more before king Ahasuerus, and
let the king giue her royall estate vnto another that is better
then she.<note> Heb. if it be good with the king. , Heb. from before him. , Heb. that it passe not away. , Hebr. vnto her companion.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And when the kings
decree, which he shal make, shalbe published throughout all his
empire, (for it is great:) all the wiues shall giue to their
husbands honour, both to great and small.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the saying
pleased the king and the princes, and the king did according to the
word of Memucan:<note> Heb. was good in the eyes of the king.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For he sent
letters into all the kings prouinces, into euery prouince,
according to the writing thereof, and to euery people after their
language, that euery man should beare rule in his owne house, and
that it should be published according to the language of euerie
people.<note> Hebr. that one should publish it according to the language of his people.</note></ab>



</div>