<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEsther_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Mordecai is aduanced. 3 Esther
maketh suite to reuerse Hamans letters. 7 Ahasuerus granteth to the
Iewes to defend themselues. 15 Mordecais honour, and the Iewes
ioy.</head>

<ab n="1">On that day
did the King Ahasuerus giue the house of Haman, the Iewes enemy,
vnto Esther the Queene; and Mordecai came before the King; for
Esther hade told what he was vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the king
tooke off his Ring which he had taken from Haman, and gaue it vnto
Mordecai. And Esther set Mordecai ouer the house of Haman.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
Esther spake yet againe before the king, and fell downe at his
feet, and besought him with teares, to put away the mischiefe of
Haman the Agagite, and his deuice, that he had deuised against the
Iewes.<note> Heb. and she wept and besought him.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then the king
helde out the golden scepter toward Esther. So Esther arose, and
stood before the king,</ab>

<fw>Esthers request.</fw>
<ab n="5">And said, If
it please the king, and if I haue found fauour in his sight, and
the thing seeme right before the king, and I bee pleasing in his
eyes, let it be written to reuerse the letters deuised by Haman the
sonne of Hammedatha the Agagite, which hee wrote to destroy the
Iewes, which are in all the kings prouinces.<note> Heb. the deuice. , Or, who wrote.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For how can I
endure to see the euill that shall come vnto my people? or how can
I endure to see the destruction of my kinred?<note> Heb. be able that I may see.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Then
the king Ahasuerus said vnto Esther the Queene, and to Mordecai the
Iewe, Behold, I haue giuen Esther the house of Haman, and him they
haue hanged vpon the gallowes, because hee layde his hand vpon the
Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="8">Write ye also
for the Iewes, as it liketh you, in the Kings name, and seale it
with the Kings ring: for the writing which is written in the Kings
name, and sealed with the Kings ring, may no man
reuerse.<note> See Chap. 1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then were the
kings scribes called at that time, in the third moneth, (that is,
the month Siuan) on the three and twentieth day thereof, and it was
written (according to all that Mordecai commanded) vnto the Iewes,
and to the Lieutenants, and the deputies and rulers of the
prouinces, which are from India vnto Ethiopia, an hundred, twentie
and seuen prouinces, vnto euery prouince according to the writing
thereof, and vnto euery people after their language, and to the
Iewes, according to their writing, and according to their
language.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he wrote in
the king Ahasuerus name, and sealed it with the kings Ring, and
sent letters by Postes, on horsebacke, and riders on mules, camels,
and yong dromedaries:</ab>
<ab n="11">Wherein the King
granted the Iewes, which were in euery citie, to gather themselues
together, and to stand for their life, to destroy, to slay, and to
cause to perish all the power of the people and prouince that would
assault them, both little ones, and women, and to take the spoile
of them for a pray:</ab>
<ab n="12">Upon one day, in
all the prouinces of king Ahasuerus, namely vpon the thirteenth day
of the twelfth moneth, which is the moneth Adar.</ab>
<ab n="13">The copy of the
writing, for a commandement to bee giuen in euery prouince, was
published vnto all people, and that the Iewes should be readie
against that day, to auenge themselues on their
enemies.<note> Heb. reuealed.</note></ab>

<fw>The Iewes ioy.</fw>
<ab n="14">So the posts that
rode vpon mules and camels went out, being hastened, and pressed on
by the kings commandement, and the decree was giuen at Shushan the
palace.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And
Mordecai went out from the presence of the king, in royall
apparell, of blew and white, and with a great crowne of gold, and
with a garment of fine linnen, and purple, and the citie of Shushan
reioyced, and was glad:<note> Or, violet.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The Iewes had
light and gladnesse, and ioy and honour.</ab>
<ab n="17">And in euery
prouince, and in euery city, whithersoeuer the kings commandement,
and his decree came, the Iewes had ioy and gladnes, a feast and a
good day: And many of the people of the land became Iewes; for the
feare of the Iewes fell vpon them.</ab>



</div>