<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEsther_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The great mourning of Mordecai and
the Iewes. 4 Esther vnderstanding it, sendeth to Mordecai, who
sheweth the cause, and aduiseth her to vndertake the suit. 10 Shee
excusing her selfe is threatned by Mordecai. 15 She appointing a
fast, vndertaketh the suit.</head>


<fw>Hamans suit made knowen to
Esther.</fw>
<ab n="1">When Mordecai
perceiued all that was done, Mordecai rent his clothes, and put on
sackcloth with ashes, and went out into the midst of the citie, and
cried with a loud and a bitter crie:</ab>
<ab n="2">And came euen
before the kings gate: for none might enter into the kings gate
clothed with sackcloth.</ab>
<ab n="3">And in euery
prouince, whithersoeuer the kings commaundement, and his decree
came, there was great mourning among the Iewes, and fasting, and
weeping, and wailing, and many lay in sackcloth and
ashes.<note> Heb. sackecloth and ashes were laid vnder many.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ So
Esthers maides and her chamberlaines came, and told it her: then
was the Queene exceedingly grieued, and she sent raiment to clothe
Mordecai, and to take away the sackcloth from him: but he receiued
it not.<note> Heb. Eunuches.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then called
Esther for Hatach, one of the kings chamberlaines, whom he had
appointed to attend vpon her, and gaue him a commaundement to
Mordecai, to know what it was, and why it was.<note> Heb. whom he had set before her.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">So Hatach
went forth to Mordecai, vnto the street of the citie, which was
before the kings gate:</ab>
<ab n="7">And Mordecai
tolde him of all that had happened vnto him, and of the summe of
the money that Haman had promised to pay to the Kings treasuries
for the Iewes, to destroy them.</ab>
<ab n="8">Also he gaue
him the copie of the writing of the decree, that was giuen at
Shushan to destroy them, to shewe it vnto Esther, and to declare it
vnto her, and to charge her that she should goe in vnto the king,
to make supplication vnto him, and to make request before him, for
her people.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Hatach
came and told Esther the words of Mordecai.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Againe
Esther spake vnto Hatach, and gaue him commaundement vnto
Mordecai;</ab>
<ab n="11">All the Kings
seruants, and the people of the kings prouinces do know, that
whosoeuer, whether man or woman, shall come vnto the King into the
inner court, who is not called, there is one lawe of his to put him
to death, except such to whom the King shall hold out the golden
scepter, that he may liue: but I haue not beene called to come in
vnto the King, these thirtie dayes.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they tolde to
Mordecai Esthers words.</ab>

<fw>Her fast, and suit to the King.</fw>
<ab n="13">Then Mordecai
commanded to answere Esther; Thinke not with thy selfe that thou
shalt escape in the kings house, more then all the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="14">For if thou
altogether holdest thy peace at this time, then shall there
enlargement and deliuerance arise to the Iewes from another place,
but thou and thy fathers house shall be destroyed: And who knoweth,
whether thou art come to the kingdome for such a time as
this?<note> Heb. respiration.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then Esther
bade them returne Mordecai this answere:</ab>
<ab n="16">Goe, gather
together all the Iewes that are present in Shushan, and fast yee
for me, and neither eate nor drinke three dayes, night or day: I
also and my maidens will fast likewise, and so will I goe in vnto
the king, which is not according to the Law, and if I perish, I
perish.<note> Heb. found</note></ab>
<ab n="17">So Mordecai went
his way, and did according to all that Esther had commanded
him.<note> Heb. passed</note></ab>



</div>