<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEsther_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Esther aduenturing on the kings
fauour, obteineth the grace of the golden scepter, and inuiteth the
king and Haman to a banquet. 6 She being incouraged by the king in
her suit, inuiteth them to another banquet the next day. 9 Haman
proud of his aduancement, repineth at the contempt of Mordecai. 14
By the counsell of Zeresh, he buildeth for him a paire of
gallous.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came
to passe on the third day, that Esther put on her royall apparell,
and stood in the inner court of the kings house, ouer against the
kings house: and the King sate vpon his royall throne in the royall
house, ouer against the gate of the house.</ab>
<ab n="2">And it was
so, when the king saw Esther the Queene standing in the court, that
shee obtained fauour in his sight: and the king helde out to Esther
the golden scepter that was in his hand: So Esther drew neere, and
touched the top of the scepter.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then sayd the
King vnto her, What wilt thou, Queene Esther? and what is thy
request? it shall bee euen giuen thee to the halfe of the
kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Esther
answered, If it seeme good vnto the King, let the King and Haman
come this day vnto the banquet that I haue prepared for
him.</ab>

<fw>Her fast, and suit to the King.</fw>
<ab n="5">Then the King
sayd, Cause Haman to make haste, that he may doe as Esther hath
said: So the king and Haman came to the banquet that Esther had
prepared.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
the king said vnto Esther at the banquet of wine, What is thy
petition, and it shall be granted thee? and what is thy request?
euen to the halfe of the kingdome it shall be performed.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then answered
Esther, and said, My petition, and my request is,</ab>
<ab n="8">If I haue
found fauour in the sight of the king, and if it please the king to
grant my petition, and to performe my request, let the king, and
Haman, come to the banquet that I shall prepare for them, and I wil
do to morow, as the king hath said.<note> Heb. to doe.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then
went Haman foorth that day, ioyfull, and with a glad heart: but
when Haman saw Mordecai in the kings gate, that hee stood not vp,
nor mooued for him, hee was full of indignation against
Mordecai.</ab>
<ab n="10">Neuerthelesse
Haman refrained himselfe, and when he came home, hee sent and
called for his friends, and Zeresh his wife.<note> Heb. caused to come.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Haman told
them of the glory of his riches, and the multitude of his children,
and all the things wherein the king had promoted him, and how he
had aduanced him aboue the Princes, and seruants of the
king.</ab>
<ab n="12">Haman said
moreouer, Yea Esther the Queene did let no man come in with the
king vnto the banquet that she had prepared, but my selfe; and to
morrow am I inuited vnto her also with the king.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yet all this
auaileth me nothing, so long as I see Mordecai the Iew sitting at
the kings gate.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then saide
Zeresh his wife, and all his friends vnto him, Let a gallous be
made of fifty cubits hie, and to morrow speake thou vnto the king,
that Mordecai may be hanged thereon: then goe thou in merily with
the king vnto the banquet. And the thing pleased Haman, and hee
caused the gallous to be made.<note> Heb. tree.</note></ab>



</div>