<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEsther_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Esther-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Haman aduanced by the king, and
despised by Mordecai, seeketh reuenge vpon all the Iewes. 7 Hee
casteth Lots. 8 Hee obtaineth by calumniation, a Decree of the
king, to put the Iewes to death.</head>

<ab n="1">After these
things did king Ahasuerus promote Haman, the sonne of Amedatha the
Agagite, and aduanced him, and set his seate aboue all the princes
that were with him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And all the
kings seruants, that were in the kings gate, bowed, and reuerenced
Haman, for the king had so commanded concerning him: but Mordecai
bowed not, nor did him reuerence.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then the
kings seruants, which were in the kings gate, sayd vnto Mordecai,
Why transgressest thou the kings commandement?</ab>
<ab n="4">Now it came
to passe, when they spake daily vnto him, and he hearkened not vnto
them; that they told Haman, to see whether Mordecai his matters
would stand, for he had told them that he was a Iewe.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when
Haman saw that Mordecai bowed not, nor did him reuerence, then was
Haman full of wrath.</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee
thought scorne to lay hands on Mordecai alone, for they had shewed
him the people of Mordecai: wherefore Haman sought to destroy all
the Iewes, that were throughout the whole kingdome of Ahasuerus,
euen the people of Mordecai.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ In the
first moneth (that is, the moneth Nisan) in the twelfth yeere of
king Ahasuerus, they cast Pur, that is, the lot, before Haman, from
day to day, and from moneth to moneth, to the twelfth moneth, that
is the moneth Adar.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
Haman saide vnto king Ahasuerus: There is a certaine people
scattered abroad, and dispersed among the people, in all the
prouinces of thy kingdome, and their lawes are diuerse from all
people, neither keepe they the kings lawes; therefore it is not for
the kings profit to suffer them.<note> Heb. meete or, equall.</note></ab>

<fw>Hamans suit made knowen to
Esther.</fw>
<ab n="9">If it please
the king, let it be written, that they may be destroyed: and I will
pay ten thousand talents of siluer to the handes of those that haue
the charge of the businesse, to bring it into the kings
treasuries.<note> Heb. to destroy them. , Heb. weigh.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the king tooke
his ring from his hand, and gaue it vnto Haman the sonne of
Ammedatha the Agagite, the Iewes enemie.<note> Or, oppressour.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the king saide
vnto Haman, The siluer is giuen to thee, the people also, to doe
with them, as it seemeth good to thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then were the
kings scribes called on the thirteenth day of the first moneth, and
there was written, according to all that Haman had commanded, vnto
the kings Lieutenants, and to the gouernours, that were ouer euery
prouince, and to the rulers of euery people of euery prouince,
according to the writing thereof, and to euery people, after their
language, in the name of king Ahasuerus was it written, and sealed
with the kings ring.<note> Or, secretaries.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the letters
were sent by posts into all the kings prouinces, to destroy, to
kill, and to cause to perish all Iewes, both yong and olde, litle
children and women, in one day, euen vpon the thirteenth day of the
twelfth moneth (which is the moneth Adar) and to take the spoile of
them for a pray.</ab>
<ab n="14">The copie of the
writing for a commandement to bee giuen in euery prouince, was
published vnto all people, that they should bee ready against that
day.</ab>
<ab n="15">The postes went
out, being hastened by the kings commandement, and the decree was
giuen in Shushan the palace: and the king and Haman sate downe to
drinke, but the citie Shushan was perplexed.</ab>



</div>