<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The Israelites come to Sin. 2 They
murmure for want of bread. 4 God promiseth them bread from heauen.
11 Quailes are sent, 14 and Manna. 16 The ordering of Manna. 25 It
was not to bee found on the Sabbath. 32 An Omer of it is
preserued.</head>


<fw>Murmuring.</fw>
<ab n="1">And they tooke
their iourney from Elim, and all the Congregation of the children
of Israel came vnto the wildernesse of Sin, which is betweene Elim
and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second moneth after their
departing out of the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the whole
Congregation of the children of Israel murmured against Moses and
Aaron in the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the children
of Israel saide vnto them, Would to God wee had died by the hand of
the Lord in the land of Egypt, when wee sate by the flesh pots, and
when we did eate bread to the full: for ye haue brought vs forth
into this wildernesse, to kill this whole assembly with
hunger.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then said
the Lord vnto Moses, Behold, I will raine bread from heauen for
you: and the people shall goe out, and gather a certaine rate euery
day, that I may proue them, whether they will walke in my Law, or
no.<note> Hebr. the portion of a day in his day.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And it shall come
to passe, that on the sixt day, they shall prepare that which they
bring in, and it shall be twice as much as they gather
dayly.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses and
Aaron said vnto all the children of Israel, At euen, then ye shall
know that the Lord hath brought you out from the land of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="7">And in the
morning, then ye shall see the glory of the Lord, for that he
heareth your murmurings against the Lord: And what are wee, that
yee murmure against vs?</ab>
<ab n="8">And Moses said,
This shalbe when the Lord shal giue you in the euening flesh to
eate, and in the morning bread to the full: for that the Lord
heareth your murmurings which ye murmure against him; and what are
wee? your murmurings are not against vs, but against the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Moses
spake vnto Aaron, Say vnto all the Congregation of the children of
Israel, Come neere before the Lord: for hee hath heard your
murmurings.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe as Aaron spake vnto the whole Congregation of the children of
Israel, that they looked toward the wildernesse, and behold, the
glory of the Lord appeared in the cloude.<note> Chap. 13. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>Quailes. Manna.</fw>
<ab n="12">I haue heard the
murmurings of the children of Israel: Speake vnto them, saying, At
euen ye shall eat flesh, and in the morning ye shalbe filled with
bread: and ye shal know that I am the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it came to
passe, that at euen the Quailes came vp, and couered the campe: and
in the morning the dew lay round about the hoste.<note> Numb.11 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And when the dewe
that lay was gone vp, behold, vpon the face of the wildernesse
there lay a small round thing, as small as the hoare frost on the
ground.<note> Numb.11 7. psal.78. 24. wisd.16 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And when the
children of Israel saw it, they said one to another, It is Manna:
for they wist not what it was. And Moses said vnto them, This is
the bread which the Lord hath giuen you to eate.<note> Or, what is this? or it is a portion. , Ioh. 6.31. 1.Cor.10 3</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ This is
the thing which the Lord hath commanded: gather of it euery man
according to his eating: an Omer for euery man, according to the
number of your persons, take yee euery man for them which are in
his tents.<note> Heb. by the polle or head. , Heb. soules.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the children
of Israel did so, and gathered some more, some lesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">And when they did
mete it with an Omer, he that gathered much, had nothing ouer, and
he that gathered litle, had no lacke: they gathered euery man
according to his eating.<note> 2.Cor.8. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Moses saide,
Let no man leaue of it till the morning.</ab>
<ab n="20">Notwithstanding
they hearkened not vnto Moses, but some of them left of it vntill
the morning, and it bred wormes, and stanke: and Moses was wroth
with them.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they gathered
it euery morning, euery man according to his eating: and when the
Sunne waxed hot, it melted.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And it
came to passe that on the sixt day they gathered twice as much
bread, two Omers for one man: and all the rulers of the
Congregation came and told Moses.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he said vnto
them, This is that which the Lord hath said, To morrow is the rest
of the holy Sabbath vnto the Lord: bake that which you will bake,
to day, and seethe that ye will seethe, and that which remaineth
ouer, lay vp for you to be kept vntill the morning.</ab>

<fw>Manna reserued.</fw>
<ab n="24">And they laid it
vp till the morning, as Moses bade: and it did not stinke, neither
was there any worme therein.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Moses saide,
Eate that to day, for to day is a Sabbath vnto the Lord: to day yee
shall not finde it in the field.</ab>
<ab n="26">Sixe dayes ye
shall gather it, but on the seuenth day which is the Sabbath, in it
there shall be none.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And it
came to passe, that there went out some of the people on the
seuenth day for to gather, and they found none.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, How long refuse yee to keepe my Commandements, and my
Lawes?</ab>
<ab n="29">See, for that the
Lord hath giuen you the Sabbath, therefore hee giueth you on the
sixt day the bread of two dayes: abide yee euery man in his place:
let no man goe out of his place on the seuenth day.</ab>
<ab n="30">So the people
rested on the seuenth day.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the house of
Israel called the name thereof Manna: and it was like Coriander
seed, white: and the taste of it was like wafers made with
hony.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And Moses
said, This is the thing which the Lord commandeth: Fill an Omer of
it to bee kept for your generations, that they may see the bread
wherewith I haue fed you in the wildernesse, when I brought you
forth from the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="33">And Moses sayd
vnto Aaron, Take a pot, and put an Omer full of Manna therein, and
lay it vp before the Lord, to be kept for your generations.</ab>
<ab n="34">As the Lord
commaunded Moses, so Aaron layd it vp before the Testimonie, to be
kept.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the children
of Israel did eat Manna fortie yeeres, vntill they came to a land
inhabited: they did eate Manna, vntill they came vnto the borders
of the land of Canaan.<note> Iosh.5. 1 2. nehem. 9.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Now an Omer is
the tenth part of an Ephah.</ab>



</div>