<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 God instructeth the Israelites in
their iourney. 5 Pharaoh pursueth after them. 10 The Israelites
murmure. 13 Moses comforteth them. 15 God instructeth Moses. 19 The
cloud remoueth behinde the campe. 21 The Israelites passe through
the Red-sea, 23 which drowneth the Egyptians.</head>


<fw>Pharaoh pursueth.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, that they turne and encampe before Pi-hahiroth,
betweene Migdol and the sea, ouer against Baal-Zephon: before it
shall ye encampe by the sea.<note> Num. 33. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For Pharaoh will
say of the children of Israel, They are intangled in the land, the
wildernesse hath shut them in.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I will harden
Pharaohs heart, that he shall follow after them, and I will be
honoured vpon Pharaoh, and vpon all his hoste, That the Egyptians
may know that I am the Lord. And they did so.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And it was
told the King of Egypt, that the people fled: And the heart of
Pharaoh and of his seruants was turned against the people, and they
said, Why haue wee done this, that we haue let Israel goe from
seruing vs?</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee made ready
his charet, and tooke his people with him.</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee tooke sixe
hundred chosen charets, and all the charets of Egypt, and captaines
ouer euery one of them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the Lord
hardened the heart of Pharaoh King of Egypt, and he pursued after
the children of Israel: and the children of Israel went out with an
high hand.</ab>
<ab n="9">But the Egyptians
pursued after them (all the horses and charets of Pharaoh, and his
horsemen, and his army) and ouertooke them encamping by the sea,
beside Pi-hahiroth before Baal-Zephon.<note> Iosh. 24. 6. 1.macc. 4.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And when
Pharaoh drew nigh, the children of Israel lift vp their eyes, and
behold, the Egyptians marched after them, and they were sore
afraid: and the children of Israel lift vp their eyes, and beholde,
the Egyptians marched after them, and they were sore afraid: and
the children of Israel cried out vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they said
vnto Moses, Because there were no graues in Egypt, hast thou taken
vs away to die in the wildernesse? Wherefore hast thou dealt thus
with vs, to cary vs foorth out of Egypt?</ab>

<fw>The sea diuided.</fw>
<ab n="12">Is not this the
word that wee did tell thee in Egypt, saying, Let vs alone, that we
may serue the Egyptians? For it had bene better for vs to serue the
Egyptians, then that wee should die in the wildernesse.<note> Chap. 6. 9,</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And Moses
saide vnto the people, Feare ye not, stand still, and see the
saluation of the Lord, which he will shew to you to day: for the
Egyptians whom ye haue seene to day, ye shall see them againe no
more for euer.<note> Or, For whereas you haue seene the Egyptians to day, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord shall
fight for you, and ye shall hold your peace.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Wherefore criest thou vnto me? Speake vnto
the children of Israel, that they goe forward.</ab>
<ab n="16">But lift thou vp
thy rodde, and stretch out thine hand ouer the Sea, and diuide it:
and the children of Israel shall goe on dry ground thorow the mids
of the Sea.</ab>
<ab n="17">And I, beholde, I
will harden the hearts of the Egyptians, and they shall follow
them: and I will get mee honour vpon Pharaoh, and vpon all his
hoste, vpon his charets, and vpon his horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Egyptians
shall know that I am the Lord, when I haue gotten me honour vpon
Pharaoh, vpon his charets, and vpon his horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And the
Angel of God which went before the campe of Israel, remoued and
went behind them, and the pillar of the cloud went from before
their face, and stood behinde them.</ab>
<ab n="20">And it came
betweene the campe of the Egyptians, and the campe of Israel, and
it was a cloud and darkenesse to them, but it gaue light by night
to these: so that the one came not neere the other all the
night.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Moses
stretched out his hand ouer the Sea, and the Lord caused the Sea to
goe backe by a strong East winde all that night, and made the Sea
dry land, and the waters were diuided.<note> Iosh. 4. 23. psalme 114. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And the children
of Israel went into the midst of the Sea vpon the dry ground, and
the waters were a wall vnto them on their right hand, and on their
left.<note> Psal. 78. 13. 1.cor. 10, 1. Hebr.11.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
Egyptians pursued, and went in after them, to the midst of the Sea,
euen all Pharaohs horses, his charets and his horsemen.</ab>

<fw>Pharaoh drowned.</fw>
<ab n="24">And it came to
passe, that in the morning watch the Lord looked vnto the hoste of
the Egyptians, through the pillar of fire, and of the cloude, and
troubled the hoste of the Egyptians,</ab>
<ab n="25">And tooke off
their charet wheeles, that they draue them heauily: So that the
Egyptians said, Let vs flee from the face of Israel: for the Lord
fighteth for them, against the Egyptians.<note> Or, made them to goe heauily.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Stretch out thine hand ouer the Sea, that
the waters may come againe vpon the Egyptians, vpon their charets,
and vpon their horsemen.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Moses
stretched foorth his hand ouer the sea, and the sea returned to his
strength when the morning appeared: and the Egyptians fled against
it: and the Lord ouerthrew the Egyptians in the midst of the
sea.<note> Hebr. shooke off.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And the waters
returned, and couered the charets, and the horsemen, and all the
hoste of Pharaoh that came into the sea after them: there remained
not so much as one of them.<note> Psal.106. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">But the children
of Israel walked vpon drie land, in the midst of the sea, and the
waters were a wall vnto them on their right hand, and on their
left.</ab>
<ab n="30">Thus the Lord
saued Israel that day out of the hand of the Egyptians: and Israel
sawe the Egyptians dead vpon the sea shore.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Israel saw
that great worke which the Lord did vpon the Egyptians: &amp; the
people feared the Lord, and beleeued the Lord, and his seruant
Moses.<note> Hebr. hand.</note></ab>



</div>