<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The murraine of beasts. 8 The
plague of boyles, and blaines. 13 His message about the haile. 22
The plague of haile. 27 Pharaoh sueth to Moses, 35 but yet is
hardened.</head>

<ab n="1">Then the Lord
said vnto Moses, Goe in vnto Pharaoh, and tell him, Thus saith the
Lord God of the Hebrewes, Let my people goe, that they may serue
me.</ab>
<ab n="2">For if thou
refuse to let them goe, and wilt hold them still,</ab>
<ab n="3">Behold, the
hand of the Lord is vpon thy cattell which is in the field, vpon
the horses, vpon the asses, vpon the camels, vpon the oxen, and
vpon the sheepe: there shall be a very grieuous murraine.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
shall seuer betweene the cattell of Israel, and the cattell of
Egypt, and there shall nothing die of all that is the childrens of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Lord
appointed a set time, saying, To morrow the Lord shall doe this
thing in the land.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Lord
did that thing on the morrow; and all the cattell of Egypt died,
but of the cattell of the children of Israel died not one.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Pharaoh
sent, and beholde, there was not one of the cattell of the
Israelites dead. And the heart of Pharaoh was hardened, and he did
not let the people goe.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
the Lord saide vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, Take to you handfuls of
ashes of the fornace, and let Moses sprinkle it towards the heauen,
in the sight of Pharaoh:</ab>

<fw>Pharaoh obstinate.</fw>
<ab n="9">And it shall
become small dust in all the land of Egypt, and shall bee a boyle
breaking forth with blaines, vpon man and vpon beast, throughout
all the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they tooke
ashes of the fornace, and stood before Pharaoh, and Moses sprinkled
it vp toward heauen: and it became a boile breaking forth with
blaines, vpon man and vpon beast.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Magicians
could not stand before Moses, because of the boiles: for the boile
was vpon the magicians, and vpon all the Egyptians.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the Lord
hardened the heart of Pharaoh, and hee hearkened not vnto them, as
the Lord had spoken vnto Moses.<note> Chap.4. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Rise vp earely in the morning, and stand
before Pharaoh, and say vnto him, Thus saith the Lord God of the
Hebrewes, Let my people goe, that they may serue me.</ab>
<ab n="14">For I will at this
time send all my plagues vpon thine heart, and vpon thy seruants,
and vpon thy people: that thou mayest knowe that there is none like
me in all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="15">For now I will
stretch out my hand, that I may smite thee and thy people, with
pestilence, and thou shalt be cut off from the earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">And in very deede,
for this cause haue I raised thee vp, for to shewe in thee my
power, and that my name may be declared throughout all the
earth.<note> Rom.9. 17. , Heb. made thee stand.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">As yet exaltest
thou thy selfe against my people, that thou wilt not let them
goe?</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold, to morrow
about this time, I wil cause it to raine a very grieuous haile,
such as hath not bene in Egypt, since the foundation thereof euen
vntill now.</ab>
<ab n="19">Send therefore
now, and gather thy cattell, and all that thou hast in the field:
for vpon euery man and beast which shal be found in the field, and
shal not bee brought home, the haile shall come downe vpon them,
and they shall die.</ab>
<ab n="20">Hee that feared
the word of the Lord amongst the seruants of Pharaoh, made his
seruants and his cattell flee into the houses.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he that
regarded not the word of the Lord, left his seruants and his
cattell in the field.<note> Heb. set not his heart vnto.</note></ab>

<fw>The plague of haile.</fw>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Stretch forth thine hand toward heauen, that
there may be haile in all the land of Egypt, vpon man and vpon
beast, and vpon euery herbe of the field, thorowout the land of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Moses
stretched foorth his rod toward heauen, and the Lord sent thunder
and haile, and the fire ranne along vpon the ground, and the Lord
rained haile vpon the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="24">So there was
haile, and fire mingled with the haile, very grieuous, such as
there was none like it in all the land of Egypt, since it became a
nation.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the haile
smote throughout all the land of Egypt, all that was in the field,
both man and beast: and the haile smote euery herbe of the fielde,
and brake euery tree of the field.</ab>
<ab n="26">Onely in the land
of Goshen where the children of Israel were, was there no
haile.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And Pharaoh
sent, and called for Moses and Aaron, and said vnto them, I haue
sinned this time: the Lord is righteous, and I and my people are
wicked.</ab>
<ab n="28">Entreat the Lord,
(for it is enough) that there be no more mighty thunderings and
haile, and I will let you goe, and ye shall stay no
longer.<note> Hebr. voyces of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And Moses saide
vnto him, Assoone as I am gone out of the citie, I will spread
abroad my hands vnto the Lord, and the thunder shall cease, neither
shall there be any more haile: that thou mayest know how that the
earth is the Lords.<note> Psal.24.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But as for thee
and thy seruants, I know that ye will not yet feare the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the flaxe, and
the barley was smitten: for the barley was in the eare, and the
flaxe was bolled:</ab>
<ab n="32">But the wheat and
the rye were not smitten: for they were not growen vp.<note> Hebr. hidden: or, darke.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And Moses went out
of the city from Pharaoh, and spread abroad his hands vnto the
Lord: and the thunders and haile ceased, and the raine was not
powred vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="34">And when Pharaoh
saw that the raine, and the haile and the thunders were ceased, hee
sinned yet more, and hardened his heart, he and his
seruants.</ab>

<fw>Locusts threatned,</fw>
<ab n="35">And the heart of
Pharaoh was hardened, neither would he let the children of Israel
goe, as the Lord had spoken by Moses.<note> Hebr. by the hand of Moses.</note></ab>



</div>