<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 The offerings are deliuered to the
workemen. The liberalitie of the people is restrained. 8 The
curtaines of Cherubims. 14 The curtaines of goats haire. 19 The
couering of skinnes. 20 The boards with their sockets. 31 The
barres. 35 The vaile. 37 The hanging for the doore.</head>

<ab n="1">Then wrought
Bezaleel and Aholiab, and euery wise hearted man, in whome the Lord
put wisedome and vnderstanding, to know how to worke all maner of
worke for the seruice of the Sanctuary, according to all that the
Lord had commanded.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Moses called
Bezaleel and Aholiab, and euery wise hearted man, in whose heart
the Lord had put wisedome, euen euery one whose heart stirred him
vp to come vnto the worke to doe it.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they receiued
of Moses all the offering which the children of Israel had brought,
for the worke of the seruice of the Sanctuarie, to make it withall.
And they brought yet vnto him free offerings euery morning.</ab>
<ab n="4">And al the wisemen
that wrought all the worke of the Sanctuary, came euery man from
his worke which they made.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And they
spake vnto Moses, saying, The people bring much more then enough
for the seruice of the worke which the Lord commaunded to
make.</ab>

<fw>Curtaines, boards.</fw>
<ab n="6">And Moses gaue
commandement, and they caused it to bee proclaimed throughout the
campe, saying, Let neither man nor woman make any more worke for
the offering of the Sanctuarie: so the people were restrained from
bringing.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the stuffe
they had was sufficient for all the worke to make it, and too
much.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And euery
wise hearted man, among them that wrought the worke of the
Tabernacle, made ten curtaines, of fine twined linnen, and blew,
and purple, and scarlet: with Cherubims of cunning worke made he
them.<note> Chap. 26. 3,4.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The length of one
curtaine was twentie &amp; eight cubites, and the breadth of one
curtaine foure cubites: the curtaines were all of one cise.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he coupled
the fiue curtaines one vnto another: and the other fiue curtaines
he coupled one vnto another.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he made
loopes of blew, on the edge of one curtaine, from the seluedge in
the coupling: likewise hee made in the vttermost side of another
curtaine, in the coupling of the second.</ab>
<ab n="12">Fiftie loopes
made he in one curtaine, and fiftie loopes made hee in the edge of
the curtaine which was in the coupling of the second: the loopes
held one curtaine to another.<note> Chap. 26. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he made
fiftie taches of gold, and coupled the curtaines one vnto another
with the taches. So it became one tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And he
made curtaines of goats haire, for the tent ouer the Tabernacle:
eleuen curtaines he made them.</ab>
<ab n="15">The length of one
curtaine was thirtie cubites, and foure cubites was the breadth of
one curtaine: the eleuen curtaines were of one cise.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he coupled
fiue curtaines by themselues, and sixe curtaines by
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he made
fiftie loopes vpon the vttermost edge of the curtaine in the
coupling, and fiftie loopes made he vpon the edge of the curtaine,
which coupleth the second.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he made
fiftie taches of brasse to couple the tent together that it might
be one.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he made a
couering for the tent of rammes skinnes died red, and a couering of
badgers skinnes aboue that.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And hee
made boards for the Tabernacle of Shittim wood, standing
up.</ab>

<fw>The Vaile.</fw>
<ab n="21">The length of a
board was ten cubites, and the breadth of a board one cubite and a
halfe.</ab>
<ab n="22">One board had two
tenons, equally distant one from another: thus did he make for all
the boards of the tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he made
boards for the Tabernacle: twentie boards for the South side,
Southward.</ab>
<ab n="24">And fourtie
sockets of siluer hee made vnder the twentie boards: two sockets
vnder one board for his two tenons, and two sockets vnder another
board, for his two tenons.</ab>
<ab n="25">And for the other
side of the Tabernacle which is toward the North corner, he made
twentie boards.</ab>
<ab n="26">And their fourtie
sockets of siluer: two sockets vnder one board, and two sockets
vnder another board.</ab>
<ab n="27">And for the sides
of the Tabernacle westward, he made sixe boards.</ab>
<ab n="28">And two boards
made he for the corners of the Tabernacle, in the two
sides.</ab>
<ab n="29">And they were
coupled beneath and coupled together at the head thereof, to one
ring: thus hee did to both of them in both the corners.<note> Heb. twinned.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And there were
eight boards, and their sockets were sixteene sockets of siluer:
vnder euery board two sockets.<note> Heb. two sockets, two sockets vnder one board.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And he
made barres of Shittim wood: five for the boards of the one side of
the Tabernacle,<note> Chap. 25. 28. &amp; 30.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And fiue barres
for the boards of the other side of the Tabernacle, and fiue barres
for the boards of the Tabernacle for the sides westward.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he made the
middle barre to shoot thorow the boards from the one end to the
other.</ab>
<ab n="34">And he ouerlaid
the boards with gold, and made their rings of golde to be places
for the barres, and ouerlaide the barres with gold.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And he
made a Uaile of blew, and purple, and scarlet, and fine twined
linnen: with Cherubims made he it of cunning worke.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he made
thereunto foure pillars of Shittim wood, and ouerlaide them with
golde: their hookes were of gold: and he cast for them foure
sockets of siluer.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ And hee
made an hanging for the Tabernacle doore of blew and purple, and
scarlet, and fine twined linnen, of needle worke,<note> Hebr. the worke of a needle worker or embroiderer.</note></ab>

<fw>The Arke.</fw>
<ab n="38">And the fiue
pillars of it with their hooks: and he ouerlaid their chapiters and
their fillets with gold: but their fiue sockets were of
brasse.</ab>



</div>