<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Moses song. 22 The people want
water. 23 The waters at Marah are bitter. 25 A tree sweetneth them.
27 At Elim are twelue wels, and seuentie palme trees.</head>

<ab n="1">Then sang Moses
and the children of Israel this song vnto the Lord, and spake,
saying, I will sing vnto the Lord: for he hath triumphed
gloriously, the horse and his rider hath he throwen into the
Sea.<note> Wisd. 1. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord is my
strength and song, and he is become my saluation: he is my God, and
I will prepare him an habitation, my fathers God, and I wil exalt
him.</ab>
<ab n="3">The Lord is a man
of warre: the Lord is his Name.</ab>

<fw>Israels song of thankesgiuing.</fw>
<ab n="4">Pharaohs charets
and his hoste hath he cast into the sea: his chosen captaines also
are drowned in the red Sea.</ab>
<ab n="5">The depths haue
couered them: they sanke into the bottome as a stone.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thy right hand, O
Lord, is become glorious in power, thy right hand, O Lord, hath
dashed in pieces the enemie.</ab>
<ab n="7">And in the
greatnesse of thine excellencie thou hast ouerthrowen them, that
rose vp against thee: thou sentest forth thy wrath, which consumed
them as stubble.</ab>
<ab n="8">And with the blast
of thy nostrils the waters were gathered together: the floods stood
vpright as an heape, and the depths were congealed in the heart of
the Sea.</ab>
<ab n="9">The enemie said, I
will pursue, I wil ouertake, I wil diuide the spoile: my lust shall
be satisfied vpon them: I will draw my sword, mine hand shall
destroy them.<note> Or, repossesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thou didst blow
with thy wind, the sea couered them, they sanke as lead in the
mighty waters.</ab>
<ab n="11">Who is like vnto
thee, O Lord, amongst the gods? who is like thee, glorious in
holinesse, fearefull in praises, doing wonders!<note> Or, mighty ones?</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thou stretchedst
out thy right hand, the earth swallowed them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou in thy
mercie hast led forth the people which thou hast redeemed: thou
hast guided them in thy strength vnto thy holy habitation.</ab>
<ab n="14">The people shall
heare, and be afraid: sorrow shall take hold on the inhabitants of
Palestina.<note> Deut. 2. 25. iosh.2. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then the dukes of
Edom shal be amased: the mighty men of Moab trembling shall take
hold vpon them: all the inhabitants of Canaan shal melt
away.</ab>
<ab n="16">Feare and dread
shall fall vpon them, by the greatnesse of thine arme they shall be
as still as a stone, till thy people passe ouer, O Lord, till the
people passe ouer which thou hast purchased.<note> Deut 2. 29. iosh.2. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Thou shalt bring
them in, and plant them in the mountaine of thine inheritance, in
the place, O Lord, which thou hast made for thee to dwell in, in
the Sanctuary, O Lord, which thy hands haue established.</ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord shal
reigne for euer and euer.</ab>

<fw>Israels song of thankesgiuing.</fw>
<ab n="19">For the horse of
Pharaoh went in with his charets and with his horsemen into the
sea, and the Lord brought againe the waters of the Sea vpon them:
But the children of Israel went on drie land in the mids of the
sea.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And Miriam
the prophetesse the sister of Aaron, tooke a timbrell in her hand,
and all the women went out after her, with timbrels &amp; with
dances.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Miriam
answered them, Sing ye to the Lord, for he hath triumphed
gloriously: the horse and his rider hath he throwen into the
sea.</ab>
<ab n="22">So Moses brought
Israel from the red sea, and they went out into the wildernesse of
Shur: and they went three dayes in the wildernesse, and found no
water.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And when
they came to Marah, they could not drinke of the waters of Marah,
for they were bitter: therefore the name of it was called
Marah.<note> That is, Bitternesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the people
murmured against Moses, saying, What shall wee drinke?</ab>
<ab n="25">And he cried vnto
the Lord: and the Lord shewed him a tree, which when hee had cast
into the waters, the waters were made sweete: there he made a
statute &amp; an ordinance, and there he proued them,<note> Ecclus. 38.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And said, If thou
wilt diligently hearken to the voice of the Lord thy God, and wilt
doe that which is right in his sight, and wilt giue eare to his
Commandements, and keepe all his Statutes, I will put none of these
diseases vpon thee, which I haue brought vpon the Egyptians: for I
am the Lord that healeth thee.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And they
came to Elim: where were twelue wels of water, and threescore and
ten palme trees, and they encamped there by the waters.<note> Num. 33. 9.</note></ab>




</div>