<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The beginning of the yeere is
changed. 3 The Passeouer is instituted. 11 The Rite of the
Passeouer. 15 Vnleauened bread. 29 The first borne are slaine. 31
The Israelites are driuen out of the lande. 37 They come to
Succoth. 43 The ordinance of the Passeouer.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">This moneth shalbe
vnto you the beginning of moneths: it shall be the first moneth of
the yeere to you.</ab>

<fw>The Passeouer is instituted.</fw>
<ab n="3">¶ Speake ye
vnto all the Congregation of Israel, saying, In the tenth day of
this moneth they shall take to them euery man a lambe, according to
the house of their fathers, a lambe for an house.<note> Or, kidde.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And if the
houshold be too little for the lambe, let him and his neighbour
next vnto his house, take it according to the number of the soules:
euery man according to his eating shall make your count for the
lambe.</ab>
<ab n="5">Your lambe shall
be without blemish, a male of the first yeere: yee shall take it
out from the sheepe or from the goates.<note> Heb. sonne of a yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And ye shall keepe
it vp vntill the fourteenth day of the same moneth: and the whole
assembly of the congregation of Israel shall kill it in the
euening.<note> Hebr. betweene the two euenings.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they shall
take of the blood and strike it on the two side postes, and on the
vpper doore poste, of the houses wherin they shall eate it.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they shall eat
the flesh in that night roste with fire, and vnleauened bread, and
with bitter herbes they shall eate it.</ab>
<ab n="9">Eate not of it
raw, nor sodden at all with water, but roste with fire: his head,
with his legs, and with the purtenance thereof.</ab>
<ab n="10">And ye shall let
nothing of it remaine vntill the morning: and that which remaineth
of it vntill the morning, ye shall burne with fire.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And thus
shall ye eate it: with your loines girded, your shooes on your
feet, and your staffe in your hand: and ye shall eate it in haste:
it is the Lords Passeouer.</ab>
<ab n="12">For I will passe
through the land of Egypt this night, and will smite all the first
borne in the land of Egypt, both man &amp; beast, and against all
the gods of Egypt I will execute iudgement: I am the
Lord.<note> Or, princes.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the blood
shall be to you for a token vpon the houses where you are: and when
I see the blood, I will passe ouer you, and the plague shall not
bee vpon you to destroy you, when I smite the land of
Egypt.<note> Heb. for a destruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And this day
shall be vnto you for a memoriall: and you shall keepe in a feast
to the Lord, throughout your generations: you shall keepe it a
feast by an ordinance for euer.</ab>

<fw>The Passeouer is instituted.</fw>
<ab n="15">Seuen dayes shall
ye eate vnleauened bread, euen the first day yee shall put away
leauen out of your houses: For whosoeuer eateth leauened bread,
from the first day vntil the seuenth day, that soule shall be cut
off from Israel.</ab>
<ab n="16">And in the first
day there shalbe an holy conuocation, and in the seuenth day there
shall be an holy conuocation to you: no maner of worke shalbe done
in them, saue that which euery man must eate, that onely may bee
done of you.<note> Heb. soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And yee shall
obserue the feast of vnleauened bread: for in this selfe same day
haue I brought your armies out of the land of Egypt; therefore
shall ye obserue this day in your generations, by an ordinance for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ In the
first moneth, on the fourteenth day of the moneth at euen, ye shall
eate vnleauened bread vntill the one and twentieth day of the
moneth at euen.<note> Leuit. 23. 5. num. 28. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Seuen dayes shall
there bee no leauen found in your houses: for whosoeuer eateth that
which is leauened, euen that soule shall be cut off from the
congregation of Israel, whether he be a stranger, or borne in the
land.</ab>
<ab n="20">Yee shall eate
nothing leauened: in all your habitations shall ye eate vnleauened
bread.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then Moses
called for all the Elders of Israel, and said vnto them; Draw out
and take you a lambe, according to your families, and kill the
Passeouer.<note> Or, kidde.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And ye shall take
a bunch of hysope, and dip it in the blood that is in the bason,
and strike the lintel and the two side postes with the blood that
is in the bason: and none of you shall goe out at the doore of his
house, vntill the morning.<note> Heb.11. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For the Lord wil
passe through to smite the Egyptians: and when hee seeth the blood
vpon the lintel, and on the two side-postes, the Lord will passe
ouer the doore, and will not suffer the destroyer to come in vnto
your houses to smite you.</ab>
<ab n="24">And ye shall
obserue this thing for an ordinance to thee, and to thy sonnes for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="25">And it shall come
to passe when yee bee come to the land, which the Lord will giue
you, according as he hath promised, that ye shall keepe this
seruice.</ab>

<fw>First-borne slaine.</fw>
<ab n="26">And it shall come
to passe, when your children shall say vnto you, What meane you by
this seruice?<note> Iosh.4.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">That ye shall
say, It is the sacrifice of the Lords Passeouer, who passed ouer
the houses of the children of Israel in Egypt, when he smote the
Egyptians, and deliuered our houses. And the people bowed the head,
and worshipped.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the children
of Israel went away, and did as the Lord had commanded Moses and
Aaron, so did they.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And it
came to passe that at midnight the Lord smote all the first borne
in the land of Egypt, from the first borne of Pharaoh that sate on
his throne, vnto the first borne of the captiue that was in the
dungeon, and all the first borne of cattell.<note> Chap. 11. 4. , Wisd.18. 11. , Heb. house of the pit.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Pharaoh rose
vp in the night, hee and all his seruants, and all the Egyptians;
and there was a great cry in Egypt: for there was not a house,
where there was not one dead.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And hee
called for Moses and Aaron by night, and said, Rise vp, and get you
forth from amongst my people, both you and the children of Israel:
and goe, serue the Lord, as ye haue said.</ab>
<ab n="32">Also take your
flockes and your heards, as ye haue said: and bee gone, and blesse
me also.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the Egyptians
were vrgent vpon the people that they might send them out of the
land in haste: for they said, We be all dead men.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the people
tooke their dough before it was leauened, their kneading troughes
beeing bound vp in their clothes vpon their shoulders.<note> Or, dough.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And the children
of Israel did according to the word of Moses: and they borrowed of
the Egyptians iewels of siluer, and iewels of gold, and
raiment.<note> Chap. 3. 22. and 11. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And the Lord gaue
the people fauour in the sight of the Egyptians, so that they lent
vnto them such things as they required: and they spoiled the
Egyptians.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ And the
children of Israel iourneyed from Rameses to Succoth, about sixe
hundred thousand on foote that were men, beside
children.<note> Num.33. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And a mixed
multitude went vp also with them, and flocks and heards, euen very
much cattell.<note> Hebr. a great mixture.</note></ab>

<fw>The Passeouer must be
remembred.</fw>
<ab n="39">And they baked
vnleauened cakes of the dough, which they brought forth out of
Egypt; for it was not leauened: because they were thrust out of
Egypt, and could not tarry, neither had they prepared for
themselues any victuall.</ab>
<ab n="40">¶ Now the
soiourning of the children of Israel, who dwelt in Egypt, was foure
hundred and thirtie yeeres.<note> Gen. 15. 13. acts 7.6 gal. 3.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And it came to
passe at the end of the foure hundred and thirtie yeeres, euen the
selfe same day it came to passe, that all the hosts of the Lord
went out from the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="42">It is a night to
be much obserued vnto the Lord, for bringing them out from the land
of Egypt: This is that night of the Lord to be obserued of all the
children of Israel, in their generations.<note> Hebr. a night of obseruations.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses and Aaron, This is the ordinance of the
Passeouer: there shall no stranger eate thereof.</ab>
<ab n="44">But euery mans
seruant that is bought for money, when thou hast circumcised him,
then shall he eate thereof.</ab>
<ab n="45">A forreiner, and
an hired seruant shall not eate thereof.</ab>
<ab n="46">In one house
shall it be eaten, thou shalt not carie foorth ought of the flesh
abroad out of the house, neither shall ye breake a bone
thereof.<note> Numb. 9. 12. , Ioh. 19. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">All the
Congregation of Israel shall keepe it.<note> Heb. doe it.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And when a
stranger shall soiourne with thee, and will keepe the Passeouer to
the Lord, let all his males be circumcised, and then let him come
neere, and keepe it: and he shall be as one that is borne in the
land: for no vncircumcised person shall eate thereof.</ab>
<ab n="49">One law shall be
to him that is home-borne, and vnto the stranger that soiourneth
among you.</ab>
<ab n="50">Thus did all the
children of Israel: as the Lord commanded Moses and Aaron, so did
they.</ab>
<ab n="51">And it came to
passe the selfe same day, that the Lord did bring the children of
Israel out of the land of Egypt, by their armies.</ab>



</div>