<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Iethro bringeth to Moses his wife
and two sonnes. 7 Moses entertaineth him. 13 Iethros counsell is
accepted. 27 Iethro departeth.</head>

<ab n="1">When Iethro the
Priest of Midian, Moses father in law, heard of all that God had
done for Moses, and for Israel his people, and that the Lord had
brought Israel out of Egypt:<note> Chap. 2. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then Iethro Moses
father in law tooke Zipporah Moses wife, after he had sent her
backe,</ab>
<ab n="3">And her two
sonnes, of which the name of the one was Gershom: for he said, I
haue bene an alien in a strange land.<note> Chap. 2. 22. , That is, A stranger there.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the name of
the other was Eliezer: for the God of my father, said he, was mine
helpe, and deliuered me from the sword of Pharaoh.<note> That is, my God is an helpe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Iethro Moses
father in law came with his sonnes and his wife vnto Moses into the
wildernes, where he encamped at the mount of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he said vnto
Moses, I thy father in law Iethro am come vnto thee, and thy wife,
and her two sonnes with her.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And Moses
went out to meete his father in law, and did obeysance, and kissed
him: and they asked each other of their welfare, and they came into
the tent.<note> Heb. peace.</note></ab>

<fw>Iethros counsell to Moses,
obeyed.</fw>
<ab n="8">And Moses told his
father in law, all that the Lord had done vnto Pharaoh, and to the
Egyptians for Israels sake, and all the trauaile that had come vpon
them by the way, and how the Lord deliuered them.<note> Heb. found them.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Iethro
reioyced for all the goodnesse which the Lord had doue to Israel:
whom he had deliuered out of the hand of the Egyptians.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Iethro said,
Blessed be the Lord, who hath deliuered you out of the hand of the
Egyptians, and out of the hand of Pharaoh, who hath deliuered the
people from vnder the hand of the Egyptians.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now I know that
the Lord is greater then all gods: for in the thing wherein they
dealt proudly, hee was aboue them.<note> Chap.1. 10, 16, 22. and 5. 7. and 14. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And Iethro, Moses
father in law, tooke a burnt offering and sacrifices for God: and
Aaron came, and all the Elders of Israel, to eat bread with Moses
father in law before God.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And it
came to passe on the morrow, that Moses sate to iudge the people:
and the people stood by Moses, from the morning vnto the
euening.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when Moses
father in law saw all that he did to the people, he said, What is
this thing that thou doest to the people? Why sittest thou thy
selfe alone, and all the people stand by thee from morning vnto
euen?</ab>
<ab n="15">And Moses said
vnto his father in law, Because the people come vnto me to enquire
of God.</ab>
<ab n="16">When they haue a
matter, they come vnto mee, and I iudge betweene one and another,
and I doe make them know the statutes of God and his
Lawes.<note> Hebr. a man and his fellow.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Moses father
in law saide vnto him, The thing that thou doest, is not
good.</ab>
<ab n="18">Thou wilt surely
weare away, both thou, and this people that is with thee: for this
thing is too heauy for thee; thou art not able to performe it thy
selfe alone.<note> Hebr. Fading thou wilt fade. , Deut. 1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Hearken now vnto
my voyce, I will giue thee counsell, and God shall be with thee: Be
thou for the people to Godward, that thou mayest bring the causes
vnto God:</ab>
<ab n="20">And thou shalt
teach them ordinances and lawes, and shalt shew them the way
wherein they must walke, and the worke that they must doe.</ab>

<fw>Iethros counsell to Moses,
obeyed.</fw>
<ab n="21">Moreouer thou
shalt prouide out of all the people able men, such as feare God,
men of trueth, hating couetousnesse, and place such ouer them, to
bee rulers of thousands, and rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties,
and rulers of tennes.</ab>
<ab n="22">And let them
iudge the people at all seasons: and it shall bee that euery great
matter they shall bring vnto thee, but euery small matter they shal
iudge: so shall it be easier for thy selfe, and they shall beare
the burden with thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">If thou shalt doe
this thing, and God command thee so, then thou shalt bee able to
endure, and all this people shall also goe to their place in
peace.</ab>
<ab n="24">So Moses
hearkened to the voice of his father in law, and did all that he
had said.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Moses chose
able men out of all Israel, and made them heads ouer the people,
rulers of thousands, rulers of hundreds, rulers of fifties, and
rulers of tennes.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they iudged
the people at all seasons: the hard causes they brought vnto Moses,
but euery small matter they iudged themselues.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And Moses
let his father in law depart, and he went his way into his owne
land.</ab>



</div>