<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Moses is called vp into the
Mountaine. 3 The people promise obedience. 4 Moses buildeth an
Altar, and twelue pillars. 6 Hee sprinkleth the blood of the
Couenant. 9 The glory of God appeareth. 14 Aaron and Hur haue the
charge of the people. 15 Moses goeth into the Mountaine, where he
continueth 40. dayes, and 40. nights.</head>

<ab n="1">And hee said vnto
Moses, Come vp vnto þe Lord,thou, and Aaron, Nadab
and Abihu, and seuentie of the Elders of Israel: and worship ye a
farre off.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Moses alone
shall come neere the Lord: but they shall not come nigh, neither
shall the people goe vp with him.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And Moses
came and told the people all the words of the Lord, and all the
iudgements: and all the people answered with one voyce, and said,
All the words which the Lord hath said, will we doe.<note> Chap. 19. 8. and 24 3. 7. deut. 5. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Moses wrote
all the words of the Lord, and rose vp early in the morning, and
builded an Altar vnder the hill, and twelue pillars, according to
the twelue tribes of Israel.</ab>

<fw>The people promise.</fw>
<ab n="5">And he sent yong
men of the children of Israel, which offered burnt offerings, and
sacrificed peace offerings of oxen, vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses tooke
halfe of the blood, and put it in basons, and halfe of the blood he
sprinkled on the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he tooke the
booke of the couenant, and read in the audience of the people: and
they saide, All that the Lord hath said, will we doe, and be
obedient.<note> Verse 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Moses tooke
the blood and sprinkled it on the people, and said, Behold the
blood of the Couenant which the Lord hath made with you, concerning
all these words.<note> 1.Pet. 1. 2. Hebr.9. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then went
vp Moses and Aaron, Nadab and Abihu, and seuenty of the Elders of
Israel:</ab>
<ab n="10">And they saw the
God of Israel: and there was vnder his feet, as it were a paued
worke of a Saphire stone, and as it were the body of heauen in his
clearenesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">And vpon the
Nobles of the children of Israel he layd not his hand: also they
saw God, and did eate and drinke.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
Lord sayd vnto Moses, Come vp to me into the mount, and be there,
and I will giue thee Tables of stone, and a Law, and Commandements
which I haue written, that thou mayest teach them.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Moses rose
vp, and his minister Ioshua: and Moses went vp into the mount of
God.</ab>
<ab n="14">And hee saide
vnto the Elders, Tary ye here for vs, vntill wee come againe vnto
you: and behold, Aaron and Hur are with you: If any man haue any
matters to doe, let him come vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Moses went vp
into the Mount, and a cloud couered the Mount.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the glory of
the Lord abode vpon mount Sinai, and the cloud couered it sixe
dayes: and the seuenth day hee called vnto Moses out of the midst
of the cloud.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the sight of
the glory of the Lord was like deuouring fire, on the top of the
mount, in the eyes of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Moses went
into the midst of the cloud, and gate him vp into the mount: and
Moses was in the mount forty dayes, and forty nights.<note> Chap. 34. 28. deut. 9. 9.</note></ab>



</div>