<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Of slander and false witnesse. 3.6
Of iustice. 4 Of charitablenesse. 10 Of the yeere of rest. 12 Of
the Sabbath. 13 Of idolatrie. 14 Of the three feasts. 18 Of the
blood and the fat of the sacrifice. 20 An Angel is promised, with a
blessing, if they obey him.</head>

<ab n="1">Thou shalt not
raise a false report: put not thine hand with the wicked to bee an
vnrighteous witnesse.<note> Or, receiue</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ Thou shalt
not follow a multitude to doe euill: neither shalt thou speake in a
cause, to decline after many, to wrest iudgement:<note> Heb. answere.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Neither
shalt thou countenance a poore man in his cause.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ If thou
meete thine enemies oxe or his asse going astray, thou shalt surely
bring it backe to him againe.</ab>
<ab n="5">If thou see the
asse of him that hateth thee, lying vnder his burden, and wouldest
forbeare to helpe him, thou shalt surely helpe with
him.<note> Deu. 22.4 , Or, wilt thou cease to helpe him? or, &amp; wouldest cease to leaue thy businesse for him: thou shalt surely leaue it to ioyne with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou shalt not
wrest the iudgement of thy poore in his cause.</ab>
<ab n="7">Keepe thee farre
from a false matter: and the innocent and righteous slay thou not:
for I will not iustifie the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And thou
shalt take no gift: for the gift blindeth the wise, and peruerteth
the words of the righteous.<note> Deut. 16. 19. ecclus. 20.28. , Hebr. the seeing.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Also thou
shalt not oppresse a stranger: for yee know the heart of a
stranger, seeing yee were strangers in the land of
Egypt.<note> Heb. soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And sixe yeres
thou shalt sow thy land, and shalt gather in the fruites
thereof:<note> Leuit. 25. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But the seuenth
yeere thou shalt let it rest, and lie still, that the poore of thy
people may eate, and what they leaue, the beasts of the field shall
eate. In like maner thou shalt deale with thy vineyard, and with
thy oliue yard.<note> Or, oliue trees.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Sixe dayes thou
shalt doe thy worke, and on the seuenth day thou shalt rest: that
thine oxe and thine asse may rest, and the sonne of thy handmayd,
&amp; the stranger may be refreshed.<note> Chap. 20. 8. deut. 5. 13. luke 13. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And in all things
that I haue said vnto you, be circumspect: and make no mention of
the names of other gods, neither let it be heard out of thy
mouth.</ab>

<fw>Three solemne feasts.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ Three
times thou shalt keepe a feast vnto me in the yeere.<note> Deut. 16. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thou shalt keepe
the feast of vnleauened bread: thou shalt eate vnleauened bread
seuen daies, as I commanded thee in the time appointed of the
moneth Abib: for in it thou camest out from Egypt: and none shall
appeare before me emptie:<note> Chap. 13.3 &amp; 34.18. , Deut. 16. 16 ecclus. 35. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the feast of
haruest, the first fruits of thy labours, which thou hast sowen in
the field: and the feast of ingathering which is in the end of the
yeere, when thou hast gathered in thy labours out of the
field.</ab>
<ab n="17">Three times in
the yeere all thy males shall appeare before the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="18">Thou shalt not
offer the blood of my sacrifice with leauened bread, neither shall
the fat of my sacrifice remaine vntill the morning.<note> Or, feast.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The first of the
first fruits of thy land thou shalt bring into the house of the
Lord thy God: thou shalt not seethe a kid in his mothers
milke.<note> Chap. 34. 26. deut. 14 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Behold, I
send an Angel before thee to keepe thee in the way, and to bring
thee into the place which I haue prepared.<note> Chap. 33. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Beware of him,
and obey his voice, prouoke him not: for he will not pardon your
transgressions: for my name is in him.</ab>
<ab n="22">But if thou shalt
indeed obey his voice, and doe all that I speake, then I wil be an
enemie vnto thine enemies, and an aduersarie vnto thine
aduersaries.<note> Or, I will afflict them that afflict thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For mine Angel
shall goe before thee, and bring thee in vnto the Amorites, and the
Hittites, and the Perizzites, and the Canaanites, the Hiuites, and
the Iebusites: and I will cut them off.<note> Chap. 33.2. , Iosh.24. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Thou shalt not
bow downe to their gods, nor serue them, nor doe after their
workes: but thou shalt vtterly ouerthrowe them, and quite breake
downe their images.<note> Deut. 7. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And yee shall
serue the Lord your God, and he shall blesse thy bread, and thy
water: and I will take sicknes away from the midst of thee.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ There
shall nothing cast their yong, nor bee barren in thy land: the
number of thy dayes I will fulfill.<note> Deut. 7. 14.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods promise.</fw>
<ab n="27">I will send my
feare before thee, and will destroy all the people to whom thou
shalt come, and I will make all thine enemies turne their backes
vnto thee.<note> Heb. necks</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And I will send
hornets before thee, which shall driue out the Hiuite, the
Canaanite, and the Hittite from before thee.<note> Iosh. 24. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">I will not driue
them out from before thee in one yeere, lest the land become
desolate, and the beast of the field multiply against thee.</ab>
<ab n="30">By little and
little I will driue them out from before thee, vntill thou be
increased and inherit the land.</ab>
<ab n="31">And I will set
thy bounds from the Red sea, euen vnto the sea of the Philistines,
and from the desert vnto the riuer: for I will deliuer the
inhabitants of the land into your hand: and thou shalt driue them
out before thee.</ab>
<ab n="32">Thou shalt make
no couenant with them, nor with their gods.<note> Chap. 34. 15. deut. 7. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">They shall not
dwell in thy land, lest they make thee sinne against me: for if
thou serue their gods, it will surely be a snare vnto
thee.<note> Deut. 7. 16. iosh.23. 13. iudg.2 3.</note></ab>



</div>