<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 The people come to Sinai. 3 Gods
message by Moses vnto the people out of the mount. 8 The peoples
answere returned againe. 10 The people are prepared against the
third day. 12 The mountaine must not be touched. 16 The fearefull
presence of God vpon the Mount.</head>

<ab n="1">In the third
moneth when the children of Israel were gone forth out of the land
of Egypt, the same day came they into the wildernesse of
Sinai.</ab>
<ab n="2">For they were
departed from Rephidim, and were come to the desert of Sinai, and
had pitched in the wildernesse, and there Israel camped before the
mount.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Moses went vp
vnto God: and the Lord called vnto him out of the mountaine,
saying, Thus shalt thou say to the house of Iacob, and tell the
children of Israel:<note> Acts 7.38</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Ye haue seene what
I did vnto the Egyptians, and how I bare you on Eagles wings, and
brought you vnto my selfe.<note> Deut. 29. 2.</note></ab>

<fw>peoples promise.</fw>
<ab n="5">Now therfore if ye
will obey my voice indeed, and keepe my couenant, then ye shall be
a peculiar treasure vnto me aboue all people: for all the earth is
mine.<note> Deut. 5.2. , Deut. 10.14. psal.24.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And ye shall be
vnto me a kingdome of Priestes, and an holy nation. These are the
wordes which thou shalt speake vnto the children of
Israel.<note> 1. Pet.2.9. reuel. 1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And Moses
came and called for the Elders of the people, and layd before their
faces all these wordes which the Lord commanded him.</ab>
<ab n="8">And all the people
answered together, and said, All that the Lord hath spoken, we will
doe. And Moses returned the wordes of the people vnto the
Lord.<note> Chap. 24.3,7. deut. 5.27. &amp; 26.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Loe, I come vnto thee in a thicke cloud, that the
people may heare when I speake with thee, and beleeue thee for
euer: And Moses told the wordes of the people vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Goe vnto the people, and sanctifie them to
day and to morrow, and let them wash their clothes.</ab>
<ab n="11">And be ready
against the thirde day: for the third day the Lord will come downe
in the sight of all the people, vpon mount Sinai.</ab>
<ab n="12">And thou shalt
set bounds vnto the people round about, saying, Take heed to your
selues, that ye goe not vp into the mount, or touch the border of
it: whosoeuer toucheth the mount, shall be surely put to
death.<note> Heb.12. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">There shall not a
hand touch it, but he shall surely be stoned or shot thorow,
whether it be beast, or man, it shall not liue: when the trumpet
soundeth long, they shall come vp to the mount.<note> Or, Cornet</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And Moses
went downe from the mount vnto the people, and sanctified the
people; and they washed their clothes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And hee said vnto
the people, Be ready against the third day: come not at your
wiues.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And it
came to passe on the third day in the morning, that there were
thunders and lightnings, and a thicke cloud vpon the mount, and the
voyce of the trumpet exceeding lowd, so that all the people that
was in the campe, trembled.</ab>

<fw>The tenne Commandements.</fw>
<ab n="17">And Moses brought
foorth the people out of the campe to meete with God, and they
stood at the nether part of the mount.</ab>
<ab n="18">And mount Sinai
was altogether on a smoke, because the Lord descended vpon it in
fire: and the smoke thereof ascended as the smoke of a furnace, and
the whole mount quaked greatly.<note> Deut.4. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And when the
voyce of the trumpet sounded long, and waxed lowder and lowder,
Moses spake, and God answered him by a voyce.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord came
downe vpon mount Sinai, on the top of the mount: and the Lord
called Moses vp to the top of the mount, and Moses went vp.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Goe downe, charge the people, lest they breake thorow
vnto the Lord to gaze, and many of them perish.<note> Heb. contest.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And let the
Priestes also which come neere to the Lord, sanctifie themselues,
lest the Lord breake foorth vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Moses said
vnto the Lord, The people cannot come vp to mount Sinai: for thou
chargedst vs, saying, Set bounds about the mount, and sanctifie
it.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the Lord said
vnto him, Away, get thee downe, and thou shalt come vp, thou, and
Aaron with thee: but let not the Priestes and the people breake
through, to come vp vnto the Lord, lest hee breake foorth vpon
them.</ab>
<ab n="25">So Moses went
downe vnto the people, and spake vnto them.</ab>



</div>