<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 The Lord refuseth to goe as he had
promised with the people. 4 The people murmure thereat. 7 The
Tabernacle is remoued out of the Campe. 9 The Lord talketh
familiarly with Moses. 12 Moses desireth to see the Glory of
God.</head>


<fw>He talketh with God.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Depart, and goe vp hence, thou and the people which
thou hast brought vp out of the land of Egypt, vnto the land which
I sware vnto Abraham, to Isaac, &amp; to Iacob, saying, Unto thy
seed will I giue it.<note> Gene. 12. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And I will send an
Angel before thee, and I will driue out the Canaanite, the Amorite,
and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, the Hiuite, and the
Iebusite:<note> Deut. 7. 22. iosh. 24. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Unto a land
flowing with milke and hony: For I will not goe vp in the midst of
thee: for thou art a stiffenecked people, lest I consume thee in
the way.<note> Chap. 32. 9. deut. 9. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And when
the people heard these euill tidings, they mourned: and no man did
put on him his ornaments.</ab>
<ab n="5">For the Lord had
saide vnto Moses, Say vnto the children of Israel, Ye are a
stiffenecked people: I wil come vp into the midst of thee in a
moment, &amp; consume thee: Therefore now put off thy ornaments
from thee, that I may know what to doe vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the children
of Israel stript themselues of their ornaments, by the mount
Horeb.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Moses tooke
the Tabernacle, &amp; pitched it without the campe, a farre off
from the campe, and called it the Tabernacle of the Congregation:
And it came to passe, that euery one which sought the Lord, went
out vnto the Tabernacle of the Congregation, which was without the
campe.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came to
passe when Moses went out vnto the Tabernacle, that all the people
rose vp, and stood euery man at his tent doore, and looked after
Moses, vntill he was gone into the Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="9">And it came to
passe as Moses entred into the Tabernacle, the cloudy pillar
descended, and stood at the doore of the Tabernacle, and the Lord
talked with Moses.</ab>
<ab n="10">And all the
people saw the cloudy pillar stand at the Tabernacle doore: and all
the people rose vp, and worshipped euery man in his tent
doore.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses face to face, as a man speaketh vnto his friend.
And he turned againe into the campe, but his seruant Ioshua the
sonne of Nun, a yong man, departed not out of the
Tabernacle.</ab>

<fw>God not seene.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And Moses
saide vnto the Lord, See, thou sayest vnto mee, Bring vp this
people, and thou hast not let mee know whome thou wilt send with
me. Yet thou hast said, I knowe thee by name, and thou hast also
found grace in my sight.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now therefore, I
pray thee, If I haue found grace in thy sight, shewe mee now thy
way that I may know thee, that I may find grace in thy sight: and
consider that this nation is thy people.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he said, My
presence shall go with thee, and I will giue thee rest.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he said vnto
him, If thy presence goe not with mee, carie vs not vp
hence.</ab>
<ab n="16">For wherein shall
it bee knowen here, that I and thy people haue found grace in thy
sight? is it not in that thou goest with vs? So shall we be
separated, I and thy people, from all the people that are vpon the
face of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, I will doe this thing also that thou hast spoken: for
thou hast found grace in my sight, and I know thee by name.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he said, I
beseech thee, shew me thy glory.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he said, I
will make all my goodnesse passe before thee, and I will proclaime
the name of the Lord before thee: and will bee gracious to whom I
wil be gracious, and wil shew mercie on whom I will shew
mercie.<note> Rom. 9. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And he said, Thou
canst not see my face: for there shall no man see mee, and
liue.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the Lord
said, Beholde, there is a place by mee, and thou shalt stand vpon a
rocke.</ab>
<ab n="22">And it shall come
to passe, while my glory passeth by, that I will put thee in a
clift of the rocke, and will couer thee with my hand, while I passe
by.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I wil take
away mine hand, and thou shalt see my backe parts: but my face
shall not be seene.</ab>



</div>