<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-40-40-Leviticus.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 The Tabernacle is commanded to be
reared, 9 and anointed. 13 Aaron and his sonnes to be sanctified.
16 Moses performeth all things accordingly. 34 A cloude couereth
the Tabernacle.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">On the first day
of the first moneth shalt thou set vp the Tabernacle of the Tent of
the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thou shalt put
therein the Arke of the Testimonie, and couer the Arke with the
Uaile:</ab>

<fw>The Tabernacle is reared vp.</fw>
<ab n="4">And thou shalt
bring in the Table, and set in order the things that are to be set
in order vpon it, and thou shalt bring in the Candlesticke, and
light the lampes thereof.<note> Chap.26. 35. , Heb. the order thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And thou shalt set
the Altar of gold for the incense before the Arke of the
Testimonie, and put the hanging of the doore to the
Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="6">And thou shalt set
the Altar of the burnt offering, before the doore of the Tabernacle
of the Tent of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thou shalt set
the Lauer betweene the Tent of the Congregation and the Altar, and
shalt put water therein.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou shalt set
vp the Court round about, and hang vp the hanging at the Court
gate.</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou shalt
take the annoynting oyle, and annoynt the Tabernacle and all that
is therein, and shalt hallow it, and all the vessels thereof: and
it shalbe holy.</ab>
<ab n="10">Aud thou shalt
annoynt the Altar of the burnt offering, and all his vessels, and
sanctifie the Altar: and it shalbe an Altar most Holy.<note> Heb. Holines of Holinesses.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And thou shalt
annoynt the Lauer and his foot, and sanctifie it.</ab>
<ab n="12">And thou shalt
bring Aaron and his sonnes vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, and wash them with water.</ab>
<ab n="13">And thou shalt
put vpon Aaron the holy garments, and anoynt him, and sanctifie
him, that he may minister vnto me in the Priests office.</ab>
<ab n="14">And thou shalt
bring his sonnes, and clothe them with coats.</ab>
<ab n="15">And thou shalt
anoynt them, as thou didst anoynt their father, that they may
minister vnto mee in the Priests office: For their anoynting shall
surely be an euerlasting Priesthood, throughout their
generations.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus did Moses:
according to all that the Lord commanded him, so did he.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And it
came to passe in the first moneth, in the second yeere, on the
first day of the moneth, that the Tabernacle was reared
vp.<note> Num.7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Moses reared
vp the Tabernacle, and fastened his sockets, and set vp the boards
thereof, and put in the barres thereof, and reared vp his
pillars.</ab>

<fw>The Tabernacle is reared vp.</fw>
<ab n="19">And he spread
abroad the tent ouer the Tabernacle, and put the couering of the
Tent aboue vpon it, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And he
tooke and put the testimony into the Arke, and set the staues on
the Arke, and put the Mercie-seat aboue vpon the Arke.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he brought
the Arke into the Tabernacle, and set vp the Uaile of the couering,
and couered the Arke of the Testimony, as the Lord commanded
Moses.<note> Chap. 35. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And hee
put the Table in the Tent of the Congregation, vpon the side of the
Tabernacle Northwaed, without the Uaile.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he set the
bread in order vpon it, before the Lord, as the Lord had commanded
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And he put
the candlesticke in the Tent of the Congregation, ouer against the
Table, on the side of the Tabernacle Southward.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he lighted
the lampes before the Lord, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And he put
the golden Altar in the Tent of the Congregation, before the
Uaile.</ab>
<ab n="27">And he burnt
sweet incense thereon, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And hee
set vp the hanging, at the doore of the Tabernacle.</ab>

<fw>The Tabernacle is reared vp.</fw>
<ab n="29">And he put the
Altar of burnt offering by the doore of the Tabernacle of the Tent
of the Congregation, and offered vpon it the burnt offering, and
the meat offring, as the Lord commanded Moses.<note> Exod.30. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And he set
the Lauer betweene the Tent of the Congregation and the Altar,
&amp; put water there, to wash withall.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Moses, and
Aaron and his sonnes, washed their hands, and their feet
thereat.</ab>
<ab n="32">When they went
into the Tent of the Congregation, and when they came neere vnto
the Altar, they washed, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="33">And hee reared vp
the Court round about the Tabernacle, and the Altar, &amp; set vp
the hanging of the Court gate: so Moses finished the worke.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Then a
cloud couered the Tent of the Congregation, and the glory of the
Lord filled the Tabernacle.<note> Numb.9. 15. 1.king. 8.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And Moses was not
able to enter into the Tent of the Congregation, because the cloud
abode thereon, and the glory of the Lord filled the
Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="36">And when the
cloud was taken vp from ouer the Tabernacle, the children of Israel
went onward in all their iourneys:<note> Hebr. iourneyed.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">But if the cloud
were not taken vp, then they iourneyed not, till the day that it
was taken vp.</ab>
<ab n="38">For the cloud of
the Lord was vpon the Tabernacle by day, and fire was on it by
night, in the sight of all the house of Israel, throughout all
their iourneys.</ab>



</div>