<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Of theft. 5 Of dammage. 7 Of
trespasses. 14. Of borrowing. 16 Of fornication. 18 Of witchcraft.
19 Of bestialitie. 20 Of idolatrie. 21 Of strangers, widowes, and
fatherlesse. 25 Of vsurie. 26 Of pledges. 28 Of reuerence to
Magistrates. 29 Of the first fruits.</head>


<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="1">If a man shal
steale an oxe, or a sheepe, and kill it, or sell it; he shall
restore fiue oxen for an oxe, and foure sheepe for a
sheepe.<note> Or, goate. , 2. Sam. 12. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ If a thiefe
bee found breaking vp, and be smitten that he die, there shal no
blood be shed for him.</ab>
<ab n="3">If the Sunne be
risen vpon him, there shall be blood shed for him: for hee should
make full restitution: if he haue nothing, then he shall bee sold
for his theft.</ab>
<ab n="4">If the theft be
certainely found in his hand aliue, whether it bee oxe or asse, or
sheepe, he shall restore double.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ If a man
shall cause a field or vineyard to be eaten, and shall put in his
beast, and shall feede in another mans field: of the best of his
owne field, and of the best of his owne vineyard shall he make
restitution.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ If fire
breake out, and catch in thornes, so that the stackes of corne, or
the standing corne, or the field be consumed therewith; hee that
kindled the fire, shall surely make restitution.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ If a man
shal deliuer vnto his neighbour money or stuffe to keepe, and it be
stollen out of the mans house; if the thiefe be found, let him pay
double.</ab>
<ab n="8">If the thiefe be
not found, then the master of the house shall be brought vnto the
Iudges, to see whether he haue put his hande vnto his neighbours
goods.</ab>
<ab n="9">For all maner of
trespasse, whether it be for oxe, for asse, for sheepe, for
raiment, or for any maner of lost thing, which another challengeth
to be his: the cause of both parties shall come before the Iudges,
and whome the Iudges shall condemne, he shall pay double vnto his
neighbour.</ab>
<ab n="10">If a man deliuer
vnto his neighbour an asse, or an oxe, or a sheepe, or any beast to
keepe, and it die, or be hurt, or driuen away, no man seeing
it,</ab>
<ab n="11">Then shall an
othe of the Lord be betweene them both, that hee hath not put his
hand vnto his neighbours goods: and the owner of it shall accept
thereof, and he shall not make it good.</ab>
<ab n="12">And if it be
stollen from him, he shall make restitution vnto the owner
thereof.<note> Gene. 31. 39.</note></ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="13">If it be torne in
pieces, then let him bring it for witnesse, and hee shall not make
good that which was torne.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And if a
man borrowe ought of his neighbour, and it be hurt, or die, the
owner thereof being not with it, he shall surely make it
good.</ab>
<ab n="15">But if the owner
thereof be with it, he shall not make it good: If it bee an hired
thing, it came for his hire.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And if a
man entice a maide that is not betrothed, and lie with her, he
shall surely endow her to be his wife.<note> Deut. 22. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">If her father
vtterly refuse to giue her vnto him, he shall pay money according
to the dowrie of virgins.<note> Hel. weigh</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Thou shalt
not suffer a witch to liue.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Whosoeuer
lieth with a beast, shall surely be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Hee that
sacrificeth vnto any god saue vnto the Lord onely, hee shall be
vtterly destroyed.<note> Deut. 13. 13, 14, 15. 1. mac. 2. 24</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Thou shalt
neither vexe a stranger, nor oppresse him: for ye were strangers in
the land of Egypt.<note> Leuit. 19. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Yee shall
not afflict any widow, or fatherlesse child.<note> Zac. 7.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">If thou afflict
them in any wise, and they crie at all vnto mee, I will surely
heare their crie.</ab>
<ab n="24">And my wrath
shall waxe hote, and I will kill you with the sword: and your wiues
shall be widowes, and your children fatherlesse.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ If thou
lend money to any of my people that is poore by thee, thou shalt
not be to him as an vsurer, neither shalt thou lay vpon him
vsurie.<note> Leuit. 25. 37. deut. 23 19. psal. 15. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">If thou at all
take thy neighbors raiment to pledge, thou shalt deliuer it vnto
him by that the sun goeth downe.</ab>
<ab n="27">For that is his
couering onely, it is his raiment for his skinne: wherein shal he
sleepe? and it shal come to passe, when he crieth vnto mee, that I
will heare: for I am gracious.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Thou shalt
not reuile the Gods, nor curse the ruler of thy people.<note> Acts 23.5 , Or, Iudges</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Thou shalt
not delay to offer the first of thy ripe fruits, and of thy
liquors: the first borne of thy sonnes shalt thou giue vnto
me.<note> Heb. thy fulnesse. , Heb. Teare , Chap. 13. 2, 12. &amp; 34. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Likewise shalt
thou do with thine oxen, and with thy sheepe: seuen dayes it shall
be with his damme, on the eight day thou shalt giue it me.</ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ And ye
shall be holy men vnto me: neither shall ye eate any flesh that is
torne of beasts in the field: yee shall cast it to the
dogs.<note> Leuit.22. 8. ezek.44. 31.</note></ab>



</div>