<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-31-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 Bezaleel and Aholiab are called
and made meet for the worke of the Tabernacle. 12 The obseruation
of the Sabbath is againe commanded. 18 Moses receiueth the two
Tables.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">See, I haue called
by name, Bezaleel the sonne of Uri, the sonne of Hur, of the tribe
of Iudah:<note> 1. Chron. 2.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And I haue filled
him with the Spirit of God, in wisedome, and in vnderstanding, and
in knowledge, and in all maner of workemanship,</ab>
<ab n="4">To deuise cunning
workes, to worke in golde, and in siluer, and in brasse,</ab>
<ab n="5">And in cutting of
stones, to set them, and in caruing of timber, to worke in all
maner of workemanship.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I, behold, I
haue giuen with him, Aholiab the sonne of Ahisamach, of the tribe
of Dan, and in the hearts of all that are wise hearted I haue put
wisedome, that they may make all that I haue commanded
thee:</ab>
<ab n="7">The Tabernacle of
the Congregation, and the Arke of the Testimony, and the
Mercie-seat that is thereupon, &amp; all the furniture of the
Tabernacle:<note> Heb. vessels</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the Table, and
his furniture, and the pure Candlesticke, with all his furniture,
and the Altar of incense:</ab>

<fw>Bezaleel and Aholiab called.</fw>
<ab n="9">And the Altar of
burnt offering, with all his furniture, and the Lauer and his
foote:</ab>
<ab n="10">And the clothes
of seruice, and the holy garments for Aaron the Priest, and the
garments of his sonnes, to minister in the Priests office:</ab>
<ab n="11">And the anointing
oyle, and sweet incense for the Holy place: according to all that I
haue commanded thee, shall they doe.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Speake thou also
vnto the children of Israel, saying, Uerely my Sabbaths ye shall
keepe: for it is a signe betweene me and you, throughout your
generations, that ye may know that I am the Lord, that doth
sanctifie you.</ab>
<ab n="14">Yee shall keepe
the Sabbath therefore: for it is holy vnto you: Euery one that
defileth it, shall surely be put to death: for whosoeuer doth any
worke therein, that soule shall be cut off from amongst his
people.<note> Chap. 20. 8. deut. 5. 1 2. ezek. 20, 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Sixe dayes may
worke bee done, but in the seuenth is the Sabbath of rest, holy to
the Lord: whosoeuer doth any worke in the Sabbath day, he shall
surely be put to death.<note> Heb. holilinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Wherefore the
children of Israel shall keepe the Sabbath, to obserue the Sabbath
throughout their generations, for a perpetuall couenant.</ab>
<ab n="17">It is a signe
betweene me and the children of Israel for euer: for in sixe dayes
the Lord made heauen and earth, and on the seuenth day he rested,
and was refreshed.<note> Gen. 1.31 and 2.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And he
gaue vnto Moses, when hee had made an end of communing with him
vpon mount Sinai, two tables of Testimonie, tables of stone,
written with the finger of God.<note> Deut. 9. 10.</note></ab>



</div>