<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 The Tables are renued. 5 The Name
of the Lord proclaimed. 8 Moses intreateth God to go with them. 10
God maketh a couenant with them, repeating certaine dueties of the
first Table. 28 Moses after fourtie dayes in the Mount commeth
downe with the Tables. 29 His face shineth, and he couereth it with
a vaile.</head>


<fw>Two new Tables.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Hew thee two Tables of stone, like vnto the first: and
I will write vpon these Tables, the words that were in the first
Tables which thou brakest.<note> Deut. 10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And be ready in
the morning, and come vp in the morning vnto mount Sinai, and
present thy selfe there to me, in the top of the mount.</ab>
<ab n="3">And no man shall
come vp with thee, neither let any man bee seene throughout all the
mount, neither let the flockes nor herds feede before that
mount.<note> Chap. 19. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And he
hewed two Tables of stone, like vnto the first, and Moses rose vp
earely in the morning, and went vp vnto mount Sinai, as the Lord
had commanded him, and tooke in his hand the two tables of
stone.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Lord
descended in the cloud, and stood with him there, and proclaimed
the Name of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Lord
passed by before him, and proclaimed, The Lord, The Lord God,
mercifull and gracious, long suffering, and abundant in goodnesse
and trueth,</ab>
<ab n="7">Keeping mercie for
thousands, forgiuing iniquitie and transgression and sinne, and
that will by no meanes cleere the guiltie, visiting the iniquitie
of the fathers vpon the children, and vpon the childrens children,
vnto the third and to the fourth generation.<note> Exod.20. 5. deut.5. 9. ierem. 32, 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Moses made
haste, and bowed his head toward the earth, and worshipped.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he said, If
now I haue found grace in thy sight, O Lord, let my Lord, I pray
thee, goe amongst vs, (for it is a stiffenecked people,) and pardon
our iniquitie, and our sinne, and take vs for thine
inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And he
said, Behold, I make a couenant: before all thy people, I wil doe
marueiles, such as haue not beene done in all the earth, nor in any
nation: and all the people amongst which thou art, shall see the
worke of the Lord: for it is a terrible thing that I will doe with
thee.<note> Deut.5.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Obserue thou that
which I command thee this day: Behold, I driue out before thee the
Amorite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and
the Hiuite, and the Iebusite.</ab>

<fw>Against idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="12">Take heed to thy
selfe, lest thou make a couenant with the inhabitants of the land
whither thou goest, lest it be for a snare in the midst of
thee.<note> Chap.23. 32. deut. 7. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But ye shall
destroy their altars, breake their images, and cut downe their
groues.<note> Hebr. statues.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For thou shalt
worship no other god: for the Lord, whose name is Ielous, is a
Ielous God:<note> Chap.20. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Lest thou make a
couenant with the inhabitants of the land, and they goe a whoring
after their gods, and doe sacrifice vnto their gods, and one call
thee, and thou eate of his sacrifice,</ab>
<ab n="16">And thou take of
their daughters vnto thy sonnes, and their daughters goe a whoring
after their gods, and make thy sonnes goe a whoring after their
gods.<note> 1.King. 11.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Thou shalt make
thee no molten gods.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ The feast
of vnleauened bread shalt thou keepe: Seuen dayes thou shalt eate
vnleauened bread, as I commanded thee in the time of the moneth
Abib: for in the moneth Abib thou camest out from
Egypt.<note> Chap. 23. 15. , Chap. 13. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">All that openeth
the matrixe is mine: and euery firstling amongst thy cattell,
whether oxe or sheepe, that is male.<note> Chap. 22. 29. ezech. 44.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But the firstling
of an Asse thou shalt redeeme with a lambe: and if thou redeeme him
not, then shalt thou breake his necke. All the first borne of thy
sonnes thou shalt redeeme: and none shall appeare before me
empty.<note> Or, kid. , Chap. 23. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Sixe dayes
thou shalt worke, but on the seuenth day thou shalt rest: in earing
time and in haruest thou shalt rest.<note> Chap. 23. 12. deut. 5. 12. luke 13. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And thou
shalt obserue the feast of weekes, of the first fruits of wheat
haruest, and the feast of ingathering at the yeeres
end.<note> Chap. 23. 16. , Hebr. reuolution of the yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Thrice in
the yeere shall all your men children appeare before the Lord God,
the God of Israel.<note> Chap. 23. 14.17. deu. 16.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For I will cast
out the nations before thee, and enlarge thy borders: neither shall
any man desire thy land, when thou shalt goe vp to appeare before
the Lord thy God, thrice in the yeere.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thou shalt not
offer the blood of my sacrifice with leauen, neither shall the
sacrifice of the feast of Passeouer be left vnto the
morning.<note> Chap. 23. 18.</note></ab>

<fw>Moses face shineth.</fw>
<ab n="26">The first of the
first fruits of thy land thou shalt bring vnto the house of the
Lord thy God. Thou shalt not seeth a kid in his mothers
milke.<note> Exod. 23. 19. deut. 14 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Write thou these words: for after the tenour of these
wordes, I haue made a couenant with thee, and with
Israel.<note> Deut. 4. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And hee was there
with the Lord forty dayes and forty nights: he did neither eat
bread, nor drinke water; and he wrote vpon the Tables the words of
the couenant, the ten Commandements.<note> Chap.24. 18. deut.9. 9. , Hebr. words.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And it
came to passe when Moses came downe from mount Sinai (with the two
Tables of Testimony in Moses hand, when hee came downe from the
mount) that Moses wist not that the skin of his face shone, while
he talked with him.</ab>
<ab n="30">And when Aaron
and all the children of Israel saw Moses, behold, the skinne of his
face shone, and they were afraid to come nigh him.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Moses called
vnto them, and Aaron and all the rulers of the Congregation
returned vnto him, and Moses talked with them.</ab>
<ab n="32">And afterward all
the children of Israel came nigh: and he gaue them in commandement
all that the Lord had spoken with him in mount Sinai.</ab>
<ab n="33">And till Moses
had done speaking with them, he put a vaile on his
face.<note> 2.Cor.3. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But when Moses
went in before the Lord to speake with him, hee tooke the vaile
off, vntill he came out: And hee came out and spake vnto the
children of Israel, that which he was commanded.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the children
of Israel saw the face of Moses, that the skinne of Moses face
shone: and Moses put the vaile vpon his face againe, vntill hee
went in to speake with him.</ab>



</div>