<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 The people in the absence of
Moses, cause Aaron to make a calfe. 7 God is angred thereby. 11 At
the intreatie of Moses he is appeased. 15 Moses commeth downe with
the Tables. 19 He breaketh them. 20 He destroyeth the calfe. 22
Aarons excuse for himselfe. 25 Moses causeth the Idolaters to bee
slaine. 30 He prayeth for the people.</head>


<fw>The molten calfe.</fw>
<ab n="1">And when the
people saw that Moses delayed to come downe out of the mount, the
people gathered themselues together vnto Aaron, and said vnto him,
Up, make vs gods which shall goe before vs: for as for this Moses,
the man that brought vs vp out of the land of Egypt, we wot not
what is become of him.<note> Acts. 7. 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Aaron saide
vnto them, Breake off the golden earerings which are in the eares
of your wiues, of your sonnes, and of your daughters, and bring
them vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="3">And all the people
brake off the golden earerings, which were in their eares, and
brought them vnto Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee receiued
them at their hand, and fashioned it with a grauing toole, after
hee had made it a molten calfe: and they said, These be thy gods, O
Israel, which brought thee vp out of the land of Egypt.<note> Psal. 106. 19. 1.king. 12. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And when Aaron saw
it, he built an altar before it, and Aaron made proclamation, and
said, To morrow is a feast to the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they rose vp
early on the morrow, and offered burnt offerings, and brought peace
offerings: and the people sate downe to eate and to drinke, and
rose vp to play.<note> 1. Cor. 10. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And the
Lord said vnto Moses, Goe, get thee downe: for thy people which
thou broughtest out of the land of Egypt, haue corrupted
themselues.<note> Deut. 9. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">They haue turned
aside quickly out of the way which I commaunded them: they haue
made them a molten Calfe, and haue worshipped it, and haue
sacrificed thereunto, and saide, These bee thy gods, O Israel,
which haue brought thee vp out of the land of Egypt.<note> Deut. 9. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, I haue seene this people, and behold, it is a
stiffenecked people.<note> Chap. 33.3. deut. 9. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Now therefore let
me alone, that my wrath may waxe hot against them, and that I may
consume them: and I will make of thee a great nation.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Moses
besought the Lord his God, and said, Lord, why doeth thy wrath ware
hot against thy people, which thou hast brought foorth out of the
land of Egypt, with great power, and with a mighty
hand?<note> Psal. 106, 25. , Hebr. the face of the Lord.</note></ab>

<fw>Tables broken.</fw>
<ab n="12">Wherefore should
the Egyptians speake and say, For mischiefe did he bring them out,
to slay them in the mountaines, &amp; to consume them from the face
of the earth? Turne from thy fierce wrath, and repent of this euill
against thy people.<note> Num. 14. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Remember Abraham,
Isaac, and Israel thy seruants, to whom thou swarest by thine owne
selfe, and saidest vnto them, I will multiply your seed as the
starres of heauen: and all this land that I haue spoken of, will I
giue vnto your seed, and they shall inherit it for
euer.<note> Gene. 12. 7. and 15.7. and 48.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the Lord
repented of the euill which he thought to doe vnto his
people.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And Moses
turned, and went downe from the Mount, and the two Tables of the
Testimony were in his hand: the Tables were written on both their
sides; on the one side, and on the other were they written.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Tables
were the worke of God; and the writing was the writing of God,
grauen vpon the Tables.<note> Chap. 31. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And when Ioshua
heard the noise of the people as they shouted, hee said vnto Moses,
There is a noise of warre in the campe.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he said, It
is not the voyce of them that shout for mastery, neither is it the
voyce of them that cry for being ouercome: but the noyse of them
that sing doe I heare.<note> Heb. weaknesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And it
came to passe, assoone as he came nigh vnto the campe, that he saw
the Calfe, and the dancing: and Moses anger waxed hot, and he cast
the Tables out of his hands, and brake them beneath the
mount.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he tooke the
Calfe which they had made, and burnt it in the fire, and ground it
to powder, and strawed it vpon the water, and made the children of
Israel drinke of it.<note> Deut. 9. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Moses said
vnto Aaron, What did this people vnto thee, that thou hast brought
so great a sinne vpon them?</ab>
<ab n="22">And Aaron said,
Let not the anger of my lord waxe hot: thou knowest the people,
that they are set on mischiefe.</ab>
<ab n="23">For they said
vnto me, Make vs gods which shall goe before vs: for as for this
Moses, the man that brought vs vp out of the land of Egypt, we wot
not what is become of him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And I said vnto
them, Whosoeuer hath any gold, let them breake it off: So they gaue
it mee: then I cast it into the fire, &amp; there came out this
Calfe.</ab>

<fw>Moses prayer: He talketh with
God.</fw>
<ab n="25">¶ And when
Moses saw that the people were naked, (for Aaron had made them
naked vnto their shame, amongst their enemies)<note> Hebr. those that rose vp against them.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Then Moses stood
in the gate of the campe, and saide, Who is on the Lords side? let
him come vnto mee. And all the sonnes of Leui gathered themselues
together vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="27">And hee said vnto
them, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Put euery man his sword by
his side, and go in and out from gate to gate throughout the campe,
and slay euery man his brother, and euery man his companion, and
euery man his neighbour.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the children
of Leui did according to the word of Moses; and there fell of the
people that day about three thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="29">For Moses had
said, Consecrate your selues to day to the Lord, euen euery man
vpon his sonne, and vpon his brother, that he may bestow vpon you a
blessing this day.<note> Or, And Moses said, Consecrate your selues to day to the Lord, because euery man hath bene against his sonne, and against his brother, &amp;c. , Hebr. fill your hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And it
came to passe on the morrow, that Moses said vnto the people, Ye
haue sinned a great sinne: And now I will goe vp vnto the Lord;
peraduenture I shall make an atonement for your sinne.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Moses
returned vnto the Lord, and said, Oh, this people haue sinned a
great sinne, and haue made them gods of gold.</ab>
<ab n="32">Yet now, if thou
wilt forgiue their sinne; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of
thy Booke, which thou hast written.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Whosoeuer hath sinned against me, him will I blot out
of my Booke.</ab>
<ab n="34">Therefore now
goe, leade the people vnto the place of which I haue spoken vnto
thee: Behold, mine Angel shall goe before thee; Neuerthelesse in
the day when I visit, I will visit their sinne vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the Lord
plagued the people, because they made the Calfe, which Aaron
made.</ab>



</div>