<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Frogges are sent. 8 Pharaoh sueth
to Moses, 12 and Moses by prayer remoueth them away. 16 The dust is
turned into lice, which the Magicians could not doe. 20 The swarmes
of flies. 25 Pharaoh inclineth to let the people goe, 32 but yet is
hardened.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, Goe vnto Pharaoh, and say vnto him; Thus sayeth
the Lord, Let my people goe, that they may serue me.</ab>
<ab n="2">And if thou
refuse to let them goe, beholde, I will smite all thy borders with
frogges.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the riuer
shall bring foorth frogges abundantly, which shall goe vp and come
into thine house, and into thy bed-chamber, and vpon thy bed, and
into the house of thy seruants, and vpon thy people, and into thine
ouens, and into thy kneading troughes.<note> Or, dough.</note></ab>

<fw>Plagues of frogges, of lyce, of
flyes,</fw>
<ab n="4">And the
frogges shall come vp both on thee, and vpon thy people, and vpon
all thy seruants.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And
the Lord spake vnto Moses; Say vnto Aaron, Stretch foorth thine
hand with thy rodde ouer the streames, ouer the riuers, and ouer
the ponds, and cause frogges to come vp vpon the land of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Aaron
stretched out his hand ouer the waters of Egypt, and the frogges
came vp, and couered the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the
Magicians did so with their inchantments, and brought vp frogges
vpon the land of Egypt.<note> Wisd. 17. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then
Pharaoh called for Moses, and Aaron, and said, Intreat the Lord,
that hee may take away the frogges from me, and from my people: and
I will let the people goe, that they may doe sacrifice vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Moses
saide vnto Pharaoh, Glory ouer mee: when shall I entreat for thee,
and for thy seruants, and for thy people, to destroy the frogges
from thee, and thy houses, that they may remaine in the riuer
onely?<note> Or haue this honour ouer me, &amp;c. , Or, against when. , Hebr. to cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And he said, To
morrow. And hee said, Bee it according to thy word: That thou
mayest know that there is none like vnto the Lord our
God.<note> Or, against to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the frogs
shall depart from thee, and from thy houses, and from thy seruants,
and from thy people; they shall remaine in the riuer onely.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Moses and
Aaron went out from Pharaoh, and Moses cried vnto the Lord because
of the frogs which he had brought against Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord did
according to the word of Moses: and the frogges died out of the
houses, out of the villages, and out of the fields.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they gathered
them together vpon heapes, and the land stanke.</ab>
<ab n="15">But when Pharaoh
saw that there was respit, he hardned his heart, and hearkened not
vnto them, as the Lord had said.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Say vnto Aaron, Stretch out thy rod, and
smite the dust of the land, that it may become lice, thorowout all
the land of Egypt.</ab>

<fw>Plagues of frogges, of lyce, of
flyes,</fw>
<ab n="17">And they did so:
for Aaron stretched out his hand with his rod, and smote the dust
of the earth, and it became lice, in man and in beast: all the dust
of the land became lice throughout all the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Magicians
did so with their enchantments to bring foorth lice, but they could
not: so there were lice vpon man and vpon beast.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then the Magicians
said vnto Pharaoh; This is the singer of God. And Pharaohs heart
was hardned, and he hearkened not vnto them, as the Lord had
said.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Rise vp early in the morning, and stand
before Pharaoh: loe, he commeth foorth to the water, and say vnto
him; Thus saith the Lord, Let my people goe, that they may serue
me.</ab>
<ab n="21">Els, if thou wilt
not let my people goe, beholde, I will send swarmes of flies vpon
thee, and vpon thy seruants, and vpon thy people, and into thy
houses: and the houses of the Egyptians shall bee full of swarmes
of flies, and also the ground whereon they are.<note> Or, a mixture of noysome beasts, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And I will seuer
in that day the lande of Goshen in which my people dwell, that no
swarmes of flies shall be there, to the end thou maiest know that I
am the Lord in the midst of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I will put a
diuision betweene my people and thy people: to morrow shall this
signe be.<note> Hebr. a redemption. , Or, by to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the Lord did
so: and there came a grieuous swarme of flies into the house of
Pharaoh, and into his seruants houses, and into all the lande of
Egypt: the land was corrupted by reason of the swarme of
flies.<note> Wisd.16. 9. , Or, destroyed.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And Pharaoh
called for Moses and for Aaron, and said, Goe yee, sacrifice to
your God in the land.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Moses said, It
is not meete so to doe; for we shal sacrifice the abomination of
the Egyptians, to the Lord our God: Loe, shall we sacrifice the
abomination of the Egyptians before their eyes, and will they not
stone vs?</ab>
<ab n="27">We will goe three
dayes iourney into the wildernesse, and sacrifice to the Lord our
God, as he shall command vs.<note> Chap.3. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And Pharaoh said,
I wil let you goe that ye may sacrifice to the Lord your God, in
the wildernes: onely you shall not goe very farre away: intreate
for me.</ab>

<fw>of the murraine.</fw>
<ab n="29">And Moses said,
Behold, I goe out from thee, and I will intreate the Lord that the
swarmes of flies may depart from Pharaoh, from his seruants, and
from his people to morrow: but let not Pharaoh deale deceitfully
any more, in not letting the people goe to sacrifice to the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Moses went out
from Pharaoh, and intreated the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="31">And the Lord did
according to the word of Moses: and he remooued the swarmes of
flies from Pharaoh, from his seruants, and from his people: there
remained not one.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Pharaoh
hardened his heart at this time also, neither would hee let the
people goe.</ab>



</div>