<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Moses rod is turned into a
Serpent. 6 His hand is leprous. 10 He is loath to bee sent. 14
Aaron is appointed to assist him. 18 Moses departeth from Iethro.
21 Gods message to Pharaoh. 24 Zipporah circumciseth her sonne. 27
Aaron is sent to meet Moses. 31 The people beleeueth
them.</head>


<fw>Moses his signes.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Moses
answered, and said, But behold, they will not beleeue mee, nor
hearken vnto my voice: for they will say, The Lord hath not
appeared vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
said vnto him, What is that in thine hand? and hee said, A
rod.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he said,
Cast it on the ground: And he cast it on the ground, and it became
a serpent: and Moses fled from before it.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
said vnto Moses, Put forth thine hand, and take it by the taile:
And he put foorth his hand, and caught it, and it became a rod in
his hand:</ab>
<ab n="5">That they may
beleeue that the Lord God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the
God of Isaac, and the God of Iacob hath appeared vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
the Lord said furthermore vnto him, Put now thine hand into thy
bosome. And he put his hand into his bosome: and when hee tooke it
out, behold, his hand was leprous as snowe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he said,
Put thine hand into thy bosome againe. And hee put his hand into
his bosome againe, and plucked it out of his bosome, and behold, it
was turned againe as his other flesh.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it shall
come to passe, if they wil not beleeue thee, neither hearken to the
voice of the first signe, that they will beleeue the voice of the
latter signe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall
come to passe, if they will not beleeue also these two signes,
neither hearken vnto thy voice, that thou shalt take of the water
of the riuer, and powre it vpon the drie land: and the water which
thou takest out of the riuer, shall become blood vpon the drie
land.<note> Heb. shalbe and shall be.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And Moses
saide vnto the Lord, O my lord, I am not eloquent, neither
heretofore, nor since thou hast spoken vnto thy seruant: but I am
slow of speach, and of a slow tongue.<note> Heb. a man of words. , Heb. since yesterday nor since the third day.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord said
vnto him, Who hath made mans mouth? or who maketh the dumbe or
deafe, or the seeing, or þ<note/> blind? haue not I the
Lord?</ab>

<fw>Moses and Aaron goe to Pharaoh.</fw>
<ab n="12">Now therefore goe,
and I will be with thy mouth, and teach thee what thou shalt
say.<note> Matth. 10 19. mar.13. 11. luk. 12. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he said, O my
Lord, send, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt
send.<note> Or, shouldest.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the anger of
the Lord was kindled against Moses, and hee said, Is not Aaron the
Leuite thy brother? I know that he can speake well. And also
behold, he commeth foorth to meet thee: and when he seeth thee, hee
will be glad in his heart.</ab>
<ab n="15">And thou shalt
speake vnto him, and put words in his mouth, and I wil be with thy
mouth, &amp; with his mouth, and will teach you what ye shall
doe.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he shal be thy
spokesman vnto the people: and he shall be, euen hee shall be to
thee in stead of a mouth, and thou shalt be to him in stead of
God.<note> Chap.7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And thou shalt
take this rod in thine hand, wherewith thou shalt doe
signes.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And Moses
went and returned to Iethro his father in law, and said vnto him,
Let me goe, I pray thee, and returne vnto my brethren, which are in
Egypt, and see whether they bee yet aliue. And Iethro said to
Moses, Goe in peace.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the Lord said
vnto Moses in Midian, Goe, returne into Egypt: for all the men are
dead which sought thy life.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Moses tooke
his wife, and his sonnes, and set them vpon an asse, and he
returned to the land of Egypt. And Moses tooke the rod of God in
his hand.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, When thou goest to returne into Egypt, see that thou
doe all those wonders before Pharaoh, which I haue put in thine
hand: but I wil harden his heart, that hee shall not let the people
goe.</ab>
<ab n="22">And thou shalt say
vnto Pharaoh, Thus saith the Lord, Israel is my sonne, euen my
first borne.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I say vnto
thee, let my sonne goe, that he may serue mee: and if thou refuse
to let him goe, behold, I will slay thy sonne, euen thy first
borne.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And it came
to passe by the way in the Inne, that the Lord met him, and sought
to kill him.</ab>

<fw>Moses and Aaron goe to Pharaoh.</fw>
<ab n="25">Then Zipporah
tooke a sharpe stone, and cut off the foreskinne of her sonne, and
cast it at his feete, and said, Surely a bloody husband art thou to
mee.<note> Or, knife. , Heb. made it touch.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">So he let him goe:
then she said, A bloody husband thou art, because of the
Circumcision.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And the
Lord said to Aaron, Goe into the wildernesse to meete Moses. And
hee went and met him in the mount of God, and kissed him.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Moses tolde
Aaron all the wordes of the Lord, who had sent him, and all the
signes which hee had commanded him.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And Moses
and Aaron went, and gathered together all the elders of the
children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Aaron spake
all the wordes which the Lord had spoken vnto Moses, and did the
signes in the sight of the people.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the people
beleeued: And when they heard that the Lord had visited the
children of Israel, and that he had looked vpon their affliction,
then they bowed their heads and worshipped.</ab>




</div>