<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-50-50-Exodus.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The children of Israel after
Iosephs death do multiply. 8 The more they are oppressed by a new
King, the more they multiply. 15 The godlines of the Midwiues, in
sauing the men children aliue. 22 Pharaoh commandeth the male
children to be cast into the riuer.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe these
are the names of the children of Israel, which came into Egypt,
euery man &amp; his household, came with Iacob.<note> Gen.46. 8. exod. 6. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Reuben,
Simeon, Leui, and Iudah,</ab>
<ab n="3">Issachar,
Zebulun and Beniamin,</ab>
<ab n="4">Dan, and
Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.</ab>
<ab n="5">And all the
soules that came out of the loynes of Iacob, were seuentie soules:
for Ioseph was in Egypt already.<note> Heb. thigh. , Gen.46. 27. deut. 10.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Ioseph
died, and all his brethren, and all that generation.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
the children of Israel were fruitfull, and increased aboundantly,
and multiplied, and waxed exceeding mighty, and the land was filled
with them.<note> Acts.7. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Now there
arose vp a new King ouer Egypt, which knew not Ioseph.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he said
vnto his people, Behold, the people of the children of Israel are
moe and mightier then we.</ab>
<ab n="10">Come on, let vs
deale wisely with them, lest they multiply, and it come to passe
that when there falleth out any warre, they ioyne also vnto our
enemies, and fight against vs, and so get them vp out of the
land.</ab>

<fw>Pharaohs crueltie.</fw>
<ab n="11">Therefore they did
set ouer them task-masters, to afflict them with their burdens: And
they built for Pharaoh treasure-cities, Pithom and Raamses.</ab>
<ab n="12">But the more they
afflicted them, the more they multiplied and grew: and they were
grieued because of the children of Israel.<note> Hebr. and as they afflicted them, so they multiplied, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the Egyptians
made the children of Israel to serue with rigour.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they made
their liues bitter, with hard bondage, in morter and in bricke, and
in all maner of seruice in the fielde: all their seruice wherein
they made them serue, was with rigour.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And the
King of Egypt spake to the Hebrew midwiues, (of which the name of
one was Shiphrah, and the name of the other Puah.)</ab>
<ab n="16">And he said, When
ye do the office of a midwife to the Hebrew-women, and see them
vpon the stooles, if it be a sonne, then ye shall kill him: but if
it be a daughter, then shee shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="17">But the midwiues
feared God, and did not as the King of Egypt commanded them, but
saued the men children aliue.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the King of
Egypt called for the midwiues, &amp; said vnto them, Why haue ye
done this thing, and haue saued the men children aliue?</ab>
<ab n="19">And the midwiues
said vnto Pharaoh, Because the Hebrew women are not as the Egyptian
women: for they are liuely, and are deliuered ere the midwiues come
in vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore God
dealt well with the midwiues: and the people multiplied and waxed
very mighty.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it came to
passe, because the midwiues feared God, that hee made them
houses.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Pharaoh
charged all his people, saying, Euery sonne that is borne, yee
shall cast into the riuer, and euery daughter ye shall saue
aliue.</ab>



</div>