<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 The first borne are sanctified to
God. 3 The memoriall of the Passeouer is commanded. 11 The
firstlings of beasts are set apart. 17 The Israelites goe out of
Egypt, and cary Iosephs bones with them. 20 They come to Etham. 21
God guideth them by a pillar of a cloud, and a pillar of
fire.</head>


<fw>The Passeouer must be
remembred.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Sanctifie vnto me
all the first borne, whatsoeuer openeth the wombe, among the
children of Israel, both of man and of beast: it is
mine.<note> Chap. 22. 29. and 34. 19. leuit. 27 26. num. 3. 13. &amp; 8.16. luke 2.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And Moses
said vnto the people, Remember this day, in which yee came out from
Egypt, out of the house of bondage: for by strength of hand the
Lord brought you out from this place: there shall no leauened bread
be eaten.<note> Hebr. seruants.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">This day came yee
out, in the moneth Abib.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And it
shalbe when the Lord shall bring thee into the land of the
Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Hiuites,
and the Iebusites, which he sware vnto thy fathers to giue thee, a
land flowing with milke and hony, that thou shalt keepe this
seruice in this moneth.</ab>
<ab n="6">Seuen dayes thou
shalt eate vnleauened bread, and in the seuenth day shall be a
feast to the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">Unleauened bread
shall be eaten seuen dayes: and there shall no leauened bread bee
seene with thee: neither shall there be leauen seene with thee in
all thy quarters.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And thou
shalt shew thy sonne in that day, saying, This is done because of
that which the Lord did vnto mee, when I came forth out of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall bee
for a signe vnto thee, vpon thine hand, and for a memoriall
betweene thine eyes, that the Lords law may be in thy mouth: for
with a strong hande hath the Lord brought thee out of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou shalt
therfore keepe this ordinance in his season from yeere to
yere.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And it
shalbe when the Lord shall bring thee into the land of the
Canaanites as he sware vnto thee, and to thy fathers, and shall
giue it thee:</ab>
<ab n="12">That thou shalt
set apart vnto the Lord all that openeth the matrix, and euery
firstling that commeth of a beast, which thou hast, the males shall
be the Lords.<note> Chap. 22. 29. and 34. 19. ezek. 44.30. , Heb. cause to passe ouer.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And euery
firstling of an asse thou shalt redeeme with a lambe: and if thou
wilt not redeeme it, then thou shalt breake his necke, and all the
first borne of man amongst thy children shalt thou
redeeme.<note> Or, kidde.</note></ab>

<fw>A cloud and fire.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ And it
shalbe when thy sonne asketh thee in time to come, saying, What is
this? That thou shalt say vnto him; By strength of hand the Lord
brought vs out from Egypt, from the house of bondage.<note> Hebr. to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe when Pharaoh would hardly let vs goe, that the Lord slew all
the first borne in the land of Egypt, both the first borne of man,
and the first borne of beast: Therefore I sacrifice to the Lord all
that openeth the matrix, being males: but all the first borne of my
children I redeeme.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it shall be
for a token vpon thine hand, and for frontlets betweene thine eyes.
For by strength of hand the Lord brought vs foorth out of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And it
came to passe when Pharaoh had let the people goe, that God led
them not through the way of the land of the Philistines, although
that was neere: For God saide, Lest peraduenture the people repent
when they see warre, and they returne to Egypt:</ab>
<ab n="18">But God ledde the
people about through the way of the wildernesse of the Red sea: and
the children of Israel went vp harnessed out of the land of
Egypt.<note> Or, by fiue in a ranke.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Moses tooke
the bones of Ioseph with him: for hee had straitly sworne the
children of Israel, saying; God will surely visite you, and ye
shall cary vp my bones away hence with you.<note> Gene. 50. 25. iosh, 24. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And they
tooke their iourney from Succoth, and encamped in Etham, in the
edge of the wildernesse.<note> Num. 33. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the Lord went
before them by day in a pillar of a cloud, to lead them the way,
and by night in a pillar of fire, to giue them light to goe by day
and night.<note> Num. 14. 14. deut. 1. 33. psal. 78. 14. 1. cor. 10.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">He tooke not away
the pillar of the cloud by day, nor the pillar of fire by night,
from before the people.<note> Nehem.9. 19.</note></ab>



</div>