<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-26-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 The ten curtaines of the
Tabernacle. 7 The eleuen curtaines of goats haire. 14 The couering
of Rammes skinnes. 15 The boards of the Tabernacle, with their
sockets and barres. 31 The Vaile for the Arke. 36 The hanging for
the doore.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer thou
shalt make the Tabernacle with ten curtaines of fine twined linnen,
and blew, and purple, and scarlet: with Cherubims of cunning worke
shalt thou make them.<note> Heb. the worke of a cunning workeman or Embroderer.</note></ab>

<fw>The Tabernacle and
appertinances.</fw>
<ab n="2">The length of one
curtaine shalbe eight and twenty cubits, and the bredth of one
curtaine, foure cubits: and euery one of the curtaines shall haue
one measure.</ab>
<ab n="3">The fiue curtaines
shalbe coupled together one to another: and other fiue curtaines
shalbe coupled one to another.</ab>
<ab n="4">And thou shalt
make loopes of blew vpon the edge of the one curtaine, from the
seluedge in the coupling, and likewise shalt thou make in the
vttermost edge of another curtaine, in the coupling of the
second.</ab>
<ab n="5">Fiftie loopes
shalt thou make in the one curtaine, and fiftie loopes shalt thou
make in the edge of the curtaine, that is in the coupling of the
second, that the loopes may take hold one of another.</ab>
<ab n="6">And thou shalt
make fiftie taches of gold, and couple the curtaines together with
the taches: and it shall be one tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And thou
shalt make curtaines of goats haire, to be a couering vpon the
tabernacle: eleuen curtaines shalt thou make.</ab>
<ab n="8">The length of one
curtaine shalbe thirtie cubites, and the bredth of one curtaine
foure cubites: and the eleuen shalbe all of one measure.</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou shalt
couple fiue curtaines by themselues, and sixe curtaines by
themselues, and shalt double the sixt curtaine in the forefront of
the tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
make fiftie loopes on the edge of the one curtaine, that is outmost
in the coupling, and fiftie loopes in the edge of the curtaine
which coupleth the second.</ab>
<ab n="11">And thou shalt
make fiftie taches of brasse, and put the taches into the loopes,
and couple the tent together, that it may be one.<note> Or, couering.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the remnant
that remaineth of the curtaines of the tent, the halfe curtaine
that remaineth shall hang ouer the backe side of the
tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="13">And a cubite on
the one side, and a cubite on the other side of that which
remaineth in the length of the curtaines of the tent, it shall hang
ouer the sides of the tabernacle, on this side, and on that side to
couer it.<note> Heb. in the remainder or surplusage</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And thou shalt
make a couering for the tent of rammes skinnes died red, and a
couering aboue of badgers skinnes.</ab>

<fw>The Tabernacle and
appertinances.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ And thou
shalt make boards for the Tabernacle of Shittim wood standing
vp.</ab>
<ab n="16">Ten cubits shall
be the length of a board, and a cubite and an halfe shall be the
breadth of one board.</ab>
<ab n="17">Two tenons shall
there be in one board set in order one against another: thus shalt
thou make for all the boards of the Tabernacle.<note> Heb. hands</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And thou shalt
make the boards for the Tabernacle, twentie boards on the Southside
Southward.</ab>
<ab n="19">And thou shalt
make fourtie sockets of siluer, vnder the twenty boards: two
sockets vnder one board for his two tenons, and two sockets vnder
another board for his two tenons.</ab>
<ab n="20">And for the
second side of the Tabernacle on the Northside there shall bee
twentie boards,</ab>
<ab n="21">And their fourtie
sockets of siluer: two sockets vnder one board, and two sockets
vnder another board.</ab>
<ab n="22">And for the sides
of the Tabernacle Westward thou shalt make sixe boards.</ab>
<ab n="23">And two boards
shalt thou make for the corners of the tabernacle in the two
sides.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they shall be
coupled together beneath, and they shall be coupled together aboue
the head of it vnto one ring: thus shall it bee for them both; they
shall be for the two corners.<note> Heb. twinned.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And they shall be
eight boards, and their sockets of siluer sixteene sockets: two
sockets vnder one board, and two sockets vnder another
board.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And thou
shalt make barres of Shittim wood: fiue for the boards of the one
side of the Tabernacle,</ab>
<ab n="27">And fiue barres
for the boards of the other side of the Tabernacle, and fiue barres
for the boards of the side of the Tabernacle for the two sides
Westward.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the middle
barre in the mids of the boards, shall reach from ende to
ende.</ab>
<ab n="29">And thou shalt
ouerlay the boards with gold, and make their rings of gold for
places for the barres: and thou shalt ouerlay the barres with
gold.</ab>
<ab n="30">And thou shalt
reare vp the Tabernacle according to the fashion therof, which was
shewed thee in the mount.<note> Chap. 25. 9.40. acts 7.44. heb.8. 5.</note></ab>

<fw>The Altar of burnt offering.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ And thou
shalt make a Uaile of blew, and purple, and scarlet, and fine
twined linnen of cunning worke: with Cherubims shall it be
made.</ab>
<ab n="32">And thou shalt
hang it vpon foure pillars of Shittim wood, ouerlayd with gold:
their hookes shalbe of gold, vpon the foure sockets of
siluer.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And thou
shalt hang vp the Uaile vnder the taches, that thou maist bring in
thither within the Uaile, the Arke of the Testimony: and the Uaile
shall diuide vnto you, betweene the holy place and the most
holy.</ab>
<ab n="34">And thou shalt
put the Mercie-seat vpon the Arke of the Testimony, in the most
holy place.</ab>
<ab n="35">And thou shalt
set the table without the Uaile, and the candlesticke ouer against
the table, on the side of the Tabernacle toward the South: and thou
shalt put the table on the North side.</ab>
<ab n="36">And thou shalt
make an Hanging for the doore of the Tent, of blew, and purple and
scarlet, and fine twined linnen, wrought with needle worke.</ab>
<ab n="37">And thou shalt
make for the Hanging fiue pillars of Shittim wood, and ouerlay them
with gold, and their hookes shalbe of gold: and thou shalt cast
fiue sockets of brasse for them.</ab>



</div>