<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Lawes for men seruants. 5 For the
seruant whose eare is boared. 7 For women seruants. 12 For
manslaughter. 16 For stealers of men. 17 For cursers of parents. 18
For smiters. 22 For a hurt by chance. 28 For an oxe that goareth.
33 For him that is an occasion of harme.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are the
Iudgements which thou shalt set before them.</ab>
<ab n="2">If thou buy an
Hebrew seruant, sixe yeeres he shall serue, and in the seuenth he
shall goe out free for nothing.<note> Leuit.25. 41. deut. 15 12. iere. 34. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">If he came in by
himselfe, he shal goe out by himselfe: if he were married, then his
wife shall goe out with him.<note> Hebr. with his body.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">If his master haue
giuen him a wife, and she haue borne him sonnes or daughters; the
wife and her children shall be her masters, and he shall go out by
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="5">And if the seruant
shall plainely say, I loue my master, my wife, and my children, I
will not goe out free:<note> Hebr. saying, shall say.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then his master
shall bring him vnto the Iudges, hee shall also bring him to the
doore, or vnto the doore post, and his master shall boare his eare
through with an aule, and he shall serue him for euer.</ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ And if a
man sell his daughter to be a mayd seruant, shee shall not goe out
as the men seruants doe.</ab>
<ab n="8">If she please not
her master, who hath betrothed her to himselfe, then shall he let
her be redeemed: To sell her vnto a strange nation hee shall haue
no power, seeing he hath dealt deceitfully with her.<note> Hebr. be euill in the eyes of, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And if he haue
betrothed her vnto his sonne, he shall deale with her after the
maner of daughters.</ab>
<ab n="10">If he take him
another wife, her food, her rayment, and her duety of mariage shall
he not diminish.</ab>
<ab n="11">And if he doe not
these three vnto her, then shall she goe out free without
money.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ He that
smiteth a man, so that he die, shalbe surely put to
death.<note> Leuit.24. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And if a man lye
not in wait, but God deliuer him into his hand, then I will appoint
thee a place whither hee shall flee:<note> Deut. 19. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But if a man come
presumptuously vpon his neighbour to slay him with guile, thou
shalt take him from mine Altar, that he may die.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And he
that smiteth his father, or his mother, shall bee surely put to
death.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And he
that stealeth a man, and selleth him, or if he be found in his
hand, he shall surely be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And hee
that curseth his father or his mother, shall surely bee put to
death.<note> Leuit. 20. 9. prou. 20. 20. matth. 15.4. mark. 7.10. , Or reuileth.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And if men
striue together, and one smite another with a stone, or with his
fist, and he die not, but keepeth his bed:<note> Or his neighbour.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">If hee rise
againe, and walke abroad vpon his staffe, then shall hee that smote
him, be quit: onely he shall pay for the losse of his time, and
shall cause him to be throughly healed.<note> Hebr. ceasing.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And if a
man smite his seruant, or his mayd, with a rod, and hee die vnder
his hand, hee shall bee surely punished:<note> Hebr. auenged.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Notwithstanding,
if he continue a day or two, hee shall not be punished, for he is
his money.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ If men
striue, and hurt a woman with child, so that her fruit depart from
her, and yet no mischiefe follow, he shalbe surely punished,
according as the womans husband will lay vpon him, and hee shall
pay as the Iudges determine.</ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="23">And if any
mischiefe follow, then thou shalt giue life for life,</ab>
<ab n="24">Eye for eye,
tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foote for foote,<note> Leuit. 24. 20. deut.19 21. matth. 5. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Burning for
burning, wound for wound, stripe for stripe.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And if a
man smite the eye of his seruant, or the eye of his mayd, that it
perish, hee shall let him goe free for his eyes sake.</ab>
<ab n="27">And if he smite
out his man seruants tooth, or his mayde seruants tooth, hee shal
let him goe free for his tooths sake.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ If an oxe
gore a man, or a woman, that they die, then the oxe shal be surely
stoned, and his flesh shall not be eaten: but the owner of the oxe
shall be quitte.<note> Gene. 9. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">But if the oxe
were wont to push with his horne in time past, and it hath bene
testified to his owner, and he hath not kept him in, but that he
hath killed a man or a woman; the oxe shall be stoned, and his
owner also shall bee put to death.</ab>
<ab n="30">If there be layed
on him a summe of money, then he shall giue for the ransome of his
life, whatsoeuer is layd vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="31">Whether hee haue
gored a sonne, or haue gored a daughter, according to this
iudgement shall it bee done vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="32">If the oxe shall
push a man seruant, or a mayd seruant, hee shall giue vnto their
master thirty shekels, and the oxe shalbe stoned.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And if a
man shall open a pit, or if a man shall digge a pit, and not couer
it, and an oxe or an asse fall therein:</ab>
<ab n="34">The owner of the
pit shall make it good, and giue money vnto the owner of them, and
the dead beast shalbe his.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And if one
mans oxe hurt anothers, that he die, then they shall sell the liue
oxe, and diuide the money of it, and the dead oxe also they shall
diuide.</ab>
<ab n="36">Or if it bee
knowen that the oxe hath vsed to push in time past, and his owner
hath not kept him in, hee shall surely pay oxe for oxe, and the
dead shall be his owne.</ab>



</div>