<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Pharaoh chideth Moses and Aaron
for their message. 5 Hee encreaseth the Israelites taske. 15 Hee
checketh their complaints. 19 They cry out vpon Moses and Aaron. 22
Moses complaineth to God.</head>

<ab n="1">And afterward
Moses and Aaron went in, and tolde Pharaoh, Thus saith the Lord God
of Israel, Let my people goe, that they may holde a feast vnto mee
in the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Pharaoh
said, Who is the Lord, that I should obey his voyce to let Israel
goe? I know not the Lord, neither will I let Israel goe.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they
said, The God of the Hebrewes hath met with vs: let vs goe, we pray
thee, three dayes iourney into the desert, and sacrifice vnto the
Lord our God, lest hee fall vpon vs with pestilence, or with the
sword.<note> Chap.3. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the King
of Egypt said vnto them, Wherfore doe ye, Moses and Aaron, let the
people from their workes? get you vnto your burdens.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Pharaoh
said, Behold, the people of the land now are many, &amp; you make
them rest from their burdens.</ab>

<fw>Israel oppressed.</fw>
<ab n="6">And Pharaoh
commanded the same day the taske-masters of the people, and their
officers, saying;</ab>
<ab n="7">Yee shall no
more giue the people straw to make bricke, as heretofore: let them
goe and gather straw for themselues.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the tale
of the brickes which they did make heretofore, you shall lay vpon
them: you shall not diminish ought thereof: for they be idle;
therefore they cry, saying, Let us goe and sacrifice to our
God.</ab>
<ab n="9">Let there
more worke be layde vpon the men, that they may labour therein, and
let them not regard vaine wordes.<note> Heb. let the worke be heauy vpon the men.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
taske-masters of the people went out, and their officers, and they
spake to the people, saying, Thus saith Pharaoh, I will not giue
you straw.</ab>
<ab n="11">Goe ye, get you
straw where you can find it: yet not ought of your worke shall be
diminished.</ab>
<ab n="12">So the people were
scattered abroad throughout al the land of Egypt, to gather stubble
in stead of straw.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the
taske-masters hasted them, saying; Fulfill your workes, your dayly
taskes, as when there was straw.<note> Hebr. a matter of a day in his day.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the officers
of the children of Israel, which Pharaohs task-masters had set ouer
them, were beaten, and demanded, Wherefore haue ye not fulfilled
your taske, in making bricke, both yesterday and to day, as
heretofore?</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then the
officers of the children of Israel came and cryed vnto Pharaoh,
saying, Wherefore dealest thou thus with thy seruants?</ab>
<ab n="16">There is no straw
giuen vnto thy seruants, and they say to vs, Make bricke: and
beholde, thy seruants are beaten; but the fault is in thine owne
people.</ab>
<ab n="17">But he said, Ye
are idle, ye are idle: therefore ye say, Let vs goe and doe
sacrifice to the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">Goe therefore now
and worke: for there shall no straw bee giuen you, yet shall ye
deliuer the tale of brickes.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the officers
of the children of Israel did see that they were in euill case,
after it was said, Yee shall not minish ought from your brickes of
your dayly taske.</ab>

<fw>Gods promise.</fw>
<ab n="20">¶ And they
met Moses and Aaron, who stood in the way, as they came foorth from
Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they said vnto
them; The Lord looke vpon you, and iudge, because you haue made our
sauour to be abhorred in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of
his seruants, to put a sword in their hand to slay vs.<note> Hebr. to stinke.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And Moses returned
vnto the Lord, and said, Lord, Wherefore hast thou so euill
intreated this people? Why is it that thou hast sent me?</ab>
<ab n="23">For since I came
to Pharaoh to speake in thy Name, he hath done euill to this
people, neither hast thou deliuered thy people at all.<note> Heb. deliuering thou hast not deliuered.</note></ab>



</div>