<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 The ten Commandements. 18 The
people are afraid. 20 Moses comforteth them. 22 Idolatrie is
forbidden. 24 Of what sort the Altar should be.</head>

<ab n="1">And God spake all
these words, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">I am the Lord thy
God, which haue brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the
house of bondage:<note> Deut.5.6. psal. 81.10. , Hebr. seruants.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thou shalt haue no
other Gods before me.</ab>

<fw>The tenne Commandements.</fw>
<ab n="4">Thou shalt not
make vnto thee any grauen Image, or any likenesse of any thing that
is in heauen aboue, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in
the water vnder the earth.<note> Leuit.26. 1. psal. 97. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou shalt not bow
downe thy selfe to them, nor serue them: For I the Lord thy God am
a iealous God, visiting the iniquitie of the fathers vpon the
children, vnto the thirde and fourth generation of them that hate
me:</ab>
<ab n="6">And shewing mercy
vnto thousands of them that loue mee, and keepe my
Commandements.</ab>
<ab n="7">Thou shalt not
take the Name of the Lord thy God in vaine: for the Lord will not
holde him guiltlesse, that taketh his Name in vaine.<note> Leuit. 19. 12. deut. 5. 11. matt. 5. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Remember the
Sabbath day, to keepe it holy.</ab>
<ab n="9">Sixe dayes shalt
thou labour, and doe all thy worke:<note> Chap. 23. 12. ezech. 20.12. luke 13.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But the seuenth
day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God: in it thou shalt not doe
any worke, thou, nor thy sonne, nor thy daughter, thy man seruant,
nor thy mayd seruant, nor thy cattell, nor thy stranger that is
within thy gates:</ab>
<ab n="11">For in sixe dayes
the Lord made heauen and earth, the sea, and all that in them is,
and rested the seuenth day: wherefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath
day, and halowed it.<note> Gene. 2.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Honour thy
father and thy mother: that thy dayes may bee long vpon the land,
which the Lord thy God giueth thee.<note> Deut. 5. 16. mat. 15.4. ephes. 6.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Thou shalt not
kill.<note> Matth. 5.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thou shalt not
commit adultery.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou shalt not
steale.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thou shalt not
beare false witnes against thy neighbour.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thou shalt not
couet thy neighbours house, thou shalt not couet thy neighbours
wife, nor his man seruant, nor his maid seruant, nor his oxe, nor
his asse, nor any thing that is thy neighbours.<note> Rom. 7.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And all
the people saw the thundrings, and the lightnings, and the noise of
the trumpet, and the mountaine smoking: and when the people saw it,
they remooued, and stood a farre off.<note> Hebr.12.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And they saide
vnto Moses, Speake thou with vs, and wee will heare: But let not
God speake with vs, lest we die.<note> Deut. 5. 24. and 18. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Moses said
vnto the people, Feare not: for God is come to prooue you, and that
his feare may bee before your faces, that ye sinne not.</ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="21">And the people
stood afarre off, and Moses drew neere vnto the thicke darkenes,
where God was.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
Lord said vnto Moses, Thus thou shalt say vnto the children of
Israel, Yee haue seene that I haue talked with you from
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="23">Ye shall not make
with me gods of siluer, neither shall ye make vnto you gods of
gold.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ An Altar
of earth thou shalt make vnto me, and shalt sacrifice thereon thy
burnt offerings, and thy peace offerings, thy sheepe, and thine
oxen: In all places where I record my Name, I will come vnto thee,
and I will blesse thee.</ab>
<ab n="25">And if thou wilt
make mee an Altar of stone, thou shalt not build it of hewen stone:
for if thou lift vp thy toole vpon it, thou hast polluted
it.<note> Deut. 27. 5.iosh. 8. 31. , Hebr. build them with hewing.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Neither shalt
thou goe vp by steps vnto mine Altar, that thy nakednesse be not
discouered thereon.</ab>



</div>