<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-35-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 The Sabbath. 4 The free gifts for
the Tabernacle. 20 The readinesse of the people to offer. 30
Bezaleel and Aholiab are called to the worke.</head>


<fw>Free gifts are offered.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Moses gathered
all the Congregation of the children of Israel together, and said
vnto them; These are the wordes which the Lord hath commanded, that
yee should doe them.</ab>
<ab n="2">Sixe dayes shall
worke be done, but on the seuenth day there shall be to you an holy
day, a Sabbath of rest to the Lord: whosoeuer doeth worke therein,
shall be put to death.<note> Chap. 20. 9. leuit. 23. 3. deut. 5. 12. luke 13. 14. , Hebr. Helinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Ye shall kindle no
fire throughout your habitations vpon the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And Moses
spake vnto all the Congregation of the children of Israel, saying,
This is the thing which the Lord commanded, saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Take ye from
amongst you an offring vnto the Lord: Whosoeuer is of a willing
heart, let him bring it, an offering of the Lord, gold, and siluer,
and brasse,<note> Chap. 25. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And blew, and
purple, and scarlet, and fine linnen, and goats haire,</ab>
<ab n="7">And rammes skinnes
died red, &amp; badgers skinnes, and Shittim wood,</ab>
<ab n="8">And oyle for the
light, and spices for anoynting oyle, and for the sweet
incense:</ab>
<ab n="9">And Onix stones,
and stones to be set for the Ephod, and for the brestplate.</ab>
<ab n="10">And euery wise
hearted among you, shall come and make all that the Lord hath
commanded:</ab>
<ab n="11">The Tabernacle,
his tent, and his couering, his taches, &amp; his barres, his
pillars, and his sockets:<note> Chap. 26. 31</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The Arke and the
staues thereof, with the Mercy seat, and the Uaile of the
couering:</ab>
<ab n="13">The Table and his
staues, and all his vessels, and the Shewbread,</ab>
<ab n="14">The Candlesticke
also for the light, and his furniture, and his lamps, with the oyle
for the light,</ab>
<ab n="15">And the incense
Altar, and his staues, and the anoynting oyle, and the sweet
incense, and the hanging for the doore, at the entring in of the
Tabernacle:<note> Chap. 30. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The Altar of
burnt offering with his brasen grate, his staues, and all his
vessels, the Lauer and his foot:<note> Chap. 27. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The hangings of
the Court, his pillars, and their sockets, and the hanging for the
doore of the Court:</ab>
<ab n="18">The pinnes of the
Tabernacle, and the pinnes of the Court, and their coards:</ab>

<fw>Free gifts are offered.</fw>
<ab n="19">The cloathes of
seruice, to doe seruice in the holy place, the holy garments for
Aaron the Priest, and the garments of his sonnes to minister in the
Priests office.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And all
the Congregation of the children of Israel departed from the
presence of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they came
euery one whose heart stirred him vp, and euery one whom his spirit
made willing, and they brought the Lords offering to the worke of
the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and for all his seruice, and
for the holy garments.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they came
both men and women, as many as were willing hearted, and brought
bracelets, and earerings, and rings, &amp; tablets, all iewels of
gold: and euery man that offered, offered an offering of gold vnto
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">And euery man
with whom was found blew, and purple, and scarlet, and fine linnen,
and goates haire, and red skinnes of rammes, and badgers skinnes,
brought them.</ab>
<ab n="24">Euery one that
did offer an offering of siluer and brasse, brought the Lords
offering: and euery man with whom was found Shittim wood for any
worke of the seruice, brought it.</ab>
<ab n="25">And all the women
that were wise hearted, did spin with their hands, and brought that
which they had spun, both of blew, and of purple, and of scarlet,
and of fine linnen.</ab>
<ab n="26">And all the women
whose heart stirred them vp in wisedome, spunne goats
haire.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the rulers
brought Onix stones, and stones to be set for the Ephod, and for
the brestplate:</ab>
<ab n="28">And spice, and
oyle for the light, and for the anoynting oyle, and for the sweet
incense.<note> Chap. 30 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The children of
Israel brought a willing offering vnto the Lord, euery man and
woman, whose heart made them willing to bring for all maner of
worke, which the Lord had commanded to be made by the hands of
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And Moses
said vnto the children of Israel, See, the Lord hath called by name
Bezaleel the sonne of Uri, the sonne of Hur, of the tribe of
Iudah.<note> Chap. 31. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And he hath
filled him with the Spirit of God, in wisedome, in vnderstanding,
and in knowledge, and in all maner of workemanship:</ab>

<fw>The people liberall.</fw>
<ab n="32">And to deuise
curious workes, to worke in gold, &amp; in siluer, and in
brasse,</ab>
<ab n="33">And in the
cutting of stones, to set them, and in caruing of wood, to make any
maner of cunning worke.</ab>
<ab n="34">And he hath put
in his heart that he may teach, both he and Aholiab the sonne of
Ahisamach of the tribe of Dan.</ab>
<ab n="35">Them hath hee
filled with wisedome of heart, to worke all manner of worke, of the
ingrauer, and of the cunning workeman, and of the embroiderer, in
blew, and in purple, in scarlet, and in fine linnen, and of the
weauer, euen of them that doe any worke, and of those that deuise
cunning worke.</ab>



</div>