<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Moses is encouraged to go to
Pharaoh. 7 His age. 8 His rod is turned into a Serpent. 11 The
sorcerers do the like. 13 Pharaohs heart is hardened. 14 Gods
message to Pharaoh. 19 The riuer is turned into blood.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
said vnto Moses, See, I haue made thee a god to Pharaoh, and Aaron
thy brother shalbe thy prophet.</ab>
<ab n="2">Thou shalt
speake all that I command thee, and Aaron thy brother shall speake
vnto Pharaoh, that he send the children of Israel out of his
land.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I will
harden Pharaohs heart, and multiplie my signes and my wonders in
the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="4">But Pharaoh
shall not hearken vnto you, that I may lay my hand vpon Egypt, and
bring forth mine armies, and my people the children of Israel, out
of the land of Egypt, by great iudgments.</ab>

<fw>The rod a serpent.</fw>
<ab n="5">And the
Egyptians shall knowe that I am the Lord, when I stretch forth mine
hand vpon Egypt, and bring out the children of Israel from among
them.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses and
Aaron did as the Lord commanded them, so did they.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Moses was
fourescore yeres olde, and Aaron fourescore and three yeeres old,
when they spake vnto Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
the Lord spake vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, saying:</ab>
<ab n="9">When Pharaoh
shall speake vnto you, saying, Shew a miracle for you: then thou
shalt say vnto Aaron, Take thy rod and cast it before Pharaoh, and
it shall become a serpent.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And Moses
and Aaron went in vnto Pharaoh, and they did so as the Lord had
commanded: and Aaron cast downe his rod before Pharaoh, and before
his seruants, and it became a serpent.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then Pharaoh also
called the wise men and the sorcerers; now the Magicians of Egypt,
they also did in like maner with their enchantments.</ab>
<ab n="12">For they cast
downe euery man his rod, and they became serpents: but Aarons rod
swallowed vp their rods.</ab>
<ab n="13">And hee hardened
Pharaohs heart, that hee hearkened not vnto them, as the Lord had
said.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Pharaohs heart is hardened: he refuseth to
let the people goe.</ab>
<ab n="15">Get thee vnto
Pharaoh in the morning, loe, he goeth out vnto the water, and thou
shalt stand by the riuers brinke, against hee come: and the rod
which was turned to a serpent, shalt thou take in thine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="16">And thou shalt say
vnto him, The Lord God of the Hebrewes hath sent me vnto thee,
saying; Let my people goe, that they may serue mee in the
wildernesse: and beholde, hitherto thou wouldest not heare.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thus saith the
Lord, In this thou shalt know that I am the Lord: behold, I will
smite with the rod that is in my hand, vpon the waters which are in
the riuer, and they shalbe turned to blood.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the fish that
is in the riuer shall die, and the riuer shall stincke, and the
Egyptians shall loathe to drinke of the water of the riuer.</ab>

<fw>Bloody waters.</fw>
<ab n="19">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, Say vnto Aaron, Take thy rod, &amp; stretch
out thine hand vpon the waters of Egypt, vpon their streames, vpon
their riuers, and vpon their ponds, and vpon all their pooles of
water, that they may become blood, and that there may be blood
throughout all the land of Egypt, both in vessels of wood, and in
vessels of stone.<note> Heb. Gathering of their waters.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Moses and
Aaron did so, as the Lord commanded: and he lift vp the rod and
smote the waters that were in the riuer, in the sight of Pharaoh,
and in the sight of his seruants: and all the waters that were in
the riuer, were turned to blood.<note> Chap. 17. 5. , Psal.78. 44.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the fish that
was in the riuer died: and the riuer stunke, and the Egyptians
could not drinke of the water of the riuer: and there was blood
throughout all the land Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Magicians
of Egypt did so, with their enchantments: and Pharaohs heart was
hardened, neither did he hearken vnto them, as the Lord had
said.<note> Wis.17.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Pharaoh turned
and went into his house, neither did hee set his heart to this
also.</ab>
<ab n="24">And all the
Egyptians digged round about the riuer for water to drinke: for
they could not drinke of the water of the riuer.</ab>
<ab n="25">And seuen dayes
were fulfilled after that the Lord had smitten the riuer.</ab>



</div>