<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 God renueth his promise by his
Name IEHOVAH. 14 The genealogie of Reuben, 15 of Simeon, 16 of
Leui, of whom came Moses and Aaron.</head>

<ab n="1">Then the Lord
said vnto Moses, Now shalt thou see what I will doe to Pharaoh: for
with a strong hand shall hee let them goe, and with a strong hand
shall he driue them out of his land.</ab>
<ab n="2">And God spake
vnto Moses, and said vnto him, I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I
appeared vnto Abraham, vnto Isaac, and vnto Iacob, by the Name of
God Almighty, but by my name IEHOVAH was I not knowen to
them.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I haue
also established my Couenant with them, to giue them the land of
Canaan, the land of their pilgrimage, wherein they were
strangers.</ab>
<ab n="5">And I haue
also heard the groning of the children of Israel, whom the
Egyptians keepe in bondage: and I haue remembred my
Couenant.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore say
vnto the children of Israel, I am the Lord, and I will bring you
out from vnder the burdens of the Egyptians, and I will rid you out
of their bondage: and I will redeeme you with a stretched out arme,
and with great iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I will
take you to mee for a people, and I will be to you a God: and ye
shall know that I am the Lord your God, which bringeth you out from
vnder the burdens of the Egyptians.</ab>

<fw>Moses is sent to king Pharaoh.</fw>
<ab n="8">And I will
bring you in vnto the lande concerning the which I did sweare to
giue it, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Iacob, and I will giue it you
for an heritage, I am the Lord.<note> Heb. lift vp my hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Moses spake so vnto the children of Israel: but they hearkened not
vnto Moses, for anguish of spirit, and for cruell
bondage.<note> Heb. shortnesse: or, straitnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="11">Goe in, speake
vnto Pharaoh King of Egypt, that he let the children of Israel goe
out of his land.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Moses spake
before the Lord, saying, Behold, the children of Israel haue not
hearkened vnto me: how then shal Pharaoh heare me, who am of
vncircumcised lips?</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses and vnto Aaron, &amp; gaue them a charge vnto the
children of Israel, and vnto Pharaoh King of Egypt, to bring the
children of Israel out of the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ These be
the heads of their fathers houses: The sonnes of Reuben the first
borne of Israel, Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi: these be the
families of Reuben.<note> Gen.46.9 1. chro. 5.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the sonnes of
Simeon: Iemuel, and Iamin, and Ohad and Iachin, and Zohar, and
Shaul the sonne of a Canaanitish woman: these are the families of
Simeon.<note> 1. Chron. 4.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And these
are the names of the sonnes of Leui, according to their
generations: Gershon and Kohath and Merari: and the yeeres of the
life of Leui, were an hundred, thirtie and seuen
yeeres.<note> Num.3.17 1 chron.6.1</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The sonnes of
Gershon: Libni and Shimi, according to their families.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the sonnes of
Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel. And the yeeres of
the life of Kohath, were an hundred thirtie and three
yeeres.<note> Num.26. 57. 1.chro. 6.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the sonnes of
Merari: Mahali and Mushi: these are the families of Leui, according
to their generations.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Amram tooke
him Iochebed his fathers sister to wife, and shee bare him Aaron
and Moses: and the yeeres of the life of Amram were an hundred, and
thirtie and seuen yeeres.<note> Chap.2.2. num.26.59</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And the
sonnes of Izhar: Korah and Nepheg, and Zichri.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the sonnes of
Uzziel: Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Zithri.</ab>

<fw>Moses is sent to king Pharaoh.</fw>
<ab n="23">And Aaron tooke
him Elisheba daughter of Amminadab sister of Naashon to wife, and
she bare him Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the sonnes of
Korah, Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph: these are the families of
the Korhites.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Eleazar Aarons
sonne tooke him one of the daughters of Putiel to wife, and she
bare him Phinehas: these are the heads of the fathers of the
Leuites, according to their families.<note> Num. 25. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">These are that
Aaron and Moses, to whom the Lord said, Bring out the children of
Israel from the land of Egypt, according to their armies.</ab>
<ab n="27">These are they
which spake to Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the children of
Israel from Egypt: These are that Moses and Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And it came
to passe on the day when the Lord spake vnto Moses in the land of
Egypt,</ab>
<ab n="29">That the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying, I am the Lord: speake thou vnto Pharaoh
king of Egypt, all that I say vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Moses said
before the Lord, Behold, I am of vncircumcised lips, and how shall
Pharaoh hearken vnto mee?</ab>



</div>