<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 What the Israelites must offer for
the making of the Tabernacle. 10 The forme of the Arke. 17 The
Mercy-seat, with the Cherubims. 23 The table, with the furniture
thereof. 31 The candlesticke, with the instruments
thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, that they bring me an offering: of euery man
that giueth it willingly with his heart, ye shall take my
offering.<note> Hebr. take for me. , Or, heaue offering. , Chap. 35. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And this is the
offering which ye shall take of them; Gold, and siluer, and
brasse,</ab>
<ab n="4">And blew, and
purple, and scarlet, and fine linnen, and goats haire:<note> Or, silke.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And rammes skinnes
died red, and badgers skinnes, and Shittim wood:</ab>
<ab n="6">Oile for the
light, spices for anointing oile, and for sweet incense:</ab>
<ab n="7">Onix stones, and
stones to be set in the Ephod, and in the brest plate.<note> Chap.28. 4. , Chap. 28. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And let them make
mee a Sanctuary, that I may dwell amongst them:</ab>
<ab n="9">According to all
that I shew thee, after the patterne of the Tabernacle, and the
patterne of all the instruments thereof, euen so shall ye make
it.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And they
shall make an Arke of Shittim wood: two cubites and a halfe shalbe
the length thereof, and a cubite and an halfe the breadth thereof,
and a cubite &amp; a halfe the height thereof.<note> Chap. 37. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And thou shalt
ouerlay it with pure gold, within and without shalt thou ouerlay
it: and shalt make vpon it a crowne of gold round about.</ab>
<ab n="12">And thou shalt
cast foure rings of gold for it, and put them in the foure corners
thereof, and two rings shal be in the one side of it, and two rings
in the other side of it.</ab>
<ab n="13">And thou shalt
make staues of Shittim wood, and ouerlay them with gold.</ab>
<ab n="14">And thou shalt
put the staues into the rings, by the sides of the Arke, that the
Arke may be borne with them.</ab>
<ab n="15">The staues shall
be in the rings of the Arke: they shal not be taken from
it.</ab>
<ab n="16">And thou shalt
put into the Arke the Testimonie which I shall giue thee.</ab>

<fw>The Mercieseat, and
Candlesticke.</fw>
<ab n="17">And thou shalt
make a Mercieseat of pure gold: two cubites and a halfe shalbe the
length thereof, and a cubite and a halfe the breadth
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="18">And thou shalt
make two Cherubims of gold: of beaten worke shalt thou make them,
in the two endes of the Mercie-seat.</ab>
<ab n="19">And make one
Cherub on the one end, and the other Cherub on the other end: euen
of the Mercie-seat shall yee make the Cherubims, on the two ends
thereof.<note> Or, of the matter of the Mercie seate.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And the Cherubims
shall stretch forth their wings on high, couering the Mercie-seat
with their wings, and their faces shall looke one to another:
toward the Mercie-seat shall the faces of the Cherubims be.</ab>
<ab n="21">And thou shalt
put the Mercie-seat aboue vpon the Arke, and in the Arke thou shalt
put the Testimonie that I shall giue thee.</ab>
<ab n="22">And there I wil
meet with thee, and I will commune with thee, from aboue the
Mercie-seat, from betweene the two Cherubims which are vpon the
Arke of the Testimonie, of all things which I will giue thee in
commaundement vnto the children of Israel.<note> Numb. 7 89.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Thou shalt
also make a table of Shittim wood: two cubites shall bee the length
thereof, and a cubite the bredth thereof, and a cubite and a halfe
the height thereof.<note> Chap. 37. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And thou shalt
ouerlay it with pure gold, and make thereto a crowne of gold round
about.</ab>
<ab n="25">And thou shalt
make vnto it a border of an hand bredth round about, and thou shalt
make a golden crowne to the border thereof round about.</ab>
<ab n="26">And thou shalt
make for it foure rings of gold, and put the rings in the foure
corners that are on the foure feete thereof.</ab>
<ab n="27">Ouer against the
border shall the rings be for places of the staues to beare the
table.</ab>
<ab n="28">And thou shalt
make the staues of Shittim wood, and ouerlay them with gold, that
the table may be borne with them.</ab>
<ab n="29">And thou shalt
make the dishes thereof, and spoones therof, and couers thereof,
and bowles thereof, to couer withall: of pure gold shalt thou make
them.<note> Or, to powre out withall.</note></ab>

<fw>The Mercieseat, and
Candlesticke.</fw>
<ab n="30">And thou shalt
set vpon the Table Shew-bread before me alway.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And thou
shalt make a Candlesticke of pure gold: of beaten worke shall the
candlesticke bee made; his shaft and his branches, his bowles, his
knops, and his flowers shall be of the same.<note> Chap.37. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And sixe branches
shall come out of the sides of it: three branches of the
candlesticke out of the one side, and three branches of the
candlesticke out of the other side:</ab>
<ab n="33">Three bowles made
like vnto almonds, with a knop and a flower in one branch: and
three bowles made like almonds in the other branch, with a knop and
a flower: so in the sixe branches that come out of the
candlesticke.</ab>
<ab n="34">And in the
candlesticke shall bee foure bowles made like vnto almonds, with
their knops and their flowers.</ab>
<ab n="35">And there shal be
a knop vnder two branches of the same, and a knop vnder two
branches of the same, and a knop vnder two branches of the same,
according to the sixe branches that proceede out of the
candlesticke.</ab>
<ab n="36">Their knops and
their branches shall be of the same: all it shall bee one beaten
worke of pure gold.</ab>
<ab n="37">And thou shalt
make the seuen lamps thereof: and they shall light the lampes
thereof, that they may giue light ouer against it.<note> Or, cause to ascend. , Heb. the face of it.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And the tongs
thereof, and the snuffe dishes therof shalbe of pure gold.</ab>
<ab n="39">Of a talent of
pure gold shall hee make it, with all these vessels.</ab>
<ab n="40">And looke that
thou make them after their patterne, which was shewed thee in the
mount.<note> Acts 7.44 heb.8. 5. , Heb. which thou wast caused to see.</note></ab>



</div>