<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CExodus_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-29-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 The sacrifice and ceremonies of
consecrating the Priests. 38 The continuall burnt offering. 45 Gods
promise to dwell among the children of Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">And this is the
thing that thou shalt doe vnto them, to hallow them, to minister
vnto me in the Priests office: Take one yong bullocke, and two
rammes without blemish,<note> Leuit. 9.2</note></ab>

<fw>The consecration of the
Priests.</fw>
<ab n="2">And vnleauened
bread, and cakes unleauened, tempered with oyle, and wafers
vnleauened, annointed with oile: of wheaten flowre shalt thou make
them.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thou shalt put
them into one basket, and bring them in the basket, with the
bullocke and the two rammes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Aaron and his
sonnes thou shalt bring vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, and shalt wash them with water.</ab>
<ab n="5">And thou shalt
take the garments, and put vpon Aaron the coat, and the robe of the
Ephod, and the Ephod, and the brestplate, and gird him with the
curious girdle of the Ephod.</ab>
<ab n="6">And thou shalt put
the Miter vpon his head, and put the holy Crowne vpon the
Miter.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then shalt thou
take the annointing oyle, and powre it vpon his head, and annoint
him.<note> Chap. 30. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And thou shalt
bring his sonnes, and put coats vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou shalt
gird them with girdles, (Aaron and his sonnes) and put the bonnets
on them: and the priests office shall be theirs for a perpetuall
statute: and thou shalt consecrate Aaron and his
sonnes.<note> Heb. bind. , Heb. fill the hand of. , Chap. 28. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
cause a bullocke to bee brought before the Tabernacle of the
Congregation: and Aaron and his sonnes shall put their hands vpon
the head of the bullocke.<note> Leuit. 1.4</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And thou shalt
kill the bullocke before the Lord, by the doore of the Tabernacle
of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="12">And thou shalt
take of the blood of the bullocke, and put it vpon the hornes of
the altar with thy finger, and powre all the blood beside the
bottome of the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="13">And thou shalt
take all the fat that couereth the inwards, and the caule that is
aboue the liuer, and the two kidneis, and the fat that is vpon
them, and burne them vpon the altar.<note> Leuit. 3.3 , It seemeth by Anatomy, and the Hebrewe Doctours, to be the midriffe.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But the flesh of
the bullocke, and his skinne, and his doung shalt thou burne with
fire without the campe, it is a sinne offering.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Thou shalt
also take one ram, and Aaron and his sonnes shall put their hands
vpon the head of the ram.</ab>
<ab n="16">And thou shalt
slay the ramme, and thou shalt take his blood, and sprinkle it
round about vpon the altar.</ab>

<fw>The consecration of the
Priests.</fw>
<ab n="17">And thou shalt
cut the ramme in pieces, and wash the inwards of him, and his legs,
and put them vnto his pieces, and vnto his head.<note> Or, vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And thou shalt
burne the whole ramme vpon the Altar: it is a burnt offering vnto
the Lord: It is a sweet sauour, an offering made by fire vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And thou
shalt take the other ramme: and Aaron and his sonnes shall put
their hands vpon the head of the ramme.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then shalt thou
kill the ramme, and take of his blood, and put it vpon the tip of
the right eare of Aaron, and vpon the tip of the right eare of his
sonnes, and vpon the thumbe of their right hand, and vpon the great
toe of their right foot, and sprinckle the blood vpon the Altar
round about.</ab>
<ab n="21">And thou shalt
take of the blood that is vpon the Altar, and of the anointing
oyle, and sprinkle it vpon Aaron, and vpon his garments, and vpon
his sonnes, and vpon the garments of his sonnes with him: and hee
shall be hallowed, and his garments, and his sonnes, and his sonnes
garments with him.</ab>
<ab n="22">Also thou shalt
take of the ram the fat and the rumpe, and the fat that couereth
the inwards, &amp; the caule aboue the liuer, and the two kidneis,
and the fat that is vpon them, and the right shoulder, for it is a
ram of consecration:</ab>
<ab n="23">And one loafe of
bread, and one cake of oyled bread, and one wafer out of the basket
of the vnleauened bread, that is before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">And thou shalt
put all in the hands of Aaron, and in the hands of his sonnes, and
shalt waue them for a waue-offering before the Lord.<note> Or, shake to and fro.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And thou shalt
receiue them of their hands, and burne them vpon the Altar for a
burnt offering, for a sweet sauour before the Lord: it is an
offering made by fire vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="26">And thou shalt
take the brest of the ramme of Aarons consecrations, and waue it
for a waue-offering before the Lord, and it shalbe thy
part.</ab>
<ab n="27">And thou shalt
sanctifie the brest of the waue-offering, and the shoulder of the
heaue offering, which is waued, and which is heaued vp of the ramme
of the consecration, euen of that which is for Aaron, and of that
which is for his sonnes.</ab>

<fw>The consecration of the
Priests.</fw>
<ab n="28">And it shalbe
Aarons, and his sonnes by a statute for euer, from the children of
Israel: for it is an heaue offering: and it shall be an heaue
offering from the children of Israel, of the sacrifice of their
peace offrings, euen their heaue offering vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And the
holy garments of Aaron shall be his sonnes after him, to bee
anoynted therein, and to be consecrated in them.</ab>
<ab n="30">And that sonne
that is Priest in his stead, shal put them on seuen dayes, when he
commeth into the Tabernacle of the Congregation to minister in the
holy place.<note> Hebr. He of his sonnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And thou
shalt take the ramme of the consecration, and seethe his flesh in
the holy place.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Aaron and his
sonnes shall eate the flesh of the ramme, and the bread that is in
the basket, by the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Cōgregation.<note> Leuit. 8.31. matth. 12.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And they shall
eate those things, wherewith the atonement was made, to consecrate
and to sanctifie them: but a stranger shall not eate thereof,
because they are holy.</ab>
<ab n="34">And if ought of
the flesh of the consecrations, or of the bread remaine vnto the
morning, then thou shalt burne the remainder with fire: it shall
not be eaten, because it is holy.</ab>
<ab n="35">And thus shalt
thou doe vnto Aaron, and to his sonnes, according to all things
which I haue commaunded thee: seuen dayes shalt thou consecrate
them.</ab>
<ab n="36">And thou shalt
offer euery day a bullocke for a sinne offering, for atonement: and
thou shalt clense the Altar, when thou hast made an atonement for
it, and thou shalt anoynt it, to sanctifie it.</ab>
<ab n="37">Seuen dayes thou
shalt make an atonement for the Altar, and sanctifie it: and it
shalbe an Altar most holy: whatsoeuer toucheth the Altar, shalbe
holy.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ Now this
is that which thou shalt offer vpon the Altar; two lambs of the
first yere, day by day continually.<note> Num. 28.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">The one lambe
thou shalt offer in the morning: and the other lambe thou shalt
offer at euen:</ab>
<ab n="40">And with the one
lambe a tenth deale of flowre mingled with the fourth part of an
Hin of beaten oyle: and the fourth part of an Hin of wine for a
drinke offering.</ab>

<fw>The consecration of the
Priests.</fw>
<ab n="41">And the other
lambe thou shalt offer at Euen, and shalt doe thereto, according to
the meat offering of the morning, and according to the drinke
offering thereof, for a sweet sauour, an offering made by fire vnto
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="42">This shalbe a
continuall burnt offering throughout your generations, at the doore
of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, before the Lord,where I wil
meete you, to speake there vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="43">And there I will
meet with the children of Israel: and the Tabernacle shalbe
sanctified by my glory.<note> Or, Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And I will
sanctifie the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and the Altar: I will
sanctifie also both Aaron and his sonnes, to minister to me in the
Priests office.</ab>
<ab n="45">¶ And I will
dwell amongst the children of Israel, and will be their
God.<note> Leuit. 26.12. 2. cor. 6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And they shall
know that I am the Lord their God, that brought them foorth out of
the land of Egypt, that I may dwell amongst them: I am the Lord
their God.</ab>



</div>