<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 A vision whereby is shewed the
preseruation of some, 5 and the destruction of the rest. 8 God
cannot be intreated for them.</head>

<ab n="1">Hee cryed also in
mine eares, with a loude voyce, saying; Cause them that hauecharge
ouer the citie, to draw neere, euen euery man with his destroying
weapon in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="2">And behold, sixe
men came from the way of the higher gate, which lyeth toward the
North, and euery man a slaughter weapon in his hand: and one man
among them was clothed with linnen, with a writers inkehorne by his
side, and they went in and stood beside the brasen
altar.<note> Heb. which is turned. , Heb. a weapon of his breaking in pieces. , Heb. vpon his loines.</note></ab>

<fw>The marked.</fw>
<ab n="3">And the glory of
the God of Israel was gone vp from the Cherub whereupon hee was, to
the threshold of the house, and he called to the man clothed with
linnen, which had the writers inkehorne by his side.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord sayd
vnto him, Goe through the middest of the citie, through the middest
of Ierusalem, and set a marke vpon the foreheads of the men that
sigh, and that cry for all the abominations, that bee done in the
middest thereof.<note> Heb. marke a marke. , Exod.12. 7. reuel.7.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And to the
others he said in mine hearing, Goe ye after him through the citie,
and smite: let not your eye spare, neither haue ye
pitie.<note> Heb. mine eares.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Slay vtterly olde
and yong; both maides, and litle children, and women: but come not
neere any man vpon whom is the marke, and begin at my sanctuary:
then they began at the ancient men which were before the
house.<note> Hebr. to destruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And hee sayd vnto
them, Defile the house, and fill the courts with the slaine, goe ye
forth: and they went forth and slew in the citie.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And it came
to passe while they were slaying them, and I was left, that I fell
vpon my face, and cryed and said, Ah, Lord God, wilt thou destroy
all the residue of Israel, in thy powring out of thy fury vpon
Ierusalem?</ab>
<ab n="9">Then sayd he vnto
me; The iniquity of the house of Israel and Iudah is exceeding
great, and the land is full of blood, and the citie full of
peruersenesse: for they say; The Lord hath forsaken the earth, and
the Lord seeth not.<note> Heb. filled with. , Or, wresting of iudgement. , Cha.8.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And as for me
also, mine eye shal not spare, neither will I haue pitie, but I
will recompence their way vpon their head.<note> Cha.5.11. and 7.4. &amp; 8.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And behold, the
man clothed with linnen, which had the inkehorne by his side,
reported the matter, saying; I haue done as thou hast commanded
me.<note> Heb. returned the word.</note></ab>



</div>