<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_41" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLI.</head>
<head>The measures, parts, chambers and
ornaments of the Temple.</head>

<ab n="1">Afterward he
brought me to the Temple, and measured the posts, six cubites broad
on the one side, and sixe cubites broad on the other side, which
was the bredth of the Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the bredth of
the doore was tenne cubites, and the sides of the doore were fiue
cubites on the one side, and fiue cubites on the other side, and he
measured the length thereof fortie cubites, and the bredth twentie
cubites.<note> Or, entrance.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then went he
inward, and measured the post of the doore two cubites, and the
doore sixe cubites, and the bredth of the doore seuen
cubites.</ab>
<ab n="4">So he measured
the length therof twentie cubites, and the bredth twentie cubites
before the temple, and he said vnto me; This is the most holy
place.</ab>

<fw>The buildings, and chambers of the
Temple</fw>
<ab n="5">After he measured
the wall of the house sixe cubites, and the bredth of euerie
side-chamber foure cubites round about the house on euery
side.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the
side-chambers were three, one ouer an other, and thirtie in order,
and they entred into the wall which was of the house for the side
chambers round about, that they might haue hold, but they had not
hold in the wall of the house.<note> Heb. side-chamber ouer side-chamber. , Or, three and thirty times, or foot. , Heb. be holden.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And there was an
enlarging and a winding about still vpward to the side-chambers,
for the winding about of the house went still vpward round about
the house: therefore the bredth of the house was still vpward, and
so increased from the lowest chamber to the highest by the
middest.<note> Heb. it was made broader and went round.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">I saw also the
height of the house round about; the foundations of the
side-chambers were a full reede of sixe great cubites.</ab>
<ab n="9">The thicknesse of
the wall which was for the side chamber without, was fiue cubites,
and that which was left, was the place of the side-chambers that
were within.</ab>
<ab n="10">And betweene the
chambers was the widenesse of twentie cubites round about the house
on euery side.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the doores
of the side-chambers were toward the place that was left, one doore
toward the North, and an other doore toward the South, and the
bredth of the place that was left, was fiue cubites round
about.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now the building
that was before the seperate place, at the end toward the West, was
seuenty cubites broad, and the wall of the building was fiue
cubites thicke round about, and the length thereof ninety
cubites.</ab>
<ab n="13">So he measured
the house, an hundreth cubites long, and the separate place and the
building with the walles thereof, an hundreth cubites long.</ab>
<ab n="14">Also the bredth
of the face of the house, and of the separate place toward the
East, an hundreth cubites.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he measured
the length of the building ouer against the separate place which
was behind it, and the galleries thereof on the one side, and on
the other side an hundreth cubites with the inner temple, and the
porches of the court.<note> Or, seuerall walkes, Or, walkes with pillars.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The doore-posts
and the narrow windows, and the galleries round about on their
three stories, ouer against the doore sieled with wood round about,
and from the ground vp to the windows, &amp; the windows were
couered.<note> Heb. sieling of wood. , Or, and the ground vnto the windowes.</note></ab>

<fw>The buildings, and chambers of the Temple, for
Priests, &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="17">To that aboue
the doore, euen vnto the inner house and without, and by all the
wall round about within and without by measure.<note> Heb. measures.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And it was made
with Cherubims and Palme trees, so that a Palme tree was betweene a
Cherub and a Cherub, and euery Cherub had two faces.</ab>
<ab n="19">So that the face
of a man was toward the Palme-tree on the one side, and the face of
a yong lyon toward the Palme-tree on the other side: it was made
through all the house round about.</ab>
<ab n="20">From the ground
vnto aboue the doore were Cherubims and Palme-trees made, &amp; on
the wall of the temple.</ab>
<ab n="21">The postes of
the Temple were squared, and the face of the Sanctuary, the
appearance of the one as the appearance of the other.<note> Heb. poste.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The altar of
wood was three cubits high, and the length thereof two cubits; and
the corners thereof and the length thereof and the walles thereof
were of wood: and hee said vnto mee; This is the Table that is
before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the Temple
and the Sanctuarie had two doores.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the doores
had two leaues a piece, two turning leaues, two leaues for the one
doore, and two leaues for the other doore.</ab>
<ab n="25">And there were
made on them, on the doores of the Temple, Cherubims and
Palme-trees, like as were made vpon the walles, and there were
thicke planckes vpon the face of the porch without.</ab>
<ab n="26">And there were
narrow windowes and Palme-trees on the one side and on the other
side, on the sides of the porch, and vpon the side chambers of the
house, and thicke plankes.</ab>



</div>