<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the parable of a boiling
pot, 6 is shewed the irreuocable destruction of Ierusalem. 15 By
the signe of Ezekiel not mourning for the death of his wife, 19 is
shewed the calamity of the Iewes to be beyond all
sorow.</head>

<ab n="1">Againe in the
ninth yeere, in the tenth moneth, in the tenth day of the moneth,
the word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man,
Write thee the name of the day, euen of this same day: the king of
Babylon set himselfe against Ierusalem this same day.</ab>
<ab n="3">And vtter a
parable vnto the rebellious house, and say vnto them, Thus sayth
the Lord God, Set on a pot, set it on, and also powre water into
it.</ab>
<ab n="4">Gather the pieces
thereof into it, euen euery good piece, the thigh, and the
shoulder; fill it with the choice bones.</ab>
<ab n="5">Take the choice
of the flocke, and burne also the bones vnder it, and make it boyle
well, and let him seethe the bones of it therein.<note> Or, heape.</note></ab>

<fw>Ezekiels wife.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶ Wherefore
thus sayth the Lord God, Woe to the bloodie citie, to the pot whose
scumme is therein, and whose scumme is not gone out of it; bring it
out piece by piece, let no lot fall vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="7">For her blood is
in the middest of her: she set it vpon the toppe of a rocke, she
powred it vpon the ground to couer it with dust:</ab>
<ab n="8">That it might
cause furie to come vp to take vengeance: I haue set her blood vpon
the top of a rocke, that it should not be couered.</ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God; Woe to the bloody citie, I will euen make the
pile for fire, great.<note> Nah. 3.1. Abac.2. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Heape on wood,
kindle the fire, consume the flesh, and spice it well, and let the
bones be burnt.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then set it
empty vpon the coales thereof, that the brasse of it may be hot and
may burne, and that the filthinesse of it may be molten in it, that
the scum of it may be consumed.</ab>
<ab n="12">She hath wearied
herselfe with lies, and her great scumme went not forth out of her:
her scumme shall be in the fire.</ab>
<ab n="13">In thy
filthinesse is lewdnesse, because I haue purged thee, and thou wast
not purged, thou shalt not be purged from thy filthinesse any more,
till I haue caused my fury to rest vpon thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">I the Lord haue
spoken it, it shall come to passe, and I will doe it, I will not
goe backe, neither will I spare, neither will I repent, according
to thy wayes and according to thy doings, shall they iudge thee,
saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Also the
word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="16">Sonne of man,
behold, I take away from thee the desire of thine eyes with a
stroke: yet neither shalt thou mourne, nor weepe, neither shall thy
teares runne downe.<note> Heb. goe.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Forbeare to
crie, make no mourning for the dead, bind the tire of thine head
vpon thee, and put on thy shooes vpon thy feete, and couer not thy
lips, and eate not the bread of men.<note> Heb. be silent. , Heb. vpper lip. And so vers.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">So I spake vnto
the people in the morning, and at euen my wife died, and I did in
the morning as I was commanded.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And the
people said vnto me; Wilt thou not tell vs what these things are to
vs, that thou doest so?</ab>
<ab n="20">Then I answered
them, The word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>

<fw>Prophet is a signe.</fw>
<ab n="21">Speake vnto the
house of Israel; Thus saith the Lord God; Behold, I will prophane
my sanctuarie, the excellencie of your strength, the desire of your
eyes, and that which your soule pitieth; and your sonnes and your
daughters, whom yee haue left, shall fall by the sword.<note> Heb. the pitie of your soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And yee shall
doe as I haue done: yee shall not couer your lips, nor eate the
bread of men.</ab>
<ab n="23">And your tires
shall be vpon your heads, and your shooes vpon your feet: yee shall
not mourne nor weepe, but yee shall pine away for your iniquities,
and mourne one towards an other.</ab>
<ab n="24">Thus Ezekiel is
vnto you a signe: according to all that he hath done, shall yee
doe: and when this commeth, yee shall know that I am the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="25">Also thou sonne
of man, shall it not be in the day when I take from them their
strength, the ioy of their glorie, the desire of their eyes, and
that whereupon they set their minds, their sonnes and their
daughters;<note> Heb. the lifting vp of the soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">That he that
escapeth in that day, shall come vnto thee, to cause thee to heare
it with thine eares?</ab>
<ab n="27">In that day
shall thy mouth be opened to him which is escaped, and thou shalt
speake &amp; be no more dumbe, and thou shalt be a signe vnto them,
and they shall know that I am the Lord.</ab>



</div>