<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-40-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 The time, maner and end of the
vision. 6 The description of the East gate, 20 of the North gate,
24 of the South gate, 32 of the East gate, 35 and of the North
gate. 39 Eight Tables. 44 The chambers. 48 The porch of the
house.</head>

<ab n="1">In the fiue and
twentieth yeere of our captiuitie, in the beginning of the yere, in
the tenth day of the moneth, in the fourteenth yeere after that the
citie was smitten, in the selfe same day, the hand of the Lord was
vpon mee, and brought me thither.</ab>
<ab n="2">In the visions of
God brought he me into the land of Israel, and set mee vpon a very
high mountaine, by which was as the frame of a citie on the
South.<note> Or, vpon which.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And he brought
mee thither, and behold, there was a man, whose appearance was like
the appearance of brasse, with a line of flaxe in his hand, &amp; a
measuring reed; and he stood in the gate.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the man saide
vnto mee; Sonne of man, behold with thine eyes, and heare with
thine eares, &amp; set thine heart vpon all that I shall shew thee:
for to the intent that I might shew them vnto thee, art thou
brought hither: declare all that thou seest, to the house of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">And behold a wall
on the outside of the house round about: and in the mans hand a
measuring reed of sixe cubites long, by the cubite, and an hand
breadth: so hee measured the breadth of the building, one reed, and
the height one reed.</ab>

<fw>The measuring of the Temple, and of the
buildings of it.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶ Then came
hee vnto the gate which looketh toward the East, and went vp the
staires thereof, and measured the threshold of the gate, which was
one reed broad, and the other threshold of the gate, which was one
reed broad.<note> Heb. whose face was the way toward the East.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And euery little
chamber was one reed long, and one reed broad, and betweene the
litle chambers were fiue cubites, &amp; the threshold of the gate,
by the porch of the gate within was one reed.</ab>
<ab n="8">He measured also
the porch of the gate within, one reed.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then measured hee
the porch of the gate, eight cubites, and the postes thereof two
cubits, and the porch of the gate was inward.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the litle
chambers of the gate Eastward, were three on this side, and three
on that side, they three were of one measure, and the postes had
one measure on this side, and on that side.</ab>
<ab n="11">And hee measured
the breadth of the entrie of the gate, ten cubits, and the length
of the gate, thirteene cubites.</ab>
<ab n="12">The space also
before the litle chambers was one cubite on this side, and the
space was one cubite on that side, and the litle chambers were sixe
cubites on this side, and sixe cubits on that side.<note> Hebr. limit, or bound.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Hee measured
then the gate from the roofe of the one litle chamber to the roofe
of another: the breadth was fiue and twentie cubits, doore against
doore.</ab>
<ab n="14">He made also
postes of threescore cubites, euen vnto the poste of the court
round about the gate.</ab>
<ab n="15">And from the
face of the gate of the entrance, vnto the face of the porch of the
inner gate, were fiftie cubites.</ab>
<ab n="16">And there were
narrow windows to the litle chambers, and to their posts within the
gate round about, and likewise to the arches: and windowes were
round about inward: and vpon ech post were palme-trees.<note> Heb. closed. , Or, galleries, or porches. , Or, within.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Then brought he
me into the outward court, and loe there were chambers, and a
pauement, made for the court round about: thirtie chambers were
vpon the pauement.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the pauement
by the side of the gates ouer against the length of the gates, was
the lower pauement.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then hee
measured the breadth from the forefront of the lower gate, vnto the
forefront of the inner court without, an hundred cubits Eastward
and Northward.<note> Or, from without.</note></ab>

<fw>The measuring of the Temple, and of the
buildings of it.</fw>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
gate of the outward court, that looked toward the North, he
measured the length thereof, and the breadth thereof.<note> Heb. whose face was.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the little
chambers thereof were three on this side, and three on that side,
and the postes thereof, and the arches thereof were after the
measure of the first gate: the length thereof was fiftie cubites,
and the breadth fiue and twentie cubites.<note> Or, galleries or porches.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And their
windowes, and their arches, and their palme trees, were after the
measure of the gate that looketh towards the East, and they went vp
vnto it by seuen steps, and the arches thereof were before
them.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the gate of
the inner court was ouer against the gate toward the North and
toward the East, and hee measured from gate to gate an hundreth
cubites.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ After
that hee brought me toward the South, and behold a gate toward the
South, and he measured the postes thereof, and the arches thereof
according to these measures.</ab>
<ab n="25">And there were
windowes in it, and in the arches thereof round about, like those
windowes, the length was fiftie cubites, and the breadth fiue and
twentie cubites.</ab>
<ab n="26">And there were
seuen steps to goe vp to it, and the arches thereof were before
them, and it had palme trees, one on this side, and another on that
side vpon the postes thereof.</ab>
<ab n="27">And there was a
gate in the inner court toward the South, and he measured from gate
to gate toward the South an hundred cubites.</ab>
<ab n="28">And hee brought
me to the inner court by the South gate, and he measured the South
gate according to these measures,</ab>
<ab n="29">And the little
chambers thereof, and the postes thereof, and the arches thereof
according to these measures, and there were windowes in it, and in
the arches thereof round about: it was fiftie cubites long, and
fiue and twentie cubites broad.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the arches
round about were fiue and twenty cubits long, and fiue cubites
broad.<note> Hebr. breadth.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And the arches
thereof were toward the vtter court, and palme trees were vpon the
postes thereof, and the going vp to it had eight steps.</ab>

<fw>The measuring of the Temple, and of the
buildings of it.</fw>
<ab n="32">¶ And hee
brought me into the inner court toward the East, and hee measured
the gate according to these measures.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the little
chambers thereof, and the postes thereof, and the arches thereof
were according to these measures, and there were windowes therein,
and in the arches thereof round about, it was fiftie cubites long,
and fiue and twentie cubits broad.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the arches
thereof were toward the outward court, and palme trees were vpon
the postes thereof on this side, and on that side, and the going vp
to it had eight steps.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And hee
brought me to the North gate, and measured it according to these
measures.</ab>
<ab n="36">The little
chambers thereof, the postes thereof, and the arches thereof and
the windowes to it round about: the length was fiftie cubites, and
the breadth fiue and twentie cubites.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the postes
thereof were toward the vtter court, and palme trees were vpon the
posts thereof on this side, and on that side, and the going vp to
it had eight steps.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the
chambers, and the entries thereof were by the postes of the gates,
where they washed the burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And in
the porch of the gate were two tables on this side, and two tables
on that side, to slay thereon the burnt offering, and the sinne
offering, and the trespasse offering.</ab>
<ab n="40">And at the side
without, as one goeth vp to the entry of the North gate, were two
tables, and on the other side, which was at the porch of the gate,
were two tables.<note> Or, at the steppe.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">Foure tables
were on this side, and foure tables on that side, by the side of
the gate; eight tables, whereupon they slew their
sacrifices.</ab>
<ab n="42">And the foure
tables were of hewen stone for the burnt offering, of a cubite and
an halfe long, and a cubite &amp; a halfe broad, and one cubit
high: whereupon also they laide the instruments wherewith they
slewe the burnt offering and the sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="43">And within were
hooks, an hand broad, fastened round about, and vpon the tables was
the flesh of the offering.<note> Or, andirons or the two harthstones.</note></ab>

<fw>The buildings, and chambers of the
Temple</fw>
<ab n="44">¶ And
without the inner gate were the chambers of the singers in the
inner court, which was at the side of the North gate: and their
prospect was toward the South, one at the side of the East gate,
hauing the prospect toward the North.</ab>
<ab n="45">And hee said
vnto me; This chamber whose prospect is toward the South, is for
the priests, the keepers of the charge of the house.<note> Or, ward: or, ordinance, and so ver. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And the chamber
whose prospect is toward the North, is for the priests the keepers
of the charge of the altar: these are the sonnes of Zadok among the
sonnes of Leui, which come neere to the Lord to minister vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="47">So he measured
the court, an hundreth cubites long, and an hundreth cubites broad
foure square, and the altar that was before the house.</ab>
<ab n="48">¶ And he
brought me to the porch of the house, and measured each post of the
porch, fiue cubites on this side, and fiue cubites on that side:
and the bredth of the gate was three cubites on this side, and
three cubites on that side.</ab>
<ab n="49">The length of
the porch was twentie cubites, and the bredth eleuen cubites, and
he brought me by the steps, whereby they went vp to it, and there
were pillars by the posts, one on this side, and another on that
side.</ab>



</div>