<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_42" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-42-43.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLII.</head>
<head>1 The chambers for the Priests. 13
The vse therof. 19 The measures of the outward court.</head>

<ab n="1">Then he brought
me foorth into the vtter court, the way toward the North, and hee
brought mee into the chamber, that was ouer against the separate
place, &amp; which was before the building toward the
North.</ab>
<ab n="2">Before the length
of an hundreth cubites was the North doore, and the breadth was
fiftie cubits.</ab>

<fw>The buildings, and chambers of the Temple, for
Priests, &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="3">Ouer against the
twentie cubites which were for the inner court, and ouer against
the pauement which was for the vtter court, was gallerie against
gallery in three stories.</ab>
<ab n="4">And before the
chambers was a walke of ten cubites breadth inward, a way of one
cubite, and their doores toward the North.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now the
vpper-chambers were shorter: for the galleries were higher then
these, then the lower, and then the middlemost of the
building.<note> Or, did eate of these. , Or, and the building consisted of the lower and the middle-most.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For they were in
three stories, but had not pillars as the pillars of the courts:
therefore the building was straitned more then the lowest, and the
middlemost from the ground.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the wall that
was without ouer against the chambers towards the vtter court on
the forepart of the chambers, the length thereof was fiftie
cubites.</ab>
<ab n="8">For the length of
the chambers that were in the vtter court was fiftie cubites: and
loe, before the Temple were an hundreth cubites.</ab>
<ab n="9">And from vnder
these chambers was the entrie on the East side, as one goeth into
them from the vtter court.<note> Or, from the place. , Or, he, that brought me. , Or, as hee came.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The chambers
were in the thickenes of the wall of the court toward the East,
ouer against the separate place, and ouer against the
building.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the way
before them was like the appearance of the chambers, which were
toward the North, as long as they and as broad as they, and all
their goings out were both according to their fashions, and
according to their doores.</ab>
<ab n="12">And according to
the doores of the chambers that were toward the South, was a doore
in the head of the way, euen the way directly before ye wall toward
the East, as one entreth into them.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then sayd
hee vnto mee, The North chambers, and the South chambers, which are
before the separate place, they be holy chambers, where
þ<note/> Priests that approach vnto the Lord shall eate
the most holy things: there shall they lay the most holy things,
and the meat offering, &amp; the sinne offering, and the trespasse
offring, for the place is holy.</ab>

<fw>God returneth.</fw>
<ab n="14">When the Priests
enter therein, then shall they not goe out of the holy place into
the vtter court, but there they shall lay their garments, wherein
they minister: for they are holy, and shall put on other garments,
and shall approch to those things which are for the people.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now when hee had
made an end of measuring the inner house, hee brought mee foorth
toward the gate, whose prospect is toward the East, and measured it
round about.</ab>
<ab n="16">He measured the
East side with the measuring reede, fiue hundreth reedes, with the
measuring reed round about.<note> Heb. wind.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Hee measured the
North side fiue hundreth reedes, with a measuring reed round
about.</ab>
<ab n="18">Hee measured the
South side fiue hundreth reedes, with the measuring reede.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Hee
turned about to the West side, and measured fiue hundreth reedes
with the measuring reed.</ab>
<ab n="20">He measured it
by the foure sides: it had a wall round about fiue hundreth reedes
long, and fiue hundreth broad, to make a separation betweene the
Sanctuary and the prophane place.</ab>



</div>