<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The type of Ezekiels remouing. 8
It shewed the captiuitie of Zedekiah. 17 Ezekiels trembling sheweth
the Iewes desolation. 21 The Iewes presumptuous prouerbe is
reprooued. 26 The speedinesse of the Vision.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of the
Lord also came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man,
thou dwellest in the middest of a rebellious house, which haue eyes
to see, and see not: they haue eares to heare, and heare not: for
they are a rebellious house.</ab>

<fw>The type of the captiuitie.</fw>
<ab n="3">Therefore thou
sonne of man, prepare thee stuffe for remoouing, and remooue by day
in their sight, and thou shalt remoue from thy place to another
place in their sight; it may be they will consider, though they bee
a rebellious house.<note> Or, instruments.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then shalt thou
bring foorth thy stuffe by day in their sight, as stuffe for
remoouing: and thou shalt goe foorth at euen in their sight, as
they that goe foorth into captiuitie.<note> Heb. as the goings foorth of captiuity.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Digge thou
through the wall in their sight, and cary out thereby.<note> Hebr. digge for thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In their sight
shalt thou beare it vpon thy shoulders, and cary it foorth in the
twy light: thou shalt couer thy face, that thou see not the ground:
for I haue set thee for a signe vnto the house of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I did so as I
was commanded: I brought forth my stuffe by day, as stuffe for
captiuity, and in the euen I digged through the wall with mine
hand, I brought it foorth in the twy light, and I bare it vpon my
shoulder in their sight.<note> Heb. digged for me.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And in the
morning came the word of the Lord vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="9">Sonne of man,
hath not the house of Israel, the rebellious house, sayd vnto thee,
What doest thou?</ab>
<ab n="10">Say thou vnto
them; Thus saith the Lord God; This burden concerneth the Prince in
Ierusalem, and all the house of Israel that are among them.</ab>
<ab n="11">Say, I am your
signe: like as I haue done, so shall it be done vnto them: they
shall remooue and goe into captiuitie.<note> Heb. by remouing goe into captiuitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Prince
that is among them, shall beare vpon his shoulder in the twylight,
and shall goe forth: they shall digge through the wall to cary out
thereby: he shall couer his face, that he see not the ground with
his eyes.</ab>
<ab n="13">My net also will
I spread vpon him, and he shall be taken in my snare, and I wil
bring him to Babylon to the land of the Caldeans, yet shall hee not
see it, though he shall die there.<note> Chap. 17. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I will
scatter toward euery winde all that are about him to helpe him, and
all his bands, and I wil draw out the sword after them.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they shall
know that I am the Lord, when I shal scatter them among the
nations, and disperse them in the countreys.</ab>

<fw>The type of the captiuitie.</fw>
<ab n="16">But I will leaue
a few men of them from the sword, from the famine, and from the
pestilence, that they may declare all their abominations among the
heathen whither they come, and they shall know that I am the
Lord.<note> Heb. men of number.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Moreouer,
the worde of the Lord came to me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="18">Sonne of man,
eate thy bread with quaking, and drinke thy water with trembling
and with carefulnesse,</ab>
<ab n="19">And say vnto the
people of the land; Thus sayth the Lord God, of the inhabitants of
Ierusalem, and of the land of Israel; They shall eat their bread
with carefulnes, and drinke their water with astonishment, that her
land may be desolate from all that is therein, because of the
violence of them that dwell therein.<note> Heb. the fulnesse thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And the cities
that are inhabited, shall be laid waste, and the land shall be
desolate, and yee shall know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And the
word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="22">Sonne of man,
what is that prouerbe, that ye haue in the land of Israel, saying;
The dayes are prolonged, and euery vision faileth?</ab>
<ab n="23">Tell them
therefore, Thus sayth the Lord God; I will make this prouerbe to
cease, and they shall no more vse it as a prouerbe in Israel: but
say vnto them, The dayes are at hand, and the effect of euery
vision.</ab>
<ab n="24">For there shall
bee no more any vaine vision, nor flattering diuination, within the
house of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="25">For I am the
Lord: I will speake, &amp; the word that I shall speake, shall come
to passe: it shall be no more prolonged: for in your dayes, O
rebellious house, will I say the word, and will performe it, sayth
the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Againe
the word of the Lord came to me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="27">Sonne of man,
behold, they of the house of Israel say; The vision that he seeth
is for many dayes to come, and he prophecieth of the times that are
far off.<note> 2.Pet.3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore say
vnto them, Thus saith the Lord God, There shal none of my words be
prolonged any more, but the worde which I haue spoken, shall be
done, sayth the Lord God.</ab>




</div>