<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_43" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-42-43.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIII.</head>
<head>1 The returning of the glory of God
into the Temple. 7 The sinne of Israel hindered Gods presence. 10
The Prophet exhorteth them to repentance, and obseruation of the
Law of the house. 13 The measures, 18 and the ordinances of the
Altar.</head>

<ab n="1">Afterward he
brought me to the gate, euen the gate that looketh toward the
East.</ab>
<ab n="2">And behold, the
glory of the God of Israel came from the way of the East: and his
voice was like a noise of many waters, and the earth shined with
his glory.<note> Chap.1. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And it was
according to the appearance of the vision which I saw, euen
according to the vision that I saw, when I came to destroy the
citie: and the visions were like the vision that I saw by the riuer
Chebar: and I fell vpon my face.<note> Chap.1.4. and 8.4. , Or, when I came to prophecie that the citie should be destroyed. See chap.9. 2,5.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the glorie of
the Lord came into the house by the way of the gate, whose prospect
is toward the East.</ab>
<ab n="5">So the Spirit
tooke me vp, and brought mee into the inner court, and behold, the
glory of the Lord filled the house.</ab>

<fw>The Altar, and his ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="6">And I heard him
speaking vnto me out of the house, &amp; the man stood by
me.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And he
said vnto me, Sonne of man, the place of my throne, and the place
of the soles of my feete, where I will dwell in the midst of the
children of Israel for euer, and my holy Name, shall the house of
Israel no more defile, neither they, nor their kings, by their
whoredome, nor by the carkeises of their kings in their high
places.</ab>
<ab n="8">In their setting
of their threshold by my thresholds, and their post by my postes,
and the wall betweene me and them, they haue euen defiled my holy
Name by their abominations that they haue committed: wherefore I
haue consumed them in mine anger.<note> Or, for there was but a wall betweene me and them.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Now let them put
away their whoredome, and the carkeises of their kings farre from
me, and I wil dwell in the middest of them for euer.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Thou
sonne of man, shew the house to the house of Israel, that they may
be ashamed of their iniquities, and let them measure the
patterne.<note> Or, summe, or number.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And if they be
ashamed of all that they haue done; shew them the forme of the
house, and the fashion thereof, and the goings out thereof, and the
commings in thereof, and all the formes thereof, and all the
ordinances thereof, and all the formes thereof, and all the lawes
thereof: &amp; write it in their sight, that they may keepe the
whole forme thereof, and all the Ordinances therof, and doe
them.</ab>
<ab n="12">This is the law
of the house; Upon the top of the mountaine, the whole limit
thereof round about shall be most holy: behold, this is the law of
the house.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And these
are the measures of the Altar after the cubites; the cubite is a
cubite and an hand breadth, euen the bottom shalbe a cubite, and
the breadth a cubite, and the border thereof by the edge therof
round about shalbe a spanne, and this shalbe the higher place of
the Altar.<note> Hebr. bosome. , Hebr. lippe.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And from the
bottom vpon the ground, euen to the lower settle, shalbe two
cubits, and the breadth one cubite, and from the lesser settle euen
to the greater settle shalbe foure cubites, and the breadth one
cubite.</ab>
<ab n="15">So the Altar
shalbe foure cubites, and from the altar and vpward shalbe foure
hornes.<note> Heb. Marel, that is, the Mountaine of God. , Hebr. Ariel, that is, the Lyon of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the altar
shalbe twelue cubites long, twelue broad, square in the foure
squares thereof.</ab>

<fw>The Altar, and his ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="17">And the settle
shall bee fourteene cubites long, and fourteene broad in the foure
squares thereof, and the border about it shalbe halfe a cubite, and
the bottome thereof shall be a cubite about, and his staires shall
looke toward the East.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And he
said vnto me, Sonne of man, thus saith the Lord God, These are the
ordinances of the Altar in the day when they shall make it to offer
burnt offrings thereon, and to sprinkle blood thereon.</ab>
<ab n="19">And thou shalt
giue to the Priests the Leuites that be of the seede of Zadok,
which approch vnto me, to minister vnto me, saith the Lord God, a
yong bullocke for a sinne offering.</ab>
<ab n="20">And thou shalt
take of the blood thereof, and put it on the foure hornes of it,
and on the foure corners of the settle, and vpon the border round
about: thus shalt thou cleanse and purge it.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thou shalt take
the bullocke also of the sinne offering, and he shall burne it in
the appointed place of the house without the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="22">And on the
second day thou shalt offer a kidde of the goats without blemish
for a sinne offering, and they shall cleanse the Altar, as they did
cleanse it with the bullocke.</ab>
<ab n="23">When thou hast
made an ende of cleansing it, thou shalt offer a yong bullocke
without blemish, and a ramme out of the flocke, without
blemish.</ab>
<ab n="24">And thou shalt
offer them before the Lord, and the Priests shall cast salt vpon
them, and they shall offer them vp for a burnt offering vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">Seuen dayes
shalt thou prepare euery day a goate for a sinne offering: they
shall also prepare a yong bullocke, and a ramme out of the flocke,
without blemish.</ab>
<ab n="26">Seuen dayes shal
they purge the Altar and purifie it, and they shall consecrate
themselues.<note> Heb. fill their hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And when these
dayes are expired, it shall be that vpon the eight day and so
forward, the Priests shall make your burnt offerings vpon the
Altar, and your peace offerings; and I will accept you, saith the
Lord God.<note> Or, thanke-offrings.</note></ab>



</div>