<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 The presumption of the Princes. 4
Their sinne and iudgement. 13 Ezekiel complaining, God sheweth him
his purpose in sauing a remnant, 21 and punishing the wicked. 22
The Glory of God leaueth the Citie. 24 Ezekiel is returned to the
captiuitie.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer the
Spirit lift me vp, and brought me vnto the East gate of the Lords
house, which looketh Eastward: and behold at the doore of the gate
fiue and twenty men; among whom I saw Iaazaniah the sonne of Azur,
and Pelatiah the sonne of Benaiah, Princes of the people.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then said he vnto
me; Sonne of man, these are the men that deuise mischiefe, &amp;
giue wicked counsel in this city.</ab>

<fw>The cauldron.</fw>
<ab n="3">Which say, It is
not neere, let vs build houses: this citie is the caldron, and we
be the flesh.<note> Or, it is not for vs to build houses neere. , 2.Pet.3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Therefore
prophecie against them, prophecie, O sonne of man.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Spirit of
the Lord fell vpon me, and said vnto me, Speake, thus saith the
Lord; Thus haue ye said, O house of Israel: for I know the things
that come into your minde, euery one of them.</ab>
<ab n="6">Ye haue
multiplyed your slaine in this citie, and yee haue filled the
streetes thereof with the slaine.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore thus
sayth the Lord God; Your slaine whom ye haue laid in the middest of
it, they are the flesh, and this citie is the cauldron: but I wil
bring you foorth out of the middest of it.</ab>
<ab n="8">Ye haue feared
the sword, and I will bring a sword vpon you, saith the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I will bring
you out of the middest thereof, and deliuer you into the hands of
strangers, and will execute iudgements among you.</ab>
<ab n="10">Yee shall fall
by the sword, I will iudge you in the border of Israel, and ye
shall know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="11">This citie shall
not be your cauldron, neither shall ye be the flesh in the middest
thereof, but I will iudge you in the border of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">And ye shall
know that I am the Lord: for yee haue not walked in my statutes,
neither executed my iudgements, but haue done after the maners of
the heathen that are round about you.<note> Or, which haue not walked.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And it
came to passe, when I prophecied, that Pelatiah the sonne of
Benaiah died: then fell I downe vpon my face, and cried with a loud
voice, and said; Ah Lord God, wilt thou make a full end of the
remnant of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="14">Againe the word
of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="15">Sonne of man,
thy brethren, euen thy brethren, the men of thy kinred, and all the
house of Israel wholly are they, vnto whom the inhabitants of
Ierusalem haue sayd; Get yee farre from the Lord: vnto vs is this
land giuen in possession.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore say,
Thus sayth the Lord God; Although I haue cast them farre off among
the heathen, and although I haue scattered them among the
countreys, yet will I be to them as a little Sanctuarie in the
countreys where they shall come.</ab>

<fw>A new spirit.</fw>
<ab n="17">Therefore say,
Thus saith the Lord God; I will euen gather you from the people,
and assemble you out of the countreys where ye haue beene
scattered, and I will giue you the land of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they shall
come thither, and they shall take away all the detestable things
thereof, and all the abominations thereof from thence.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I wil giue
them one heart, and I wil put a new spirit within you: and I will
take the stonie heart out of their flesh, and will giue them an
heart of flesh,<note> Ier.31.39. cha.36.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">That they may
walke in my statutes, and keepe mine ordinances, and doe them: and
they shall be my people, and I will be their God.</ab>
<ab n="21">But as for them
whose heart walketh after the heart of their detestable things, and
their abominations, I wil recompense their way vpon their owne
heads, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Then did
the Cherubims lift vp their wings, and the wheeles besides them,
and the glory of the God of Israel was ouer them aboue.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the glory of
the Lord went vp from the middest of the citie, and stood vpon the
mountaine, which is on the East side of the citie.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶
Afterwards the spirit tooke me vp, and brought me in vision by the
spirit of God into Caldea to them of the captiuity: so the vision
that I had seene, went vp from me.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then I spake
vnto them of the captiuity, all the things that the Lord had shewed
me.</ab>



</div>