<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_37" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-37-38.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVII.</head>
<head>1 By the resurrection of dry bones,
11 the dead hope of Israel is reuiued, 15 by the vniting of two
stickes, 18 is shewed the incorporation of Israel into Iudah. 20
The promises of Christs kingdome.</head>

<ab n="1">The hand of the
Lord was vpon mee, and caried mee out in the Spirit of the Lord,
and set mee downe in the middest of the valley which was full of
bones,</ab>
<ab n="2">And caused mee to
passe by them round about, and beholde, there were very many in the
open valley, and loe, they were very drie.<note> Or, champian.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And hee said vnto
mee, Sonne of man, can these bones liue? and I answered, O Lord
God, thou knowest.</ab>
<ab n="4">Againe he said
vnto me, Prophecie vpon these bones, and say vnto them; O yee drie
bones, heare the word of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">Thus saith the
Lord God vnto these bones, Behold, I wil cause breath to enter into
you, and ye shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I wil lay
sinewes vpon you, and wil bring vp flesh vpon you, and couer you
with skinne, and put breath in you, and ye shall liue, and ye shall
know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">So I prophecied
as I was commanded: and as I prophecied, there was a noise, and
beholde a shaking, and the bones came together, bone to his
bone.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when I
beheld, loe, the sinews and the flesh came vp vpon them, and the
skin couered them aboue; but there was no breath in them.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then said he vnto
mee, Prophecie vnto the winde, prophecie sonne of man, and say to
the winde, Thus saith the Lord God; Come from the foure windes, O
breath, and breathe vpon these slaine, that they may
liue.<note> Or, breath.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So I prophecied
as he commanded mee, and the breath came into them, and they liued,
and stood vp vpon their feet, an exceeding great armie.</ab>

<fw>The vnitie of all the tribes.</fw>
<ab n="11">¶ Then he
said vnto me, Sonne of man, these bones are the whole house of
Israel: behold, they say; Our bones are dried, and our hope is
lost, wee are cut off for our parts.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore
prophecie and say vnto them, Thus saith the Lord God, Behold, O my
people, I wil open your graues, and cause you to come vp out of
your graues, and bring you into the land of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="13">And ye shall
know that I am the Lord, when I haue opened your graues, O my
people, and brought you vp out of your graues,</ab>
<ab n="14">And shall put my
spirit in you, and yee shall liue, and I shall place you in your
owne land: then shall ye know that I the Lord haue spoken it, and
perfourmed it, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ The word
of the Lord came againe vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="16">Moreouer thou
sonne of man, take thee one sticke, and write vpon it, For Iudah
and for the children of Israel his companions: then take another
sticke, and write vpon it; For Ioseph the sticke of Ephraim, and
for all the house of Israel his companions.</ab>
<ab n="17">And ioyne them
one to another into one sticke, and they shall become one in thine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And when
the children of thy people shall speake vnto thee, saying, Wilt
thou not shew vs what thou meanest by these?</ab>
<ab n="19">Say vnto them,
Thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I will take the sticke of Ioseph
which is in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel his
fellowes, and will put them with him, euen with the sticke of
Iudah, and make them one sticke, and they shall be one in mine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
stickes whereon thou writest, shalbe in thine hand before their
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="21">And say vnto
them, Thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I will take the children of
Israel from among the heathen whither they be gone, and will gather
them on euery side, and bring them into their owne land.</ab>
<ab n="22">And I will make
them one nation in the land vpon the mountaines of Israel, and one
King shall be king to them all: and they shalbe no more two
nations, neither shall they bee diuided into two kingdomes any more
at all.<note> Iohn 10. 16.</note></ab>

<fw>The vnitie of all the tribes.</fw>
<ab n="23">Neither shall
they defile themselues any more with their idoles, nor with their
detestable things, nor with any of their transgressions: but I will
saue them out of all their dwelling places, wherein they haue
sinned, and will cleanse them: so shall they be my people, and I
will be their God.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Dauid my
seruant shall be King ouer them, and they all shall haue one
shepheard: they shall also walke in my iudgements, and obserue my
statutes, and doe them.<note> Isai 40.11. iere.23.5. and 30.9. cha. 34. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And they shall
dwell in the land that I haue giuen vnto Iacob my seruant, wherin
your fathers haue dwelt, and they shall dwell therein, euen they
and their children, and their childrens children for euer, and my
seruant Dauid shalbe their prince for euer.</ab>
<ab n="26">Moreouer I will
make a couenant of peace with them, it shall be an euerlasting
couenant wich them, and I will place them and multiply them, and
will set my Sanctuary in the middest of them for
euermore.<note> Psal.89.4. cha. 34.25. , 2. Cor.6. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">My Tabernacle
also shalbe with them: yea, I will be their God, and they shalbe my
people.<note> Chap. 11. 20. and 14.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And the heathen
shal know that I the Lord doe sanctifie Israel, when my Sanctuarie
shalbe in the middest of them for euermore.</ab>



</div>