<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 A relation vnto Pharaoh, 3 of the
glory of Assyria, 10 and the fall thereof, for pride. 18 The like
destruction of Egypt.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe in the eleuenth yeere, in the third moneth, in the first day
of the moneth, that the word of the Lord came vnto mee,
saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man,
speake vnto Pharaoh king of Egypt, and to his multitude, Whom art
thou like in thy greatnesse?</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Behold,
the Assyrian was a Cedar in Lebanon with faire branches, and with a
shadowing shrowd, and of an hie stature, and his top was among the
thicke boughes.<note> Heb. faire of branches.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The waters made
him great, the deepe set him vp on high with her riuers running
round about his plants, and sent out her little riuers vnto all the
trees of the field.<note> Or, nourished. , Or, brought him vp. , Heb. conduits.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore his
height was exalted aboue all the trees of the field, and his
boughes were multiplied, and his branches became long because of
the multitude of waters, when he shot foorth.<note> Or, when it sent them foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">All the foules of
heauen made their nests in his boughes, and vnder his branches did
all the beastes of the field bring foorth their yong, and vnder his
shadow dwelt all great nations.<note> Dan.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thus was hee
faire in his greatnesse, in the length of his branches: for his
roote was by great waters.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Cedars in the
garden of God could not hide him: the Firre trees were not like his
boughes, and the chesnut trees were not like his branches: not any
tree in the garden of God, was like vnto him in his
beautie.<note> Gen.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">I haue made him
faire by the multitude of his branches: so that all the trees of
Eden, that were in the garden of God, enuied him.</ab>

<fw>The glory, and fall of Assyria.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ Therefore
thus saith the Lord God, Because thou hast lifted vp thy selfe in
height, and hee hath shot vp his top among the thicke boughes, and
his heart is lifted vp in his height;</ab>
<ab n="11">I haue therefore
deliuered him into the hand of the mightie one of the heathen: hee
shall surely deale with him, I haue driuen him out for his
wickednesse.<note> Heb. in doing hee shall doe vnto him.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And strangers,
the terrible of the nations haue cut him off, and haue left him:
vpon the mountaines and in all the valleys his branches are fallen,
and his boughes are broken by all the riuers of the land, and all
the people of the earth are gone downe from his shadow, and haue
left him.</ab>
<ab n="13">Upon his ruine
shal all the foules of the heauen remaine, &amp; all the beasts of
the field shalbe vpon his branches,</ab>
<ab n="14">To the ende that
none of all the trees by the waters exalt themselues for their
height, neither shoot vp their top among the thicke boughes,
neither their trees stand vp in their height, all that drinke
water: for they are all deliuered vnto death, to the nether parts
of the earth in the middest of the children of men, with them that
go downe to the pit.<note> Or, stand vpon themselues for their height.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thus saith the
Lord God, In the day when hee went downe to the graue, I caused a
mourning, I couered the deepe for him, and I restrained the floods
therof, and the great waters were stayed; and I caused Lebanon to
mourne for him, and all the trees of the field fainted for
him.<note> Hebr. to be blacke.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I made the
nations to shake at the sound of his fall, when I cast him downe to
hell with them that descend into the pit: and all the trees of
Eden, the choice and best of Lebanon, all that drinke water, shall
be comforted in the nether parts of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">They also went
downe into hell with him vnto them that be slaine with the sword,
and they that were his arme, that dwelt vnder his shadow in the
middest of the heathen.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ To whom
art thou thus like in glory &amp; in greatnesse among the trees of
Eden? yet shalt thou be brought downe with the trees of Eden vnto
the nether parts of the earth: thou shalt lie in the middest of the
vncircumcised, with them that be slaine by the sword: this is
Pharaoh and all his multitude, saith the Lord God.</ab>



</div>