<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 God answereth idolaters according
to their owne heart. 6 They are exhorted to repent, for feare of
iudgements, by meanes of seduced prophets. 12 Gods irreuocable
sentence of famine, 15 of noisome beasts, 17 of the sword, 19 and
of pestilence. 22 A remnant shalbe reserued for example of
others.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came
certaine of the Elders of Israel vnto me, and sate before
me.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the word of
the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Sonne of man,
these men haue set vp their idoles in their heart, and put the
stumbling blocke of their iniquitie before their face: should I be
enquired of at all by them?</ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore speake
vnto them, and say vnto them, Thus saith the Lord God; Euery man of
the house of Israel that setteth vp his idoles in his heart, and
putteth the stumbling blocke of his iniquitie before his face, and
commeth to the Prophet, I the Lord will answere him that commeth,
according to the multitude of his idoles,</ab>
<ab n="5">That I may take
the house of Israel in their owne heart, because they are all
estranged from mee through their idoles.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Therefore
say vnto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord God, Repent, and
turne your selues from your idoles, and turne away your faces from
all your abominations.<note> Or, others.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For euery one of
the house of Israel, or of the stranger that soiourneth in Israel,
which separateth himselfe from me, and setteth vp his idols in his
heart, and putteth the stumbling blocke of his iniquitie before his
face, and commeth to a prophet to enquire of him concerning me, I
the Lord will answere him by my selfe.</ab>
<ab n="8">And I wil set my
face against that man, and will make him a signe and a prouerbe,
and I will cut him off from the midst of my people, and yee shall
know that I am the Lord.<note> Deut. 28. 37.chap.5. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And if the
prophet bee deceiued when hee hath spoken a thing, I the Lord haue
deceiued that prophet, and I will stretch out my hand vpon him, and
will destroy him from the midst of my people Israel.<note> 1.Kings. 22.23.</note></ab>

<fw>Noah, Daniel, Iob.</fw>
<ab n="10">And they shall
beare the punishment of their iniquitie: the punishment of the
prophet shall bee euen as the punishment of him that seeketh vnto
him:</ab>
<ab n="11">That the house
of Israel may goe no more astray from me, neither be polluted any
more with all their transgressions; but that they may be my people,
and I may bee their God, sayeth the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ The word
of the Lord came againe to me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Sonne of man,
when the land sinneth against mee by trespassing grieuously, then
will I stretch out mine hand vpon it, and will breake the staffe of
the bread thereof, and will send famine vpon it, and will cut off
man and beast from it.<note> Leuit.26.26. chap.4.16. and 5.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Though these
three men, Noah, Daniel and Iob were in it, they should deliuer but
their owne soules by their righteousnes, saith the Lord
God.<note> Iere 15.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ If I
cause noisome beastes to passe through the land, and they spoile
it, so that it bee desolate, that no man may passe through because
of the beasts:<note> Or, bereaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Though these
three men were in it, as I liue, saith the Lord God, they shall
deliuer neither sonnes nor daughters: they onely shalbe deliuered,
but the land shalbe desolate.<note> Hebr. in the midst of it.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Or if I
bring a sword vpon that land, and say, Sword, goe through the
lande, so that I cut off man and beast from it:</ab>
<ab n="18">Though these
three men were in it, as I liue, saith the Lord God, they shall
deliuer neither sonnes nor daughter, but they onely shall bee
deliuered themselues.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Or if I
send a pestilence into that land, and powre out my fury vpon it in
blood, to cut off from it man and beast:</ab>
<ab n="20">Though Noah,
Daniel and Iob were in it, as I liue, saith the Lord God, they shal
deliuer neither son nor daughter: they shall but deliuer their owne
soules by their righteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="21">For thus saith
the Lord God, How much more when I send my foure sore iudgements
vpon Ierusalem; the sword, and the famine, and the noisome beast,
and the pestilence, to cut off from it man and beast?<note> Or, also when.</note></ab>

<fw>Of the Vine.</fw>
<ab n="22">¶ Yet
behold, therein shalbe left a remnant that shalbe brought foorth,
both sonnes and daughters: behold, they shall come foorth vnto you,
and ye shall see their way and their doings: and ye shalbe
comforted concerning the euill that I haue brought vpon Ierusalem,
euen concerning all that I haue brought vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they shall
comfort you when yee see their wayes and their doings: and ye shal
know that I haue not done without cause, all that I haue done in
it, saith the Lord God.</ab>



</div>