<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_47" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-46-47.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVII.</head>
<head>1 The vision of the holy waters. 6
The vertue of them. 13 The borders of the land. 22 The diuision of
it by lot.</head>

<ab n="1">Afterward hee
brought me againe vnto the doore of the house, and behold, waters
issued out from vnder the threshold of the house Eastward: for the
forefront of the house stood toward the East, and the waters came
downe from vnder from the right side of the house, at the South
side of the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then brought hee
me out of the way of the gate Northward, and ledde me about the way
without vnto the vtter gate by the way that looketh Eastward, and
behold, there ranne out waters on the right side.</ab>

<fw>The vision of waters.</fw>
<ab n="3">And when the man
that had the line in his hand, went forth Eastward, he measured a
thousand cubites, and he brought me through the waters: the waters
were to the ancles.<note> Heb. waters of the ancles.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Againe he
measured a thousand, and brought me through the waters; the waters
were to the knees: againe he measured a thousand, and brought mee
through; the waters were to the loynes.</ab>
<ab n="5">Afterward hee
measured a thousand, and it was a riuer, that I could not passe
ouer: for the waters were risen, waters to swimme in, a riuer that
could not be passed ouer.<note> Heb. waters of swimming.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And hee
said vnto me, Sonne of man, hast thou seene this? Then hee brought
me, and caused me to returne to the brinke of the riuer.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now when I had
returned, behold, at the banke of the riuer were very many trees on
the one side and on the other.<note> Heb. lip. , Reu. 22.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then said he vnto
me, These waters issue out toward the East country, and go downe
into the desert, and goe into the sea: which being brought foorth
into the sea, the waters shalbe healed.<note> Or, plaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall come
to passe, that euery thing that liueth, which mooueth,
whithersoeuer the riuers shall come, shall liue, and there shall be
a very great multitude of fish, because these waters shall come
thither: for they shall be healed, and euery thing shall liue
whither the riuer commeth.<note> Heb. two riuers.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And it shall
come to passe that the fishers shall stand vpon it, from Engedi
euen vnto En-eglaim; they shall be a place to spread foorth nets,
their fish shall bee according to their kindes, as the fish of the
great Sea, exceeding many.</ab>
<ab n="11">But the myrie
places thereof, and the marishes thereof, shall not be healed, they
shall be giuen to salt.<note> Or, and that which shall not be healed.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And by the riuer
vpon the banke thereof on this side, and on that side, shall grow
all trees for meat, whose leafe shal not fade, neither shal the
fruit thereof be consumed: it shall bring forth new fruit,
according to his moneths, because their waters they issued out of
the Sanctuarie, and the fruite thereof shall be for meate, and the
leafe thereof for medicine.<note> Heb. shall come vp. , Or, principall. , Or, for bruises and sores. , Reu.22.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Thus
sayth the Lord God, This shall be the border, whereby yee shall
inherite the land, according to the twelue tribes of Israel: Ioseph
shall haue two portions.</ab>

<fw>The borders, and portions of the
Tribes.</fw>
<ab n="14">And yee shall
inherite it, one as well as an other: concerning the which I lifted
vp mine hand to giue it vnto your fathers, and this land shal fall
vnto you for inheritance.<note> Or, swore. , Gen. 12. 7. and 17. 8. and 26. 3. and 28. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And this shall
be the border of the land toward the North side from the great Sea,
the way of Hethlon, as men goe to Zedad:</ab>
<ab n="16">Hamath,
Berothah, Sibraim, which is betweene the border of Damascus, and
the border of Hamath: Hazar Hatticon, which is by the coast of
Hauran.<note> Or, the middle village.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the border
from the Sea shall be Hazar-enan, the border of Damascus, and the
North northward, and the border of Hamath: and this is the North
side.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the East
side yee shall measure from Hauran, and from Damascus, and from
Gilead, and from the land of Israel by Iordan, from the border vnto
the East sea: &amp; this is the East side.<note> Heb from betweene.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the South
side Southward from Tamar, euen to the waters of strife in Kadesh,
the riuer, to the great Sea; and this is the South side
Southward.<note> Or, Meribah. , Or, valley. , Or, toward Teman.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The West side
also shall be the great Sea from the border, till a man come ouer
against Hamath: this is the West side.</ab>
<ab n="21">So shall yee
diuide this land vnto you according to the Tribes of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And it
shall come to passe, that yee shall diuide it by lot for an
inheritance vnto you, and to the strangers that soiourne among you,
which shall beget children among you, and they shall be vnto you as
borne in the countrey among the children of Israel; they shall haue
inheritance with you among the Tribes of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="23">And it shall
come to passe that in what Tribe the stranger soiourneth, there
shall yee giue him his inheritance, saith the Lord God.</ab>



</div>