<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the type of a siege, is
shewed the time from the defection of Ieroboam to the captiuitie. 9
By the prouision of the siege, is shewed the hardnesse of the
famine.</head>

<ab n="1">Thou also sonne of
man, take thee a tile, and lay it before thee, and pourtray vpon it
the citie, euen Ierusalem,</ab>
<ab n="2">And lay siege
against it, and build a fort against it, and cast a mount against
it: set the campe also against it, and set battering rammes against
it round about.<note> Or, chiefe leaders.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Moreouer take thou
vnto thee an yron panne, and set it for a wall of yron betweene
thee and the city, and set thy face against it, and it shalbe
besieged, and thou shalt lay siege against it: this shalbe a signe
to the house of Israel.<note> Or, a flat plate, or slice.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Lie thou also vpon
thy left side, and lay the iniquitie of the house of Israel vpon
it: according to the number of the dayes that thou shalt lie vpon
it, thou shalt beare their iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="5">For I haue layed
vpon thee the yeeres of their iniquitie, according to the number of
the dayes, three hundreth and ninetie daies. So shalt thou beare
the iniquitie of the house of Israel.<note> Num.14.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And when thou hast
accomplished them, lie againe on thy right side, and thou shalt
beare the iniquitie of the house of Iudah fourtie dayes: I haue
appointed thee each day for a yeere.<note> Hebr. a day for a yeere, a day for a yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore thou
shalt set thy face toward the siege of Ierusalem, and thine arme
shalbe vncouered, and thou shalt prophecie against it.</ab>
<ab n="8">And behold, I wil
lay bands vpon thee, and thou shalt not turne thee from one side to
an other, till thou hast ended the dayes of thy siege.<note> Hebr. from thy side to thy side.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Take thou
also vnto thee wheat, and barley, and beanes, and lentils, and
millet, and fitches, and put them in one vessell, and make thee
bread thereof according to the number of the dayes that thou shalt
lie vpon thy side; three hundreth and ninetie dayes shalt thou eate
thereof.<note> Or, spelt.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And thy meate
which thou shalt eat, shalbe by weight twentie shekels a day: from
time to time shalt thou eat it.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thou shalt drinke
also water by measure, the sixt part of an hin: from time to time
shalt thou drinke.</ab>

<fw>Great famine.</fw>
<ab n="12">And thou shalt
eate it as barley cakes, &amp; thou shalt bake it with doung that
commeth out of man in their sight.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord
said, Euen thus shall the children of Israel eat their defiled
bread among the Gentiles, whither I will driue them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then said I, Ah
Lord God, behold, my soule hath not bene polluted: for from my
youth vp euen til now, haue I not eaten of that which dieth of it
selfe, or is torne in pieces, neither came there abominable flesh
into my mouth.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then he said vnto
me, Loe, I haue giuen thee cowes doung for mans doung and thou
shalt prepare thy bread therewith.</ab>
<ab n="16">Moreouer he said
vnto me, Sonne of man, behold, I wil breake the staffe of bread in
Ierusalem, and they shall eat bread by weight, and with care, and
they shal drinke water by measure, and with
astonishment:<note> Leuit. 26. 26. chap 5. 16. and 13. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">That they may
want bread and water, &amp; be astonied one with an other, and
consume away for their iniquitie.</ab>



</div>