<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_46" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-45-46.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-46-47.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVI.</head>
<head>1 Ordinances for the Prince, in his
worship, 9 and for the people. 16 An order for the Princes
inheritance. 19 The courts for boyling and baking.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord God, The gate of the inner court, that looketh toward the
East, shalbe shut the sixe working dayes: but on the Sabbath it
shall be opened, and in the day of the New moone it shalbe
opened.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Prince
shall enter by the way of the porch of that gate without, and shall
stand by the post of the gate, and the Priests shall prepare his
burnt offering, and his peace offerings, and he shall worship at
the threshold of the gate: then he shall goe foorth, but the gate
shall not be shut vntil the euening.</ab>
<ab n="3">Likewise the
people of the land shall worship at the doore of this gate before
the Lord, in the Sabbaths, and in the New moones.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the burnt
offering that the Prince shall offer vnto the Lord in the Sabbath
day, shall be sixe lambes without blemish, and a ramme without
blemish.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the meat
offring shalbe an Ephah for a ramme, and the meate offering for the
lambes as he shalbe able to giue, and an Hin of oile to an
Ephah.<note> Hebr. the gift of his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And in the day of
the New moone it shall be a yong bullocke without blemish, and sixe
lambes, and a ramme: they shalbe without blemish.</ab>
<ab n="7">And hee shall
prepare a meat offering, an Ephah for a bullocke, and an Ephah for
a ramme, and for the lambs, according as his hand shall attaine
vnto, and an Hin of oile to an Ephah.</ab>

<fw>Of the Prince, and his
offerings.</fw>
<ab n="8">And when the
Prince shall enter, he shall goe in by the way of the porch of that
gate, and he shall goe foorth by the way thereof.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ But when
the people of the land shall come before the Lord, in the solemne
feasts, he that entreth in by the way of the North gate to worship,
shall goe out by the way of the South gate: and he that entreth by
the way of the South gate, shall goe forth by the way of the North
gate: he shall not returne by the way of the gate whereby he came
in, but shall goe foorth ouer against it.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the Prince
in the midst of them when they goe in, shal goe in, and when they
goe foorth, shall goe forth.</ab>
<ab n="11">And in the
feasts, and in the solemnities, the meat offering shalbe an Ephah
to a bullocke, and an Ephah to a ramme, and to the lambes, as he is
able to giue, and an Hin of oile to an Ephah.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now when the
Prince shall prepare a voluntary burnt offering or peace offerings,
voluntarily vnto the Lord, one shall then open him the gate that
looketh toward the East, and he shall prepare his burnt offering,
and his peace offerings, as hee did on the Sabbath day, then he
shall goe foorth, and after his going foorth, one shall shut the
gate.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou shalt daily
prepare a burnt offering vnto the Lord, of a lambe of the first
yeere, without blemish thou shalt prepare it euery
morning.<note> Hebr. of his yeere. , Hebr. morning by morning.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And thou shalt
prepare a meat offering for it euery morning; the sixt part of an
Ephah, and the third part of an Hin of oyle, to temper with the
fine flowre; a meat offering continually, by a perpetual ordinance
vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thus shall they
prepare the lambe, and the meat offering, and the oyle, euery
morning, for a continuall burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Thus
saith the Lord God, If the prince giue a gift vnto any of his
sonnes, the inheritance thereof shall be his sonnes, it shall be
their possession by inheritance:</ab>
<ab n="17">But if hee giue
a gift of his inheritance to one of his seruants, then it shalbe
his to the yeere of libertie: after, it shall returne to the
Prince, but his inheritance shalbe his sonnes for them.</ab>

<fw>The vision of waters.</fw>
<ab n="18">Moreouer, the
Prince shall not take of the peoples inheritance by oppression, to
thrust them out of their possession: but hee shall giue his sonnes
inheritance out of his owne possession, that my people be not
scattered euery man from his possession.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ After, he
brought me through the entry, which was at the side of the gate,
into the holy chambers of the Priests which looked toward
þe North: and behold, there was a place on the two
sides Westward.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then said hee
vnto me, This is the place where the Priests shall boyle the
trespasse offring, and the sinne offering, where they shall bake
the meate offering: that they beare them not out into the vtter
court, to sanctifie the people.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then hee brought
me foorth into the vtter court, and caused me to passe by the foure
corners of the court, and behold, in euery corner of the court
there was a court.<note> Heb. a court in a corner of a court, and a court in a corner of a court.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">In the foure
corners of the court there were courts ioyned of fourtie cubits
long, and thirtie broad: these foure corners were of one
measure.<note> Or, made with chimneys. , Heb. cornered.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And there was a
new building round about in them, round about them foure and it was
made with boyling places vnder the rowes round about.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then said he
vnto me, These are the places of them that boyle, where the
ministers of the house shall boyle the sacrifice of the
people.</ab>



</div>