<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-39-39.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>1 Gods iudement vpon Gog. 8 Israels
victory. 11 Gogs buriall in Hamon-Gog. 17 The feast of the Foules.
23 Israel hauing beene plagued for their sinnes, shall be gathered
againe with eternall fauour.</head>

<ab n="1">Therefore thou
sonne of man, prophecie against Gog, and say, Thus saith the Lord
God; Behold, I am against thee O Gog, the chiefe prince of Meshech
&amp; Tubal.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I will turne
thee backe, and leaue but the sixt part of thee, and will cause
thee to come vp from the North parts, and will bring thee vpon the
mountaines of Israel:<note> Or, strike thee with sixe plagues, Or, drawe thee backe, with an book of six teeth, as chap. 38. 4. , Heb. the sides of the North.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Gog, and Magog.</fw>
<ab n="3">And I will smite
thy bow out of thy left hand, and will cause thine arrowes to fall
out of thy right hand.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou shalt fall
vpon the mountaines of Israel, thou &amp; all thy bands, and the
people that is with thee: I will giue thee vnto the rauenous birds
of euery sort, and to the beasts of the field to be
deuoured.<note> Heb. wing. , Heb. to deuoure.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou shalt fall
vpon the open field, for I haue spoken it, saith the Lord
God.<note> Hebr. the face of the field.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I will send a
fire on Magog, and among them that dwell carelesly in the yles, and
they shall know that I am the Lord.<note> Or, confidently.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So will I make my
holy Name knowen in the midst of my people Israel, and I will not
let them pollute my holy Name any more, and the heathen shall know
that I am the Lord, the holy One in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Behold, it
is come, and it is done, saith the Lord God, this is the day
whereof I haue spoken.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they that
dwell in the cities of Israel, shall goe forth, and shall set on
fire, and burne the weapons, both the shields and the bucklers, the
bowes and the arrowes, and the handstaues and the speares, and they
shall burne them with fire seuen yeeres.<note> Or, iauelins. , Or, make a fire of them.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So that they
shall take no wood out of the field, neither cut downe any out of
the forrests: for they shall burne the weapons with fire, and they
shall spoile those that spoiled them, and rob those that robbed
them, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And it
shal come to passe at that day, that I will giue vnto Gog a place
there of graues in Israel, the valley of the passengers on the East
of the Sea: and it shall stop the noses of the passengers, and
there shall they burie Gog, and all his multitude, and they shal
call it, the valley of Hamon-gog.<note> Or, mouthes. , That is, the multitude of Gog.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And seuen
moneths shall the house of Israel bee burying of them, that they
may cleanse the land.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yea all the
people of the land shall burie them, and it shall be to them a
renowne the day that I shall be glorified, saith the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they shall
seuer out men of continual emploiment, passing through the land, to
burie with the passengers those that remaine vpon the face of the
earth to clense it: after the end of seuen moneths shall they
search.<note> Heb. men of continuance.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Gog, and Magog.</fw>
<ab n="15">And the
passengers that passe through the lande, when any seeth a mans
bone, then shall he set vp a signe by it, till the buriers haue
buried it in the valley of Hamon-gog.<note> Heb. build</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And also the
name of the citie shall be Hamonah: thus shal they clense the
land.<note> That is, the multitude.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And thou
sonne of man, Thus saith the Lord God, Speake vnto euery feathered
foule, and to euery beast of the field, Assemble your selues, and
come, gather your selues on euery side to my sacrifice that I doe
sacrifice for you, euen a great sacrifice vpon the mountaines of
Israel, that ye may eat flesh and drinke blood.<note> Heb. to the foule of euery wing. , Or, slaughter.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Ye shall eate
the flesh of the mightie, and drinke the blood of the princes of
the earth, of rammes, of lambes and of goats, of bullocks, all of
them fatlings of Bashan.<note> Heb. great goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And yee shall
eate fat till yee be full, and drinke blood till yee be drunken, of
my sacrifice which I haue sacrificed for you.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thus yee shall
be filled at my table with horses and charets, with mightie men,
and with all men of warre, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="21">And I will set
my glory among the heathen, and all the heathen shal see my
iudgement that I haue executed, and my hande that I haue laid vpon
them.</ab>
<ab n="22">So the house of
Israel shall know that I am the Lord their God from that day and
forward.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
heathen shall knowe that the house of Israel went into captiuitie
for their iniquitie: because they trespassed against me, therefore
hid I my face from them, and gaue them into the hand of their
enemies; so fell they all by the sword.</ab>
<ab n="24">According to
their vncleannesse, and according to their transgressions haue I
done vnto them, and hid my face from them.</ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Now will I bring againe the captiuitie of
Iacob, and haue mercie vpon the whole house of Israel, and will be
ielous for my holy Name:</ab>
<ab n="26">After that they
haue borne their shame, and all their trespasses, wherby they haue
trespassed against me, when they dwelt safely in their lande, and
none made them afraid.</ab>

<fw>The measuring of the Temple, and of the
buildings of it.</fw>
<ab n="27">When I haue
brought them againe from the people, and gathered them out of their
enemies lands, and am sanctified in them in the sight of many
nations;<note> Chap. 36. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Then shall they
know that I am the Lord their God, which caused them to be led into
captiuitie among the heathen: but I haue gathered them vnto their
owne land, and haue left none of them any more there.<note> Hebr. by my causing of them &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Neither will I
hide my face any more from them: for I haue powred out my Spirit
vpon the house of Israel, saith the Lord God.<note> Ioel 2. 28. acts. 2.17.</note></ab>



</div>