<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The iudgement of Israel for their
idolatrie. 8 A remnant shall be blessed. 11 The faithfull are
exhorted to lament their calamities.</head>

<ab n="1">And the worde of
the Lord came vnto mee, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man, set
thy face towardes the mountaines of Israel, and prophecie against
them,<note> Cha.36.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And say, Ye
mountaines of Israel, Heare the word of the Lord God, Thus saith
the Lord God to the mountaines and to the hilles, to the riuers and
to the valleys, Behold, I, euen I will bring a sword vpon you, and
I will destroy your high places.</ab>
<ab n="4">And your altars
shalbe desolate, and your images shall be broken: and I will cast
downe your slaine men before your idoles.<note> Or, sunne images, and so vers. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And I will lay the
dead carkeises of the children of Israel before their idoles, and I
will scatter your bones round about your altars.<note> Heb. giue.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In all your
dwelling places the cities shall be laid waste, and the high places
shalbe desolate, that your altars may be laid waste and made
desolate, and your idols may be broken and cease, and your images
may bee cut downe, and your workes may be abolished.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the slaine
shall fall in the midst of you, and ye shall knowe that I am the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Yet will I
leaue a remnant, that he may haue some, that shall escape the sword
among the nations, when ye shalbe scattered through the
countreys.</ab>

<fw>The desolation of Israel.</fw>
<ab n="9">And they that
escape of you shall remember me among the nations, whither they
shalbe caried captiues, because I am broken with their whorish
heart which hath departed from me, and with their eyes which goe a
whoring after their idoles: and they shall loathe themselues for
the euils which they haue committed in all their
abominations.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they shall
know that I am the Lord, and that I haue not said in vaine, that I
would doe this euill vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Thus sayth
the Lord God; Smite with thine hand, and stampe with thy foot, and
say, Alas, for all the euill abominations of the house of Israel:
for they shall fall by the sword, by the famine, and by the
pestilence.<note> Chap. 21. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">He that is farre
off shall die of the pestilence, and he that is neere shall fall by
the sword, and hee that remaineth and is besieged, shall die by the
famine: thus will I accomplish my furie vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then shal ye know
that I am the Lord, when their slaine men shalbe among their idoles
round about their altars, vpon euery high hill in all the tops of
the mountaines, and vnder euery greene tree, and vnder euery thicke
oke, the place where they did offer sweet sauour to all their
idoles.</ab>
<ab n="14">So will I stretch
out my hand vpon them, and make the land desolate, yea more
desolate then the wildernesse towards Diblath, in all their
habitations, and they shall know that I am the Lord.<note> Or, desolate from the wildernesse.</note></ab>



</div>