<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The vision of the coales of fire,
to bee scattered ouer the citie. 8 The vision of the
Cherubims.</head>

<ab n="1">Then I looked,
and beholde, in the firmament that was aboue the head of the
Cherubims, there appeared ouer them as it were a Saphir stone, as
the appearance of the likenesse of a throne.<note> Cha.1.22.</note></ab>

<fw>The vision of the Cherubims.</fw>
<ab n="2">And hee spake
vnto the man clothed with linnen, and sayd, Goe in between the
wheeles, euen vnder the Cherub, and fill thine hand with coales of
fire from betweene the Cherubims, and scatter them ouer the city.
And he went in my sight.<note> Heb. the hollow of thine hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now the Cherubims
stood on the right side of the house, when the man went in, and the
cloud filled the inner court.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then the glory of
the Lord went vp from the Cherub, and stood ouer the threshold of
the house, and the house was filled with the cloud, and the court
was full of the brightnesse of the Lords glory.<note> Hebr. was lifted vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the sound of
the Cherubims wings was heard euen to the vtter court, as the voice
of the Almighty God when he speaketh.<note> Chap.1. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe that when he had commanded the man clothed with linnen,
saying; Take fire from betweene the wheeles, from betweene the
Cherubims; then he went in and stood beside the wheeles.</ab>
<ab n="7">And one Cherub
stretched forth his hand from betweene the Cherubims vnto the fire
that was betweene the Cherubims: and tooke thereof, and put it into
the handes of him that was clothed with linnen, who tooke it, and
went out.<note> Hebr. sent foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And there
appeared in the Cherubims, the forme of a mans hand vnder their
wings.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when I
looked, behold the foure wheeles by the Cherubims, one wheele by
one Cherub, and an other wheele by an other Cherub: and the
appearance of the wheeles was as the colour of a Berill
stone.<note> Chap.1. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And as for their
appearances, they foure had one likenes as if a wheele had bene in
the midst of a wheele.</ab>
<ab n="11">When they went,
they went vpon their foure sides; they turned not as they went, but
to the place whither the head looked, they followed it; they turned
not as they went.</ab>
<ab n="12">And their whole
body, and their backes, and their handes, and their wings, and the
wheeles, were ful of eyes round about, euen the wheeles that they
foure had.<note> Hebr. flesh.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">As for the
wheeles, it was cried vnto them in my hearing, O
wheele.<note> Or, they were called in my hearing, wheele, or Galgal.</note></ab>

<fw>The vision of the Cherubims.</fw>
<ab n="14">And euery one
had foure faces: the first face was the face of a Cherub, and the
second face was the face of a man, and the third the face of a
lion, and the fourth the face of an eagle.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
Cherubims were lifted vp, this is the liuing creature that I saw by
the riuer of Chebar.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when the
Cherubims went, the wheeles went by them: and when the Cherubims
lift vp their wings, to mount vp from the earth, the same wheels
also turned not frō beside them.</ab>
<ab n="17">When they stood,
these stood, and when they were lifted vp, these lift vp themselues
also: for the spirit of the liuing creature was in
them.<note> Or, of life.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Then the glory
of the Lord departed from off the threshold of the house, and stood
ouer the Cherubims.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
Cherubims lift vp their wings, and mounted vp from the earth in my
sight: when they went out, the wheeles also were besides them, and
euery one stood at the doore of the East gate of the Lords house,
and the glorie of the God of Israel was ouer them aboue.</ab>
<ab n="20">This is the
liuing creature that I saw vnder the God of Israel, by the riuer of
Chebar, and I knew that they were the Cherubims.</ab>
<ab n="21">Euery one had
foure faces a piece, and euery one foure wings, and the likenesse
of the handes of a man was vnder their wings.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the
likenesse of their faces was the same faces which I saw by the
riuer of Chebar, their appearances and themselues: they went euery
one straight forward.</ab>



</div>