<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 A Catalogue of sinnes in
Ierusalem. 13 God will burne them as drosse in his furnace. 23 The
generall corruption of Prophets, Priests, Princes, and
people.</head>


<fw>Ierusalems sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="1">Moreouer the word
of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Now thou sonne of
man, wilt thou iudge, wilt thou iudge the bloodie citie? yea thou
shalt shew her all her abominations.<note> Chap.20. 41. and 23. 36. , Or, plead for. , Heb. citie of bloods. , Heb. make her know.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then say thou,
Thus saith the Lord God; The citie sheadeth blood in the middest of
it, that her time may come, and maketh idoles against herselfe to
defile herselfe.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou art become
guilty in thy blood that thou hast shed, and hast defiled thy selfe
in thine idoles, which thou hast made, and thou hast caused thy
daies to draw neere, and art come euen vnto thy yeeres; therfore
haue I made thee a reproch vnto the heathen, and a mocking to all
countries.<note> 2.Kings. 21.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Those that be
neere, and those that be farre from thee, shall mocke thee which
art infamous, and much vexed.<note> Heb. polluted of name, much in vexation.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Behold the
princes of Israel, euerie one were in thee to their power to shead
blood.<note> Heb. arme.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">In thee haue they
set light by father and mother: in the middest of thee haue they
dealt by oppression with the stranger: in thee haue they vexed the
fatherlesse and the widow:<note> Or, deceit</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Thou hast
despised mine holy things, &amp; hast prophaned my
sabbaths:</ab>
<ab n="9">In thee are men
that carie tales to shead blood: and in thee they eate vpon the
mountaines: in the middest of thee they commit
lewdnesse.<note> Heb. men of slanders.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">In thee haue
they discouered their fathers nakednesse: in thee haue they humbled
her that was set apart for pollution.<note> Leuit. 18. 8. and 20. 11. , Leuit. 18. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And one hath
committed abomination with his neighbours wife, and an other hath
lewdly defiled his daughter in law, and an other in thee hath
humbled his sister, his fathers daughter.<note> Or, euery one. , Leuit. 18. 20. , Ier.5.8. , Or, euery one. , Or, by lewdnesse. , Leuit. 18. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">In thee haue
they taken gifts to shead blood: thou hast taken vsury and
increase, and thou hast greedily gained of thy neighbours by
extortion, and hast forgotten me, saith the Lord God.</ab>

<fw>Israel as drosse.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ Behold
therefore, I haue smitten mine hand at thy dishonest gaine which
thou hast made, and at thy blood which hath bene in the midst of
thee.<note> Chap.21. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Can thine heart
indure, or can thine hands be strong in the dayes that I shall
deale with thee? I the Lord haue spoken it, and will doe
it.</ab>
<ab n="15">And I will
scatter thee among the heathen, and disperse thee in the countreys,
and will consume thy filthinesse out of thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">And thou shalt
take thine inheritance in thy selfe in the sight of the heathen,
and thou shalt know that I am the Lord.<note> Or, shalt be prophaned</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the word of
the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">Sonne of man,
the house of Israel is to me become drosse: all they are brasse,
and tinne, and yron, and lead in the midst of the furnace: they are
euen the drosse of siluer.<note> Heb. drosses.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Because ye are all become drosse, behold
therefore I will gather you into the midst of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="20">As they gather
siluer, and brasse, and yron, and lead, and tinne into the midst of
the furnace, to blow the fire vpon it, to melt it: so will I gather
you in mine anger, and in my fury, and I will leaue you there, and
melt you.<note> Heb. according to the gathering.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Yea, I will
gather you, and blow vpon you in the fire of my wrath, and ye
shalbe melted in the midst thereof.</ab>
<ab n="22">As siluer is
melted in the midst of the furnace, so shall ye be melted in the
middest thereof, and ye shall know that I the Lord haue powred out
my furie vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
word of the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="24">Son of man, say
vnto her, Thou art the land that is not cleansed, nor rained vpon
in the day of indignation.</ab>
<ab n="25">There is a
conspiracie of her prophets in the middest thereof like a roaring
lyon, rauening the praye: they haue deuoured soules: they haue
taken the treasure and precious things: they haue made her many
widowes in the midst thereof.<note> Matth. 23 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Her priests haue
violated my law, and haue prophaned mine holy things: they haue put
no difference betweene the holy and prophane, neither haue they
shewed difference between the vncleane and the cleane, and haue hid
their eyes from my Sabbaths, and I am prophaned among
them.<note> Heb. offered violence to.</note></ab>

<fw>False prophets.</fw>
<ab n="27">Her princes in
the midst thereof are like wolues rauening the praye, to shed
blood, and to destroy soules, to get dishonest gaine.<note> Mic.3.11 zeph. 3.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And her prophets
haue dawbed them with vntempered morter, seeing vanity, and
diuining lies vnto them, saying, Thus saith the Lord God, when the
Lord hath not spoken.</ab>
<ab n="29">The people of
the land haue vsed oppression, and exercised robbery, and haue
vexed the poore and needie: yea, they haue oppressed the stranger
wrongfully.<note> Or, deceit. , Heb. without right.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And I sought for
a man among them, that should make vp the hedge, and stand in the
gap before me for the land, that I should not destroy it: but I
found none.</ab>
<ab n="31">Therefore haue I
powred out mine indignation vpon them, I haue consumed them with
the fire of my wrath: their owne way haue I recompensed vpon their
heads, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>