<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_48" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-48-48.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVIII.</head>
<head>1. 23 The portions of the twelue
Tribes, 8 of the Sanctuarie, 15 of the citie and Suburbs, 21 and of
the Prince. 30 The dimensions and gates of the citie.</head>


<fw>The borders, and portions of the
Tribes.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now these are the
names of the Tribes, from the North end to the coast of the way of
Hathlon, as one goeth to Hamath, Hazarenan, the border of Damascus
Northward, to þ<note/> coast of Hamath (for these are his
sides East &amp; West) a portion for Dan.</ab>
<ab n="2">And by the border
of Dan, from the East side vnto the West, a portion for
Asher.</ab>
<ab n="3">And by the border
of Asher, from the East side euen vnto the West side, a portion for
Naphtali.</ab>
<ab n="4">And by the border
of Naphtali, from the East side vnto the West side, a portion for
Manasseh.</ab>
<ab n="5">And by the border
of Manasseh, from the East side vnto the West side, a portion for
Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="6">And by the border
of Ephraim, from the East side euen vnto the West side, a portion
for Reuben.</ab>
<ab n="7">And by the border
of Reuben, from the East side vnto the West side, a portion for
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And by the
border of Iudah, from the East side vnto the West side, shall be
the offring which they shall offer of fiue and twentie thousand
reedes in bredth, and in length as one of the other parts, from the
East side vnto the West side, and the Sanctuarie shall be in the
midst of it.</ab>
<ab n="9">The oblation that
yee shall offer vnto the Lord, shall be of fiue and twentie
thousand in length, and of ten thousand in bredth.</ab>
<ab n="10">And for them,
euen for the priests shall be this holy oblation, toward the North,
fiue and twentie thousand in length, and toward the West ten
thousand in bredth, and toward the East ten thousand in bredth, and
toward the South fiue and twentie thousand in length, &amp; the
sanctuarie of the Lord shall be in the midst thereof.</ab>
<ab n="11">It shall be for
the Priests that are sanctified, of the sonnes of Zadok, which haue
kept my charge, which went not astray when the children of Israel
went astray, as the Leuites went astray.<note> Or, the sanctified portion shall be for the priests. , Or, ward, or, ordinance.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And this
oblation of the land that is offred, shalbe vnto them a thing most
holy by the border of the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="13">And ouer against
the border of the Priests, the Leuites shall haue fiue and twentie
thousand in length, and tenne thousand in bredth: all the length
shalbe fiue and twentie thousand, and the bredth tenne
thousand.</ab>

<fw>The suburbs, and gates of the
citie.</fw>
<ab n="14">And they shall
not sell of it, neither exchange, nor alienate the first fruits of
the land: for it is holy vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And the
fiue thousand that are left in the breadth ouer against the fiue
and twentie thousand, shall bee a prophane place for the citie, for
dwelling, and for suburbs, and the citie shall be in the midst
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="16">And these shall
bee the measures thereof, the North side foure thousand and fiue
hundred, and the South side foure thousand and fiue hundred, and on
the East side foure thousand, and fiue hundred, and the West side
foure thousand and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the suburbs
of the city shall be toward the North two hundred and fiftie, and
toward the South two hundred and fifty, and toward the East two
hundred and fiftie, and toward the West two hundred and
fiftie.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the residue
in length ouer against the oblation of the holy portion, shalbe ten
thousand Eastward, and ten thousand Westward: and it shall be ouer
against the oblation of the holy portion, and the increase thereof
shall bee for food vnto them that serue the citie.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they that
serue the citie, shall serue it out of all the tribes of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="20">All the oblation
shall bee fiue and twentie thousand, by fiue and twentie thousand:
ye shall offer the holy oblation foure square, with the possession
of the citie.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And the
residue shall bee for the prince on the one side, and on the other
of the holy oblation, and of the possession of the citie ouer
against the fiue and twentie thousand, of the oblation toward the
East border, and Westward ouer against the fiue and twentie
thousand toward the West border, ouer against the portions for the
prince, and it shall be the holy oblation, and the Sanctuarie of
the house shall be in the middest thereof.</ab>

<fw>The suburbs, and gates of the
citie.</fw>
<ab n="22">Moreouer, from
the possession of the Leuites, and from the possession of the
citie, being in the midst of that which is the princes, betweene
the border of Iudah, and the border of Beniamin, shall bee for the
prince.</ab>
<ab n="23">As for the rest
of the tribes, from the East side vnto the West side, Beniamin
shall haue a portion:<note> Heb. one portion.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And by the
border of Beniamin, from the East side vnto the West side, Simeon
shall haue a portion:</ab>
<ab n="25">And by the
border of Simeon, from the East side vnto the West side, Issachar a
portion:</ab>
<ab n="26">And by the
border of Issachar, from the East side vnto the West side, Zebulun
a portion:</ab>
<ab n="27">And by the
border of Zebulun from the East side vnto the West side, Gad a
portion:</ab>
<ab n="28">And by the
border of Gad, at the South side Southward, the border shall be
euen from Tamar, vnto the waters of strife in Kadesh, and to the
riuer toward the great Sea.<note> Or, Meribah Kadesh.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">This is the land
which ye shal diuide by lot vnto the tribes of Israel for
inheritance, and these are their portions, saith the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And these
are the goings out of the citie, on the North side foure thousand
and fiue hundred measures.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the gates of
the citie shall bee after the names of the tribes of Israel, three
gates Northward, one gate of Reuben, one gate of Iudah, one gate of
Leui.</ab>
<ab n="32">And at the East
side foure thousand and fiue hundred: and three gates; and one gate
of Ioseph, one gate of Beniamin, one gate of Dan.</ab>
<ab n="33">And at the South
side foure thousand and fiue hundred measures, and three gates: one
gate of Simeon, one gate of Issachar, one gate of Zebulun.</ab>
<ab n="34">At the West side
foure thousand and fiue hundred, with their three gates: one gate
of Gad, one gate of Asher, one gate of Naphtali.</ab>
<ab n="35">It was round
about eighteene thousand measures, and the name of the citie from
that day shall be, The Lord is there.<note> Heb. Iehouah Shammah.</note></ab>



</div>