<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-34-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-36-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 The land of Israel is comforted,
both by destruction of the heathen, who spitefully vsed it, 8 and
by the blessings of God promised vnto it. 16 Israel was reiected
for their sinne, 21 and shall be restored without their desert. 25
The blessings of Christs kingdome.</head>

<ab n="1">Also thou sonne
of man, prophecie vnto the mountaines of Israel, and say; Ye
mountaines of Israel, Heare the word of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Comfort to the Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord God, Because the enemy had said against you, Aha, euen the
ancient high places are ours in possession:<note> Chap.62.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therfore
prophecie and say, Thus saith the Lord God, Because they haue made
you desolate, and swallowed you vp on euery side, that ye might be
a possession vnto the residue of the heathen, and ye are taken vp
in the lips of talkers, and are an infamy of the
people:<note> Heb. because for because. , Or, ye are made to come vp on the lip of the tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore ye
mountaines of Israel, heare the word of the Lord God, Thus saith
the Lord God to the mountaines and to the hilles, to the riuers and
to the valleys, to the desolate wastes, and to the cities that are
forsaken, which became a pray and derision to the residue of the
heathen that are round about:<note> Or, bottomes or dales.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Surely in the fire of my ielousie haue I spoken
against the residue of the heathen, and against al Idumea, which
haue appointed my land into their possession, with the ioy of all
their heart, with despitefull minds to cast it out for a
praye.</ab>
<ab n="6">Prophecie
therefore concerning the land of Israel, and say vnto the
mountaines and to the hilles, to the riuers and to the valleys,
Thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I haue spoken in my iealousie and
in my furie, because ye haue borne the shame of the
heathen,</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, I haue lifted vp mine hand, Surely the heathen
that are about you, they shall beare their shame.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But ye, O
mountaines of Israel, ye shall shoot forth your branches, and yeeld
your fruit to my people of Israel, for they are at hand to
come.</ab>
<ab n="9">For behold, I am
for you, and I will turne vnto you, and ye shall be tilled and
sowen.</ab>
<ab n="10">And I will
multiplie men vpon you, all the house of Israel, euen all of it,
and the cities shall be inhabited, and the wastes shall be
builded.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I will
multiply vpon you man and beast, and they shall increase and bring
fruite, and I will settle you after your olde estates: and will doe
better vnto you, then at your beginnings, and ye shall know that I
am the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Comfort to the Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="12">Yea I will cause
men to walke vpon you, euen my people Israel, and they shall
possesse thee, and thou shalt be their inheritance, and thou shalt
no more henceforth bereaue them of men.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thus saith the
Lord God, Because they say vnto you, Thou land deuourest vp men,
and hast bereaued thy nations,</ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore thou
shalt deuoure men no more, neither bereaue thy nations any more,
saith the Lord God.<note> Or, cause to fall.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Neither will I
cause men to heare in thee the shame of the heathen any more,
neither shalt thou beare the reproch of the people any more,
neither shalt thou cause the nations to fall any more, saith the
Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Moreouer
the worde of the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="17">Sonne of man,
when the house of Israel dwelt in their own land, they defiled it
by their owne way, and by their doings: their way was before me as
the vncleannesse of a remooued woman.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wherefore I
powred my furie vpon them for the blood that they had shed vpon the
land, and for their idoles wherewith they had polluted it.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I scattered
them among the heathen, and they were dispersed through the
countreys: according to their way and according to their doings I
iudged them.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when they
entred vnto the heathen whither they went, they prophaned my holy
Name, when they said to them, These are the people of the Lord, and
are gone forth out of his land.<note> Isa.52.5. rom.2.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ But I had
pitie for mine holy Name, which the house of Israel had prophaned
among the heathen, whither they went.</ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore say
vnto the house of Israel, Thus saith the Lord God, I doe not this
for your sakes, O house of Israel, but for mine holy Names sake,
which ye haue prophaned among the heathen, whither ye went.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I will
sanctifie my great Name which was prophaned among the heathen,
which ye haue prophaned in the midst of them, and the heathen shall
know, that I am the Lord, saith the Lord God, when I shall be
sanctified in you before their eyes.<note> Or, your.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For I will take
you from among the heathen, and gather you out of all countreys,
and will bring you into your owne land.</ab>

<fw>A new heart.</fw>
<ab n="25">¶ Then will
I sprinckle cleane water vpon you, and ye shalbe cleane: from all
your filthinesse, and from all your idoles wil I cleanse
you.</ab>
<ab n="26">A new heart also
will I giue you, and a new spirit will I put within you, and I will
take away the stonie heart out of your flesh, and I will giue you
an heart of flesh.<note> Iere.32. 39.chap. 11.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And I wil put my
Spirit within you, and cause you to walke in my Statutes, and ye
shall keepe my iudgements, and doe them.<note> Chap. 11. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And ye shall
dwel in the land that I gaue to your fathers, and ye shall be my
people, and I wil be your God.</ab>
<ab n="29">I wil also saue
you from all your vncleannesses, and I will call for the corne, and
will increase it, and lay no famine vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="30">And I will
multiply the fruit of the tree, and the increase of the field, that
yee shall receiue no more reproch of famine among the
heathen.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then shall yee
remember your owne euil waies, and your doings that were not good,
and shall lothe your selues in your owne sight for your iniquities,
and for your abominations.</ab>
<ab n="32">Not for your
sakes doe I this, saith the Lord God, be it knowen vnto you: be
ashamed and confounded for your owne wayes, O house of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="33">Thus saith the
Lord God, In the day that I shall haue cleansed you from all your
iniquities, I will also cause you to dwell in the cities, and the
wastes shalbe builded.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the desolate
land shalbe tilled, whereas it lay desolate in the sight of all
that passed by.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they shall
say, This land that was desolate, is become like the garden of
Eden, and the waste and desolate and ruined cities, are become
fenced, and are inhabited.<note> Chap.28. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Then the heathen
that are left round about you, shall know that I the Lord build the
ruined places, and plant that that was desolate: I the Lord haue
spoken it, and I wil doe it.<note> Chap.17. 24. and 22. 14. and 37. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Thus saith the
Lord God, I wil yet for this bee enquired of by the house of
Israel, to doe it for them: I will increase them with men like a
flocke.</ab>

<fw>Drie bones.</fw>
<ab n="38">As the holy
flocke, as the flocke of Ierusalem in her solemne feastes, so shal
the waste cities be filled with flocks of men, and they shall know
that I am the Lord.<note> Hebr. flocke of holy things.</note></ab>



</div>