<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-34-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>The iudgment of Mount Seir, for
their hatred of Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer the word
of the Lord came vnto mee, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man, set
thy face against mount Seir, and prophecie against it,</ab>
<ab n="3">And say vnto it,
Thus saith the Lord God; Behold, O mount Seir, I am against thee,
and I will stretch out mine hand against thee, and I will make thee
most desolate.<note> Heb. desolation and desolation.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I will lay thy
cities waste, and thou shalt be desolate, and thou shalt know that
I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">Because thou hast
had a perpetuall hatred, and hast shed the blood of the children of
Israel by the force of the sword in the time of their calamitie, in
the time that their iniquitie had an end;<note> Or, hatred of old. , Heb. powred out the children. , Heb. hands.</note></ab>

<fw>The iudgement of mount Seir.</fw>
<ab n="6">Therefore, as I
liue, saith the Lord God, I will prepare thee vnto blood, and blood
shall pursue thee: sith thou hast not hated blood, euen blood shall
pursue thee.</ab>
<ab n="7">Thus will I make
mount Seir most desolate, and cut off from it him that passeth out,
&amp; him that returneth.<note> Heb. desolation and desolation.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I will fill
his mountaines with his slaine men: in thy hilles, and in thy
valleis, and in all thy riuers shall they fall that are slaine with
the sword.</ab>
<ab n="9">I will make thee
perpetuall desolations, &amp; thy cities shall not returne, and ye
shal know that I am the Lord</ab>
<ab n="10">Because thou
hast said; These two nations, and these two countries shall be
mine, and we will possesse it, whereas the Lord was
there:<note> Psal.83. 4,13. , Or, though the Lord was there.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore, as I
liue, saith the Lord God, I will euen doe according to thine anger,
and according to thine enuie, which thou hast vsed out of thy
hatred against them: and I will make my selfe knowen amongst them,
when I haue iudged thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">And thou shalt
know, that I am the Lord, and that I haue heard all thy blasphemies
which thou hast spoken against the mountaines of Israel, saying;
They are layed desolate, they are giuen vs to consume.<note> Heb. to deuoure.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Thus with your
mouth yee haue boasted against me, &amp; haue multiplied your words
against me: I haue heard them.<note> Heb. magnified.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thus saith the
Lord God; When the whole earth reioyceth, I will make thee
desolate.</ab>
<ab n="15">As thou didst
reioyce at the inheritance of the house of Israel, because it was
desolate, so will I doe vnto thee: thou shalt be desolate, O mount
Seir, and all Idumea, euen all of it, and they shall know that I am
the Lord.</ab>



</div>