<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 The rich supply of Tyrus. 26 The
great and vnrecouerable fall thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of the
Lord came againe vnto mee, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Now thou sonne of
man, take vp a lamentation for Tyrus;</ab>
<ab n="3">And say vnto
Tyrus, O thou that art situate at the entrie of the sea, which art
a merchant of the people for many Iles, Thus saith the Lord God; O
Tyrus, thou hast said, I am of perfit beautie.<note> Hebr. perfit of beautie.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Thy borders are
in the midst of the seas, thy builders haue perfected thy
beautie.<note> Hebr. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">They haue made
all thy shippe bords of firre trees of Senir: they haue taken
Cedars from Lebanon, to make mastes for thee.<note> Hebr. built.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Of the okes of
Bashan haue they made thine oares: the companie of the Ashurites
haue made thy benches of Yuorie, brought out of the Iles of
Chittim.<note> Or, they haue made hatches of Yuorie well troden. , Heb. the daughter.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Fine linnen with
broidred worke from Egypt, was that which thou spreddest forth to
be thy saile, blew and purple from the Iles of Elishah was that
which couered thee.<note> Or, purple and scarlet.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The inhabitants
of Zidon and Aruad were thy mariners: thy wise men, O Tyrus, that
were in thee, were thy pilots.</ab>
<ab n="9">The ancients of
Gebal, and the wise men thereof were in thee thy calkers, all the
ships of the sea with their mariners were in thee, to occupie thy
merchandise.<note> Or, stoppers of chinks. Heb. strengthners.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They of Persia,
and of Lud, and of Phut were in thine army, thy men of warre: they
hanged the shield and helmet in thee: they set forth thy
comelines.</ab>
<ab n="11">The men of Aruad
with thine armie were vpon thy wals round about, and the Gammadims
were in thy towres: they hanged their shields vpon thy wals round
about: they haue made thy beautie perfect.</ab>

<fw>Tyrus riches, and destruction.</fw>
<ab n="12">Tarshish was thy
merchant by reason of the multitude of all kinde of riches: with
siluer, yron, tinne, and lead they traded in thy faires.</ab>
<ab n="13">Iauan, Tubal and
Meshech, they were thy merchants: they traded the persons of men,
and vessels of brasse in thy market.<note> Or, merchandise.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">They of the
house of Togarmah traded in thy faires with horses, and horsemen,
and mules.</ab>
<ab n="15">The men of Dedan
were thy merchants, many Iles were the merchandise of thine hand:
they brought thee for a present, hornes of Iuorie, and
Ebenie.</ab>
<ab n="16">Syria was thy
merchant by reason of the multitude of the wares of thy making:
they occupied in thy faires with Emeraulds, purple, and broidered
worke, and fine linen, and Corall, and Agate.<note> Hebr. workes. , Or, Chrysoprase.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Iudah and the
land of Israel they were thy merchants: they traded in thy market
wheate of Minnith, and Pannag, and honie, and oyle, &amp;
balme.<note> Or, rosin.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Damascus was thy
merchant in the multitude of the wares of thy making, for the
multitude of all riches: in the wine of Helbon, and white
wooll.</ab>
<ab n="19">Dan also and
Iauan going to and fro, occupyed in thy faires: bright yron, Cassia
and Calamus were in thy market.<note> Or, Meuzall.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Dedan was thy
merchant in precious clothes for charets.<note> Hebr. clothes of freedome.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Arabia and all
the princes of Kedar, they occupied with thee in lambes and rammes
and goats: in these were they thy merchants.<note> Heb. they were the merchants of thy hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The merchants of
Shebah and Raamah, they were thy merchants: they occupied in thy
faires with chiefe of all spices, and with all precious stones and
golde.</ab>
<ab n="23">Haran, and
Canneh, and Eden, the merchants of Shebah, Asshur and Chilmad were
thy merchants.</ab>
<ab n="24">These were thy
merchants in all sorts of things, in blewe clothes and broidered
worke, and in chests of rich apparell, bound with cordes and made
of Cedar among thy merchandise.<note> Or, excellent things. , Heb. foldings.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The ships of
Tarshish did sing of thee in thy market, and thou wast replenished,
and made very glorious in the middest of the seas.</ab>

<fw>Tyrus riches, and destruction.</fw>
<ab n="26">¶ Thy
rowers haue brought thee into great waters: the East winde hath
broken thee in the middest of the Seas.<note> Heb. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Thy riches and
thy faires, thy merchandise, thy mariners, and thy pilots, thy
calkers, and the occupiers of thy merchandise, and all thy men of
warre that are in thee, and in all thy company, which is in the
midst of thee, shall fall into the middest of the seas, in the day
of thy ruine.<note> Reu. 18. 9,&amp;c. , Or, euen withall. , Or, heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">The suburbs
shall shake at the sound of the crie of thy pilots.<note> Or, waues.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And all that
handle the oare; the mariners, and all the pilots of the Sea, shal
come downe from their ships, they shall stand vpon the
land;</ab>
<ab n="30">And shall cause
their voice to be heard against thee, and shall crie bitterly, and
shall cast vp dust vpon their heads, they shall wallow themselues
in the ashes.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they shall
make themselues vtterly balde for thee, and girde them with
sackecloth, and they shall weepe for thee with bitternesse of heart
and bitter wailing.</ab>
<ab n="32">And in their
wailing, they shall take vp a lamentation for thee, and lament ouer
thee, saying; What citie is like Tyrus, like the destroyed in the
middest of the sea?</ab>
<ab n="33">When thy wares
went foorth out of the seas, thou filledst many people, thou didst
enrich the kings of the earth, with the multitude of thy riches,
and of thy merchandise.</ab>
<ab n="34">In the time when
thou shalt be broken by the seas in the depths of the waters, thy
merchandise and all thy companie in the middest of thee shal
fall.</ab>
<ab n="35">All the
inhabitants of the Iles shall bee astonished at thee, and their
kings shall be sore afraid, they shall be troubled in their
countenance.</ab>
<ab n="36">The merchants
among the people shall hisse at thee, thou shalt bee a terrour, and
neuer shalt be any more.<note> Heb. terrours. , Heb. shalt not be for euer.</note></ab>



</div>