<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 The reproofe of lying Prophets, 10
and their vntempered morter. 17 Of Prophetesses and their
pillowes.</head>


<fw>False prophets.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the worde of
the Lord came vnto mee, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man,
prophecie against the Prophets of Israel that prophecie, and say
thou vnto them that prophecie out of their owne hearts, Heare ye
the word of the Lord.<note> Heb. them that are prophets out of their owne hearts. , Ier. 23.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thus saith the
Lord God; Woe vnto the foolish prophets, that follow their owne
spirit, and haue seene nothing.<note> Heb. walke after. , Or, and things which they haue not seene.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">O Israel, thy
prophets are like the foxes in the deserts.</ab>
<ab n="5">Yee haue not gone
vp into the gaps, neither made vp the hedge for the house of
Israel, to stand in the battell in the day of the Lord.<note> Or, breaches. , Heb. hedged the hedge.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">They haue seene
vanity, and lying diuination, saying; The Lord saith, and the Lord
hath not sent them: and they haue made others to hope, that they
would confirme the word.</ab>
<ab n="7">Haue ye not seene
a vaine vision, and haue ye not spoken a lying diuination, whereas
yee say, The Lord sayth it, albeit I haue not spoken?</ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God; Because ye haue spoken vanity and seene lyes,
therefore behold, I am against you, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="9">And mine hand
shall be vpon the Prophets that see vanitie, and that diuine lyes:
they shall not bee in the assembly of my people, neither shall they
be written in the writing of the house of Israel, neither shall
they enter into the land of Israel, and ye shall know that I am the
Lord God.<note> Or, secret or counsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Because,
euen because they haue seduced my people, saying; Peace, and there
was no peace: and one built vp a wall, and loe, others dawbed it
with vntempered morter,<note> Ier.6.14. , Or, a sleight wall.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Say vnto them
which dawbe it with vntempered morter, that it shall fall: there
shall bee an ouerflowing showre, and yee, O great haile stones,
shal fall, and a stormie wind shal rent it.</ab>
<ab n="12">Loe, when the
wall is fallen, shall it not bee sayde vnto you; Where is the
dawbing wherwith ye haue dawbed it?</ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore thus
sayth the Lord God; I will euen rent it with a stormie wind in my
fury: and there shall be an ouerflowing showre in mine anger, and
great hailestones in my fury, to consume it.</ab>

<fw>Vntempered morter.</fw>
<ab n="14">So wil I breake
downe the wall that ye haue dawbed with vntempered morter, &amp;
bring it downe to the ground, so that the foundation thereof shall
be discouered, and it shall fall, and ye shall be consumed in the
middest thereof: and ye shall know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thus will I
accomplish my wrath vpon the wall, and vpon them that haue dawbed
it with vntempered morter, and will say vnto you; The wall is no
more, neither they that dawbed it:</ab>
<ab n="16">To wit, the
Prophets of Israel which prophecie concerning Ierusalem, and which
see visions of peace for her, and there is no peace, sayth the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Likewise
thou sonne of man, set thy face against the daughters of thy
people; which prophecie out of their owne heart, and prophecie thou
against them,</ab>
<ab n="18">And say, Thus
saith the Lord God; Woe to the women that sow pillowes to all arme
holes, and make kerchiefes vpon the head of euery stature to hunt
soules: Will ye hunt the soules of my people, and will yee saue the
soules aliue that come vnto you?<note> Or, elbowes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And will yee
pollute me among my people for handfuls of barley, and for pieces
of bread, to slay the soules that should not die, and to saue the
soules aliue that should not liue, by your lying to my people that
heare your lyes?</ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore thus
sayth the Lord God, Behold, I am against your pillowes, wherewith
yee there hunt the soules to make them flie, and I will teare them
from your armes, and will let the soules goe, euen the soules that
ye hunt to make them flie.<note> Or, into gardens.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Your kerchiefes
also will I teare, and deliuer my people out of your hand, and they
shalbe no more in your hand to be hunted, and yee shall know that I
am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">Because with
lyes yee haue made the heart of the righteous sad whom I haue not
made sad; and strengthened the hands of the wicked, that hee should
not returne from his wicked way by promising him life:<note> Or, that I should saue his life. Hebr. by quickning him.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore yee
shall see no more vanitie, nor diuine diuinations, for I will
deliuer my people out of your hand, and ye shall knowe that I am
the Lord. par</ab>



</div>