<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The time of Ezekiels prophecie at
Chebar. 4 His vision of foure Cherubims, 15 Of the foure wheeles,
26 and of the glory of God.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe in the thirtieth yeere, in the fourth moneth, in the fifth
day of the moneth, (as I was among the captiues by the riuer of
Chebar) that the heauens were opened, and I saw visions of
God.<note> Hebr. captiuitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">In the fifth day
of the moneth, (which was the fifth yeere of king Iehoiakins
captiuitie,)</ab>
<ab n="3">The word of the
Lord came expresly vnto Ezekiel the Priest, the sonne of Buzi, in
the land of the Caldeans, by the riuer Chebar, and the hand of the
Lord was there vpon him.<note> Hebr. Iehezkel.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And I
looked, and behold, a whirlewinde came out of the North, a great
cloude, and a fire infoulding it selfe, and a brightnesse was about
it, and out of the midst thereof as the colour of amber, out of the
midst of the fire.<note> Heb catching it selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Also out of the
midst thereof came the likenesse of foure liuing creatures, and
this was their appearance: they had the likenesse of a man.</ab>
<ab n="6">And euery one had
foure faces, and euery one had foure wings.</ab>
<ab n="7">And their feet
were straight feet, and the sole of their feet was like the sole of
a calues foot, and they sparkled like the colour of burnished
brasse.<note> Hebr. a straight foot.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And they had the
handes of a man vnder their wings on their foure sides, and they
foure had their faces and their wings.</ab>

<fw>The vision of liuing creatures.</fw>
<ab n="9">Their wings were
ioyned one to another, they turned not when they went: they went
euery one straight forward.</ab>
<ab n="10">As for the
likenesse of their faces, they foure had the face of a man, and the
face of a lyon on the right side, and they foure had the face of an
oxe on the left side: they foure also had the face of an
eagle.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus were their
faces: and their wings were stretched vpward, two wings of euery
one were ioyned one to an other, and two couered their
bodies.<note> Or, diuided aboue.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they went
euery one straight forward: whither the spirit was to goe, they
went: and they turned not when they went.</ab>
<ab n="13">As for the
likenesse of the liuing creatures, their appearance was like
burning coles of fire, and like the appearance of lamps: it went vp
and downe among the liuing creatures, and the fire was bright, and
out of the fire went foorth lightning.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the liuing
creatures ranne, and returned as the appearance of a flash of
lightning.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Now as I
behelde the liuing creatures: behold one wheele vpon the earth by
the liuing creatures, with his foure faces.</ab>
<ab n="16">The appearance of
the wheeles, and their worke was like vnto the colour of a Berill:
and they foure had one likenesse, and their appearance and their
worke was as it were a wheele in the middle of a wheele.</ab>
<ab n="17">When they went,
they went vpon their foure sides: and they returned not when they
went.</ab>
<ab n="18">As for their
rings, they were so high, that they were dreadful, and their rings
were full of eyes round about them foure.<note> Or, strakes.</note></ab>

<fw>The vision.</fw>
<ab n="19">And when the
liuing creatures went, the wheeles went by them: and when the
liuing creatures were lift vp from the earth, the wheels were lift
vp.</ab>
<ab n="20">Whithersoeuer the
spirit was to goe, they went, thither was their spirit to goe, and
the wheeles were lifted vp ouer against them: for the spirit of the
liuing creature was in the wheeles.<note> Or, of life.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">When those went,
these went, and when those stood, these stood; and when those were
lifted vp from the earth, the wheeles were lifted vp ouer against
them: for the spirit of the liuing creature was in the
wheeles.<note> Or, of life.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And the likenesse
of the firmament vpon the heads of the liuing creature was as the
colour of the terrible chrystall, stretched foorth ouer their heads
aboue.</ab>
<ab n="23">And vnder the
firmament were their wings straight, the one toward the other,
euery one had two which couered on this side, &amp; euery one had
two, which couered on that side their bodies.</ab>
<ab n="24">And when they
went, I heard the noise of their wings, like the noise of great
waters, as the voice of the Almightie, the voice of speech, as the
noise of an hoste: when they stood, they let downe their
wings.</ab>
<ab n="25">And there was a
voice from the firmament, that was ouer their heads, when they
stood, and had let downe their wings.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And aboue
the firmament that was ouer their heads, was the likenesse of a
Throne, as the appearance of a Saphyre stone, and vpon the
likenesse of the Throne was the likenesse as the appearance of a
man aboue vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="27">And I saw as the
colour of amber, as the appearance of fire round about within it:
from the appearance of his loynes euen vpward, and from the
appearance of his loynes euen downeward, I saw as it were the
appearance of fire, &amp; it had brightnesse round about.</ab>
<ab n="28">As the appearance
of the bow that is in the cloude in the day of raine, so was the
appearance of the brightnesse round about. This was the appearance
of the likenesse of the glory of the Lord: and when I saw it, I
fell vpon my face, and I heard a voice of one that spake.</ab>



</div>