<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-33-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 According to the duetie of a
watchman, in warning the people, 7 Ezekiel is admonished of his
duetie. 20 God sheweth the iustice of his wayes towards the
penitent, and towards reuolters. 17 Hee maintaineth his Iustice. 21
Vpon the newes of the taking of Ierusalem, he prophecieth the
desolation of the land. 30 Gods iudgment vpon the mockers of the
Prophets.</head>


<fw>The watchman.</fw>
<ab n="1">Againe the worde
of the Lord came vnto mee, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man,
speake to the children of thy people, and say vnto them, When I
bring the sword vpon a land, if the people of the land take a man
of their coasts, and set him for their watchman,<note> Heb. a land when I bring a sword vpon her.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">If when he seeth
the sword come vpon the land, hee blow the trumpet, and warne the
people,</ab>
<ab n="4">Then whosoeuer
heareth the sound of the trumpet, and taketh not warning, if the
sword come, and take him away, his blood shall be vpon his owne
head.<note> Heb. hee that hearing heareth.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Hee heard the
sound of the trumpet, and tooke not warning, his blood shall be
vpon him: but he that taketh warning, shall deliuer his
soule.</ab>
<ab n="6">But if the
watchman see the sword come, and blow not the trumpet, and the
people be not warned: if the sword come and take any person from
among them, he is taken away in his iniquitie: but his blood will I
require at the watchmans hand.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ So thou, O
sonne of man, I haue set thee a watchman vnto the house of Israel:
therefore thou shalt heare the worde at my mouth, and warne them
from me.<note> Chap.3. 17,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">When I say vnto
the wicked, O wicked man, thou shalt surely die, if thou doest not
speake to warne the wicked from his way, that wicked man shall die
in his iniquitie: but his blood will I require at thine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="9">Neuerthelesse if
thou warne the wicked of his way to turne from it: if he do not
turne from his way, he shal die in his iniquitie: but thou hast
deliuered thy soule.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore, O
thou sonne of man, speake vnto the house of Israel, Thus ye speake,
saying, If our transgressions and our sinnes be vpon vs, &amp; we
pine away in them, how should we then liue?</ab>

<fw>Gods wayes equall.</fw>
<ab n="11">Say vnto them,
As I liue, saith the Lord God, I haue no pleasure in the death of
the wicked, but that the wicked turne from his way &amp; liue:
turne ye, turne ye from your euill wayes, for why wil ye die, O
house of Israel?<note> 2.Sam.14 14.chap.18 32. , Chap. 18. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore thou
sonne of man, say vnto the children of thy people, The righteousnes
of the righteous shal not deliuer him in the day of his
transgression: as for the wickednes of the wicked, he shall not
fall thereby in the day that hee turneth from his wickednes,
neither shall the righteous bee able to liue for his righteousnes
in the day that he sinneth.<note> Chap. 18. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">When I shal say
to the righteous, that he shall surely liue if he trust to his owne
righteousnes and commit iniquitie, all his righteousnesses shall
not be remembred; but for his iniquitie that he hath committed, he
shall die for it.</ab>
<ab n="14">Againe, when I
say vnto the wicked, Thou shalt surely die, if hee turne from his
sinne, and do that which is lawfull and right;<note> Heb. iudgement and iustice.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">If the wicked
restore the pledge, giue againe that he had robbed, walke in the
Statutes of life without committing iniquitie, hee shall surely
liue, hee shall not die.</ab>
<ab n="16">None of his
sinnes that hee hath committed, shall be mentioned vnto him: he
hath done that which is lawfull and right; he shall surely
liue.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Yet the
children of thy people say, The way of the Lord is not equall: but
as for them, their way is not equall.</ab>
<ab n="18">When the
righteous turneth from his righteousnes, and committeth iniquitie,
he shall euen die thereby.</ab>
<ab n="19">But if the
wicked turne from his wickednes, and doe that which is lawfull and
right, he shall liue thereby.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Yet yee
say, The way of the Lord is not equall, O yee house of Israel; I
will iudge you euery one after his wayes.<note> Chap. 18. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And it
came to passe in the twelfth yeere of our captiuitie, in the tenth
moneth, in the fifth day of the moneth, that one that had escaped
out of Ierusalem, came vnto mee, saying, The city is
smitten.<note> 2.Kings. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Now the hand of
the Lord was vpon mee in the euening, afore hee that was escaped
came, and had opened my mouth vntill hee came to mee in the
morning, and my mouth was opened, and I was no more
dumbe.<note> Chap. 24. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then the word of
the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>

<fw>A loue song.</fw>
<ab n="24">Sonne of man,
they that inhabite those wastes of the land of Israel, speake,
saying, Abraham was one, and he inherited the land: but we are
many, the land is giuen vs for inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="25">Wherefore say
vnto them, Thus saith the Lord God, Ye eate with the blood, and
lift vp your eyes toward your idoles, and shed blood; and shal ye
possesse the land?</ab>
<ab n="26">Yee stand vpon
your sword; yee worke abomination, and ye defile euery one his
neighbours wife, and shall ye possesse the land?</ab>
<ab n="27">Say thou thus
vnto them, Thus saith the Lord God, As I liue, surely they that are
in the wastes, shall fall by the sword, and him that is in the open
field will I giue to the beasts to be deuoured: and they that be in
the forts and in the caues, shall die of the
pestilence.<note> Hebr. to deuoure him.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For I will lay
the land most desolate, and the pompe of her strength shall cease:
and the mountaines of Israel shall bee desolate, that none shall
passe through.<note> Hebr. desolation and desolation. , Chap.7. 24. and 24. 21. and 30. 6,7.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Then shall they
know that I am the Lord, when I haue layed the land most desolate,
because of all their abominations which they haue
committed.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Also thou
sonne of man, the children of thy people still are talking against
thee by the walles, and in the doores of the houses, and speake one
to another, euery one to his brother, saying, Come, I pray you, and
heare what is the word that commeth foorth from the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they come
vnto thee as the people commeth, and they sit before thee as my
people, and they heare thy words, but they will not doe them: for
with their mouth they shew much loue, but their heart goeth after
their couetousnesse.<note> Hebr. according to the comming of the people. , Or, my people sit before thee. , Hebr. they make loues or iestes.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And loe, thou
art vnto them as a very louely song of one that hath a pleasant
voyce, and can play well on an instrument: for they heare thy
wordes, but they doe them not.<note> Hebr. a song of loues.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And when this
commeth to passe, (loe it will come) then shall they know that a
Prophet hath bene among them.</ab>



</div>