<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-28-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Gods iudgement vpon the prince of
Tyrus, for his sacrilegious pride. 11 A lamentation, of his great
glory corrupted by sinne. 20 The iudgement of Zidon. 24 The
restauration of Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of the
Lord came againe vnto me, saying,</ab>

<fw>Tyrus no God.</fw>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man, say
vnto the prince of Tyrus, Thus saith the Lord God; Because thine
heart is lifted vp, and thou hast said, I am a God, I sit in the
seate of God in the middest of the seas; yet thou art a man and not
God, though thou set thine heart as the heart of God.<note> Heb. heart. , Isai.31. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Behold, thou art
wiser then Daniel: there is no secret that they can hide from
thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">With thy wisedome
and with thine vnderstanding thou hast gotten thee riches, and hast
gotten gold and siluer into thy treasures.</ab>
<ab n="5">By thy great
wisedome, and by thy traffique hast thou increased thy riches, and
thine heart is lifted vp because of thy riches.<note> Heb. by the greatnesse of thy wisedome.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God; Because thou hast set thine heart as the heart
of God;</ab>
<ab n="7">Behold therefore,
I will bring strangers vpon thee, the terrible of the nations: and
they shall draw their swords against the beautie of thy wisedome,
&amp; they shall defile thy brightnesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">They shall bring
thee downe to the pit, and thou shalt die the deaths of them, that
are slaine in the middest of the seas.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wilt thou yet say
before him that slayeth thee, I am God? but thou shalt be a man,
and no God in the hand of him that slayeth thee.<note> Or, woundeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thou shalt die
the deaths of the vncircumcised, by the hand of strangers: for I
haue spoken it, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Moreouer
the word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="12">Sonne of man,
take vp a lamentation vpon the king of Tyrus, and say vnto him,
Thus saith the Lord God; Thou sealest vp the summe, full of
wisedome and perfect in beautie.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou hast beene
in Eden the garden of God; euery precious stone was thy couering,
the Sardius, Topaze, and the Diamond, the Beril, the Onyx, and the
Iasper, the Saphir, the Emeraude, and the Carbuncle and gold: the
workmanship of thy tabrets and of thy pipes was prepared in thee,
in the day that thou wast created.<note> Or, ruby. , Or, chrysolite. , Or, Chysoprase.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thou art the
annointed Cherub that couereth: and I haue set thee so; thou wast
vpon the holy mountaine of God; thou hast walked vp and downe in
the middest of the stones of fire.</ab>

<fw>Her vtter ruine.</fw>
<ab n="15">Thou wast
perfect in thy wayes from the day that thou wast created, till
iniquitie was found in thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">By the multitude
of thy merchandise they haue filled the middest of thee with
violence, and thou hast sinned: therefore I will cast thee as
prophane out of the mountaine of God: and I wil destroy thee, O
couering Cherub, from the middest of the stones of fire.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thine heart was
lifted vp because of thy beautie, thou hast corrupted thy wisedome
by reason of thy brightnesse: I will cast thee to the ground: I
will lay thee before kings, that they may behold thee.</ab>
<ab n="18">Thou hast
defiled thy sanctuaries by the multitude of thine iniquities, by
the iniquitie of thy traffique: therefore will I bring forth a fire
from the middest of thee, it shall deuoure thee: and I will bring
thee to ashes vpon the earth in the sight of all them that behold
thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">All they that
know thee among the people, shall be astonished at thee: thou shalt
be a terrour, and neuer shalt thou be any more.<note> Heb. terrours.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Againe
the word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="21">Sonne of man,
set thy face against Zidon, and prophecie against it,</ab>
<ab n="22">And say, Thus
saith the Lord God; Behold, I am against thee, O Zidon, and I will
be glorified in the middest of thee: and they shall know that I am
the Lord, when I shall haue executed iudgements in her, and shall
be sanctified in her.</ab>
<ab n="23">For I will send
into her, pestilence, and blood into her streetes, and the wounded
shall be iudged in the middest of her by the sword vpon her on
euery side, and they shall know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And there
shall be no more a pricking briar vnto the house of Israel, nor any
grieuing thorne of all that are round about them that despised
them, and they shal know that I am the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thus saith the
Lord God; When I shall haue gathered the house of Israel frō
the people among whom they are scattered, and shall be sanctified
in them in the sight of the heathen, then shall they dwell in their
land, that I haue giuen to my seruant Iacob.</ab>

<fw>A staffe of reed.</fw>
<ab n="26">And they shal
dwell safely therein, and shall build houses, and plant vineyards:
yea, they shall dwell with confidence when I haue executed
iudgments vpon all those that despise them round about them, and
they shal know that I am the Lord their God.<note> Or, with confidence. , Or, spoile.</note></ab>



</div>