<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 God reprooueth the vniust parable
of sowre grapes. 5 He sheweth how he dealeth with a iust father: 10
with a wicked sonne of a iust father: 14 with a iust sonne of a
wicked father: 19 with a wicked man repenting: 24 with a iust man
reuolting. 25 Hee defendeth his iustice, 31 and exhorteth to
repentance.</head>

<ab n="1">And the word of
þe Lord came vnto me againe, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">What meane ye
that yee vse this prouerbe concerning the land of Israel, saying,
The fathers haue eaten sowre grapes, and the childrens teeth are
set on edge?<note> Iee.31 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">As I liue, saith
the Lord God, yee shall not haue occasion any more to vse this
prouerbe in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, all
soules are mine, as the soule of the father, so also the soule of
the sonne is mine: the soule that sinneth, it shall die.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ But if a
man be iust, and do that which is lawfull and right:<note> Heb. iudgment and iustice.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And hath not
eaten vpon the mountaines, neither hath lift vp his eyes to the
idoles of the house of Israel, neither hath defiled his neighbours
wife, neither hath come neere to a menstruous woman,<note> Leuit.18.20. , Leuit.18.19. and 20.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And hath not
oppressed any, but hath restored to the debtourhis pledge, hath
spoiled none by violence, hath giuen his bread to the hungrie, and
hath couered the naked with a garment,<note> Exod.22. 21. leuit.19. 15. and 25. 14. , Deut.24. 12. exod. 22.20. , Deu.15.7. isai.58.7. mat 25.35</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He that hath not
giuen foorth vpon vsurie, neither hath taken any increase, that
hath withdrawen his hand from iniquitie, hath executed true
iudgement betweene man and man,<note> Exod. 22. 25. leui.25. 36,37. deu. 23. 19. psal. 15.5.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods iustice in punishing.</fw>
<ab n="9">Hath walked in my
Statutes, and hath kept my Iudgements to deale truely; hee is iust,
hee shall surely liue, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ If hee
beget a sonne that is a robber, a shedder of blood, and that doth
the like to any one of these things,<note> Or, breaker vp of an house. , Or, that doeth to his brother, besides any of these.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And that doeth
not any of those duties, bnt euen hath eaten vpon the mountains,
and defiled his neighbours wife,</ab>
<ab n="12">Hath oppressed
the poore and needie, hath spoiled by violence, hath not restored
the pledge, and hath lift vp his eyes to the idoles, hath committed
abomination,</ab>
<ab n="13">Hath giuen
foorth vpon vsurie, and hath taken encrease: shall he then liue?
hee shall not liue: hee hath done all these abominations, hee shall
surely die, his blood shalbe vpon him.<note> Heb. bloods</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Now loe,
if hee beget a sonne that seeth all his fathers sinnes which he
hath done, and considereth, and doth not such like,</ab>
<ab n="15">That hath not
eaten vpon the mountaines, neither hath lift vp his eyes to the
idoles of the house of Israel, hath not defiled his neighbours
wife,</ab>
<ab n="16">Neither hath
oppressed any, hath not withholden the pledge, neither hath spoiled
by violence, but hath giuen his bread to the hungry, and hath
couered the naked with a garment,<note> Heb. hath not pledged the pledge or taken to pledge.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">That hath taken
off his hand from the poore, that hath not receiued vsurie nor
increase, hath executed my Iudgements, hath walked in my Statutes,
he shall not die for the iniquitie of his father, he shall surely
liue.</ab>
<ab n="18">As for his
father, because hee cruelly oppressed, spoiled his brother by
violence, and did that which is not good among his people, loe,
euen he shall die in his iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Yet say
yee, Why? doeth not the sonne beare the iniquitie of the father?
when the sonne hath done that which is lawfull and right, and hath
kept all my Statutes, and hath done them, he shall surely
liue.<note> Deut.24.16. 2.kings 14.6. 2.chron.25.4. iere.31.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The soule that
sinneth, it shal die: the sonne shall not beare the iniquitie of
the father, neither shal the father beare the iniquitie of the
sonne; the righteousnesse of the righteous shall bee vpon him, and
the wickednesse of the wicked shalbe vpon him.</ab>

<fw>Gods wayes equall.</fw>
<ab n="21">But if the
wicked will turne from all his sinnes that he hath committed and
keepe all my statutes, and doe that which is lawful and right, he
shall surely liue, he shall not die.</ab>
<ab n="22">All his
transgressions that he hath committed, they shall not be mentioned
vnto him: in his righteousnesse, that he hath done, he shall
liue.</ab>
<ab n="23">Haue I any
pleasure at all that the wicked should die, saith the Lord God ?
And not that he should returne from his wayes, and
liue?<note> Chap. 33. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">¶ But when
the righteous turneth away frō his righteousnes, &amp;
committeth iniquitie, and doth according to all the abominations
that the wicked man doth, shall he liue? all his righteousnesse
that he hath done, shall not be mentioned: in his trespasse that he
hath trespassed, and in his sinne that he hath sinned, in them
shall he die.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Yet yee
say; The way of the Lord is not equall. Heare now, O house of
Israel; Is not my way equall? are not your wayes
vnequall?<note> Chap. 33. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">When a righteous
man turneth away from his righteousnesse, &amp; committeth
iniquitie, and dieth in them; for his iniquitie that he hath done,
shall he die.</ab>
<ab n="27">Againe, when the
wicked man turneth away from his wickednesse that he hath
committed, and doth that which is lawfull and right, he shall saue
his soule aliue.</ab>
<ab n="28">Because he
considereth and turneth away from all his transgressions that he
hath committed, he shall surely liue, he shall not die.</ab>
<ab n="29">Yet saith the
house of Israel; The way of the Lord is not equall. O house of
Israel, are not my wayes equall? are not your wayes
vnequall?</ab>
<ab n="30">Therefore I will
iudge you, O house of Israel, euery one according to his wayes,
saith the Lord God; repent, and turne your selues from all your
transgressions: so iniquitie shall not be your ruine.<note> Matth. 3.2. , Or, others.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Cast away
from you all your transgressions, wherby yee haue transgressed, and
make you a new heart and a new spirit: for why will yee die, O
house of Israel?<note> Ier.32. 39 chap. 11. 19. and 36.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For I haue no
pleasure in þe death of him that dieth, saith the
Lord God: wherefore turne your selues, &amp; liue ye.<note> Chap.33.11. 2.pet.3.9. , Or, others.</note></ab>



</div>