<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-34-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-34-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 A reproofe of the shepheards. 7
Gods iudgement against them. 11 His prouidence for his flocke. 20
The kingdome of Christ.</head>


<fw>The euill, and good shepheard.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the word of
þ<note/> Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man,
prophecie against the shepheards of Israel, prophecie and say vnto
them, Thus saith the Lord God vnto the shepheards, Woe be to the
shepheards of Israel that doe feede themselues: should not the
shepheards feede the flockes?<note> Iere. 23.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Yee eate the fat,
and ye clothe you with the wooll, yee kill them that are fed: but
ye feede not the flocke.</ab>
<ab n="4">The diseased haue
ye not strengthened, neither haue yee healed that which was sicke,
neither haue ye bound vp that which was broken, neither haue yee
brought againe that which was driuen away, neither haue yee sought
that which was lost; but with force and with crueltie haue yee
ruled them.<note> 1.Pet.5.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And they were
scattered because there is no shepheard: and they became meate to
all the beasts of the field, when they were scattered.<note> Or, without a shepheard: and so verse 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">My sheepe
wandered through all the mountaines, and vpon euery high hill: yea
my flocke was scattered vpon all the face of the earth, and none
did search or seeke after them.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Therefore,
yee shepheards, heare the word of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">As I liue, saith
the Lord God, surely because my flocke became a pray, and my flocke
became meate to euery beast of the field, because there was no
shepheard, neither did my shepheards search for my flocke, but the
shepheards fed themselues, and fed not my flocke:</ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore, O yee
shepheards, heare the word of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thus saith the
Lord God, Behold, I am against the shepheards, and I will require
my flocke at their hand, and cause them to cease from feeding the
flocke, neither shall the shepheards feede themselues any more: for
I will deliuer my flock from their mouth, that they may not be meat
for them.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ For thus
saith the Lord God, Behold, I, euen I will both search my sheepe,
and seeke them out.</ab>
<ab n="12">As a shepheard
seeketh out his flocke in the day that hee is among his sheepe that
are scattered: so wil I seeke out my sheep, and will deliuer them
out of all places, where they haue bene scattered in the cloudie
and darke day.<note> Heb. according to the seeking.</note></ab>

<fw>The euill, and good shepheard.</fw>
<ab n="13">And I will bring
them out from the people, and gather them from the countreys, and
will bring them to their owne land, and feede them vpon the
mountaines of Israel by the riuers, and in all the inhabited places
of the countrey,</ab>
<ab n="14">I will feede
them in a good pasture, and vpon the high mountaines of Israel
shall their folde be: there shall they lie in a good folde, and in
a fat pasture shall they feede vpon the mountaines of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="15">I will feed my
flocke, and I will cause them to lie downe, saith the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="16">I will seeke
that which was lost, and bring againe that which was driuen away,
and will bind vp that which was broken, and will strengthen that
which was sicke: but I will destroy the fat and the strong, I will
feed them with iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="17">And as for you,
O my flocke, thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I iudge betweene
cattell and cattell, betweene the rammes and the hee
goates.<note> Heb. small cattell of lambes and kids. , Heb. great hee goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Seemeth it a
small thing vnto you, to haue eaten vp the good pasture, but ye
must tread downe with your feet the residue of your pastures? and
to haue drunke of the deepe waters, but yee must fonle the residue
with your feete?</ab>
<ab n="19">And as for my
flocke, they eate that which yee haue troden with your feete: and
they drinke that which yee haue fouled with your feete.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Therefore
thus saith the Lord God vnto them, Behold, I, euen I will iudge
betweene the fat cattell, and betweene the leane cattell.</ab>
<ab n="21">Because yee haue
thrust with side and with shoulder, and pusht all the diseased with
your hornes, till yee haue scattered them abroad:</ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore will I
saue my flocke, and they shall no more be a pray, and I will iudge
betweene cattell and cattell.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I will set
vp one shepheard ouer them, and hee shall feede them, euen my
seruant Dauid; he shall feede them, and hee shall be their
shepheard.<note> Isai 40.11. ioh. 10. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And I the Lord
will be their God, and my seruant Dauid a prince among them, I the
Lord haue spoken it.</ab>

<fw>The iudgement of mount Seir.</fw>
<ab n="25">And I will make
with them a couenant of peace, and will cause the euill beasts to
cease out of the land: and they shall dwell safely in the
wildernesse, and sleepe in the woods.</ab>
<ab n="26">And I will make
them and the places round about my hill, a blessing; and I will
cause the showre to come downe in his season: there shall bee
showres of blessing.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the tree of
the field shal yeeld her fruite, and the earth shall yeeld her
increase, and they shall be safe in their land, and shall know that
I am the Lord, when I haue broken the bands of their yoke, and
deliuered them out of the hand of those that serued themselues of
them.</ab>
<ab n="28">And they shall
no more be a pray to the heathen, neither shall the beasts of the
land deuoure them; but they shall dwell safely, and none shall make
them afraide.</ab>
<ab n="29">And I will raise
vp for them a plant of renowne, and they shall be no more consumed
with hunger in the land, neither beare the shame of the heathen any
more.<note> Isai.11.1. ier.23.5. , Or, for renowne. , Heb. taken away.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Thus shall they
know that I the Lord their God am with them, and that they, euen
the house of Israel, are my people, saith the Lord God.</ab>
<ab n="31">And yee my
flocke of my pasture, are men, and I am your God, saith the Lord
God.<note> Ioh.10. 11.</note></ab>



</div>