<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Gods vengeance, for their
insolencie against the Iewes, vpon the Ammonites. 8 Vpon Moab and
Seir. 12 Vpon Edom, 15 and vpon the Philistines.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of the
Lord came againe vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Sonne of man, set
thy face against the Ammonites, and prophecie against
them,<note> Ier.49. 1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And say vnto the
Ammonites; Heare the word of the Lord God, Thus saith the Lord God;
Because thou saidst, Aha, against my sanctuarie, when it was
prophaned, and against the land of Israel, when it was desolate,
&amp; against the house of Iudah, when they went into
captiuitie;</ab>

<fw>Against Moab.</fw>
<ab n="4">Behold therefore,
I will deliuer thee to the men of the East for a possession, and
they shall set their palaces in thee, and make their dwellings in
thee: they shall eate thy fruit, and they shall drinke thy
milke.<note> Heb. children.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And I will make
Rabbah a stable for camels, and the Ammonites a couching place for
flocks: and ye shal know that I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">For thus saith
the Lord God, Because thou hast clapped thine hands and stamped
with the feete, and reioyced in heart with all thy despite against
the land of Israel:<note> Heb. hand. , Heb. foote , Heb. soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Behold therefore,
I will stretch out mine hand vpon thee, and will deliuer thee for a
spoile to the heathen, and I will cut thee off from the people, and
I wil cause thee to perish out of the countreys: I will destroy
thee, and thou shalt know that I am the Lord.<note> Or, meate.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Thus saith
the Lord God, Because that Moab and Seir doe say, Behold, the house
of Iudah is like vnto all the heathen:<note> Ier.48.1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore
beholde, I will open the side of Moab from the cities, from his
cities which are on his frontiers, the glory of the countrey
Beth-ieshimoth, Baal-meon and Kiriathaim,<note> Heb. shoulder of Moab</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Unto the men of
the East with the Ammonites, and will giue them in possession, that
the Ammonites may not be remembred among the nations.<note> Or, against the children of Ammon.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I will
execute iudgments vpon Moab, and they shall know that I am the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Thus
saith the Lord God, Because that Edom hath dealt against the house
of Iudah by taking vengeance, and hath greatly offended, and
reuenged himselfe vpon them:<note> Heb. by reuenging reuengement.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, I will also stretch out mine hand vpon Edom,
and will cut off man and beast from it, and I will make it desolate
from Teman, and they of Dedan shall fall by the sword.<note> Or, they shall fall by the sword vnto Dedan.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I will lay
my vengeance vpon Edom by the hand of my people Israel, and they
shall doe in Edom according to mine anger, and according to my
furie, and they shall know my vengeance, saith the Lord
God.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Thus
saith the Lord God, Because the Philistines haue dealt by reuenge,
and haue taken vengeance with a despiteful heart, to destroy it for
the old hatred:<note> Or, with perpetuall hatred.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Tyrus.</fw>
<ab n="16">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Behold, I will stretch out mine hand vpon the
Philistines, and I will cut off the Cherethims, and destroy the
remnant of the Seacoast.<note> Or, hauen of the Sea.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And I wil
execute great vengeance vpon them with furious rebukes, and they
shall knowe that I am the Lord, when I shall lay my vengeance vpon
them.<note> Heb. vengeances.</note></ab>



</div>