<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Ezekiels commission: 6 His
instruction. 9 The roule of his heauie prophecie.</head>


<fw>Rebellious Israel.</fw>
<ab n="1">And he said vnto
me, Son of man, stand vpon thy feete, and I will speake vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the spirit
entred into me, when hee spake vnto me, and set me vpon my feete,
that I heard him that spake vnto me:</ab>
<ab n="3">And hee said vnto
me, Sonne of man, I send thee to the children of Israel, to a
rebellious nation that hath rebelled against mee: they and their
fathers haue transgressed against mee, euen vnto this very
day.<note> Heb. nations.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For they are
impudent children and stiffe hearted: I doe send thee vnto them,
and thou shalt say vnto them, Thus sayth the Lord God.<note> Heb. hard of face.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And they, whether
they wil heare or whether they will forbeare, (for they are a
rebellious house) yet shall know that there hath bene a Prophet
among them.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And thou
sonne of man, be not afraid of them, neither be afraid of their
wordes, though bryars and thornes be with thee, and thou doest
dwell among scorpions: be not afraid of their words, nor be
dismayed at their lookes, though they be a rebellious
house.<note> Or, rebels.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And thou shalt
speake my words vnto them, whether they will heare or whether they
will forbeare, for they are most rebellious.<note> Heb. rebellion.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But thou, sonne of
man, heare what I say vnto thee; Be not thou rebellious like that
rebellious house: open thy mouth and eate that I giue
thee.<note> Reu.10.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And when I
looked, behold, an hand was sent vnto mee, and loe, a roule of a
booke was therein.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he spread it
before me, and it was written within and without, and there was
written therein lamentations, and mourning, and woe.</ab>



</div>