<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzekiel_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezekiel-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the type of haire, 5 is
shewed the iudgement of Ierusalem for their rebellion, 12 by
famine, sword and dispersion.</head>

<ab n="1">And thou sonne of
man, take thee a sharpe knife, take thee a barbours rasor, and
cause it to passe vpon thine head and vpon thy beard: then take the
ballances to weigh, and diuide the haire.</ab>
<ab n="2">Thou shalt burne
with fire a third part in the midst of the city, when the dayes of
the siege are fulfilled, and thou shalt take a third part, and
smite about it with a knife, and a third part thou shalt scatter in
the winde, and I will draw out a sword after them.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou shalt also
take thereof a few in number, and bind them in thy
skirts.<note> Hebr. wings.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then take of them
againe, and cast them into the midst of the fire, and burne them in
the fire: for thereof shall a fire come foorth into all the house
of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Thus saith
the Lord God; This is Ierusalem: I haue set it in the midst of the
nations and countreys that are round about her.</ab>

<fw>Pestilence, famine, and the
sword.</fw>
<ab n="6">And she hath
changed my iudgements into wickednesse more then the nations, and
my statutes more then the countreyes that are round about her: for
they haue refused my iudgements and my statutes, they haue not
walked in them.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Because yee multiplied more then the nations
that are round about you, and haue not walked in my Statutes,
neither haue kept my iudgments, neither haue done according to the
iudgements of the nations that are round about you:</ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Behold, I, euen I am against thee, and will
execute iudgements in the midst of thee in the sight of the
nations.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I will doe in
thee that which I haue not done, and whereunto I will not doe any
more the like, because of all thine abominations.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore the
fathers shall eate the sonnes in the midst of thee, and the sonnes
shall eate their fathers, and I will execute iudgements in thee,
and the whole remnant of thee will I scatter into all the
windes.<note> Leuit. 26. 29. deut.28.53. 2.kin.6.29. lamen. 4.10. baruch. 2.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore, as I
liue, saith the Lord God, Surely because thou hast defiled my
Sanctuary with all thy detestable things, and with all thine
abominations, therefore will I also diminish thee, neither shall
mine eye spare, neither will I haue any pitie.<note> Chap. 7.4, 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ A third
part of thee shall die with the pestilence, and with famine shall
they be consumed in the middest of thee: and a third part shall
fall by the sword round about thee: and I will scatter a third part
into all the windes, and I wil draw out a sword after them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thus shall mine
anger be accomplished, and I will cause my fury to rest vpon them,
and I will be comforted: and they shal know that I the Lord haue
spoken it in my zeale, when I haue accomplished my fury in
them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Moreouer I will
make thee waste, and a reproch among the nations that are round
about thee, in the sight of all that passe by.</ab>
<ab n="15">So it shall bee a
reproch and a taunt, an instruction and an astonishment vnto the
nations that are round about thee, when I shall execute iudgments
in thee in anger and in furie, and in furious rebukes: I the Lord
haue spoken it.<note> Deut.28. 37.</note></ab>

<fw>Pestilence, famine, and the
sword.</fw>
<ab n="16">When I shall send
vpon them the euill arrowes of famine, which shall be for their
destruction, and which I will send to destroy you: and I wil
increase the famine vpon you, and will breake your staffe of
bread.<note> Leuit.26.26. chap.4.16. and 14.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">So will I send
vpon you famine, and euill beasts, and they shall bereaue thee, and
pestilence and blood shal passe through thee, and I will bring the
sword vpon thee: I the Lord haue spoken it.<note> Leuit.26.22.</note></ab>



</div>