<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Darius finding the decree of
Cyrus, maketh a new decree for the aduancement of the building. 13
By the helpe of the enemies, and the directions of the prophets,
the Temple is finished. 16 The feast of the Dedication is kept. 19
And the Passeouer.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Darius the
King made a decree, and search was made in the house of the rolles,
where the treasures were laide vp in Babylon.<note> Chalde, bookes. , Chalde, made to descend.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And there was
found at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the prouince of the
Medes, a rolle, and therein was a record thus written:<note> Or, Ecbatana, or in a coffer.</note></ab>

<fw>Tatnais letter to Darius,
answered.</fw>
<ab n="3">In the first
yeere of Cyrus the king, the same Cyrus the king made a decree
concerning the house of God at Ierusalem: Let the house be builded,
the place where they offered sacrifices, and let the foundations
thereof of be strongly laid, the height therof threescore cubits,
and the breadth thereof threescore cubites:</ab>
<ab n="4">With three
rowes of great stones, and a row of new timber: and let the
expences bee giuen out of the kings house.</ab>
<ab n="5">And also let
the golden, and siluer vessels of the house of God, which
Nebuchadnezzar tooke foorth out of the temple which is at
Ierusalem, and brought vnto Babylon, be restored, and brought
againe vnto the temple which is at Ierusalem, euery one to his
place, and place them in the house of God.<note> Chalde, go.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Now therefore
Tatnai, gouernour beyond the riuer, Shethar-Boznai, and your
companions the Apharsachites, which are beyond the riuer, be ye
farre from thence:<note> Chalde, their societies.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Let the worke
of this house of God alone, let the gouernour of the Iewes, and the
elders of the Iewes, build this house of God in his place.</ab>
<ab n="8">Moreouer I make
a decree, what ye shall doe to the Elders of these Iewes, for the
building of this house of God: that of the kings goods, euen of the
tribute beyond the riuer, forthwith expences be giuen vnto these
men, that they be not hindered.<note> Chalde, by me a decree is made. , Chalde, made to cease.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And that which
they haue need of, both yong bullocks, and rammes, and lambes, for
the burnt offerings of the God of heauen, wheat, salt, wine, and
oyle, according to the appoyment of the priests which are at
Ierusalem, let it be giuen them, day by day without faile:</ab>
<ab n="10">That they may
offer sacrifices of sweet sauours vnto the God of heauen, and pray
for the life of the king, and of his sonnes.<note> Chalde, of rest.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Also I haue
made a decree, that whosoeuer shall alter this word, let timber be
pulled down from his house, and being set vp, let him bee hanged
thereon, and let his house bee made a doung hill for
this.<note> Chalde, let him be destroyed.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the God
that hath caused his name to dwell there, destroy all kings and
people that shall put to their hand, to alter and to destroy this
house of God which is at Ierusalem. I Darius haue made a decree,
let it be done with speed.</ab>

<fw>The dedication.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ Then
Tatnai gouernour on this side the riuer, Shethar-Boznai, &amp;
their companions, according to that which Darius the king had sent,
so they did speedily.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the elders
of the Iewes builded, and they prospered, through the prophecying
of Haggai the Prophet, and Zechariah the sonne of Iddo, and they
builded, and finished it, according to the commandement of the God
of Israel, and according to the commandement of Cyrus and Darius,
and Artaxerxes king of Persia.<note> Chald. Decree.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And this honse
was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the
sixt yere of the reigne of Darius the king.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
children of Israel, the Priests and the Leuites, and the rest of
the children of the captiuitie, kept the dedicatiō of this
house of God, with ioy,<note> Chald. the sonnes of the transportation.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And offered at
the dedication of this house of God, an hundred bullockes, two
hundred rammes, foure hundred lambes; and for a sinne offering for
all Israel, twelue hee goates, according to the number of the
tribes of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they set
the Priests in their diuisions, and the Leuites in their courses,
for the seruice of God, which is at Ierusalem, as it is written in
the booke of Moses.<note> Chald. according to the writing. , Num.3.6. and 8.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the
children of the captiuitie kept the Passeouer, vpon the fourteenth
day of the first moneth:</ab>
<ab n="20">For the
Priestes and the Leuites were purified together, all of them were
pure, and killed the Passeouer for all the children of the
captiuitie, and for their brethren the Priests, and for
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
children of Israel, which were come againe out of captiuitie, and
all such as had separated themselues vnto them, from the
filthinesse of the heathen of the land, to seeke the Lord God of
Israel, did eate,</ab>
<ab n="22">And kept the
feast of vnleauened bread seuen dayes, with ioy: for the Lord had
made them ioyfull, and turned the heart of the king of Assyria vnto
them, to strengthen their handes in the worke of the house of God,
the God of Israel.</ab>



</div>