<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-10-10-Nehemiah.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Shechaniah encourageth Ezra to
reforme the strange mariages. 6 Ezra mourning, assembleth the
people. 9 The people at the exhortation of Ezra, repent and promise
amendment. 15 The care to performe it. 18 The names of them who had
maried strange wiues.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when Ezra
had praised, and when he had confessed, weeping, and casting
himselfe downe before the house of God, there assembled vnto him
out of Israel, a very great congregation of men, and women, and
children: for the people wept very sore.<note> Heb. wept a great weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Shechaniah
the sonne of Iehiel, one of the sonnes of Elam, answered and said
vnto Ezra, Wee haue trespassed against our God, and haue taken
strange wiues, of the people of the land: yet now there is hope in
Israel concerning this thing.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now therefore
let vs make a couenant with our God, to put away all the wiues,
&amp; such as are borne of them, according to the counsell of my
lord, and of those that tremble at the commandement of our God, and
lee it be done according to the Law.<note> Hebr. to bring forth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Arise, for
this matter belongeth vnto thee, wee also will be with thee: be of
good courage, and doe it.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then arose
Ezra, and made the chiefe Priests, the Leuites, and all Israel to
sweare, that they should doe according to this word: and they
sware.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then
Ezra rose vp from before the house of God, and went into the
chamber of Iohanan, the sonne of Eliashib: and when hee came
thither, hee did eate no bread, nor drinke water: for hee mourned
because of the transgression of them that had bene caried
away.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they made
Proclamation throughout Iudah and Ierusalem, vnto all the children
of the captiuitie, that they should gather themselues together vnto
Ierusalem;</ab>
<ab n="8">And that
whosoeuer would not come within three dayes, according to the
counsell of the Princes, and the Elders, all his substance should
be forfeited, and himselfe separated from the congregation of those
that had beene caried away.<note> Heb. deuoted.</note></ab>

<fw>Order taken for strange
mariages.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ Then
all the men of Iudah and Beniamin, gathered themselues together
vnto Ierusalem, within three dayes: it was the ninth moneth, on the
twentieth day of the moneth, and all the people sate in the streete
of the house of God, trembling because of this matter, and for the
great raine.<note> Hebr. the showres.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Ezra the Priest
stood vp, and said vnto them, Yee haue transgressed, and haue taken
strange wiues, to encrease the trespasse of Israel.<note> Hebr. haue caused to dwel, or haue brought backe.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Now therefore make
confession vnto the Lord God of your fathers, and doe his pleasure:
and separate your selues from the people of the land, and from the
strange wiues.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then all the
congregation answered, and said with a loude voice, As thou hast
said, so must we doe:</ab>
<ab n="13">But the people are
many, and it is a time of much raine, and we are not able to stand
without; neither is this a worke of one day or two: for wee are
many that haue transgressed in this thing.<note> Or, wee haue greatly offended in this thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Let now our rulers
of all the congregation stand, and let all them which haue taken
strange wiues in our cities, come at appointed times, &amp; with
them the Elders of euery citie, and the Iudges thereof; vntill the
fierce wrath of our God for this matter, be turned from
vs.<note> Or, till this matter be dispatched.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Onely
Ionathan the sonne of Asahel, and Iahaziah the sonne of Tikuah,
were employed about this matter: and Meshullam, and Shabbethai the
Leuite, helped them.<note> Heb. stood.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the children of
the captiuitie did so: and Ezra the Priest, with certaine chiefe of
the fathers, after the house of their fathers, and all of them by
their names, were separated, and sate downe in the first day of the
tenth moneth to examine the matter.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they made an
ende, with all the men that had taken strange wiues, by the first
day of the first moneth.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And among
the sonnes of the Priestes, there were found that had taken strange
wiues: namely, of the sons of Ieshua the sonne of Iozadak, and his
brethren, Maasiah, and Eliezer, and Iarib, and Gedaliah.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they gaue their
hands, that they would put away their wiues: and being guiltie,
they offered a ramme of the flocke for their trespasse.</ab>
<ab n="20">And of the sonnes
of Immer, Hanani, and Zebadiah:</ab>

<fw>Who put away strange wiues.</fw>
<ab n="21">And of the sonnes
of Harim, Maasiah, and Eliiah, and Shemaiah, and Iehiel, and
Uzziah.</ab>
<ab n="22">And of the sonnes
of Pashur: Elioenai, Maasiah, Ishmael, Nethaneel, Iozabad and
Elasah.</ab>
<ab n="23">Also of the
Leuites: Iozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah (the same is Kelitah)
Pethahiah, Iudah, and Eliezer.</ab>
<ab n="24">Of the singers
also, Eliashib; and of the porters, Shallum, and Telem, and
Uri.</ab>
<ab n="25">Moreouer of Israel,
of the sonnes of Parosh, Ramiah, and Iesiah, and Malchiah, and
Miamin, and Eleazar, and Malchiiah, and Benaiah.</ab>
<ab n="26">And of the sonnes
of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Iehiel, and Abdi, and Ieremoth,
and Eliah.</ab>
<ab n="27">And of the sonnes
of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Ieremoth, and Zabad,
and Aziza.</ab>
<ab n="28">Of the sonnes also
of Bebai: Iehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, &amp; Athlai.</ab>
<ab n="29">And of the sonnes
of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Iashub, and Sheal, and
Ramoth.</ab>

<fw>Who put away strange wiues.</fw>
<ab n="30">And of the sonnes
of Pahath Moab: Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maasiah, Mattaniah,
Bezaleel, and Binnui, and Manasseh.</ab>
<ab n="31">And of the sonnes
of Harim: Eliezer, Ishiiah, Malchiah, Shemaiah, Shimeon,</ab>
<ab n="32">Beniamin, Malluch,
and Shemariah.</ab>
<ab n="33">Of the sonnes of
Hashum: Mattenai, Mattatha, Zabad, Eliphelet, Ieremai, Manasseh,
and Shimei.</ab>
<ab n="34">Of the sonnes of
Bani: Maadai, Amram, and Uel,</ab>
<ab n="35">Benaiah, Bedaiah,
Chelluh,</ab>
<ab n="36">Uaniah, Meremoth,
Eliashib,</ab>
<ab n="37">Mattaniah,
Mattenai, and Iaasau,</ab>
<ab n="38">And Bani, and
Bennui, Shimei,</ab>
<ab n="39">And Shelemiah, and
Nathan, and Adaiah,</ab>
<ab n="40">Machnadebai,
Shashai, Sharai,<note> Or, Mabnadebai, according to some copies.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">Azareel, and
Shelemiah, Shemariah,</ab>
<ab n="42">Shallum, Amariah,
and Ioseph.</ab>
<ab n="43">Of the sonnes of
Nebo, Iehiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Iadau, and Ioel,
Benaiah.</ab>
<ab n="44">All these had taken
strange wiues: and some of them had wiues, by whom they had
children.</ab>



</div>