<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Ezra goeth vp to Ierusalem. 11 The
gracious commission of Artaxerxes to Ezra. 27 Ezra blesseth God for
his fauour.</head>


<fw>The kings letter.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now after these
things, in the reigne of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of
Seraiah, the sonne of Azariah, the sonne of Hilkiah,</ab>
<ab n="2">The sonne of
Shallum, the sonne of Zadok, the sonne of Ahitub,</ab>
<ab n="3">The sonne of
Amariah, the sonne of Azariah, the sonne of Meraioth,</ab>
<ab n="4">The sonne of
Zeraiah, the sonne of Uzzi, the sonne of Bukki,</ab>
<ab n="5">The sonne of
Abishua, the sonne of Phinehas, the sonne of Eleazar, the sonne of
Aaron the chiefe Priest:</ab>
<ab n="6">This Ezra went
vp from Babylon, and hee was a ready Scribe in the law of Moses,
which the Lord God of Israel had giuen: and the king granted him
all his request, according to the hand of the Lord his God vpon
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">And there went
vp some of the children of Israel, and of the Priests, and the
Leuites, and the Singers, and the Porters, and the Nethinims, vnto
Ierusalem, in the seuenth yeere of Artaxerxes the king.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he came to
Ierusalem in the fifth moneth, which was in the seuenth yeere of
the king.</ab>
<ab n="9">For vpon the
first day of the first moneth, began he to go vp frō Babylon,
and on the first day of the fifth moneth, came he to Ierusalem,
according to the good hand of his God vpon him.<note> He was the foundation of the going vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For Ezra had
prepared his heart to seeke the Law of the Lord, and to doe it, and
to teach in Israel, Statutes and Iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Now
this is the copy of the letter that the king Artaxerxes gaue vnto
Ezra the Priest, the Scribe, euen a Scribe of the words of the
commandements of the Lord, and of his Statutes to Israel.</ab>
<ab n="12">Artaxerxes
king of kings, Unto Ezra the Priest, a Scribe of the Law of the God
of heauen, Perfect peace, and at such a time.<note> Or, to Ezra the Priest a perfit Scribe of the Lawe of the God of heauen, Peace, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">I make a
decree, that all they of the people of Israel, and of his Priests,
and Leuites in my Realme, which are minded of their owne free-will
to goe vp to Ierusalem, goe with thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Forasmuch as
thou art sent of the king, and of his seuen counsellers, to enquire
concerning Iudah and Ierusalem, according to the Lawe of thy God,
which is in thine hand;<note> Chal. from before the King. , Esth.1.14.</note></ab>

<fw>The commission giuen to Ezra</fw>
<ab n="15">And to cary
the siluer and gold, which the king and his counsellers haue freely
offered vnto the God of Israel, whose habitation is in
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="16">And all the
siluer and gold, that thou canst find in all the prouince of
Babylon, with the free-will offering of the people, and of the
priests, offering willingly for the house of their God, which is in
Ierusalem:<note> Chap.8. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">That thou
maiest buy speedily with this money, bullockes, rammes, lambes,
with their meate offerings, and their drinke offerings, and offer
them vpon the altar of the house of your God, which is in
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="18">And whatsoeuer
shall seeme good to thee, and to thy brethren, to doe with the rest
of the siluer and gold; that doe, after the will of your
God.</ab>
<ab n="19">The vessels
also that are giuen thee, for the seruice of the house of thy God,
those deliuer thou before the God of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="20">And whatsoeuer
more shall be needfull for the house of thy God, which thou shalt
haue occasion to bestowe; bestowe it out of the kings treasure
house.</ab>
<ab n="21">And I, euen I
Artaxerxes the king, doe make a decree to all the treasurers which
are beyond the riuer, that whatsoeuer Ezra the priest, the scribe
of the law of the God of heauen, shall require of you, it be done
speedily,</ab>
<ab n="22">Unto an
hundred talents of siluer, and to an hundred measures of wheate,
and to an hundred bathes of wine, and to an hundred bathes of oyle,
and salt, without prescribing how much.<note> Chald: Cores.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Whatsoeuer is
commanded by the God of heauen, let it be diligently done, for the
house of the God of heauen: for why should there be wrath against
the realme of the king and his sonnes?<note> Heb. what soeuer is of the decree.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Also we
certifie you, that touching any of the priests, and Leuites,
singers, porters, Nethinims, or ministers of this house of God, it
shall not be lawfull to impose tolle, tribute, or custome vpon
them.</ab>
<ab n="25">And thou,
Ezra, after the wisdome of thy God, that is in thine hand, set
magistrates and iudges, which may iudge all the people, that are
beyond the riuer, all such as know the lawes of thy God, and teach
yee them that knowe them not.</ab>

<fw>The commission giuen to Ezra</fw>
<ab n="26">And whosoeuer
will not doe the law of thy God, and the law of the king, let
iudgement be executed speedily vpon him, whether it be vnto death,
or to banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to
imprisonment.<note> Chald. to rooting out.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Blessed
be the Lord God of our fathers, which hath put such a thing as
this, in the kings heart, to beautifie the house of the Lord which
is in Ierusalem:</ab>
<ab n="28">And hath
extended mercy vnto me, before the king and his counsellers, and
before all the kings mighty princes, and I was strengthned as the
hand of the Lord my God was vpon me, and I gathered together out of
Israel, chiefe men to goe vp with me.</ab>



</div>