<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The companions of Ezra, who
returned from Babylon. 15 He sendeth to Iddo for ministers for the
Temple. 21 He keepeth a fast. 24 He committeth the treasures to the
custodie of the Priests. 31 From Ahaua they come to Ierusalem. 33
The treasure is weighed in the Temple. 36 The commission is
deliuered.</head>

<ab n="1">These are now
the chiefe of their fathers, and this is the genealogie of them
that went vp with mee from Babylon, in the reigne of Artaxerxes the
king.</ab>
<ab n="2">Of the sonnes
of Phinehas, Gershom: of the sonnes of Ithamar, Daniel: of the
sonnes of Dauid, Hattush.</ab>
<ab n="3">Of the sonnes
of Shechaniah, of the sonnes of Pharosh, Zechariah, and with him
were reckoned, by genealogie of the males, an hundred and
fiftie.</ab>
<ab n="4">Of the sonnes
of Pahath Moab, Elihoenai the sonne of Zerahiah: and with him, two
hundred males.</ab>
<ab n="5">Of the sonnes
of Shechaniah, the sonne of Iahaziel, and with him three hundred
males.</ab>
<ab n="6">Of the sonnes
also of Adin, Ebed the sonne of Ionathan, and with him fiftie
males.</ab>
<ab n="7">And of the
sonnes of Elam, Ieshaiah the sonne of Athaliah, and with him
seuentie males.</ab>
<ab n="8">And of the
sonnes of Shephatiah, Zebadiah the sonne of Michael, and with him
fourescore males.</ab>
<ab n="9">Of the sonnes
of Ioab, Obadiah the sonne of Iehiel: and with him two hundred and
eighteene males.</ab>

<fw>A fast proclaimed.</fw>
<ab n="10">And of the
sonnes of Shelomith, the sonne of Iosiphiah, and with him an
hundred and threescore males.</ab>
<ab n="11">And of the
sonnes of Bebai, Zechariah the sonne of Bebai, and with him twenty
and eight males.</ab>
<ab n="12">And of the
sonnes of Azgad, Iohanan the sonne of Hakkatan, and with him an
hundred and ten males.<note> Or, the youngest son.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And of the
last sonnes of Adonikam, whose names are these: Eliphelet, Iehiel,
and Shemaiah, and with them threescore males.</ab>
<ab n="14">Of the sonnes
also of Biguai, Uthai, and Zabbud, and with them seuentie
males.<note> Or, Zaccur, as some read.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And I
gathered them together to the riuer, that runneth to Ahaua, and
there abode wee in tents three dayes: and I viewed the people, and
the Priests, and found there none of the sonnes of
Leui.<note> Or pitched.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Then sent I
for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for
Iarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for
Meshullam, chiefe men; also for Iarib, and for Elnathan, men of
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="17">And I sent
them with commandement vnto Iddo the chiefe at the place Casiphia,
and I told them what they should say vnto Iddo, and to his brethren
the Nethinims, at the place Casiphia, that they should bring vnto
vs ministers for the house of our God.<note> Hebr. I put words in their mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And by the
good hand of our God vpon vs, they brought vs a man of
vnderstanding, of the sonnes of Mahli the sonne of Leui, the sonne
of Israel, and Sherebiah, with his sonnes, and his brethren,
eighteene.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Hashabiah,
and with him Ieshaiah of the sonnes of Merari, his brethren, and
their sonnes, twentie.</ab>
<ab n="20">Also of the
Nethinims, whom Dauid, and the Princes had appointed for the
seruice of the Leuites, two hundred and twentie Nethinims: all of
them were expressed by name.<note> See Chap. 2.43.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then I
proclaimed a fast there, at the riuer Ahaua, that we might afflict
our selues before our God, to seeke of him a right way for vs, and
for our little ones, and for all our substance.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites charge.</fw>
<ab n="22">For I was
ashamed to require of the king a band of souldiers and horsmen, to
helpe vs against the enemie in the way: because wee had spoken vnto
the king, saying, The hand of our God is vpon all them for good,
that seeke him, but his power and his wrath is against all them
that forsake him.</ab>
<ab n="23">So we fasted,
and besought our God for this, and hee was intreated of vs.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Then I
separated twelue of the chiefe of the Priests, Sherebiah,
Hashabiah, and ten of their brethren with them,</ab>
<ab n="25">And weighed
vnto them the siluer and the gold, and the vessels, euen the
offering of the house of our God, which the king and his
counsellours, and his lords, and all Israel there present, had
offered:</ab>
<ab n="26">I euen weighed
vnto their hand, sixe hundred and fifty talents of siluer, and
siluer vessels an hundred talents, and of gold an hundred
talents:</ab>
<ab n="27">Also twenty
basons of gold, of a thousand drammes, and two vessels of fine
copper, precious as gold.<note> Hebr. yellow or shining brasse. , Hebr. desireable.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And I said
vnto them, Yee are holy vnto the Lord, the vessels are holy also,
and the siluer and the gold are a free-will offring vnto the Lord
God of your fathers.</ab>
<ab n="29">Watch ye, and
keepe them, vntill yee weigh them before the chiefe of the Priests,
and the Leuites, and chiefe of the fathers of Israel at Ierusalem,
in the chambers of the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="30">So tooke the
Priests and the Leuites the weight of the siluer and the gold, and
the vessels, to bring them to Ierusalem, vnto the house of our
God.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Then
wee departed from the riuer of Ahaua, on the twelfth day of the
first moneth, to goe vnto Ierusalem; and the hand of our God was
vpon vs, and hee deliuered vs from the hand of the enemie, and of
such as lay in wait by the way.</ab>
<ab n="32">And we came to
Ierusalem, and abode there three dayes.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Now on
the fourth day was the siluer and the gold, and the vessels weighed
in the house of our God, by the hand of Meremoth the sonne of Uriah
the Priest, and with him was Eleazar the sonne of Phinehas, and
with them was Iozabad the sonne of Ieshua, and Noadiah the sonne of
Binnui, Leuites:</ab>

<fw>Ezras confession and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="34">By number, and
by weight of uery one: and all the weight was written at that
time.</ab>
<ab n="35">Also the
children of those that had bene caried away which were come out of
the captiuitie, offered burnt offrings vnto the God of Israel,
twelue bullocks for all Israel, ninetie and sixe rammes, seuentie
and seuen lambes, twelue hee goates for a sinne offering: All this
was a burnt offering vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And
they deliuered the Kings commissions vnto the kings lieuteuants,
and to the gouernours on this side the riuer, and they furthered
the people, and the house of God.</ab>



</div>