<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Ezra mourneth for the affinitie of
the people with strangers. 5 He prayeth vnto God with confession of
sinnes.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe when these
things were done, the Princes came to me, saying, The people of
Israel, and the priests and the Leuites, haue not separated
themselues from the people of the lands, doing according to their
abominations, euen of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites,
the Iebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the
Amorites.</ab>
<ab n="2">For they haue
taken of their daughters for themselues, and for their sonnes: so
that the holy seed haue mingled themselues with the people of those
lands, yea the hand of the princes and rulers hath bin chiefe in
this trespasse.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when I
heard this thing, I rent my garment and my mantle, and pluckt off
the haire of my head, and of my beard, and sate downe
astonied.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then were
assembled vnto me euery one that trembled at the words of the God
of Israel, because of the transgression of those that had bene
caried away, and I sate astonied, vntill the euening
sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And at
the euening sacrifice, I arose vp from my heauinesse, and hauing
rent my garment and my mantle, I fell vpon my knees, and spread out
my hands vnto the Lord my God,<note> Or, affliction.</note></ab>

<fw>Ezras confession and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="6">And said, O my
God, I am ashamed, and blush to lift vp my face to thee, my God:
for our iniquities are increased ouer our head, and our trespasse
is growen vp vnto the heauens.<note> Or, guiltinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Since the dayes
of our fathers, haue wee beene in a great trespasse vnto this day,
&amp; for our iniquities haue we, our kings and our priests, bin
deliuered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to
captiuitie, and to a spoile, and to confusion of face, as it is
this day.</ab>
<ab n="8">And now for a
litle space grace hath bene shewed from the Lord our God, to leaue
vs a remnant to escape, and to giue vs a naile in his holy place,
that our God may lighten our eyes, and giue vs a litle reuiuing in
our bondage:<note> Hebr. moment. , Or, a pinne , That is, a constant and sure abode.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For wee were
bondmen, yet our God hath not forsaken vs in our bondage, but hath
extended mercie vnto vs in the sight of the kings of Persia, to
giue vs a reuiuing to set vp the house of our God, and to repaire
the desolations thereof, and to giue vs a wall in Iudah and in
Ierusalem.<note> Heb. to set vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And now, O our
God, what shal we say after this? for we haue forsaken thy
commandements,</ab>
<ab n="11">Which thou
hast commanded by thy seruants the prophets, saying, The land vnto
which ye go to possesse it, is an vncleane land, with the
filthinesse of the people of the lands, with their abominations,
which haue filled it from one end to another, with their
vncleannesse.<note> Heb. by the hand of thy seruants. , Exod.23. 32. deut.7.3 , Heb. from mouth to mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Nowe therefore
giue not your daughters vnto their sonnes, neither take their
daughters vnto your sonnes, nor seeke their peace or their wealth
for euer: that ye may bee strong, and eate the good of the land,
and leaue it for an inheritance to your children for euer.</ab>
<ab n="13">And after all
that is come vpon vs, for our euill deeds, and for our great
trespasse, seeing that thou, our God, hast punished vs lesse, then
our iniquities deserue, and hast giuen vs such deliuerance as
this:<note> Heb. hast withheld beneath our iniquities.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Should wee
againe breake thy commandements, and ioyne in affinitie with the
people of these abominations? wouldest thou not be angry with vs,
til thou haddest consumed vs, so that there should be no remnant,
nor escaping?</ab>
<ab n="15">O Lord God of
Israel, thou art righteous, for wee remaine yet escaped, as it is
this day: Behold, we are before thee in our trespasses: for wee can
not stand before thee, because of this.</ab>



</div>