<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The number that returne, of the
people, 36 of the Priests, 40 of the Leuites, 43 of the Nethinims,
55 of Solomons seruants, 62 of the Priests which could not shewe
their pedigree. 64 The whole number of them, with their substance.
68 Their oblations.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are
the children of the prouince, that went vp out of the captiuitie,
of those which had beene caried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the King
of Babylon had caried away vnto Babylon, and came againe vnto
Ierusalem and Iudah, euery one vnto his citie;<note> Nehem. 7.6, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Which came with
Zerubbabel, Ieshua, Nehemiah, Saraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan,
Mispar, Biguai, Rehum, Baanah: The number of the men of the people
of Israel.<note> Or, Azariah, nehe.7.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The children of
Parosh, two thousand, an hundred seuentie and two.</ab>
<ab n="4">The children of
Shephatiah, three hundred seuentie and two.</ab>

<fw>Who returned from captiuitie.</fw>
<ab n="5">The children of
Arah, seuen hundred, seuentie and fiue.</ab>
<ab n="6">The children of
Pahath-Moab, of the children of Ieshua and Ioab, two thousand,
eight hundred and twelue.<note> Nehem. 7.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The children of
Elam, a thousand, two hundred fiftie and foure.</ab>
<ab n="8">The children of
Zattu, nine hundred fourtie and fiue.</ab>
<ab n="9">The children of
Zaccai, seuen hundred and threescore.</ab>
<ab n="10">The children
of Bani, sixe hundred, fourtie and two.<note> Or, Binnui, nehem.7. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The children
of Bebai, sixe hundred, twentie and three.</ab>
<ab n="12">The children
of Azgad, a thousand, two hundred, twentie and two.</ab>
<ab n="13">The children
of Adonikam, sixe hundred, sixtie and sixe.</ab>
<ab n="14">The children
of Biguai, two thousand fiftie and sixe.</ab>
<ab n="15">The children
of Adin, foure hundred, fiftie and foure.</ab>
<ab n="16">The children
of Ater of Hezekiah, ninetie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="17">The children
of Bezai, three hundred twenty and three.</ab>
<ab n="18">The children
of Iorah, an hundred and twelue.<note> Or, Hariph, nehem. 7.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The children
of Hashum, two hundred twentie and three.</ab>
<ab n="20">The children
of Gibbar, ninetie and fiue.<note> Or, Gibeon, nehem.7.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The children
of Bethlehem, an hundred twentie and three.</ab>
<ab n="22">The children
of Netophah, fiftie and sixe.</ab>
<ab n="23">The men of
Anathoth, an hundred twentie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="24">The children
of Azmaueth, fortie and two.<note> Or, Beth-Asmaueth, Nehe.7.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The children
of Kiriath-arim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seuen hundred, and fourtie
and three.</ab>
<ab n="26">The children
of Ramah and Gaba, sixe hundred, twentie and one.</ab>
<ab n="27">The men of
Michmas, an hundred, twentie and two.</ab>
<ab n="28">The men of
Bethel and Ai, two hundred, twentie and three.</ab>
<ab n="29">The children
of Nebo, fiftie and two.</ab>
<ab n="30">The children
of Magbish, an hundred fiftie and sixe.</ab>
<ab n="31">The children
of the other Elam, a thousand, two hundred, fiftie and
foure.<note> See ver.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">The children
of Harim, three hundred and twentie.</ab>

<fw>Who returned from captiuitie.</fw>
<ab n="33">The children
of Lod Hadid, and Ono, seuen hundred, twentie and fiue.<note> Or, Harid, as it is in some copies.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">The children
of Iericho, three hundred fourtie and fiue.</ab>
<ab n="35">The children
of Senaah, three thousand and sixe hundred and thirtie.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ The
Priests. The children of Iedaiah, of the house of Ieshua, nine
hundred, seuentie and three.<note> 1.Chro. 24.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">The children
of Immer, a thousand, fiftie and two.<note> 1.Chro. 24.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">The children
of Pashur, a thousand, two hundred, fourtie and seuen.<note> 1.Chro.9. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">The children
of Harim, a thousand and seuenteene.<note> 1.Chro. 24.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">¶ The
Leuites. The children of Ieshua, and Kadmiel, of the children of
Hodauia, seuentie and foure.<note> Or, Iuda, chap.3. 9. called also Hodeuah, nehem.7.43.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">¶ The
singers. The children of Asaph, an hundred twentie and
eight.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶ The
children of the porters. The children of Shallum, the children of
Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children
of Hatita, the children of Shobai, in all, an hundred thirtie and
nine.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ The
Nethinims. The children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the
children of Tabbaoth,</ab>
<ab n="44">The children
of Keros, the children of Siaha, the children of Padon,</ab>
<ab n="45">The children
of Lebanah, the children of Hagabah, the children of Akkub,</ab>
<ab n="46">The children
of Hagab, the children of Shalmai, the children of
Hanan.<note> Or, Shamlai.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">The children
of Giddel, the children of Gahar, the children of Reaiah,</ab>
<ab n="48">The children
of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, the children of Gazzam,</ab>
<ab n="49">The children
of Uzza, the children of Paseah, the children of Besai,</ab>
<ab n="50">The children
of Asnah, the children of Mehunim, the children of
Nephushim,</ab>
<ab n="51">The children
of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,</ab>
<ab n="52">The children
of Bazluth, the children of Mehida, the children of
Harsha,<note> Or, Bazlith, in Nehem.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">The children
of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Thamah,</ab>
<ab n="54">The children
of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.</ab>

<fw>The peoples zeale.</fw>
<ab n="55">¶ The
children of Solomons seruants. The children of Sotai, the children
of Sophereth, the children of Peruda,<note> Or, Perida, in Nehem.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">The children
of Iaalah, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,</ab>
<ab n="57">The children
of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth of
Zebaim, the children of Ami.<note> Or, Amon, in Nehem.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">All the
Nethinims, and the children of Solomons seruants, were three
hundred ninetie and two.<note> Iosh.9. 21, 27. 1.chro.9.2. , 1.King.9. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">And these were
they which went vp from Tel-melah, Tel-Harfa, Cherub, Addan, and
Immer: but they could not shewe their fathers house, and their
seed, whether they were of Israel.<note> Or, pedegree.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">The children
of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda: sixe
hundred fiftie and two.</ab>
<ab n="61">¶ And of
the children of the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children
of Koz, the children of Barzillai, (which tooke a wife of the
daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their
name.)<note> 2.Sam.17 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">These sought
their register among those that were reckoned by genealogie, but
they were not found: therefore were they as polluted, put from the
priesthood.<note> Heb. they were polluted from the priesthood.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">And the
Tirshatha said vnto them, that they should not eate of the most
holy things, till there stood vp a priest with Urim &amp; with
Thummim.<note> Or, gouernour. , Exod. 28. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">¶ The
whole Congregation together, was fourtie and two thousand, three
hundred and threescore:</ab>
<ab n="65">Beside their
seruants and their maids, of whom there were seuen thousand, three
hundred thirtie and seuen: and there were among them two hundred
singing men, and singing women.</ab>
<ab n="66">Their horses
were seuen hundred, thirtie and sixe: their mules, two hundred
fourtie and fiue:</ab>
<ab n="67">Their camels,
foure hundred, thirty and fiue: their asses, sixe thousand, seuen
hundred and twentie.</ab>
<ab n="68">¶ And
some of the chiefe of the fathers, when they came to the house of
the Lord which is at Ierusalem, offered freely for the house of
God, to set it vp in his place:</ab>
<ab n="69">They gaue
after their abilitie, vnto the treasure of the worke, threescore
and one thousand drammes of golde, and fiue thousand pound of
siluer, and one hundred priests garments.<note> 1. Chron. 26.20.</note></ab>

<fw>The Altar.</fw>
<ab n="70">So the priests
and the Leuites, and some of the people, and the singers, and the
porters, and the Nethinims, dwelt intheir cities, and all Israel in
their cities.</ab>



</div>