<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Zerubbabel and Shealtiel, incited
by Haggai and Zacharie, set forward the building of the Temple. 3
Tatnai and Shether Boznai could not hinder the Iewes. 6 Their
letter to Darius against the Iewes.</head>


<fw>The Kings letter, and the
enemies.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then the
Prophets, Haggai the Prophet, and Zechariah the sonne of Iddo,
prophesied vnto the Iewes that were in Iudah and Ierusalem, in the
Name of the God of Israel, euen vnto them.<note> Agge.1.1. zach.1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then rose vp
Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel, and Ieshua the sonne of Iozadak,
and began to build the house of God which is at Ierusalem: and with
them were the Prophets of God helping them.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ At the
same time came to them Tatnai, gouernour on this side the Riuer,
and Shethar-Boznai, and their companions, and said thus vnto them;
Who hath commaunded you to build this house, and to make vp this
wall?</ab>
<ab n="4">Then said wee
vnto them after this maner, What are the names of the men that make
this building?<note> Chald. that build this building.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But the eye of
their God was vpon the Elders of the Iewes, that they could not
cause them to cease, till the matter came to Darius: and then they
returned answere by letter concerning this matter.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ The copy
of the letter that Tatnai, gouernour on this side the Riuer, and
Shethar-Boznai, and his companions the Apharsachites, which were on
this side the Riuer, sent vnto Darius the King:</ab>
<ab n="7">They sent a
letter vnto him, wherein was written thus: Unto Darius the king,
all peace.<note> Chald. in the midst whereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Be it knowen
vnto the king, that we went into the prouince of Iudea, to the
house of the great God, which is builded with great stones, &amp;
timber is laied in the wals, and this worke goeth fast on, and
prospereth in their hands.<note> Chald. stones of roling.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then asked we
those Elders, and said vnto them thus, Who commanded you to build
this house, and to make vp these walles?</ab>
<ab n="10">We asked their
names also, to certifie thee, that we might write the names of the
men that were the chiefe of them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And thus they
returned vs answere, saying, We are the seruants of the God of
heauen and earth, and build the house that was builded these many
yeeres agoe, which a great King of Israel builded, and set
vp.<note> 1.King. 6.1.</note></ab>

<fw>Tatnais letter to Darius,
answered.</fw>
<ab n="12">But after that
our fathers had prouoked the God of heauen vnto wrath: he gaue them
into the hande of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, the Caldean,
who destroyed this house, and caried the people away into
Babylon.<note> 2.Kings 24.2. and 25.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But in the
first yere of Cyrus the king of Babylon, the same king Cyrus made a
decree to build this house of God.<note> Ezra.1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the
vessels also of golde and siluer of the house of God, which
Nebuchadnezzar tooke out of the Temple that was in Ierusalem, and
brought them into the temple of Babylon, those did Cyrus the king
take out of the temple of Babylon, and they were deliuered vnto
one, whose name was Sheshbazzar, whome he had made
gouernour:<note> Ezra 1.18 and 6.5. , Or, deputy</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And said vnto
him, Take these vessels, goe, carie them into the temple that is in
Ierusalem, and let the house of God be builded in his
place.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then came the
same Sheshbazzar, and laid the foundation of the house of God,
which is in Ierusalem. And since that time, euen vntill now, hath
it bin in building, &amp; yet it is not finished.</ab>
<ab n="17">Now therefore,
if it seeme good to the king, let there be search made in the kings
treasure house which is there at Babylon, whether it be so that a
decree was made of Cyrus the king, to build this house of God at
Ierusalem: and let the king send his pleasure to vs concerning this
matter.</ab>



</div>