<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The Altar is set vp. 4 Offerings
frequented. 7 Workmen prepared. 8 The foundations of the Temple are
laid in great ioy &amp; mourning.</head>

<ab n="1">And when the
seuenth moneth was come, and the children of Israel were in the
cities: the people gathered themselues together, as one man to
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then stood vp
Ieshua the sonne of Iozadak, &amp; his brethren the priests, and
Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel, and his brethren, and builded
the Altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt offrings thereon, as
it is written in the law of Moses the man of God.<note> Or, Iosua. Hagge 1.1. , Matth.1. 12. and luke 3.27. called Zorobabel. , Matth.1. 12. and luke 3.27. called Salathiel. , Deut.12.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And they set
the altar vpon his bases, (for feare was vpon them, because of the
people of those countreys) and they offered burnt offerings thereon
vnto the Lord, euen burnt offerings, morning and euening.</ab>
<ab n="4">They kept also
the feast of tabernacles, as it is written, and offred the dayly
burnt offrings, by number, according to the custome, as the duetie
of euery day required:<note> Num. 29. 12. , Exod. 23. 16. , Hebr. the matter of the day in his day.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And afterward
offered the continuall burnt offering, both of the new moones, and
of all the set feasts of the Lord, that were consecrated, and of
euery one that willingly offred, offered a free will offering vnto
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">From the first
day of the seuenth moneth, began they to offer burnt offerings vnto
the Lord: but the foundation of the temple of the Lord was not yet
laid.<note> Hebr. the Temple of the Lord was not yet founded.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">They gaue money
also vnto the masons, and to the carpenters, and meate, and drinke,
and oyle, vnto them of Zidon, and to them of Tyre, to bring Cedar
trees from Lebanon to the sea of Ioppa: according to the grant that
they had of Cyrus king of Persia.<note> Or, workemen. , Acts 9.3.</note></ab>

<fw>The building of the Temple,
hindered.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ Now in
the second yere of their coming vnto the house of God at Ierusalem,
in the second moneth, began Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel, and
Ieshua the sonne of Iozadak, and the remnant of their brethren, the
Priests and the Leuites, and all they that were come out of the
captiuitie vnto Ierusalem: and appointed the Leuites, from twentie
yeeres olde and vpward, to set forward the worke of the house of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then stood
Ieshua, with his sons and his brethren, Kadmiel and his sonnes, the
sonnes of Iudah together, to set forward the workemen in the house
of God: the sonnes of Henadad, with their sonnes and their brethren
the Leuites.<note> Or, Hodauiah, Chap. 2.40. , Heb. as one.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And when the
builders laide the foundation of the Temple of the Lord, they set
the Priests in their apparell with Trumpets, and the Leuites the
sonnes of Asaph, with Cymbales, to praise the Lord, after the
ordinance of Dauid king of Israel.<note> 1.Chro.6. 31. and cha. 16.7. and 25, 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And they sung
together by course, in praising, and giuing thanks vnto the Lord;
Because hee is good, for his mercy endureth for euer towards
Israel. And all the people shouted with a great shoute, when they
praised the Lord; because the foundation of the house of the Lord
was laide.</ab>
<ab n="12">But many of
the Priests and Leuites, and chiefe of the fathers, who were
ancient men, that had seene the first house; when the foundation of
this house was laide before their eyes, wept with a loude voice,
and many shouted aloude for ioy:</ab>
<ab n="13">So that the
people could not discerne the noyse of the shout of ioy, from the
noyse of the weeping of the people: for the people shouted with a
loude shout, and the noyse was heard afarre off.</ab>



</div>