<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CEzra_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The Proclamation of Cyrus for the
building of the Temple. 5 The people prouide for the returne. 7
Cyrus restoreth the vessels of the Temple to
Sheshbazzar.</head>

<ab n="1">Now in the
first yeere of Cyrus King of Persia, (that the word of the Lord by
the mouth of Ieremiah, might be fulfilled) þe Lord
stirred vp the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, that he made a
proclamation throughout all his kingdome, and put it also in
writing, saying;<note> 2.Chron. 36.22. iere. 25.12. and 29.10. , Heb. caused a voice to passe.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thus sayth
Cyrus king of Persia, The Lord God of heauen hath giuen mee all the
kingdomes of the earth, and he hath charged me to build him an
house at Ierusalem, which is in Iudah.<note> Isa.44.28. &amp; 45.1, 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Who is there
among you of all his people? his God be with him, and let him goe
vp to Ierusalem, which is in Iudah, and build the house of the Lord
God of Israel (He is the God) which is in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="4">And whosoeuer
remaineth in any place where hee soiourneth, let the men of his
place helpe him with siluer, and with golde, and with goods, and
with beasts, besides the free-will offering for the house of God
that is in Ierusalem.<note> Heb. lift him vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then
rose vp the chiefe of the fathers of Iudah and Beniamin, and the
Priests, and the Leuites, with all them whose spirit God had raised
to goe vp, to build the house of the Lord which is in
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="6">And all they
that were about them, strengthened their hands with vessels of
siluer, with golde, with goods, and with beasts, and with precious
things; besides all that was willingly offered.<note> That is, helped them.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels returne from Babylon.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ Also
Cyrus the king brought foorth the vessels of the house of the Lord,
which Nebuchadnezzar had brought foorth out of Ierusalem, and had
put them in the house of his gods:<note> 2.Kings 24.13. 2.chr.36.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Euen those did
Cyrus king of Persia bring foorth, by the hand of Mithredath the
treasurer, and numbred them vnto Sheshbazzar the Prince of
Iudah.<note> See Chap. 5.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And this is the
number of them: thirtie chargers of golde, a thousand chargers of
siluer, nine and twentie kniues:</ab>
<ab n="10">Thirtie basins
of golde: siluer basins of a second sort, foure hundred and ten:
and other vessels a thousand.</ab>
<ab n="11">All the
vessels of golde and of siluer, were fiue thousand and foure
hundred. All these did Sheshbazzar bring vp with them of the
captiuitie, that were brought vp from Babylon vnto
Ierusalem.<note> Hebr. the transportation.</note></ab>



</div>