<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGalatians_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-6-6-Ephesians.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 He moueth them to deale mildly
with a brother that hath slipped, 2 and to beare one anothers
burden. 6 To bee liberall to their teachers, 9 and not wearie of
well doing. 12 He sheweth what they intend that preach
circumcision. 14 He glorieth in nothing, saue in the Crosse of
Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">Brethren, if a
man bee ouertaken in a fault: yee which are spirituall, restore
such a one in the spirit of meeknesse, considering thy selfe least
thou also be tempted.<note> Or, although.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Beare ye one
anothers burthens, and so fulfill the Law of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="3">For if a man
thinke himselfe to be something, when he is nothing, hee deceiueth
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="4">But let euery
man prooue his owne worke, and then shall he haue reioycing in him
selfe alone, and not in an other.</ab>
<ab n="5">For euery man
shall beare his owne burthen.</ab>
<ab n="6">Let him that is
taught in the word, communicate vnto him that teacheth, in all good
things.</ab>
<ab n="7">Be not deceiued,
God is not mocked: for whatsoeuer a man soweth, that shall he also
reape.</ab>
<ab n="8">For hee that
soweth to his flesh, shall of the flesh reape corruption: but he
that soweth to the spirit, shall of the spirit reape life
euerlasting.</ab>
<ab n="9">And let vs not
bee weary in well doing: for in due season we shall reape, if we
faint not.</ab>
<ab n="10">As we haue
therefore opportunitie, let vs doe good vnto all men, especially
vnto them who are of the household of faith.</ab>

<fw>The election of the Saints.</fw>
<ab n="11">Ye see how
large a letter I haue written vnto you with mine owne hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">As many as
desire to make a faire shew in the flesh, they constraine you to be
Circumcised: onely least they should suffer persecution for the
Crosse of Christ.</ab>
<ab n="13">For neither
they themselues who are circumcised, keepe the Law, but desire to
haue you circumcised, that they may glory in your flesh.</ab>

<fw>The election of the Saints.</fw>
<ab n="14">But God forbid
that I should glory, saue in the Crosse of our Lord Iesus Christ,
by whom the world is crucified vnto me, &amp; I vnto the
world.<note> Or, whereby.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For in Christ
Iesus neither circumcision auaileth any thing nor vncircumcision,
but a new creature.</ab>
<ab n="16">And as many as
walke according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercie, and
vpon the Israel of God.</ab>
<ab n="17">From henceforth
let no man trouble mee, for I beare in my body the markes of the
Lord Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="18">Brethren, the
grace of our Lord Iesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen. Unto the
Galatians, written from Rome.</ab>



</div>