<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGalatians_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Hee mooueth them to stand in their
libertie, 3 and not to obserue circumcision: 13 but rather loue,
which is the summe of the Law. 19 He reckoneth vp the workes of the
flesh, 22 and the fruits of the spirit, 25 and exhorteth to walke
in the spirit.</head>

<ab n="1">Stand fast
therefore in the libertie wherewith Christ hath made vs free, and
bee not intangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</ab>
<ab n="2">Beholde, I Paul
say vnto you that if ye be circumcised, Christ shal profite you
nothing.</ab>

<fw>Fruites of flesh, and spirit.</fw>
<ab n="3">For I testifie
againe to euery man that is circumcised, that he is a debtor to doe
the whole Law.</ab>
<ab n="4">Christ is become
of no effect vnto you, whosoeuer of you are iustified by the Law:
ye are fallen from grace.</ab>
<ab n="5">For we through
the spirit waite for the hope of righteousnesse by faith.</ab>
<ab n="6">For in Iesus
Christ, neither circumcision auaileth any thing, nor
vncircumcision, but faith which worketh by loue.</ab>
<ab n="7">Ye did run well;
who did hinder you, that ye should not obey the trueth?<note> Or, who did driue you backe?</note></ab>
<ab n="8">This perswasion
commeth not of him that calleth you.</ab>
<ab n="9">A little leauen
leaueneth the whole lumpe.</ab>
<ab n="10">I haue
confidence in you through the Lord, that you will be none otherwise
minded; but he that troubleth you, shall beare his iudgement,
whosoeuer hee be.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I,
brethren, if I yet preach circumcision, why doe I yet suffer
persecution? then is the offence of the crosse ceased.</ab>
<ab n="12">I would they
were euen cut off which trouble you.</ab>
<ab n="13">For brethren,
ye haue beene called vnto liberty, onely vse not libertie for an
occasion to the flesh, but by loue serue one another.</ab>
<ab n="14">For all the Law
is fulfilled in one word, euen in this: Thou shalt loue thy
neighbour as thy selfe.<note> Leu.19.18 mat.22.39.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But if yee bite
and deuoure one another, take heed ye be not consumed one of
another.</ab>
<ab n="16">This I say
then, Walke in the spirit, and ye shall not fulfill the lust of the
flesh.<note> Or, fulfill not.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For the flesh
lusteth against the Spirit, and the spirit against the flesh: and
these are contrary the one to the other: so that yee cannot doe the
things that yee would.</ab>
<ab n="18">But if yee be
lead of the spirit, yee are not vnder the Law.</ab>
<ab n="19">Nowe the workes
of the flesh are manifest, which are these, adulterie, fornication,
vncleannesse, lasciuiousnesse,</ab>
<ab n="20">Idolatrie,
witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, strife, seditions,
heresies,</ab>

<fw>Fruites of flesh, and spirit.</fw>
<ab n="21">Enuyings,
murthers, drunkennesse, reuellings, and such like: of the which I
tell you before, as I haue also tolde you in time past, that they
which do such things shall not inherite the kingdome of
God.</ab>
<ab n="22">But the fruit
of the spirit is loue, ioy, peace, long suffering, gentlenesse,
goodnesse, faith,</ab>
<ab n="23">Meekenesse,
temperance: against such there is no law.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they that
are Christs, haue crucified the flesh with the affections and
lustes.<note> Or, passions</note></ab>
<ab n="25">If we liue in
the Spirit, let vs also walke in the Spirit.</ab>
<ab n="26">Let vs not be
desirous of vaine glory, prouoking one another, enuying one
another.</ab>



</div>