<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGalatians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 He asketh what moued them to leaue
the faith, and hang vpon the Law? 6 They that beleeue are
iustified, 9 &amp; blessed with Abraham. 10 And this he sheweth by
many reasons.</head>

<ab n="1">O foolish
Galatians, who hath bewitched you, that you should not obey the
trueth, before whose eyes Iesus Christ hath been euidently set
forth, crucified among you?</ab>
<ab n="2">This onely would
I learne of you, receiued ye the spirit, by the works of the Law,
or by the hearing of faith?</ab>
<ab n="3">Are ye so
foolish? hauing begun in the Spirit, are ye now made perfect by the
flesh?</ab>
<ab n="4">Haue ye suffered
so many things in vaine? if it be yet in vaine.<note> Or, so great</note></ab>
<ab n="5">He therfore that
ministreth to you the Spirit, and worketh miracles among you, doeth
he it by the workes of the Law, or by the hearing of faith?</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen as Abraham
beleeued God, and it was accounted to him for
righteousnesse.<note> Or, imputed.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Knowe yee
therefore, that they which are of faith, the same are the children
of Abraham.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the
Scripture foreseeing that God would iustifie the heathen through
faith, preached before the Gospel vnto Abraham, saying, In thee
shall all nations be blessed.<note> Cen.12.3</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So then, they
which bee of faith, are blessed with faithfull Abraham.</ab>
<ab n="10">For as many as
are of the works of the lawe, are vnder the curse: for it is
written, Cursed is euery one that continueth not in all things
which are written in the booke of the Law to doe them.<note> Deu.27. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But that no man
is iustified by the Lawe in the sight of God, it is euident: for,
The iust shall liue by faith.<note> Abac.2.4. rom.1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Law is
not of faith: but the man that doeth them, shall liue in
them.<note> Leui.18.5</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Christ hath
redeemed vs from the curse of the Law, being made a curse for vs:
for it is written, Cursed is euery one that hangeth on
tree:<note> Deut.21. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">That the
blessing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles, through Iesus
Christ: that wee might receiue the promise of the Spirit through
faith.</ab>

<fw>The seed of Abraham.</fw>
<ab n="15">Brethren, I
speake after the maner of men: though it be but a mans couenant,
yet if it bee confirmed, no man disanulleth, or addeth
thereto.<note> Or, testament.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Now to Abraham
and his seede were the promises made. He saith not, And to seeds,
as of many, but as of one, And to thy seed, which is
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="17">And this I say,
that the Couenant that was confirmed before of God in Christ, the
Lawe which was foure hundred and thirtie yeres after, cannot
disanul, that it should make the promise of none effect.</ab>
<ab n="18">For if the
inheritance bee of the Law, it is no more of promise: but God gaue
it to Abraham by promise.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherefore then
serueth the Law? it was added because of transgressions, till the
seed should come, to whome the promise was made, and it was
ordeyned by Angels in the hand of a Mediatour.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now a mediatour
is not a Mediatour of one, but God is one.</ab>
<ab n="21">Is the Lawe
then against the promises of God? God forbid: for if there had
beene a Lawe giuen which could haue giuen life, verily
righteousnesse should haue bene by the Law.</ab>
<ab n="22">But the
Scripture hath concluded all vnder sinne, that the promise by faith
of Iesus Christ might be giuen to them that beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="23">But before
faith came, wee were kept vnder the Law, shut vp vnto the faith,
which should afterwards bee reuealed.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore the
Law was our Schoolemaster to bring vs vnto Christ, that we might be
iustified by Faith.</ab>
<ab n="25">But after that
Faith is come, we are no longer vnder a Schoolemaster.</ab>
<ab n="26">For ye are all
the children of God by faith in Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="27">For as many of
you as haue bene baptized into Christ, haue put on Christ.</ab>
<ab n="28">There is
neither Iewe, nor Greeke, there is neither bond nor free, there is
neither male nor female: for ye are all one in Christ
Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="29">And if yee be
Christs, then are ye Abrahams seed, and heires according to the
promise.</ab>



</div>