<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGalatians_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Galatians-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 We were vnder the Law till Christ
came, as the heire is vnder his gardian till he be of age. 5 But
Christ freed vs from the Law: 7 therefore we are seruants no longer
to it. 14 He remembreth their good will to him, and his to them, 22
and sheweth that wee are the sonnes of Abraham by the free
woman.</head>


<fw>Beggerly rudiments.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now I say, that
the heire, as long as hee is a child, differeth nothing from a
seruant, though hee bee Lord of all,</ab>
<ab n="2">But is vnder
tutors and gouernours vntill the time appointed of the
father.</ab>
<ab n="3">Euen so we, when
wee were children, were in bondage vnder the Elements of the
world:<note> Or, rudiments.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But when the
fulnes of the time was come, God sent foorth his Sonne made of a
woman, made vnder the Law,</ab>
<ab n="5">To redeeme them
that were vnder the Law, that we might receiue the adoption of
sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="6">And because yee
are sonnes, God hath sent foorth the spirit of his Sonne into your
hearts, crying Abba, Father.</ab>
<ab n="7">Wherefore thou
art no more a seruant, but a sonne; and if a sonne, then an heire
of God through Christ.</ab>
<ab n="8">Howbeit, then
when ye knew not God, yee did seruice vnto them which by nature are
no Gods.</ab>
<ab n="9">But now after
that yee haue knowen God, or rather are knowen of God, how turne ye
againe to the weak and beggerly Elements, whereunto ye desire
againe to be in bondage?<note> Or, backe. , Or, rudiments.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yee obserue
dayes, and moneths, and times, and yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="11">I am afraide of
you, lest I haue bestowed vpon you labour in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="12">Brethren, I
beseech you, be as I am; for I am as ye are, ye haue not iniured me
at all.</ab>
<ab n="13">Ye know how
through infirmitie of the flesh, I preached the Gospel vnto you at
the first.</ab>
<ab n="14">And my
temptation which was in my flesh ye despised not, nor reiected, but
receiued mee as an Angel of God, euen as Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="15">Where is then
the blessednes you spake of? for I beare you record, that if it had
bin possible, ye would haue plucked out your own eyes, and haue
giuen them to me.<note> Or, what was then?</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Am I therefore
become your enemie, because I tell you the trueth?</ab>
<ab n="17">They zelously
affect you, but not well: yea, they would exclude you, that you
might affect them.<note> Or, vs.</note></ab>

<fw>Free and bond.</fw>
<ab n="18">But it is good
to bee zealously affected alwayes in a good thing, and not onely
when I am present with you.</ab>
<ab n="19">My litle
children, of whom I trauaile in birth againe, vntill Christ bee
formed in you:</ab>
<ab n="20">I desire to bee
present with you now, and to change my voyce, for I stand in doubt
of you.<note> Or, I am perplexed for you.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Tell me, ye
that desire to be vnder the Law, doe ye not heare the Law?</ab>
<ab n="22">For it is
written, that Abraham had two sonnes, the one by a bondmaid, the
other by a freewoman.</ab>
<ab n="23">But he who was
of the bondwoman, was borne after the flesh: but hee of the
freewoman, was by promise.</ab>
<ab n="24">Which things
are an Allegorie; for these are the two Couenants; the one from the
mount Sinai, which gendereth to bondage, which is Agar.<note> Or, testaments.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For this Agar
is mount Sinai in Arabia, and answereth to Ierusalem, which now is,
and is in bondage with her children.<note> Or, is in the same ranke with.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But Ierusalem
which is aboue is free, which is the mother of vs all.</ab>
<ab n="27">For it is
written, Reioyce thou barren that bearest not, breake foorth and
cry thou that traueilest not; for the desolate hath many moe
children then she which hath an husband.<note> Esay 54.1</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Now wee,
brethren, as Isaac was, are the children of promise.</ab>
<ab n="29">But as then hee
that was borne after the flesh, persecuted him that was borne after
the Spirit, euen so it is now.</ab>
<ab n="30">Neuerthelesse,
what saith the Scripture? Cast out the bondwoman and her sonne: for
the son of the bondwoman shall not bee heire with the son of the
freewoman.<note> Gen.21. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">So then,
brethren, we are not children of the bondwoman, but of the
free.</ab>



</div>