<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGenesis_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-31-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 Iacob vpon displeasure departeth
secretly. 19 Rachel stealeth her fathers images. 22 Laban pursueth
after him, 26 and complaineth of the wrong. 34 Rachels policie to
hide the images. 36 Iacobs complaint of Laban. 43 The couenant of
Laban and Iacob at Galeed.</head>

<ab n="1">And he heard the
words of Labans sonnes, saying, Iacob hath taken away all that was
our fathers; and of that which was of our fathers, hath hee gotten
all this glory.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Iacob behelde
the countenance of Laban, and behold, it was not toward him as
before.<note> Hebr. as yesterday and the day before.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the LORD said
vnto Iacob, Returne vnto the land of thy fathers, and to thy
kindred; and I wil be with thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iacob sent
and called Rachel and Leah, to the field vnto his flocke,</ab>
<ab n="5">And said vnto
them, I see your fathers countenance, that it is not toward mee as
before: but the God of my father hath bene with me.</ab>
<ab n="6">And yee know,
that with all my power I haue serued your father.</ab>
<ab n="7">And your father
hath deceiued mee, and changed my wages ten times: but God suffered
him not to hurt me.</ab>
<ab n="8">If hee said thus,
The speckled shall be thy wages, then all the cattell bare
speckled: and if he said thus, The ring-straked shalbe thy hire,
then bare all the cattell ring-straked.</ab>
<ab n="9">Thus God hath
taken away the cattell of your father, and giuen them to
mee.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe at the time that the cattell conceiued, that I lifted vp mine
eyes and saw in a dreame, and behold, the rammes which leaped vpon
the cattell were ring-straked, speckled and grisled.<note> Or, hee goates.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the Angel of
God spake vnto me in a dreame, saying, Iacob; And I said, Here am
I.</ab>

<fw>Iacob fleeing, is pursued by
Laban.</fw>
<ab n="12">And hee said,
Lift vp now thine eyes, and see, all the rammes which leape vpon
the cattell are ring-straked, speckled and grisled: for I haue
seene all that Laban doeth vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">I am the God of
Bethel, where thou annoyntedst the pillar, and where thou vowedst a
vow vnto mee: now arise, get thee out from this land, and returne
vnto the land of thy kindred.<note> Chap. 28. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Rachel and
Leah answered, and said vnto him; Is there yet any portion or
inheritance for vs in our fathers house?</ab>
<ab n="15">Are we not
counted of him strangers? for he hath sold vs, and hath quite
deuoured also our money.</ab>
<ab n="16">For all the
riches which God hath taken from our father, that is ours, and our
childrens: now then whatsoeuer God hath said vnto thee,
doe.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Then
Iacob rose vp, and set his sonnes and his wiues vpon
camels.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he caried
away all his cattell, and all his goods which he had gotten, the
cattell of his getting, which hee had gotten in Padan Aram, for to
goe to Isaac his father in the land of Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Laban went
to sheare his sheepe: and Rachel had stollen the Images that were
her fathers.<note> Hebr. Teraphim.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Iacob stale
away vnawares to Laban the Syrian, in that he told him not that he
fled.<note> Hebr. the heart of Laban.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">So hee fled with
all that hee had, and he rose vp and passed ouer the Riuer, and set
his face toward the mount Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="22">And it was tolde
Laban on the third day, that Iacob was fled.</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee tooke
his brethren with him, and pursued after him seuen dayes iourney,
and they ouertooke him in the mount Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="24">And God came to
Laban the Syrian in a dreame by night, and saide vnto him, Take
heed that thou speake not to Iacob either good or bad.<note> Hebr. from good to bad.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Then
Laban ouertooke Iacob. Now Iacob had pitched his tent in the mount:
and Laban with his brethren pitched in the mount of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Laban said
to Iacob, What hast thou done, that thou hast stollen away vnawares
to me, and caried away my daughters, as captiues taken with the
sword?</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore didst
thou flie away secretly, and steale away from me, and didst not
tell mee? that I might haue sent thee away with mirth, and with
songs, with tabret, and with harpe,<note> Hebr. hast stollen me.</note></ab>

<fw>Iacob fleeing, is pursued by
Laban.</fw>
<ab n="28">And hast not
suffered me to kisse my sonnes and my daughters? thou hast now done
foolishly in so doing.</ab>
<ab n="29">It is in the
power of my hand to doe you hurt: but the God of your father spake
vnto mee yesternight, saying, Take thou heed, that thou speake not
to Iacob either good or bad.</ab>
<ab n="30">And now though
thou wouldest needes bee gone, because thou sore longedst after thy
fathers house; yet wherefore hast thou stollen my gods?</ab>
<ab n="31">And Iacob
answered and said to Laban, Because I was afraid: for I said,
Peraduenture thou wouldest take by force thy daughters from
me.</ab>
<ab n="32">With whomsoeuer
thou findest thy gods, let him not liue: before our brethren
discerne thou what is thine with me, and take it to thee: for Iacob
knew not that Rachel had stollen them.</ab>
<ab n="33">And Laban went
into Iacobs tent, and into Leahs tent, and into the two maid
seruants tents: but he found them not. Then went he out of Leahs
tent, and entred into Rachels tent.</ab>
<ab n="34">Now Rachel had
taken the images, and put them in the camels furniture, and sate
vpon them: and Laban searched all the tent, but found them
not.<note> Hebr. felt.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And shee said to
her father, Let it not displease my lord, that I cannot rise vp
before thee; for the custome of women is vpon mee: and he searched,
but found not the images.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And Iacob
was wroth, and chode with Laban: and Iacob answered and said to
Laban, what is my trespasse? what is my sinne, that thou hast so
hotly pursued after me?</ab>
<ab n="37">Whereas thou
hast searched all my stuffe, what hast thou found of all thy
houshold stuffe? set it here before my brethren, and thy brethren,
that they may iudge betwixt vs both.<note> Hebr. felt.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">This twentie
yeeres haue I bene with thee: thy ewes and thy shee goates haue not
cast their yong, and the rammes of thy flocke haue I not
eaten.</ab>
<ab n="39">That which was
torne of beasts, I brought not vnto thee: I bare the losse of it;
of my hand didst thou require it, whether stollen by day, or
stollen by night.<note> Exod.22. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Thus I was in
þ<note/> day, the drought consumed mee, and the frost by
night, aud my sleep departed from mine eyes.</ab>

<fw>Their couenant.</fw>
<ab n="41">Thus have I bene
twentie yeres in thy house: I serued thee fourteene yeeres for thy
two daughters, and sixe yeres for thy cattel; and thou hast changed
my wages ten times.</ab>
<ab n="42">Except the God
of my father, the God of Abraham, and the feare of Isaac had bin
with me, surely thou hadst sent me away now emptie: God hath seene
mine affliction, and the labour of my hands, &amp; rebuked thee
yesternight.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ And Laban
answered and said vnto Iacob, These daughters are my daughters, and
these children are my children, and these cattell are my cattell,
and all that thou seest, is mine: and what can I doe this day vnto
these my daughters, or vnto their children which they haue
borne?</ab>
<ab n="44">Now therefore
come thou, let vs make a couenant, I and thou: and let it be for a
witnesse betweene me and thee.</ab>
<ab n="45">And Iacob tooke
a stone, and set it vp for a pillar.</ab>
<ab n="46">And Iacob saide
vnto his brethren, Gather stones: and they tooke stones, and made
an heape, and they did eate there vpon the heape.</ab>
<ab n="47">And Laban called
it Iegar-Sahadutha: but Iacob called it Galeed.<note> That is, The heape of witnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And Laban said,
This heape is a witnesse betweene mee and thee this day. Therefore
was the name of it called Galeed,</ab>
<ab n="49">And Mizpah: for
he said, The LORD watch betweene me and thee when we are absent one
from another.<note> That is, A beacon: or, watch tower.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">If thou shalt
afflict my daughters, or if thou shalt take other wiues beside my
daughters, no man is with vs; See, God is witnesse betwixt mee and
thee.</ab>
<ab n="51">And Laban said
to Iacob, Behold this heape, and behold this pillar, which I haue
cast betwixt me and thee.</ab>
<ab n="52">This heape be
witnesse, and this pillar be witnesse, that I will not passe ouer
this heape to thee, and that thou shalt not passe ouer this heape,
and this pillar vnto me, for harme.</ab>
<ab n="53">The God of
Abraham, and the God of Nahor, the God of their father, iudge
betwixt vs. And Iacob sware by the feare of his father
Isaac.</ab>

<fw>Iacobs prayer.</fw>
<ab n="54">Then Iacob
offred sacrifice vpon the mount, and called his brethren to eate
bread, and they did eate bread, and taried all night in the
mount.<note> Or, killed beasts.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And earely in
the morning, Laban rose vp and kissed his sonnes, and his
daughters, and blessed them: and Laban departed, and returned vnto
his place.</ab>



</div>