<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGenesis_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-26-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 Isaac because of famine went to
Gerar. 2 God instructeth, and blesseth him. 7 Hee is reproued by
Abimelech for denying his wife. 12 He groweth rich. 18 He diggeth
Esek, Sitnah, and Rehoboth. 23 Abimelech maketh a couenant with him
at Beersheba. 34 Esaus wiues.</head>

<ab n="1">And there was a
famine in the land, besides the first famine that was in the dayes
of Abraham. And Isaac went vnto Abimelech King of the Philistims,
vnto Gerar.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the LORD
appeared vnto him and said, Goe not downe into Egypt; dwell in the
land which I shall tell thee of.</ab>
<ab n="3">Soiourne in this
land, and I wil be with thee, and will blesse thee: for vnto thee,
and vnto thy seed I will giue all these countreys, and I wil
performe the othe, which I sware vnto Abraham thy
father.<note> Chap.13. 15. and 15. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I wil make
thy seed to multiply as the starres of heauen, and will giue vnto
thy seed all these countreys: and in thy Seed shall all the nations
of the earth be blessed:<note> Chap.12. 3. and 15. 18. and 22. 18.</note></ab>

<fw>Isaac soiourneth at Beer-sheba.</fw>
<ab n="5">Because that
Abraham obeyed my voyce, and kept my charge, my Commandements, my
Statutes and my Lawes.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Isaac
dwelt in Gerar.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the men of
the place asked him of his wife: and he said, She is my sister: for
he feared to say, She is my wife; lest, said he, the men of the
place should kill me for Rebekah, because shee was faire to looke
vpon.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came to
passe when he had bene there a long time, that Abimelech king of
the Philistims looked out at a window, and saw, and behold, Isaac
was sporting with Rebekah his wife.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Abimelech
called Isaac and said, Behold, of a suretie she is thy wife: and
how saidst thou, She is my sister? And Isaac said vnto him, Because
I said, Lest I die for her.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Abimelech
said, What is this thou hast done vnto vs? one of the people might
lightly haue lien with thy wife, and thou shouldest haue brought
guiltinesse vpon vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Abimelech
charged all his people, saying, Hee that toucheth this man or his
wife, shall surely bee put to death.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then Isaac sowed
in that land, and receiued in the same yeere an hundred fold: &amp;
the LORD blessed him.<note> Heb. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the man
waxed great, and went forward, and grew vntill he became very
great.<note> Heb. went going.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For he had
possession of flocks, and possession of heards, and great store of
seruants, and the Philistims enuied him.<note> Or, husbandry.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For all the wels
which his fathers seruants had digged in the dayes of Abraham his
father, the Philistims had stopped them, &amp; filled them with
earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Abimelech
said vnto Isaac, Goe from vs: for thou art much mightier then
we.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And Isaac
departed thence, and pitched his tent in the valley of Gerar, and
dwelt there.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Isaac digged
againe the wels of water, which they had digged in the dayes of
Abraham his father: for the Philistims had stopped them after the
death of Abraham, and he called their names after the names by
which his father had called them.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Isaacs
seruants digged in the valley, and found there a well of springing
water.<note> Heb. liuing</note></ab>

<fw>Isaac soiourneth at Beer-sheba.</fw>
<ab n="20">And the heardmen
of Gerar did striue with Isaacs heardmen, saying, The water is
ours; and hee called the name of the well, Esek, because they
stroue with him.<note> That is, Contention.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And they digged
another well, and stroue for that also: and hee called the name of
it, Sitnah.<note> That is, Hatred.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And he remoued
from thence, and digged another well, and for that they stroue not:
and he called the name of it Rehoboth: and he said, For now the
LORD hath made roome for vs, and we shall be fruitfull in the
land.<note> That is, roome.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And he went vp
from thence to Beer-sheba.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the LORD
appeared vnto him the same night, and saide, I am the God of
Abraham thy father: feare not, for I am with thee, and will blesse
thee, and multiply thy seede, for my seruant Abrahams sake.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he builded
an altar there, and called vpon the name of the LORD, and pitched
his tent there: and there Isaacs seruants digged a well.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Then
Abimelech went to him from Gerar, and Ahuzzath one of his friends,
and Phichol the chiefe captaine of his armie.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Isaac saide
vnto them, Wherefore come ye to me, seeing ye hate me, and haue
sent me away from you?</ab>
<ab n="28">And they said,
we saw certainly that the LORD was with thee: and wee said, Let
there be now an othe betwixt vs, euen betwixt vs and thee, and let
vs make a couenant with thee,<note> Heb. seeing we saw.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">That thou wilt
doe vs no hurt, as we haue not touched thee, and as we haue done
vnto thee nothing but good, and haue sent thee away in peace: thou
art now the blessed of the LORD.<note> Heb. if thou shalt &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And he made them
a feast, and they did eate and drinke.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they rose vp
betimes in the morning, and sware one to another: and Isaac sent
them away, and they departed from him in peace.</ab>
<ab n="32">And it came to
passe the same day, that Isaacs seruants came, and tolde him
concerning the well which they had digged, and said vnto him, we
haue found water.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he called it
Shebah: therefore the name of the citie is Beer-sheba vnto this
day.<note> That is, an oath. , That is, the well of the oath.</note></ab>

<fw>Esau hunting, Iacob is blessed.</fw>
<ab n="34">¶ And Esau
was forty yeeres old, when he tooke to wife Iudith, the daughter of
Beeri the Hittite, and Bashemath the daughter of Elon the
Hittite:</ab>
<ab n="35">Which were a
griefe of minde vnto Isaac and to Rebekah.<note> Chap. 27. 46. , Hebr. bitternesse of spirit.</note></ab>



</div>