<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGenesis_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Isaac sendeth Esau for venison. 5
Rebekah instructeth Iacob to obtaine the blessing. 15 Iacob vnder
the person of Esau obteineth it. 30 Esau bringeth venison. 33 Isaac
trembleth. 34 Esau complaineth, and by importunitie obtaineth a
blessing. 41 He threatneth Iacob. 42 Rebekah disappointeth
it.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe that when Isaac was old, and his eyes were dimme, so that he
could not see, hee called Esau his eldest son, and said vnto him,
My sonne. And hee said vnto him, Behold, here am I.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said,
Behold now, I am old, I know not the day of my death.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now therefore
take, I pray thee, thy weapons, thy quiuer, and thy bow, and goe
out to the field, and take mee some venison.<note> Heb. hunt.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And make me
sauoury meat, such as I loue, and bring it to mee, that I may eate,
that my soule may blesse thee before I die.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Rebekah heard
when Isaac spake to Esau his sonne: and Esau went to the fielde to
hunt for venison, and to bring it.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
Rebekah spake vnto Iacob her sonne, saying, Behold, I heard thy
father speake vnto Esau thy brother, saying,</ab>
<ab n="7">Bring me venison,
and make mee sauoury meat, that I may eate, and blesse thee before
the LORD, before my death.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now therefore, my
sonne, obey my voyce, according to that which I command
thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">Goe now to the
flocke, and fetch me from thence two good kids of the goates, and I
will make them sauoury meat for thy father, such as he
loueth.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
bring it to thy father, that he may eate, and that he may blesse
thee, before his death.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Iacob said
to Rebekah his mother, Behold, Esau my brother is a hairy man, and
I am a smooth man.</ab>
<ab n="12">My father
peraduenture will feele me, and I shall seeme to him as a deceiuer,
and I shall bring a curse vpon me, and not a blessing.</ab>

<fw>Esau hunting, Iacob is blessed.</fw>
<ab n="13">And his mother
said vnto him, Upon me be thy curse, my sonne: onely obey my voice,
and go fetch me them.</ab>
<ab n="14">And hee went,
and fetched, and brought them to his mother, and his mother made
sauoury meat, such as his father loued.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Rebekah
tooke goodly raiment of her eldest sonne Esau, which were with her
in the house, and put them vpon Iacob her yonger sonne:<note> Hebr. desireable.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And shee put the
skinnes of the kids of the goats vpon his hands, and vpon the
smooth of his necke.</ab>
<ab n="17">And she gaue the
sauoury meate, and the bread, which she had prepared, into the hand
of her sonne Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And he
came vnto his father, and said, My father: And he said, Here am I:
who art thou, my sonne?</ab>
<ab n="19">And Iacob said
vnto his father, I am Esau, thy first borne; I haue done according
as thou badest mee: arise, I pray thee, sit, and eate of my
venison, that thy soule may blesse me.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Isaac said
vnto his sonne, How is it that thou hast found it so quickly, my
sonne? And he said, Because the LORD thy God brought it to
me.<note> Hebr. before me.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Isaac saide
vnto Iacob, Come neere, I pray thee, that I may feele thee, my
sonne, whether thou bee my very sonne Esau, or not.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Iacob went
neere vnto Isaac his father: and hee felt him, and said, The voyce
is Iacobs voyce, but the hands are the hands of Esau.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he discerned
him not, because his hands were hairie, as his brother Esaus hands:
So he blessed him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And he said, Art
thou my very sonne Esau? and he said, I am.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he said,
Bring it neere to me, and I will eate of my sonnes venison, that my
soule may blesse thee: and hee brought it neere to him, and he did
eate: and he brought him wine, &amp; he dranke.</ab>
<ab n="26">And his father
Isaac saide vnto him, Come neere now, and kisse me, my
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="27">And hee came
neere, and kissed him: and he smelled the smell of his raiment, and
blessed him, and said, See, the smell of my sonne is as the smell
of a field, which the LORD hath blessed.</ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore God
giue thee of the dew of heauen, and the fatnesse of the earth, and
plenty of corne and wine.<note> Heb.11. 20.</note></ab>

<fw>Esau mourneth.</fw>
<ab n="29">Let people serue
thee, and nations bow downe to thee: bee lord ouer thy brethren,
&amp; let thy mothers sonnes bow downe to thee: Cursed bee euery
one that curseth thee, and blessed be hee that blesseth
thee.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And it
came to passe, as soone as Isaac had made an ende of blessing
Iacob, and Iacob was yet scarce gone out from the presence of Isaac
his father, that Esau his brother came in from his hunting.</ab>
<ab n="31">And hee also had
made sauoury meate, and brought it vnto his father, and said vnto
his father, Let my father arise, and eat of his sonnes venison,
that thy soule may blesse me.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Isaac his
father said vnto him, Who art thou? and he said, I am thy sonne,
thy first borne Esau.</ab>
<ab n="33">And Isaac
trembled very exceedingly, and said, Who? Where is he that hath
taken venison, and brought it me, and I haue eaten of all before
thou camest, and haue blessed him? yea and he shalbe
blessed.<note> Hebr. trembled with a great trembling greatly. , Hebr. hunted.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And when Esau
heard the words of his father, he cried with a great and exceeding
bitter cry, and said vnto his father, Blesse mee, euen me also, O
my father.</ab>
<ab n="35">And hee said,
Thy brother came with subtilty, and hath taken away thy
blessing.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he said, Is
not he rightly naned Iacob? for he hath supplanted me these two
times: hee tooke away my birthright, and behold, now he hath taken
away my blessing: and hee said, Hast thou not reserued a blessing
for mee?<note> That is, A supplanter.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And Isaac
answered and saide vnto Esau, Behold, I haue made him thy lord, and
all his brethren haue I giuen to him for seruants: and with corne
and wine haue I susteined him: and what shall I doe now vnto thee,
my sonne?<note> Or, supported.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And Esau said
vnto his father, Hast thou but one blessing, my father? blesse mee,
euen mee also, O my father. And Esau lift vp his voyce, and
wept.<note> Heb.12. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And Isaac his
father answered, and said vnto him, Behold, thy dwelling shall be
the fatnesse of the earth, and of the dew of heauen from
aboue.<note> Verse 28. , Or, of the fatnesse.</note></ab>

<fw>Iacob is sent away.</fw>
<ab n="40">And by thy sword
shalt thou liue, and shalt serue thy brother: and it shall come to
passe when thou shalt haue the dominion, that thou shalt breake his
yoke from off thy necke.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And Esau
hated Iacob, because of the blessing, wherewith his father blessed
him: and Esau said in his heart, The dayes of mourning for my
father are at hand; then will I slay my brother Iacob.<note> Obad. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And these words
of Esau her elder sonne were told to Rebekah: And shee sent and
called Iacob her yonger sonne, and said vnto him, Behold, thy
brother Esau, as touching thee, doeth comfort himselfe, purposing
to kill thee.</ab>
<ab n="43">Now therefore my
sonne, obey my voice: and arise, flee thou to Laban my brother, to
Haran.</ab>
<ab n="44">And tary with
him a few dayes, vntill thy brothers furie turne away;</ab>
<ab n="45">Untill thy
brothers anger turne away from thee, and hee forget that, which
thou hast done to him: then I will send, and fetch thee from
thence: why should I be depriued also of you both in one
day?</ab>
<ab n="46">And Rebekah said
to Isaac, I am weary of my life, because of the daughters of Heth:
If Iacob take a wife of the daughters of Heth, such as these which
are of the daughters of the land, what good shall my life doe
me?<note> Chap. 26.35.</note></ab>



</div>