<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGenesis_45" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-44-45.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-45-46.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLV.</head>
<head>Ioseph maketh himselfe knowen to his
brethren. 5 Hee comforteth them in Gods prouidence. 9 Hee sendeth
for his father. 16 Pharaoh confirmeth it. 21 Ioseph furnisheth them
for their iourney, and exhorteth them to concord. 25 Iacob is
reuiued with the newes.</head>


<fw>Ioseph is knowen.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then Ioseph could
not refraine himselfe before all them that stood by him: and he
cried, Cause euery man to goe out from me; and there stood no man
with him, while Ioseph made himselfe knowen vnto his
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he wept
aloud: and the Egyptians, and the house of Pharaoh
heard.<note> Hebr. Gaue foorth his voice in weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Ioseph said
vnto his brethren, I am Ioseph; Doeth my father yet liue? and his
brethren could not answere him: for they were troubled at his
presence.<note> A&amp;s. 7. 13. , Or, terrified.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Ioseph said
vnto his brethren, Come neere to me, I pray you: and they came
neere; and he said, I am Ioseph your brother, whom ye sold into
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now therefore bee
not grieued, nor angry with your selues, that yee sold me hither:
for God did send me before you, to preserue life.<note> Hebr. neither let there be anger in your eyes. , Chap. 50. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For these two
yeeres hath the famine bene in the land: and yet there are fiue
yeeres, in the which there shall neither be earing nor
haruest.</ab>
<ab n="7">And God sent me
before you, to preserue you a posteritie in the earth, and to saue
your liues by a great deliuerance.<note> Hebr. to put for you a remnant.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">So now it was not
you that sent me hither, but God: and he hath made me a father to
Pharaoh, and lord of all his house, and a ruler throughout all the
land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="9">Haste you, and
goe vp to my father, and say vnto him, Thus saith thy sonne Ioseph;
God hath made me lord of all Egypt; come downe vnto me, tary
not.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
dwell in the land of Goshen, and thou shalt be neere vnto me, thou,
and thy children, and thy childrens children, and thy flockes, and
thy heards, and all that thou hast.</ab>
<ab n="11">And there wil I
nourish thee, (for yet there are fiue yeeres of famine) lest thou
and thy houshold, and all that thou hast, come to pouertie.</ab>

<fw>Iacob being sent for goeth to
Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="12">And behold, your
eyes see, and the eyes of my brother Beniamin, that it is my mouth
that speaketh vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="13">And you shall
tell my father of all my glory in Egypt, and of all that you haue
seene, and ye shall haste, and bring downe my father
hither.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he fel vpon
his brother Beniamins necke, and wept: and Beniamin wept vpon his
necke.</ab>
<ab n="15">Moreouer hee
kissed all his brethren, and wept vpon them: and after that, his
brethren talked with him.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
fame thereof was heard in Pharaohs house, saying, Iosephs brethren
are come: and it pleased Pharaoh well, and his
seruants.<note> Hebr. was good in the eyes of Pharaoh.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Pharaoh said
vnto Ioseph, Say vnto thy brethren, This doe yee, lade your beasts
and goe, get you vnto the land of Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="18">And take your
father, and your housholds, and come vnto mee: and I wil giue you
the good of the land of Egypt, and ye shall eat the fat of the
land.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now thou art
commanded, this doe yee; Take you wagons out of the land of Egypt
for your little ones, and for your wiues, and bring your father,
and come.</ab>
<ab n="20">Also regard not
your stuffe: for the good of all the land of Egypt is
yours.<note> Hebr. Let not your eye spare, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the children
of Israel did so: and Ioseph gaue them wagons, according to the
commandement of Pharaoh, and gaue them prouision for the
way.<note> Hebr. mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">To all of them
he gaue each man changes of raiment: but to Beniamin hee gaue three
hundred pieces of siluer, and fiue changes of raiment.</ab>
<ab n="23">And to his
father hee sent after this maner: ten asses laden with the good
things of Egypt, and ten shee asses laden with corne, and bread and
meat for his father by the way.<note> Hebr. carrying.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">So he sent his
brethren away, and they departed: and hee said vnto them, See that
yee fall not out by the way.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And they
went vp out of Egypt, and came into the land of Canaan vnto Iacob
their father,</ab>
<ab n="26">And told him,
saying, Ioseph is yet aliue, and he is gouernour ouer all the land
of Egypt. And Iacobs heart fainted, for he beleeued them
not.<note> Hebr. his.</note></ab>

<fw>Iacob being sent for goeth to
Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="27">And they told
him all the words of Ioseph, which hee had saide vnto them: and
when hee saw the wagons which Ioseph had sent to carie him, the
spirit of Iacob their father reuiued.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Israel said,
It is enough; Ioseph my sonne is yet aliue: I will goe and see him
before I die.</ab>



</div>