<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGenesis_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-36-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 Esaus three wiues. 6 His remouing
to mount Seir. 9 His sonnes. 15 The Dukes which descended of his
sonnes. 20 The sonnes and dukes of Seir. 24 Anah findeth mules. 31
The kings of Edom. 40 The dukes that descended of
Esau.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are the
generations of Esau, who is Edom.</ab>
<ab n="2">Esau tooke his
wiues of the daughters of Canaan: Adah the daughter of Elon the
Hittite, and Aholibamah the daughter of Anah the daughter of Zibeon
the Hiuite:</ab>
<ab n="3">And Bashemath
Ishmaels daughter, sister of Nebaioth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Adah bare to
Esau, Eliphaz: and Bashemath bare Reuel.<note> 1. Chron. 1.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Aholibamah
bare Ieush, and Iaalam, and Korah: these are the sonnes of Esau,
which were borne vnto him in the land of Canaan.</ab>

<fw>Esaus offspring.</fw>
<ab n="6">And Esau tooke
his wiues, and his sonnes, and his daughters, and all the persons
of his house, and his cattell, and all his beasts, and all his
substance, which he had got in the lande of Canaan: and went into
the countrey from the face of his brother Iacob.<note> Heb. soules.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For their riches
were more then that they might dwell together: and the land wherein
they were strangers, could not beare them, because of their
cattell.</ab>
<ab n="8">Thus dwelt Esau
in mount Seir: Esau is Edom.<note> Iosh. 24. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And these
are the generations of Esau, the father of the Edomites in mount
Seir.<note> Hebr. Edom.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">These are the
names of Esaus sonnes: Eliphaz the sonne of Adah the wife of Esau,
Reuel the sonne of Bashemath, the wife of Esau.<note> 1.Chro.1. 35. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the sonnes
of Eliphaz were, Teman, Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenaz.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Timna was
concubine to Eliphaz Esaus sonne, and shee bare to Eliphaz Amalek:
these were the sonnes of Adah Esaus wife.</ab>
<ab n="13">And these are
the sonnes of Reuel: Nahath and Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah: these
were the sonnes of Bashemath, Esaus wife.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And these
were the sonnes of Aholibamah, the daughter of Anah, daughter of
Zibeon Esaus wife: and she bare to Esau, Ieush and Iaalam, and
Korah.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ These
were dukes of the sonnes of Esau: the sonnes of Eliphaz the first
borne sonne of Esau, duke Teman, duke Omar, duke Zepho, duke
Kenaz,</ab>
<ab n="16">Duke Korah, duke
Gatam, and duke Amalek: These are the dukes that came of Eliphaz,
in the land of Edom: These were the sonnes of Adah.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And these
are the sonnes of Reuel Esaus sonne: duke Nahath, duke Zerah, duke
Shammah, duke Mizzah. These are the dukes that came of Reuel, in
the land of Edom: these are the sonnes of Bashemath, Esaus
wife.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And these
are the sonnes of Aholibamah Esaus wife: duke Ieush, duke Iaalam,
duke Korah: these were the dukes that came of Aholibamah the
daughter of Anah Esaus wife.</ab>
<ab n="19">These are the
sonnes of Esau, (who is Edom) and these are their dukes.</ab>

<fw>Dukes, and Kings.</fw>
<ab n="20">¶ These are
the sonnes of Seir the Horite, who inhabited the land, Lotan, and
Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah.<note> 1.Chro. 1. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Dishon, and
Ezer, and Dishan: these are the dukes of the Horites the children
of Seir in the lande of Edom.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the children
of Lotan, were Hori, and Hemam: and Lotans sister was
Timna.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the children
of Shobal were these: Aluan, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shepho, and
Onam.</ab>
<ab n="24">And these are
the children of Zibeon, both Aiah, and Anah: this was that Anah
that found the mules in the wildernesse, as he fed the asses of
Zibeon his father.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the children
of Anah were these: Dishon, and Aholibamah the daughter of
Anah.</ab>
<ab n="26">And these are
the children of Dishon: Hemdan and Eshban, &amp; Ithran, and
Cheran.</ab>
<ab n="27">The children of
Ezer are these: Bilhan and Zaauan, and Akan.</ab>
<ab n="28">The children of
Dishan are these: Uz, and Aran.</ab>
<ab n="29">These are the
dukes that came of the Horites: duke Lotan, duke Shobal, duke
Zibeon, duke Anah,</ab>
<ab n="30">Duke Dishon,
duke Ezer, duke Dishan: these are the dukes that came of Hori,
among their dukes in the land of Seir.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And these
are the kings that reigned in the land of Edom, before there
reigned any king ouer the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Bela the
sonne of Beor reigned in Edom: and the name of his citie was
Dinhabah.</ab>
<ab n="33">And Bela died,
and Iobab the sonne of Zerah of Bozra reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="34">And Iobab died,
and Husham of the land of Temani reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="35">And Husham died,
and Hadad the sonne of Bedad, (who smote Midian in the field of
Moab,) reigned in his stead: &amp; the name of his citie was
Auith.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Hadad died,
and Samlah of Masrekah, reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Samlah died,
and Saul of Rehoboth, by the riuer, reigned in his stead.</ab>
<ab n="38">And Saul died,
and Baal-hanan the sonne of Achbor reigned in his stead.</ab>

<fw>Iosephs dreames.</fw>
<ab n="39">And Baal-hanan
the sonne of Achbor died, and Hadar reigned in his stead: and the
name of his citie was Pau, and his wiues name was Mehetabel, the
daughter of Matred, the daughter of Mezahab.</ab>
<ab n="40">And these are
the names of the dukes that came of Esau, according to their
families, after their places, by their names: duke Timnah, duke
Aluah, duke Ietheth,</ab>
<ab n="41">Duke Aholibamah,
duke Elah, duke Pinon,</ab>
<ab n="42">Duke Kenaz, duke
Teman, duke Mibzar,</ab>
<ab n="43">Duke Magdiel,
duke Iram. These be the dukes of Edom, according to their
habitations, in the land of their possession: he is Esau the father
of the Edomites.<note> Heb. Edom</note></ab>



</div>