<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGenesis_49" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-48-49.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-49-50.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIX.</head>
<head>1 Iacob calleth his sonnes to blesse
them. 3 Their blessing in particular. 29 He chargeth them about his
buriall. 33 He dieth.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iacob called
vnto his sonnes, and said, Gather your selues together, that I may
tell you that which shall befall you in the last dayes.</ab>
<ab n="2">Gather your
selues together, and heare ye sonnes of Iacob, and hearken vnto
Israel your father.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Reuben,
thou art my first borne, my might, and the beginning of my
strength, the excellencie of dignitie, and the excellencie of
power:</ab>
<ab n="4">Unstable as
water, thou shalt not excell, because thou wentest vp to thy
fathers bed: then defiledst thou it. He went vp to my
couche.<note> Hebr. doe not thou excell. , Chap. 35. 22. 1. chro. 5.1. , Or, my cowche is gone.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Simeon and
Leui are brethren, instruments of crueltie are in their
habitations.<note> Or, their swords are weapons of violence.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">O my soule, come
not thou into their secret: vnto their assembly mine honour be not
thou vnited: for in their anger they slew a man, and in their selfe
will they digged downe a wall.<note> Or houghed oxen.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Cursed be their
anger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was cruell: I
will diuide them in Iacob, and scatter them in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Iudah,
thou art he whom thy brethren shall praise: thy hand shall be in
the necke of thine enemies, thy fathers children shall bow downe
before thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">Iudah is a Lyons
whelpe: from the pray my sonne thou art gone vp: he stouped downe,
hee couched as a Lyon, and as an old Lyon: who shall rouse him
vp?</ab>

<fw>Iacob blesseth his sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="10">The scepter
shall not depart from Iudah, nor a Law-giuer from betweene his
feete, vntill Shiloh come: and vnto him shall the gathering of the
people be:</ab>
<ab n="11">Binding his
foale vnto the vine, and his asses colt vnto the choice vine; he
washed his garments in wine, and his clothes in the blood of
grapes.</ab>
<ab n="12">His eyes shall
be red with wine, and his teeth white with milke.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Zebulun
shall dwell at the hauen of the sea, and hee shall be for an Hauen
of ships: and his border shall be vnto Zidon.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Issachar
is a strong asse, couching downe betweene two burdens.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he saw that
rest was good, and the land that it was pleasant: and bowed his
shoulder to beare, and became a seruant vnto tribute.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Dan shall
iudge his people, as one of the tribes of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="17">Dan shalbe a
serpent by the way, an adder in the path, that biteth the horse
heeles, so that his rider shall fall backward.<note> Heb. an arrow-snake.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">I haue waited
for thy saluation, O LORD.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Gad, a
troupe shall ouercome him: but he shall ouercome at the
last.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Out of
Asher his bread shall be fat, and he shall yeeld royall
dainties.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Naphtali
is a hinde let loose: He giueth goodly words.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Ioseph is
a fruitfull bough, euen a fruitfull bough by a well, whose branches
runne ouer the wall.<note> Hebr. daughters.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The archers haue
sorely grieued him, and shot at him, and hated him.</ab>
<ab n="24">But his bow
abode in strength, and the armes of his hands were made strong, by
the hands of the mighty God of Iacob: from thence is the
Sheapheard, the stone of Israel,</ab>
<ab n="25">Euen by the God
of thy father who shall helpe thee, and by the Almightie, who shall
blesse thee with blessings of heauen aboue, blessings of the deepe
that lyeth vnder, blessings of the breasts and of the
wombe.</ab>
<ab n="26">The blessings of
thy father haue preuailed aboue the blessings of my progenitors:
vnto the vtmost bound of the euerlasting hils, they shall bee on
the head of Ioseph, and on the crowne of the head of him that was
separate from his brethren.</ab>

<fw>His death.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ Beniamin
shall rauine as a wolfe: In the morning hee shall deuoure the pray,
and at night he shall diuide the spoile.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ All these
are the twelue tribes of Israel, and this is it that their father
spake vnto them, and blessed them: euery one according to his
blessing he blessed them.</ab>
<ab n="29">And hee charged
them and said vnto them, I am to bee gathered vnto my people: burie
me with my fathers, in the caue that is in the field of Ephron the
Hittite,<note> Chap.47. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">In the caue that
is in the field of Machpelah, which is before Mamre, in the land of
Canaan, which Abraham bought with the field of Ephron the Hittite,
for a possession of a burying place.<note> Chap. 23. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">(There they
buried Abraham and Sarah his wife, there they buried Isaac and
Rebekah his wife, and there I buried Leah.)</ab>
<ab n="32">The purchase of
the field and of the caue that is therein, was from the children of
Heth.</ab>
<ab n="33">And when Iacob
had made an end of commanding his sonnes, he gathered vp his feete
into the bed, and yeelded vp the ghost, and was gathered vnto his
people.</ab>




</div>