<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHabakkuk_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Habakkuk-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Habakkuk-Chapter-3-3-Zephaniah.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Habakkuk in his prayer, trembleth
at Gods Maiestie. 17 The confidence of his faith.</head>

<ab n="1">A prayer of
Habakkuk the prophet vpon Sigionoth.<note> Or, according to variable songs or tunes called in hebrew, Shigianoth.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">O Lord, I haue
heard thy speach, and was afraide: O Lord, reuiue thy worke in the
midst of the yeeres, in the midst of the yeeres make knowen; in
wrath remember mercy.<note> Heb. thy report or thy hearing. , Or, preserue aliue.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">God came from
Teman, and the holy on from mount Paran Selah. His glory couered
the heauens and the earth was full of his praise.<note> Or, the South.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And his
brightnesse was as the light: he had hornes comming out of his
hand, and there was the hiding of his power:<note> Or, bright beames out of his side.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Before him went
the pestilence, and burning coales went forth at his
feete.<note> Or, burning diseases.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He stood and
measured the earth: hee beheld and droue asunder the nations, and
the euerlasting mountaines were scattered, the perpetuall hilles
did bowe: his wayes are euerlasting.</ab>
<ab n="7">I saw the tents
of Cushan in affliction: and the curtaines of the land of Midian
did tremble.<note> Or, Ethiopia. , Or, vnder affliction or vanitie.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wrath for diuers sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="8">Was the Lord
displeased against the riuers? was thine anger against the riuers?
was thy wrath against the Sea, that thou didst ride vpon thine
horses, and thy charets of saluation?<note> Or, thy charets were saluation.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thy bow was made
quite naked according to the oathes of the tribes, euen thy word.
Selah. Thou didst cleaue the earth with riuers.<note> Or, thou didst cleaue the riuers of the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The mountaines
sawe thee, and they trembled: the ouerflowing of the water passed
by: the deepe vttered his voyce, and lift vp his hands on
high.</ab>
<ab n="11">The Sunne and
Moone stood still in their habitation: at the light of thine
arrowes they went, and at the shining of thy glittering
speare.<note> Iosh.10. 12. , Or, thine arrowes walked in the light, &amp;c. , Iosh.10. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thou didst march
through the land in indignation, thou didst thresh the heathen in
anger.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou wentest
forth for the saluation of thy people, euen for saluation with
thine Anointed, thou woundedst the head out of the house of the
wicked, by discouering the foundation vnto the necke.
Selah.<note> Heb. making naked.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wrath for diuers sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="14">Thou didst
strike through with his staues the head of his villages: they came
out as a whirle-winde to scatter me: their reioycing was as to
deuoure the poore secretly.<note> Heb. were tempestuous.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thou didst walke
through the Sea with thine horses, through the heape of great
waters.<note> Or, mud.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">When I heard, my
belly trembled: my lips quiuered at the voice: rottennesse entred
into my bones, and I trembled in my selfe, that I might rest in the
day of trouble: when hee commeth vp vnto the people, he wil inuade
them with his troupes.<note> Or, cut them in pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Although
the fig tree shall not blossome, neither shall fruite bee in the
vines: the labour of the Oliue shall faile, and the fields shal
yeeld no meat, the flocke shall be cut off from the folde, and
there shalbe no heard in the stalles:<note> Heb. lie.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Yet I will
reioyce in the Lord: I will ioy in the God of my saluation.</ab>
<ab n="19">The Lord God is
my strength, and he will make my feet like hindes feet, and he will
make me to walke vpon mine high places. To the chiefe singer on my
stringed instruments.<note> 2.Sam. 22.34. psal. 18.34. , Heb. Neginoth.</note></ab>



</div>