<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHabakkuk_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Habakkuk-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Vnto Habakkuk, waiting for an
answere, is shewed that he must waite by faith. 5 The iudgement
vpon the Caldean for vnsatiablenesse, 9 for couetousnesse, 12 for
crueltie, 15 for drunkennesse, 18 and for idolatrie.</head>


<fw>Stones shall crie.</fw>
<ab n="1">I will stand vpon
my watch, &amp; set mee vpon the towre, and will watch to see what
he will say vnto me, and what I shall answere when I am
reproued.<note> Isai.21.8. , Heb. fenced place. , Or, in me. , Or, when I am argued with. Heb. vpon my reproofe or arguing.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
answered me and said, write the vision, and make it plaine vpon
tables, that he may runne that readeth it.</ab>
<ab n="3">For the vision is
yet for an appointed time, but at the the end it shall speak, and
not lie: though it tary, wait for it, because it will surely come,
it wil not tary.<note> Hebr.10. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, his soule
which is lifted vp, is not vpright in him; but the iust shall liue
by his faith.<note> Iohn 3. 36. rom.1. 7. gal.3.11. heb.10.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Yea also,
because he transgresseth by wine, he is a proud man, neither
keepeth at home, who enlargeth his desire as hell, and is as death,
and cannot be satisfied, but gathereth vnto him all nations, &amp;
heapeth vnto him all people:<note> Or, how much more.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Shal not all
these take vp a parable against him, and a tanting prouerbe against
him, and say; Woe to him that increaseth that which is not his: how
long? and to him that ladeth himselfe with thicke clay.<note> Or, hoe, he.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Shall they not
rise vp suddenly that shall bite thee? and awake, that shall vexe
thee? and thou shalt be for booties vnto them?</ab>
<ab n="8">Because thou hast
spoiled many nations, all the remnant of the people shal spoile
thee: because of mens blood, and for the violence of the land, of
the citie, and of all that dwell therein.<note> Heb. bloods.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Woe to him
that coueteth an euill couetousnesse to his house, that he may set
his nest on high, that hee may be deliuered from the power of
euill.<note> Ier.22.13. , Or, gaineth an euill gaine. , Heb. palme of the hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thou hast
consulted shame to thy house, by cutting off many people, and hast
sinned against thy soule.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the stone
shall crie out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber shall
answere it.<note> Or, piece, or, fastening. , Or, witnesse against it.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Woe to
him that buildeth a towne with blood, and stablisheth a citie by
iniquitie.<note> Ezech.24. 9. nahum.3.1. , Heb. bloods.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Behold, is it
not of the Lord of hostes, that the people shall labour in the very
fire, and the people shal wearie themselues for very
vanitie?<note> Or, in vaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the earth
shall be filled with the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the
waters couer the Sea.<note> Or, by knowing the glory of the Lord. , Isai.11.9.</note></ab>

<fw>Woe to idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ Woe vnto
him that giueth his neighbour drinke: that puttest thy bottell to
him, and makest him drunken also; that thou mayest looke on their
nakednesse.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thou art filled
with shame for glory: drinke thou also, and let thy foreskin bee
vncouered: the cup of the Lords right hand shall be turned vnto
thee, and shamefull spewing shalbe on thy glory.<note> Or, more with shame then with glory. , Ier.25.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For the violence
of Lebanon shall couer thee: and the spoile of beasts, which made
them afraide, because of mens blood, and for the violence of the
land, of the city, &amp; of al that dwel therin.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ What
profiteth the grauen image, that the maker thereof hath grauen it;
the molten image, and a teacher of lies, that the maker of his
worke, trusteth therin, to make dumbe idoles.<note> Ier.10.8, 14. zec.10. 2. , Heb. The facioner of his facion.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Woe vnto him
that saith to the wood, Awake: to the dumbe stone, Arise, it shall
teach: behold, it is layed ouer with gold and siluer, and there is
no breath at all in the middest of it.</ab>
<ab n="20">But the Lord is
in his holy temple: let all the earth keepe silence before
him.<note> Psal.11.4. , Heb. be silent all the earth before him.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>