<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHaggai_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Haggai-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Haggai-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 He incourageth the people to the
worke, by promise of greater glory to the second Temple, then was
in the first. 10 In the type, of holy things and vncleane, hee
sheweth their sinnes hindred the worke. 20 Gods promise to
Zerubbabel.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
seuenth moneth, in the one and twentith day of the moneth, came the
word of the Lord by the Prophet Haggai, saying;<note> Heb. by the hand of.</note></ab>

<fw>A glorious house.</fw>
<ab n="2">Speake now to
Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel, gouernour of Iudah, and to
Iosuah the sonne of Iosedech the high priest, and to the residue of
the people, saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Who is left
among you that sawe this house in her first glory? and how do ye
see it now? Is it not in your eyes in comparison of it, as
nothing?</ab>
<ab n="4">Yet now be
strong, O Zerubbabel, saith the Lord, and bee strong, O Ioshua,
sonne of Iosedech the high Priest, and be strong all ye people of
the land, saith the Lord, and worke: (for I am with you, saith the
Lord of hosts,)</ab>
<ab n="5">According to
the word that I couenanted with you, when ye came out of Egypt, so
my Spirit remaineth among you, Feare ye not.</ab>
<ab n="6">For thus
saith the Lord of hosts, Yet once, it is a litle while, and I will
shake the heauens, and the earth, and the sea, and the drie
land.<note> Heb.12. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And I will
shake all nations, and the desire of all nations shall come, and I
will fill this house with glory, saith the Lord of hosts.</ab>
<ab n="8">The siluer is
mine, and the gold is mine, saith the Lord of hosts.</ab>
<ab n="9">The glory of
this latter house shal be greater then of the former, saith the
Lord of hostes: and in this place will I giue peace, saith the Lord
of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ In the
foure and twentieth day of the ninth moneth, in the second yeere of
Darius, came þe word of the Lord by Haggai the
Prophet, saying,</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, Aske now the priests concerning the law,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="12">If one beare holy
flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt doe touch
bread or pottage, or wine, or oile, or any meate, shall it be holy?
and the priests answered and said, No.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then said Haggai,
If one that is vncleane by a dead body, touch any of these, shal it
be vncleane? and the priests answered and said, It shalbe
vncleane.</ab>

<fw>Gods signet.</fw>
<ab n="14">Then answered
Haggai, and said, So is this people, and so is this nation before
me, saith the Lord, and so is euery worke of their hands, and that
which they offer there, is vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="15">And now I pray you
consider from this day and vpward, from before a stone was laid
vpon a stone in the Temple of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="16">Since those dayes
were, when one came to an heape of twentie measures, there were but
ten: when one came to the presse-fatte for to draw out fiftie
vessels out of the presse, there were but twentie.</ab>
<ab n="17">I smote you with
blasting, and with mildew, and with haile in all the labours of
your hands: yet yee turned not to me, saith the Lord.<note> Amos 4.9</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Consider now from
this day, and vpward from the foure and twentieth day of the ninth
moneth, euen from the day that the foundatio of the Lords Temple
was laid, consider it.</ab>
<ab n="19">Is the seed yet in
the barne? yea, as yet the vine and the fig tree, &amp; the
pomegranate, and the Oliue tree hath not brought foorth: from this
day will I blesse you.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And againe
the worde of the Lord came vnto Haggai in the foure and twentieth
day of the moneth, saying,</ab>
<ab n="21">Speake to
Zerubbabel gouernor of Iudah, saying, I wil shake the heauens and
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="22">And I will
ouerthrow the throne of kingdomes, and I will destroy the strength
of the kingdomes of the heathen, and I will ouerthrow the charets,
and those that ride in them, and the horses and their riders shall
come downe, euery one by the sword of his brother.</ab>
<ab n="23">In that day, saith
the Lord of hosts, will I take thee, O Zerubbabel, my seruant, the
son of Shealtiel, saith the Lord, and will make thee as a signet:
for I haue chosen thee, saith the Lord of hosts.</ab>



</div>