<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHaggai_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Haggai-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Haggai reproueth the people for
neglecting the building of the house. 7 Hee inciteth them to the
building. 12 He promiseth Gods assistance to them being
forward.</head>

<ab n="1">In the second
yeere of Darius the king, in the sixt moneth, in the first day of
the moneth came the worde of the Lord by Haggai the Prophet vnto
Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel, gouernour of Iudah, and to
Iosuah the sonne of Iosedech the high priest, saying;<note> Heb. by the hand of Haggai. , Or, captaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thus speaketh
the Lord of hostes, saying; This people say, The time is not come,
the time that the Lords house should be built.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then came the
word of the Lord by Haggai the prophet, saying;</ab>
<ab n="4">Is it time
for you, O yee, to dwell in your sieled houses, and this house lie
waste?</ab>
<ab n="5">Nowe
therefore thus saith the Lord of hostes; Consider your
wayes.<note> Heb. set your heart on your wayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Yee haue
sowen much and bring in litle: ye eate, but ye haue not inough: yee
drinke, but yee are not filled with drinke: yee cloth you, but
there is none warme: and hee that earneth wages, earneth wages to
put it into a bag with holes.<note> Deut.28. 38. mic.6. 14, 15. , Heb. pierced through.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Thus
saith the Lord of hostes, Consider your wayes.</ab>
<ab n="8">Goe vp to the
mountaine, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take
pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">Ye looked for
much, and loe it came to litle: and when yee brought it home, I did
blow vpon it: Why, saith the Lord of hostes? because of mine house
that is waste, and yee runne euery man vnto his owne
house.<note> Or, blow it away.</note></ab>

<fw>Contempt of religion, punished.</fw>
<ab n="10">Therefore the
heauen ouer you is stayed from dew, and the earth is staied from
her fruite.<note> Deut.28. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I called for a
drought vpon the land and vpon the mountaines, and vpon the corne,
and vpon the new wine, and vpon the oyle, and vpon that which the
ground bringeth forth, &amp; vpon men, and vpon cattell, and vpon
all the labour of the hands.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then
Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel, and Iosuah the sonne of Iosedech
the high priest, with all the remnant of the people obeyed the
voyce of the Lord their God, and the words of Haggai the Prophet
(as the Lord their God had sent him) and the people did feare
before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then spake Haggai
the Lords messenger in the Lords message vnto the people, saying; I
am with you, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the Lord
stirred vp the spirit of Zerubbabel the sonne of Shealtiel
gouernour of Iudah, and the spirit of Iosuah the sonne of Iosedech
the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people,
and they came and did worke in the house of the Lord of hostes
their God:</ab>
<ab n="15">In the foure and
twentieth day of the sixt moneth, in the second yeere of Darius the
King.</ab>



</div>