<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Christ Iesus is a Priest after the
order of Melchisedec, 11 And so, farre more excellent then the
Priests of Aarons order.</head>

<ab n="1">For this
Melchisedec king of Salem, Priest of the most high God, who met
Abraham returning from the slaughter of the Kings, and blessed
him:</ab>
<ab n="2">To whom also
Abraham gaue a tenth part of all: first being by interpretation
king of righteousnesse, and after that also king of Salem, which
is, king of peace.</ab>
<ab n="3">Without father,
without mother, without descent, hauing neither beginning of dayes
nor end of life: but made like vnto the Sonne of God, abideth a
Priest continually.<note> Gr. without pedigree.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Now consider how
great this man was, vnto whō euen the patriarch Abraham gaue
the tenth of the spoiles.</ab>
<ab n="5">And verily they
that are of the sonnes of Leui, who receiue the office of the
Priesthood, haue a commandement to take Tithes of the people
according to the Law, that is of their brethren, though they come
out of the loines of Abraham:</ab>
<ab n="6">But he whose
descent is not counted from them, receiued tithes of Abraham, and
blessed him that had the promises.<note> Or, pedigree.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And without all
contradiction, the lesse is blessed of the better.</ab>
<ab n="8">And here men that
die receiue tithes: but there hee receiueth them, of whom it is
witnessed that he liueth.</ab>
<ab n="9">And as I may so
say, Leui also who receiueth tithes, payed tithes in
Abraham.</ab>
<ab n="10">For hee was yet
in the loynes of his Father when Melchisedec met him.</ab>
<ab n="11">If therefore
perfection were by the Leuiticall Priesthood (for vnder it the
people receiued the Law) what further neede was there, that another
Priest should rise after the order of Melchisedec, and not bee
called after the order of Aaron?</ab>
<ab n="12">For the
Priesthood being chaunged, there is made of necessitie a change
also of the Law.</ab>
<ab n="13">For hee of whom
these things are spoken, pertaineth to another tribe, of which no
man gaue attendance at the Altar.</ab>

<fw>Melchisedec, and Christ.</fw>
<ab n="14">For it is euident
that our Lorde sprang out of Iuda, of which tribe Moses spake
nothing cōcerning Priesthood.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it is yet
farre more euident: for that after the similitude of Melchisedec
there ariseth another Priest,</ab>
<ab n="16">Who is made not
after the Law of a carnall commandement, but after the power of an
endles life.</ab>
<ab n="17">For hee
testifieth; Thou art a Priest for euer, after the order of
Melchisedec.</ab>
<ab n="18">For there is
verily a disanulling of the commandement going before, for the
weakenesse and vnprofitablenesse thereof.</ab>
<ab n="19">For the Law made
nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did: by the
which wee draw nigh vnto God.<note> Or, but it was the bringing in.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And in as much as
not without an othe he was made Priest,</ab>
<ab n="21">(For those
Priests were made without an oath: but this with an oath, by him
þt said vnto him, The Lord sware and wil not
repent, thou art a Priest for euer after the order of
Melchisedec)<note> Or, without swearing of an othe. , Psa. 110.4</note></ab>
<ab n="22">By so much was
Iesus made a suertie of a better Testament.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they truely
were many Priests, because they were not suffered to continue by
reason of death.</ab>
<ab n="24">But this man
because hee continueth euer, hath an vnchangeable
Priesthood.<note> Or, which passeth not from one to another.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Wherefore he is
able also to saue them to the vttermost, that come vnto God by him,
seeing hee euer liueth to make intercession for them.<note> Or, euermore.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For such an high
Priest became vs, who is holy, harmelesse, vndefiled, separate from
sinners, and made higher then the heauens.</ab>
<ab n="27">Who needeth not
daily, as those high Priests, to offer vp sacrifice, first for his
owne sins and then for the peoples: for this he did once, when he
offered vp himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="28">For the Law
maketh men high Priests which haue infirmitie, but the word of the
othe which was since the Law, maketh the Sonne, who is consecrated
for euermore.<note> Gr. perfected.</note></ab>



</div>