<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 By the eternall Priesthood of
Christ, the Leuiticall Priesthood of Aaron is abolished. 7 And the
temporall Couenant with the Fathers, by the eternal Couenant of the
Gospel.</head>


<fw>The old, and new Couenant.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now of the things
which we haue spoken, this is the summe: wee haue such an high
Priest, who is set on the right hand of the throne of the Maiestie
in the heauens:</ab>
<ab n="2">A minister of the
Sanctuary, and of the true Tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, and
not man.<note> Or, of holy things.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For euery high
Priest is ordeined to offer gifts and sacrifices: wherefore it is
of necessitie that this man haue somewhat also to offer.</ab>
<ab n="4">For if he were on
earth, he should not bee a Priest, seeing that there are Priests
that offer gifts according to the Law:<note> Or, they are Priests.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Who serue vnto the
example and shadow of heauenly things, as Moses was admonished of
God when he was about to make the Tabernacle. For see (saith he)
that thou make all things according to the paterne shewed to thee
in the mount.</ab>
<ab n="6">But now hath he
obtained a more excellent ministerie, by how much also he is the
Mediatour of a better Couenant, which was established vpon better
promises.<note> Or, Testament.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For if that first
Couenant had bene faultles, then should no place haue bene sought
for the second.</ab>
<ab n="8">For finding fault
with them, hee saith, Behold, the dayes come (saith the Lord) when
I will make a new couenant with the house of Israel, and the house
of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="9">Not according to
the Couenant that I made with their fathers, in the day when I
tooke them by the hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt,
because they continued not in my Couenant, and I regarded them not,
saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">For this is the
Couenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those
dayes, saith the Lord: I wil put my Lawes into their minde, and
write them in their hearts: and I will be to them a God, and they
shalbe to me a people.<note> Ier.31. 33. , Gr. giue. , Or, vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And they shall
not teach euery man his neighbour, and euery man his brother,
saying, Know the Lord: For all shall know me, from the least to the
greatest.</ab>
<ab n="12">For I will be
mercifull to their vnrighteousnes, and their sins &amp; their
iniquities will I remember no more.</ab>

<fw>The old, and new Couenant.</fw>
<ab n="13">In that he saith,
A new Couenant, he hath made the first olde. Now that which
decayeth and waxeth old, is readie to vanish away.</ab>



</div>