<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The authoritie and honour of our
Sauiours Priesthood. 11 Negligence in the knowledge thereof is
reprooued.</head>

<ab n="1">For euery high
Priest taken from among men, is ordeined for men in things
pertaining to God, that hee may offer both giftes &amp; sacrifices
for sins.</ab>
<ab n="2">Who can haue
compassion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way,
for that he himselfe also is compassed with infirmitie.<note> Or, can reasonably beare with.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And by reason
heereof hee ought as for the people, so also for himselfe, to offer
for sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And no man taketh
this honour vnto himselfe, but hee that is called of God, as was
Aaron.</ab>

<fw>Christes priesthood.</fw>
<ab n="5">So also, Christ
glorified not himselfe, to bee made an High Priest: but hee that
saide vnto him, Thou art my Sonne, to day haue I begotten
thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">As he saith also
in another place, Thou art a Priest for euer after the order of
Melchisedec.</ab>
<ab n="7">Who in the dayes
of his flesh, when hee had offered vp prayers and supplications,
with strong crying and teares, vnto him that was able to saue him
from death, and was heard, in that he feared.<note> Or, for his pietie.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Though hee were a
Sonne, yet learned hee obedience, by the things which he
suffered:</ab>
<ab n="9">And being made
perfect, he became the authour of eternall saluation vnto all them
that obey him,</ab>
<ab n="10">Called of God an
high Priest after the order of Melchisedec:</ab>
<ab n="11">Of whom we haue
many things to say, and hard to be vttered, seeing ye are dull of
hearing.</ab>
<ab n="12">For when for the
time yee ought to bee teachers, yee haue neede that one teach you
againe which be the first principles of the Oracles of God, and are
become such as haue need of milke, and not of strong meat.</ab>
<ab n="13">For euery one
that vseth milke, is vnskilful in the word of righteousnes: for he
is a babe.<note> Gr, hath no experience.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But strong meate
belongeth to them that are of full age, euen those who by reason of
vse haue their senses exercised to discerne both good and
euil.<note> Or, perfect. , Or of an habite, or perfection.</note></ab>



</div>