<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Philemon-Chapter-1-1-Hebrews.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Christ in these last times comming
to vs from the Father, 4 is preferred aboue the Angels, both in
Person and Office.</head>

<ab n="1">God who at sundry
times, and in diuers manners, spake in time past vnto the Fathers
by the Prophets,</ab>
<ab n="2">Hath in these last
dayes spoken vnto vs by his Sonne, whom he hath appointed heire of
all things, by whom also he made the worlds,</ab>
<ab n="3">Who being the
brightnesse of his glory, and the expresse image of his person, and
vpholding all things by the word of his power, when hee had by
himselfe purged our sinnes, sate down on þe right
hand of the Maiestie on high,<note> Wis.7.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Being made so much
better then the Angels, as hee hath by inheritance obtained a more
excellent Name then they.</ab>
<ab n="5">For vnto which of
the Angels said he at any time, Thou art my sonne, this day haue I
begotten thee? And again, I will be to him a Father, and he shall
be to me a Sonne.</ab>
<ab n="6">And againe, when
he bringeth in the first begotten into the world, hee saith, And
let all the Angels of God worship him.</ab>

<fw>Christ aboue the Angels.</fw>
<ab n="7">And of the Angels
he saith: Who maketh his Angels spirits, and his ministers a flame
of fire.</ab>
<ab n="8">But vnto the
Sonne, he saith, Thy throne, O God, is for euer and euer: a scepter
of righteousnesse is the scepter of thy kingdome.<note> Gr, rightnesse, or straightnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thou hast loued
righteousnesse, and hated iniquitie, therefore God, euen thy God
hath anointed thee with the oyle of gladnesse aboue thy
fellowes.</ab>
<ab n="10">And, thou Lord in
the beginning hast layed the foundation of the earth: and the
heauens are the works of thine hands.<note> Psa.102.2. esa.34.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They shall
perish, but thou remainest: and they all shal waxe old as doth a
garment.</ab>
<ab n="12">And as a vesture
shalt thou fold them vp, and they shall be changed, but thou art
the same, and thy yeeres shall not faile?</ab>
<ab n="13">But to which of
the Angels said hee at any time, Sit on my right hand, vntill I
make thine enemies thy footstoole?<note> Psal.110. 1. matt.22. 44.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Are they not all
ministring spirits, sent foorth to minister for them, who shall be
heires of saluation?</ab>



</div>