<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation to constant faith,
patience, and godlinesse. 22 A commendation of the New Testament
aboue the Old.</head>

<ab n="1">Wherefore, seeing
wee also are compassed about with so great a cloude of witnesses,
let vs lay aside euery weight, &amp; the sinne which doth so easily
beset vs, and let vs runne with patience vnto the race that is set
before vs,</ab>
<ab n="2">Looking vnto
Iesus the Authour and finisher of our faith, who for the ioy that
was set before him, endured the crosse, despising the shame, and is
set down at the right hand of the throne of God.<note> Or, beginner.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For consider him
that indured such contradiction of sinners against himselfe, lest
ye be wearied and faint in your mindes.</ab>
<ab n="4">Yee haue not yet
resisted vnto blood, striuing against sinne.</ab>
<ab n="5">And ye haue
forgotten the exhortation which speaketh vnto you as vnto children,
My sonne, despise not thou the chastening of the Lord, nor faint
when thou art rebuked of him.</ab>
<ab n="6">For whome the
Lord loueth hee chasteneth, and scourgeth euery sonne whom he
receiueth.</ab>
<ab n="7">If yee endure
chastening, God dealeth with you as with sonnes: for what sonne is
he whom the father chasteneth not?</ab>

<fw>Follow peace.</fw>
<ab n="8">But if ye be
without chastisement, whereof all are partakers, then are ye
bastards, and not sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Furthermore, wee
haue had fathers of our flesh, which corrected vs, and we gaue them
reuerence: shall we not much rather bee in subiection vnto the
Father of Spirits, and liue?</ab>
<ab n="10">For they verily
for a fewe dayes chastened vs after their owne pleasure, but hee
for our profit, that we might bee partakers of his
holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now no
chastening for the present seemeth to be ioyous, but grieuous:
neuerthelesse, afterward it yeeldeth the peaceable fruite of
righteousnesse, vnto them which are exercised thereby.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore lift
vp the handes which hang downe, and the feeble knees.</ab>
<ab n="13">And make
straight paths for your feete, lest that which is lame bee turned
out of the way, but let it rather bee healed.<note> Or, euen.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Followe peace
with all men, and holinesse, without which no man shall see the
Lord:</ab>
<ab n="15">Looking
diligently, lest any man faile of the grace of God, lest any roote
of bitternesse springing vp, trouble you, and thereby many be
defiled:<note> Or, fal from</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Lest there bee
any fornicatour, or profane person, as Esau, who for one morsell of
meat sold his birthright.</ab>
<ab n="17">For yee know how
that afterward when hee would haue inherited the blessing, hee was
reiected: for hee found no place of repentance, though he sought it
carefully with teares.<note> Or, way to change his minde.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For yee are not
come vnto the mount that might be touched, and that burned with
fire, nor vnto blacknesse, and darknes, and tempest,</ab>
<ab n="19">And the sound of
a trumpet, and the voyce of wordes, which voyce they that heard,
entreated that the word should not bee spoken to them any
more.</ab>
<ab n="20">For they could
not indure that which was commaunded: And if so much as a beast
touch the Mountaine, it shall be stoned, or thrust thorow with a
dart.</ab>
<ab n="21">And so terrible
was the sight, that Moses sayde, I exceedingly feare, and
quake.</ab>
<ab n="22">But ye are come
vnto mount Sion, and vnto the citie of the liuing God the heauenly
Ierusalem, and to an innumerable company of Angels:</ab>

<fw>Of mariage.</fw>
<ab n="23">To the generall
assembly, and Church of the first borne which are written in
heauen, and to God the Iudge of all, and to the spirits of iust men
made perfect:<note> Or, inrouled.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And to Iesus the
mediatour of the new Couenant, and to the blood of sprinckling,
that speaketh better things then that of Abel.<note> Or, Testament.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">See that yee
refuse not him that speaketh: for if they escaped not who refused
him that spake on earth, much more shall not we escape if wee turne
away from him that speaketh from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="26">Whose voice then
shooke the earth, but now he hath promised, saying, Yet once more I
shake not the earth onely, but also heauen.</ab>
<ab n="27">And this word
Yet once more, signifieth the remouing of those things that are
shaken, as of things that are made, that those things which cannot
be shaken may remaine.<note> Or, may be shaken.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Wherefore wee
receiuing a kingdome which cannot bee moued, let vs haue grace,
whereby wee may serue God acceptably, with reuerence and godly
feare.<note> Or, let vs hold fast.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">For our God is a
consuming fire.</ab>



</div>