<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The weakenesse of the Law
sacrifices. 10 The sacrifice of Christs body once offered, 14 for
euer, hath taken away sinnes. 19 An exhortation to hold fast the
faith, with patience and thankesgiuing.</head>

<ab n="1">For the Law
hauing a shadow of good things to come, and not the very Image of
the things, can neuer with those sacrifices which they offered
yeere by yeere continually, make the commers thereunto
perfect:</ab>
<ab n="2">For then would
they not haue ceased to be offered, because that the worshippers
once purged, should haue had no more conscience of sinnes?</ab>
<ab n="3">But in those
sacrifices there is a remembrance againe made of sinnes euery
yeere.</ab>
<ab n="4">For it is not
possible that the blood of Bulles and of Goats, should take away
sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="5">Wherefore when
hee commeth into the world, he saith, Sacrifice and offering thou
wouldest not, but a body hast thou prepared mee:<note> Or, thou hast fitted me.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In burnt
offerings, and sacrifices for sinne thou hast had no
pleasure:</ab>
<ab n="7">Then said I, Loe,
I come. (In the volume of the booke it is written of me) to doe thy
will, O God.</ab>
<ab n="8">Aboue when hee
said, Sacrifice, and offering, and burnt offerings, and offering
for sinne thou wouldest not, neither hadst pleasure therein, which
are offered by the Law:</ab>
<ab n="9">Then said he,
Loe, I come to doe thy will (O God:) He taketh away the first, that
he may establish the second.</ab>
<ab n="10">By the which
will wee are sanctified, through the offering of the body of Iesus
Christ once for all.</ab>
<ab n="11">And euery Priest
standeth dayly ministring and offering oftentimes the same
sacrifices which can neuer take away sinnes.</ab>

<fw>The liuing way.</fw>
<ab n="12">But this man
after he had offered one sacrifice for sinnes for euer, sate downe
on the right hand of God,</ab>
<ab n="13">From henceforth
expecting till his enemies be made his footstoole.</ab>
<ab n="14">For by one
offering hee hath perfected for euer them that are
sanctified.</ab>
<ab n="15">Whereof the holy
Ghost also is a witnesse to vs: for after that he had said
before,</ab>
<ab n="16">This is the
Couenant that I wil make with them after those dayes, saith the
Lord: I will put my Lawes into their hearts, and in their mindes
will I write them:<note> Iere.31. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And their sinnes
and iniquities will I remember no more.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now, where
remission of these is, there is no more offering for sinne.</ab>
<ab n="19">Hauing
therefore, brethren, boldnesse to enter into the Holiest by the
blood of Iesus,<note> Or, libertie.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">By a new and
liuing way which hee hath consecrated for vs, through the vaile,
that is to say, His flesh:<note> Or, new made.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And hauing an
high Priest ouer the house of God:</ab>
<ab n="22">Let vs drawe
neere with a true heart in full assurance of faith, hauing our
hearts sprinkled from an euill conscience, and our bodies washed
with pure water.</ab>
<ab n="23">Let vs hold fast
the profession of our faith without wauering (for he is faithfull
that promised)</ab>
<ab n="24">And let vs
consider one another to prouoke vnto loue, and to good
workes:</ab>
<ab n="25">Not forsaking
the assembling of our selues together, as the manner of some is:
but exhorting one another, and so much the more, as ye see the day
approching.</ab>
<ab n="26">For if we sinne
wilfully after that we haue receiued the knowledge of the trueth,
there remaineth no more sacrifice for sinnes,</ab>
<ab n="27">But a certaine
fearefull looking for of iudgement, and fiery indignation, which
shall deuoure the aduersaries.</ab>
<ab n="28">Hee that
despised Moses Lawe, died without mercy, vnder two or three
witnesses.</ab>

<fw>Of Faith.</fw>
<ab n="29">Of how much
sorer punishment suppose ye, shall hee be thought worthy, who hath
troden vnder foote þe Sonne of God, and hath
counted the blood of the couenant wherwith he was sanctified, an
vnholy thing, and hath done despite vnto the spirit of
grace?</ab>
<ab n="30">For we know him
that hath said, Uengeance belongeth vnto me, I wil recompence,
saith the Lord: and again, The Lord shall iudge his
people.<note> Deut.32. 35. Rom. 12. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">It is a
fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God.</ab>
<ab n="32">But call to
remembrance the former dayes, in which after yee were illuminated,
ye indured a great fight of afflictions:</ab>
<ab n="33">Partly whilest
ye were made a gazing stocke both by reproches &amp; afflictions,
and partly whilest ye became companions of them that were so
vsed.</ab>
<ab n="34">For yee had
compassion of me in my bonds, and tooke ioyfully the spoyling of
your goods, knowing in your selues that yee haue in heauen a better
and an induring substance.</ab>
<ab n="35">Cast not away
therfore your confidence which hath great recompense of
reward.</ab>
<ab n="36">For ye haue need
of patience, that shall after ye haue done the will of God ye might
receiue the promise.</ab>
<ab n="37">For yet a litle
while, and he that shall come will come, and will not tary.</ab>
<ab n="38">Now the iust
shall liue by faith: but if any man drawe backe, my soule shall
haue no pleasure in him.</ab>
<ab n="39">But wee are not
of them who draw backe vnto perdition: but of them that beleeue, to
the sauing of the soule.</ab>



</div>