<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Hee exhorteth not to fall backe
from the faith, 11 But to bee stedfast, 12 diligent, and patient to
waite vpon God, 13 because God is most sure in his
promise.</head>

<ab n="1">Therefore leauing
the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let vs goe on vnto
perfection, not laying againe the foundation of repentance from
dead workes, and of faith towards God,<note> Or, the word of the beginning of Christ.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Of the doctrine of
Baptismes, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the
dead, and of eternall iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="3">And this will we
doe, if God permit.</ab>
<ab n="4">For it is
impossible for those who were once inlightned, and haue tasted of
the heauenly gift, and were made partakers of the holy
Ghost,</ab>

<fw>Gods promise.</fw>
<ab n="5">And haue tasted
the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come;</ab>
<ab n="6">If they shall fall
away, to renue them againe vnto repentance: seeing they crucifie to
themselues the Sonne of God afresh, and put him to an open
shame.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the earth
which drinketh in the raine that commeth oft vpon it, and bringeth
forth herbes meet for them by whome it is dressed, receiueth
blessing from God.<note> Or, for.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But that which
beareth thornes and briers, is reiected, and is nigh vnto cursing,
whose end is to be burned.</ab>
<ab n="9">But beloued, wee
are perswaded better things of you, and things that accompany
saluation, though we thus speake.</ab>
<ab n="10">For God is not
vnrighteous, to forget your worke and labour of loue, which yee
haue shewed toward his Name, in that yee haue ministred to the
Saints, and doe minister.</ab>
<ab n="11">And wee desire,
that euery one of you doe shewe the same diligence, to the full
assurance of hope vnto the ende:</ab>
<ab n="12">That yee be not
slothfull, but followers of them, who through faith and patience
inherite the promises.</ab>
<ab n="13">For when God made
promise to Abraham, because hee could sweare by no greater, he
sware by himselfe,</ab>
<ab n="14">Saying, Surely,
blessing I will blesse thee, and multiplying I wil multiply
thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">And so after he
had patiently indured, he obtained the promise.</ab>
<ab n="16">For men verily
sweare by the greater, and an oath for confirmation is to them an
end of all strife.</ab>
<ab n="17">Wherein God
willing more abundantly to shewe vnto the heyres of promise the
immutabilitie of his counsell, confirmed it by an oath:<note> Gr. interposed himselfe by an oath.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">That by two
immutable things, in which it was impossible for God to lye, wee
might haue a strong consolation, who haue fled for refuge to lay
hold vpon the hope set before vs.</ab>
<ab n="19">Which hope we
haue as an anker of the soule both sure and stedfast, and which
entreth into that within the vaile,</ab>
<ab n="20">Whither the
forerunner is for vs entrrd; euen Iesus, made an high Priest for
euer after the order of Melchisedec.</ab>



</div>