<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHebrews_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-13-13-James.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Diuers admonitions, as to
Charitie, 4 To honest life, 5 To auoide couetousnes, 7 To regarde
Gods preachers, 9 To take heed of strange doctrines, 10 To confesse
Christ, 16 To giue almes, 17 To obey gouernors, 18 To pray for the
Apostle. 20 The Conclusion.</head>

<ab n="1">Let brotherly
loue continue.</ab>
<ab n="2">Bee not
forgetfull to entertaine strangers, for thereby some haue
entertayned Angels vnawares.</ab>
<ab n="3">Remember them
that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them which suffer
aduersitie, as being your selues also in the body.</ab>
<ab n="4">Mariage is
honorable in all, and the bed vndefiled: but whoremongers, and
adulterers God will iudge.</ab>
<ab n="5">Let your
conuersation bee without couetousnesse: and be content with such
things as yee haue. For hee hath said, I will neuer leaue thee, nor
forsake thee.<note> Ios.1.5.</note></ab>

<fw>Fruit of lips.</fw>
<ab n="6">So that wee may
boldly say, The Lord is my helper, and I will not feare what man
shall doe vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="7">Remember them
which haue the rule ouer you, who haue spoken vnto you the word of
God, whose faith follow, considering the end of their
conuersation.<note> Or, are the guides</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Iesus Christ the
same yesterday, and to day, and for euer.</ab>
<ab n="9">Be not caried
about with diuers and strange doctrines: for it is a good thing
that the heart be established with grace, not with meates, which
haue not profited them that haue beene occupied therein.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wee haue an
altar whereof they haue no right to eate, which serue the
Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the bodies
of those beasts, whose blood is brought into the Sanctuary by the
high Priest for sinne, are burnt without the campe.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore Iesus
also, that hee might sanctifie the people with his own blood,
suffered without the gate.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let vs goe
foorth therefore vnto him without the campe, bearing his
reproch.</ab>
<ab n="14">For here haue we
no continuing citie, but we seeke one to come.<note> Mich.2.10</note></ab>
<ab n="15">By him therefore
let vs offer the sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is,
the fruit of our lippes, giuing thankes to his Name.<note> Gr. confessing to.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But to doe good,
and to communicate forget not, for with such sacrifices God is well
pleased.</ab>
<ab n="17">Obey them that
haue the rule ouer you, and submit your selues: for they watch for
your soules, as they that must giue account, that they may doe it
with ioy, and not with griefe: for that is vnprofitable for
you.<note> Or, guide.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Pray for vs: for
we trust wee haue a good conscience in all things, willing to liue
honestly.</ab>
<ab n="19">But I beseech
you the rather to doe this, that I may be restored to you the
sooner.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now the God of
peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord Iesus, that great
shepheard of the sheepe, through the blood of the euerlasting
Couenant,<note> Or, Testament.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Make you perfect
in euery good worke to doe his will, working in you that which is
well pleasing in his sight, through Iesus Christ, to whom be glorie
for euer and euer. Amen.<note> Or, doing.</note></ab>

<fw>Aske in faith.</fw>
<ab n="22">And I beseech
you brethren, suffer the word of exhortation, for I haue written a
letter vnto you in few words.</ab>
<ab n="23">Know yee, that
our brother Timothie is set at libertie, with whom if he come
shortly, I will see you.</ab>
<ab n="24">Salute all them
that haue the rule ouer you, and al the Saints. They of Italy
salute you.</ab>
<ab n="25">Grace be with
you all. Amen. [Written to the Hebrewes, from Italy, by
Timothie.]</ab>



</div>