<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 A reproose of Ephraim, Iudah, and
Iacob. 3 By former fauours he exhorteth to repentance. 7 Ephraims
sinnes prouoke God.</head>

<ab n="1">Ephraim
feedeth on winde, and followeth after the East winde: hee daily
increaseth lies and desolation, and they doe make a couenant with
the Assyrians, and oyle is caried into Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord hath
also a controuersie with Iudah, and will punish Iacob according to
his wayes, according to his doings will he recompense
him.<note> Heb. visit vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Hee
tooke his brother by the heele in the wombe, and by his strength he
had power with God.<note> Gene.25. 26. , Heb. was a prince, or behaued himselfe princely , Gen.32. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Yea, he had
power ouer the Angel and preuailed: hee wept and made supplication
vnto him: he found him in Bethel, and there he spake with
vs.<note> Gen.35. 9,10.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Euen the Lord
God of hosts, the Lord is his memoriall.<note> Exo.3. 15</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore
turne thou to thy God: keepe mercie and iudgement, and wait on thy
God continually.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ He is
a merchant, the balances of deceit are in his hand: hee loueth to
oppresse.<note> Or, Canaan , Or, deceiue</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Ephraim
said, Yet I am become rich, I haue found mee out substance: in all
my labours they shall finde none iniquitie in mee, that were
sinne.<note> Or, all my labours suffice me not: hee shall haue punishment of iniquitie in whom is sinne. , Heb. which</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And I that am
the Lord thy God from the lande of Egypt, will yet make thee to
dwell in tabernacles, as in the dayes of the solemne feast.</ab>
<ab n="10">I haue also spoken
by the prophets, and I haue multiplied visions, and vsed
similitudes, by the ministerie of the prophets.<note> Heb. by the hand.</note></ab>

<fw>God onely saueth.</fw>
<ab n="11">Is there iniquitie
in Gilead? surely they are vanitie, they sacrifice bullocks in
Gilgal, yea their altars are as heapes in the furrowes of the
fields.<note> Chap.4. 15. and 9. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And Iacob fled
into the countrey of Syria, and Israel serued for a wife, and for a
wife he kept sheepe.<note> Gen.28. 5. , Gene.29. 20,28.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And by a Prophet
the Lord brought Israel out of Egypt, and by a Prophet was he
preserued.<note> Exod. 12. 50, 51. and 13.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Ephraim prouoked
him to anger, most bitterly: therefore shall he leaue his blood
vpon him, and his reproch shall his Lord returne vnto
him.<note> Hebr. with bitternesses. , Hebr. bloods.</note></ab>



</div>