<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 The ingratitude of Israel vnto God
for his benefits. 5 His iudgement. 8 Gods mercy toward
them.</head>

<ab n="1">When Israel
was a childe, then I loued him, and called my sonne out of
Egypt.<note> Mat.2. 15</note></ab>
<ab n="2">As they
called them, so they went from them: they sacrificed vnto Baalim,
and burnt incense to grauen images.</ab>
<ab n="3">I taught
Ephraim also to goe, taking them by their armes: but they knew not
that I healed them.</ab>
<ab n="4">I drew them
with cords of a man, with bands of loue, and I was to them as they
that take off the yoke on their iawes, and I laid meat vnto
them.<note> Heb. lift vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ He
shall not returne into the land of Egypt; but the Assyrian shall be
his king, because they refused to returne</ab>
<ab n="6">And the sword
shall abide on his cities, and shall consume his branches, and
deuoure them, because of their own counsels.</ab>
<ab n="7">And my people
are bent to backesliding from mee: though they called them to the
most High, none at all would exalt him.<note> Hebr. together they exalted not.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">How shall I
giue thee vp, Ephraim? how shall I deliuer thee, Israel? how shall
I make thee as Admah? how shall I set thee as Zeboim? mine heart is
turned within mee, my repentings are kindled together.<note> Gene. 19. 22. amos 4. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>Wait on God.</fw>
<ab n="9">I will not
execute the fiercenes of mine anger, I will not returne to destroy
Ephraim, for I am God, and not man, the Holy One in the midst of
thee, and I will not enter into the citie.</ab>
<ab n="10">They shal walke
after the Lord: he shall roare like a lyon: when he shall roare,
then the children shall tremble from the West.</ab>
<ab n="11">They shall tremble
as a bird out of Egypt, and as a doue out of the land of Assyria:
and I will place them in their houses, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">Ephraim compasseth
mee about with lies, and the house of Israel with deceit: but Iudah
yet ruleth with God, and is faithfull with the Saints.<note> Or, with the most holy</note></ab>




</div>