<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The idolatrie of the people. 6
Gods iudgements against them. 14 His promises of reconciliation
with them.</head>

<ab n="1">Say ye vnto
your brethren, Ammi, &amp; to your sisters, Ruhamah:<note> That is, my people. , That is, hauing obtained mercy.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Plead with
your mother, plead: for she is not my wife, neither am I her
husband: let her therefore put away her whordomes out of her sight,
and her adulteries from betweene her breasts;<note> Isai.50.1. , Eze.16.25</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Lest I strip
her naked, and set her as in the day that shee was borne, and make
her as a wildernesse, and set her like a drie land, and slay her
with thirst.<note> Eze.16.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I will not
haue mercy vpon her children, for they be the children of
whordomes.</ab>
<ab n="5">For their
mother hath played the harlot: shee that conceiued them hath done
shamefully: for shee sayd, I will goe after my louers, that giue me
my bread and my water, my wooll and my flaxe, mine oyle, and my
drinke.<note> Heb. drinks</note></ab>

<fw>Gods promise of reconciliation.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶
Therefore behold, I will hedge vp thy way with thornes, and make a
wall, that she shall not find her pathes.<note> Heb. wall a wall.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And she shall
follow after her louers, but she shall not ouertake them, and she
shall seeke them, but shall not find them: then shall she say, I
will goe and returne to my first husband, for then was it better
with me then now.</ab>
<ab n="8">For she did
not know that I gaue her corne, and wine, and oyle, and multiplied
her siluer and gold, which they prepared for Baal.<note> Heb. new wine. , Or, wherewith they made Baal.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore will
I returne, and take away my Corne in the time thereof, and my wine
in the season thereof, and wil recouer my wooll and my flaxe giuen
to couer her nakednesse.<note> Or, take away.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And now will I
discouer her lewdnesse in the sight of her louers, and none shall
deliuer her out of mine hand.<note> Heb. folly or villanie.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">I will also cause
all her mirth to cease, her feast daies, her new moones, and her
Sabbaths, and all her solemne feasts.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I will destroy
her vines and her figge trees, whereof she hath said; These are my
rewards that my louers haue giuen me: and I will make them a
forrest, and the beasts of the field shall eate them.<note> Heb. make desolate.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I will visite
vpon her the daies of Baalim, wherein she burnt incense to them,
and she decked her selfe with her eare-rings, and her Iewels, and
she went after her louers, and forgate me, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Therefore
behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the wildernesse, and
speake comfortably vnto her.<note> Or, friendly. Heb. to her heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And I wil giue her,
her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a doore of
hope, and she shall sing there, as in the dayes of her youth, and
as in the day when she came vp out of the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it shall be at
that day, saith the Lord, that thou shalt call mee Ishi; and shalt
call mee no more Baali.<note> That is, my husband. , That is, my Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For I will take
away the names of Baalim out of her mouth, &amp; they shal no more
be remembred by their name.</ab>

<fw>Gods promise of reconciliation.</fw>
<ab n="18">And in that day
will I make a couenant for them with the beasts of the field, and
with the foules of heauen, and with the creeping things of the
ground: and I will breake the bow and the sword, and the battell
out of the earth, and will make them to lie downe
safely.<note> Iob.5. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And I will betroth
thee vnto me for euer; yea, I will betroth thee vnto me in
righteousnesse, and in iudgement, and in louing kindnesse, and in
mercies.</ab>
<ab n="20">I will euen betroth
thee vnto me in faithfulnesse, and thou shalt know the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it shall come
to passe in that day, I will heare, saith the Lord, I will heare
the heauens, and they shall heare the earth,</ab>
<ab n="22">And the earth shall
heare the corne, and the wine, and the oyle, and they shall heare
Iezreel.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I will sow her
vnto me in the earth, and I will haue mercy vpon her that had not
obtained mercy, and I will say to them which were not my people;
Thou art my people, and they shallsay, Thou art my God.<note> Rom.9. 26. 1.pet.2. 10.</note></ab>



</div>