<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Gods iudgements against the
Priests, the people, and the princes of Israel for their manifold
sinnes, 15 vntill they repent.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare yee
this, O priests, and hearken, ye house of Israel, and giue yee
eare, O house of the king: for iudgement is toward you, because yee
haue beene a snare on Mizpah, and a net spread vpon Tabor.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the
reuolters are profound to make slaughter, though I haue bene a
rebuker of them all.<note> Or, and, &amp;c. , Heb. a correction.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I know
Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me: for now, O Ephraim, thou
committest whordome, and Israel is defiled.</ab>
<ab n="4">They will not
frame their doings to turne vnto their God: for the spirit of
whoredomes is in the midst of them, and they haue not knowen the
Lord.<note> Heb. they will not giue. , Or, their doings will not suffer them.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the pride
of Israel doth testifie to his face: therefore shall Israel and
Ephraim fall in their iniquity: Iudah also shall fall with
them.</ab>
<ab n="6">They shall goe
with their flocks, and with their heards to seeke the Lord: but
they shall not finde him, he hath withdrawen himselfe from
them.</ab>

<fw>God smiteth, &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="7">They haue
dealt treacherously against the Lord: for they haue begotten
strange children, now shall a moneth deuoure them with their
portions.</ab>
<ab n="8">Blow yee the
cornet in Gibeah, and the trumpet in Ramah: cry alowd at Beth-auen:
after thee, O Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="9">Ephraim shall
be desolate in the day of rebuke: among the tribes of Israel haue I
made knowen that which shall surely be.</ab>
<ab n="10">The Princes of
Iudah were like them that remooue the bound: therefore I will powre
out my wrath vpon them like water.</ab>
<ab n="11">Ephraim is
oppressed, and broken in iudgement: because he willingly walked
after the commandement.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore wil I be
vnto Ephraim as a moth: and to the house of Iudah as
rottennesse.<note> Or, a worme</note></ab>
<ab n="13">When Ephraim saw
his sicknesse, and Iudah saw his wound: then went Ephraim to the
Assyrian, and sent to king Iareb; yet could he not heale you, nor
cure you of your wound.<note> Or, to the king of Iareb. Or, to the king that should plead.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For I will bee vnto
Ephraim as a Lion, and as a yong Lion to the house of Iudah: I,
euen I wil teare and goe away: I will take away, and none shall
rescue him.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ I will goe
and returne to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and
seeke my face: in their affliction they will seeke me
early.<note> Heb. till they be guiltie.</note></ab>



</div>