<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Hosea to shew Gods iudgement for
spirituall whoredome, taketh Gomer, 4 and hath by her Iezreel, 6
Lo-ruhamah, 8 and Lo-ammi. 10 The restauration of Iudah and
Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of
the Lord that came vnto Hosea, the sonne of Beeri, in the dayes of
Uzziah, Iotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah kings of Iudah, and in the dayes
of Ieroboam the sonne of Ioash king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">The beginning
of the word of the Lord by Hosea: and the Lord sayd to Hosea, Goe,
take vnto thee a wife of whoredomes, and children of whoredomes:
for the land hath committed great whoredome, departing from the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">So he went and
tooke Gomer the daughter of Diblaim, which conceiued and bare him a
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
said vnto him, Call his name Iezreel; for yet a little while, and I
will auenge the blood of Iezreel vpon the house of Iehu, and will
cause to cease the kingdome of the house of Israel.<note> Heb. visit.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And it shall
come to passe at that day, that I will breake the bow of Israel in
the valley of Iezreel.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
shee conceiued againe and bare a daughter, and God sayd vnto him,
Call her name Lo-ruhamah: for I will no more haue mercy vpon the
house of Israel: but I will vtterly take them away.<note> That is, not hauing obtained mercie. , Heb. I will not adde any more to. , Or, that I should altogether pardon them.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But I will
haue mercy vpon the house of Iudah, and will saue them by the Lord
their God, and will not saue them by vow, nor by sword, nor by
battell, by horses nor by horsemen.</ab>

<fw>Hoseas wife, and children.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ Now
when shee had weaned Lo-ruhamah, she couceiued and bare a
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then sayde
God, Call his name Lo-ammi: for yee are not my people, and I will
not be your God.<note> That is, not my people.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Yet the
number of the children of Israel shall be as the sand of the sea,
which cannot bee measured nor numbred, and it shall come to passe,
that in the place where it was said vnto them, Yee are not my
people, there it shall be said vnto them, Ye are the sonnes of the
liuing God.<note> Rom.9. 25,26. , Or, in stead of that.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then shall the
children of Iudah and the children of Israel be gathered together,
and appoint themselues one head, and they shall come vp out of the
land: for great shalbe the day of Iezreel.<note> Iere.3.18. ezek.34.37</note></ab>



</div>