<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1. 12 Destruction is threatned for
their impietie, 5 and idolatrie.</head>

<ab n="1">Set the
Trumpet to thy mouth: hee shall come as an Eagle against the house
of the Lord, because they haue transgressed my Couenant, and
trespassed against my Lawe.<note> Heb. the roofe of thy mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Israel shall
crie vnto me, My God, we know thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">Israel hath
cast off the thing that is good: the enemie shall pursue
him.</ab>
<ab n="4">They haue set
vp Kings, but not by me: they haue made Princes, and I knew it not:
of their siluer and their golde haue they made them idoles, that
they may be cut off.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Thy
calfe, O Samaria, hath cast thee off: mine anger is kindled against
them: how long will it bee ere they attaine to innocencie?</ab>

<fw>The calfe of Samaria.</fw>
<ab n="6">For from
Israel was it also, the workeman made it, therefore it is not God:
but the calfe of Samaria shall be broken in pieces.</ab>
<ab n="7">For they haue
sowen the winde, and they shall reape the whirlewinde: it hath no
stalke: the budde shall yeeld no meale: if so be it yeeld, the
strangers shall swallow it vp.<note> Or, standing corne.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Israel is
swallowed vp, now shal they be among the Gentiles, as a vessell
wherein is no pleasure.</ab>
<ab n="9">For they are
gone vp to Assyria, a wilde Asse alone by himselfe; Ephraim hath
hired louers.<note> Heb. loues.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yea, though they
haue hired among the nations, now will I gather them, and they
shall sorrow a little for the burden of the King of
princes.<note> Or, begin.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Because Ephraim
hath made many altars to sinne, altars shall be vnto him to
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="12">I haue written to
him the great things of my Law, but they were counted as a strange
thing.</ab>
<ab n="13">They sacrifice
flesh for the sacrifices of mine offerings, and eate it; but the
Lord accepteth them not: now will he remember their iniquitie, and
visite their sinnes: they shal returne to Egypt.<note> Or, in the sacrifices of mine offerings, they &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For Israel hath
forgotten his maker, and buildeth temples; and Iudah hath
multiplied fenced cities: but I will send a fire vpon his cities,
and it shall deuoure the palaces thereof.</ab>



</div>