<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Ephraims glory, by reason of
idolatry, vanisheth. 5 Gods anger for their vnkindnes. 9 A promise
of Gods mercie. 15 A iudgement for rebellion.</head>

<ab n="1">When Ephraim
spake, trembling, he exalted himselfe in Israel, but, when he
offended in Baal, he died.</ab>
<ab n="2">And now they
sinne more and more, and haue made them molten images of their
siluer, and idoles according to their owne vnderstanding, all of it
the worke of the craftesmen: they say of them, Let the men that
sacrifice, kisse the calues.<note> Hebr. they adde to sinne. , Or, the sacrificers of men.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore
they shalbe as the morning cloud, and as the early dew it passeth
away, as the chaffe that is driuen with a whirlewinde out of the
floore, and as the smoke out of the chimney.</ab>
<ab n="4">Yet I am the
Lord thy God from the land of Egypt, and thou shalt know no God,
but me: for there is no sauiour beside me.<note> Isa.43.11. chap. 12. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ I did
know thee in the wildernesse, in the land of great
drought.<note> Hebr. droughts.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">According to
their pasture, so were they filled: they were filled, and their
heart was exalted: therefore haue they forgotten me.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore I
will bee vnto them as a Lion, as a Leopard by the way will I
obserue them.</ab>
<ab n="8">I will meet
them as a beare that is bereaued of her whelpes, and will rent the
kall of their heart, and there will I deuoure them like a Lion: the
wilde beast shall teare them.<note> Hebr. the beast of the field.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ O
Israel, thou hast destroied thy selfe, but in me is thine
helpe.<note> Hebr. in thy helpe.</note></ab>

<fw>Calues of the lips.</fw>
<ab n="10">I will be thy
King: where is any other that may saue thee in all thy cities? and
thy Iudges of whom thou saidst, Giue me a King and Princes?</ab>
<ab n="11">I gaue thee a king
in mine anger, and tooke him away in my wrath.<note> 1. Sam. 8. 5. and 15. 23. and 16. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The iniquitie of
Ephraim is bound vp: his sinne is hid.</ab>
<ab n="13">The sorrowes of a
traueiling woman shall come vpon him, he is an vnwise sonne, for he
should not stay long in the place of the breaking foorth of
children.<note> Hebr. a time.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I will ransome
them from the power of the graue: I will redeeme them from death: O
death, I will be thy plagues, O graue, I will be thy destruction;
repentance shall be hid from mine eyes.<note> Hebr. the hand. , 1.Cor.15. 55.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Though he
be fruitfull among his brethren, an East winde shall come, the
winde of the Lord shall come vp from the wildernesse, and his
spring shall become drie, and his fountaine shalbe dried vp: he
shall spoile the treasure of all pleasant vessels.<note> Eze. 19. 12. , Hebr. vessels of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Samaria shall
become desolate, for she hath rebelled against her God: they shall
fall by the sword: their infants shalbe dashed in pieces, and their
women with childe shalbe ript vp.</ab>



</div>