<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>The distresse and captiuitie of
Israel, for their sinnes and idolatrie.</head>

<ab n="1">Reioyce not, O
Israel, for ioy as other people: for thou hast gone a whoring from
thy God, thou hast loued a reward vpon euery corne
floore.<note> Iere. 44. 17. , Or, in, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The floore and
the winepresse shall not feede them, and the new wine shall faile
in her.<note> Or, winefat.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">They shal not
dwel in þ<note/> Lords land: but Ephraim shall returne to
Egypt, and they shall eat vncleane things in Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="4">They shall not
offer wine offrings to the Lord: neither shall they be pleasing
vnto him: their sacrifices shalbe vnto them as the bread of
mourners: all that eate thereof shall be polluted: for their bread
for their soule shall not come into the house of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Israel is threatned for her
idolatry.</fw>
<ab n="5">What will yee
doe in the solemne day, and in the day of the feast of the Lord
?</ab>
<ab n="6">For loe they
are gone, because of destruction: Egypt shall gather them vp,
Memphis shall burie them: the pleasant places for their siluer,
netles shal possesse them: thornes shall be in their
Tabernacles.<note> Heb. spoile. , Or, their siluer shall be desired, the nettle &amp;c: Heb. the desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The dayes of
visitation are come, the dayes of recompence are come, Israel shall
know it; the Prophet is a foole, the spirituall man is madde, for
the multitude of thine iniquitie and the great hatred.<note> Heb. man of the spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The watchman
of Ephraim was with my God: but the Prophet is a snare of a fouler
in all his wayes, and hatred in the house of his God.<note> Or, against</note></ab>
<ab n="9">They haue
deeply corrupted themselues as in the dayes of Gibeah: therefore he
will remember their iniquitie, he will visite their
sinnes.<note> Iudg.19. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">I found Israel like
grapes in the wildernesse: I saw your fathers as the first ripe in
the fig tree at her first time: but they went to Baalpeor, and
separated themselues vnto that shame, and their abominations were
according as they loued.<note> Num.25. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">As for Ephraim,
their glory shall flee away like a bird: from the birth and from
the wombe, and from the conception.</ab>
<ab n="12">Though they bring
vp their children, yet wil I bereaue them that there shall not be a
man left: yea, woe also to them when I depart from them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Ephraim, as I saw
Tyrus, is planted in a pleasant place: but Ephraim shall bring
foorth his children to the murderer.</ab>
<ab n="14">Giue them, O Lord:
what wilt thou giue? giue them a miscarying wombe, and drie
breasts.<note> Heb. that casteth the fruite.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">All their
wickednesse is in Gilgal: for there I hated them: for the
wickednesse of their doings I will driue them out of mine house, I
will loue them no more: all their princes are
reuolters.<note> Chap. 12. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Ephraim is smitten,
their roote is dried vp, they shall beare no fruite: yea though
they bring foorth, yet wil I slay euen the beloued fruite of their
wombe.<note> Heb. the desires.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">My God will cast
them away, because they did not hearken vnto him: and they shalbe
wanderers among the nations.</ab>



</div>