<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CHosea_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>Israel is reproued and threatned for
their impietie and idolatry.</head>

<ab n="1">Israel is an
empty vine, he bringeth forth fruite vnto himselfe: according to
the multitude of his fruite, he hath increased the altars,
according to the goodnesse of his land, they haue made goodly
images.<note> Or, a vine emptying the fruite which it giueth. , Heb. statues, or standing images.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Their heart
is diuided: now shall they be found faultie: hee shall breake downe
their altars: he shall spoile their images.<note> Or, he hath diuided their heart. , Heb. behead.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For now they
shall say, We haue no King, because we feared not the Lord, What
then should a King doe to vs?</ab>
<ab n="4">They haue
spoken words, swearing falsely in making a couenant: thus iudgement
springeth vp as hemlocke in the furrowes of the field.</ab>
<ab n="5">The
inhabitants of Samaria shall feare, because of the calues of
Bethauen: for the people thereof shall mourne ouer it, and the
priests thereof that reioyced on it, for the glory thereof, because
it is departed from it.<note> Chemarims,</note></ab>
<ab n="6">It shall be
also caried vnto Assyria for a present to King Iareb: Ephraim shall
receiue shame, and Israel shall be ashamed of his owne
counsell.<note> Chap.5. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">As for
Samaria, her King is cut off as the fome vpon the
water.<note> Heb. the face of the water.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The high
places also of Auen, the sinne of Israel, shall be destroyed: the
thorne and the thistle shall come vp on their altars; and they
shall say to the mountaines, Couer vs; and to the hilles, Fall on
vs.<note> Isai. 2. 19. luc.23.30. reu.6.16. and 9.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">O Israel,
thou hast sinned from the dayes of Gibeah: there they stood: the
battell in Gibeah against the children of iniquitie did not
ouertake them.</ab>
<ab n="10">It is in my desire
that I should chastise them, and the people shall be gathered
against them, when they shall bind themselues in their two
furrowes.<note> Or, when I shall bind them for their two transgressions, or in their two habitations.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Ephraim is as
an heifer that is taught and loueth to tread out the corne, but I
passed ouer vpon her faire necke: I will make Ephraim to ride:
Iudah shall plow, and Iacob shall breake his clods.<note> Heb. the beautie of her necke.</note></ab>

<fw>Israel vnthankefull.</fw>
<ab n="12">Sow to your selues
in righteousnesse, reape in mercie: breake vp your fallow ground:
for it is time to seeke the Lord, till he come and raine
righteousnesse vpon you.<note> Ier.4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Ye haue plowed
wickednesse, yee haue reaped iniquitie, ye haue eaten the fruite of
lies: because thou didst trust in thy way, in the multitude of thy
mightie men.</ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore shall a
tumult arise among thy people, and all thy fortresses shall bee
spoiled, as Shalman spoiled Beth-arbel in the day of battell: the
mother was dashed in pieces vpon her children.<note> 2.King.18 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">So shall Bethel
doe vnto you, because of your great wickednesse: in a morning shall
the king of Israel be vtterly cut off.<note> Hebr. the euill of your euill.</note></ab>



</div>