<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_52" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-51-53.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LII.</head>
<head>1 Christ perswadeth the Church to
beleeue his free Redemption, 7 To receiue the Ministers thereof, 9
To ioy in the power thereof, 11 And to free themselues from
bondage. 13 Christs kingdome shalbe exalted.</head>

<ab n="1">Awake, awake, put
on thy strength, O Zion, put on thy beautifull garments, O
Ierusalem the holy citie: for hencefoorth there shall no more come
into thee the vncircumcised, and the vncleane.<note> Chap. 51. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Shake thy selfe
from the dust: arise, and sit downe, O Ierusalem: loose thy selfe
from the bandes of thy necke, O captiue daughter of Zion.</ab>
<ab n="3">For thus sayth the
Lord, Yee haue solde your selues for nought: and ye shall be
redeemed without money.</ab>
<ab n="4">For thus saith the
Lord God, My people went downe aforetime into Egypt to soiourne
there, and the Assyrian oppressed them without cause.<note> Gen.46.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Now therefore,
what haue I here, sayth the Lord, that my people is taken away for
nought? they that rule ouer them, make them to howle, sayth the
Lord, and my Name continually euery day is blasphemed.<note> Ezek.36. 20,23. rom. 2.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore my
people shall know my Name: therefore they shall know in that day,
that I am he that doth speake. Behold, it is I.</ab>

<fw>The deliuerance of the Church.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ How
beautifull vpon the mountaines are the feete of him that bringeth
good tidings, that publisheth peace, that bringeth good tidings of
good, that publisheth saluation, that sayth vnto Zion, Thy God
reigneth?<note> Nahum. 1.15. rom. 10.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Thy watchmen shall
lift vp the voice, with the voice together shall they sing: for
they shall see eye to eye when the Lord shall bring againe
Zion.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Breake
foorth into ioy, sing together, yee waste places of Ierusalem: for
the Lord hath comforted his people, he hath redeemed
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="10">The Lord hath
made bare his holy arme in the eyes of all the nations, and all the
endes of the earth shall see the saluation of our God.<note> Psal.92.8. luke 3.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Depart ye,
depart ye, goe ye out from thence, touch no vncleane thing; goe ye
out of the middest of her; be yee cleane, that beare the vessels of
the Lord.<note> 2. Cor.6. 17. reuel. 18.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For ye shall not
go out with haste, nor goe by flight: for the Lord will goe before
you: and the God of Israel will be your rereward.<note> Heb. gather you vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Behold, my
seruant shal deale prudently, he shall be exalted and extolled, and
be very high.<note> Or, prosper.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">As many were
astonied at thee (his visage was so marred more then any man, and
his forme more then the sonnes of men:)<note> Cha.53.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">So shall hee
sprinckle many nations, the kings shall shut their mouthes at him:
for that which had not beene told them, shall they see, and that
which they had not heard, shall they consider.<note> Rom.15. 21.</note></ab>



</div>