<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 Sennacherib inuadeth Iudah. 4
Rabshakeh sent by Sennacherib, by blasphemous perswasions
solliciteth the people to reuolt. 22 His words are told to
Hezekiah.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe it came to
passe in the fourteenth yeere of king Hezekiah, that Sennacherib
king of Assyria came vp against all the defenced cities of Iudah,
and tooke them.<note> 2.Kings 18.13. 2.chron. 32. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the king of
Assyria sent Rabshakeh, from Lachish to Ierusalem, vnto king
Hezekiah, with a great armie: and he stood by the conduit of the
vpper poole in the high way of the fullers field.</ab>

<fw>Rabshakeh.</fw>
<ab n="3">Then came forth
vnto him Eliakim Hilkiahs sonne, which was ouer the house, and
Shebna the scribe, and Ioah Asaphs sonne the Recorder.<note> Or, secretarie.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
Rabshakeh sayd vnto them; Say yee now to Hezekiah; Thus saith the
great king, the king of Assyria; What confidence is this wherein
thou trustest?</ab>
<ab n="5">I say, (sayest
thou) (but they are but vaine words) I haue counsell and strength
for warre: Now on whom doest thou trust, that thou rebellest
against me?<note> Heb. a word of lips. , Or, but counsell and strength are for the war.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Loe, thou trustest
in the staffe of this broken reede, on Egypt; whereon if a man
leane, it will goe into his hand and pierce it: so is Pharaoh king
of Egypt to all that trust in him.<note> Eze.29. 6,7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But if thou say to
me; We trust in the Lord our God: Is it not he, whose high places
and whose altars Hezekiah hath taken away, and sayd to Iudah and to
Ierusalem; Yee shall worship before this altar?</ab>
<ab n="8">Now therefore giue
pledges, I pray thee, to my master the king of Assyria, and I will
giue thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set
riders vpon them.<note> Or, hostages.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">How then wilt thou
turne away the face of one captaine of the least of my masters
seruants: and put thy trust on Egypt for charets and for
horsemen?</ab>
<ab n="10">And am I now come
vp without the Lord against this land to destroy it? the Lord sayd
vnto me; Goe vp against this land and destroy it.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Then sayd
Eliakim and Shebna &amp; Ioah vnto Rabshakeh; Speake, I pray thee,
vnto thy seruants in the Syrian language; for we vnderstand it: and
speake not to vs in the Iewes language, in the eares of the people
that are on the wall.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ But
Rabshakeh sayd; Hath my master sent me to thy master and to thee,
to speake these words? Hath he not sent me to the men that sit vpon
the wall, that they may eate their owne dongue, and drinke their
owne pisse with you?</ab>
<ab n="13">Then Rabshakeh
stood, and cryed with a loud voice in the Iewes language, and sayd;
Heare ye the words of the great king, the king of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="14">Thus saith the
king; Let not Hezekiah deceiue you, for he shall not be able to
deliuer you.</ab>

<fw>The blasphemie of Rabshakeh.</fw>
<ab n="15">Neither let
Hezekiah make you trust in the Lord, saying; The Lord will surely
deliuer vs: this citie shall not be deliuered into the hand of the
King of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="16">Hearken not to
Hezekiah: for thus sayth the King of Assyria, Make an agreement
with mee by a present, and come out to mee: and eate yee euery one
of his vine, and euery one of his figgetree, and drinke yee euery
one the waters of his owne cisterne:<note> Or, seeke my fauour by a present. Heb. make with me a blessing.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Until I come and
take you away to a land like your owne land, a land of corne and
wine, a land of bread and vineyards:</ab>
<ab n="18">Beware lest
Hezekiah perswade you, saying; The Lord will deliuer vs. Hath any
of the gods of the nations deliuered his land out of the hand of
the king of Assyria?</ab>
<ab n="19">Where are the
gods of Hamath, and Arphad? where are the gods of Sepharuaim? and
haue they deliuered Samaria out of my hand?</ab>
<ab n="20">Who are they
amongst all the gods of these landes, that haue deliuered their
land out of my hand, that the Lord should deliuer Ierusalem out of
my hand?</ab>
<ab n="21">But they held
their peace, and answered him not a word: for the Kings
commandement was, saying; Answere him not.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Then came
Eliakim the sonne of Hilkiah, that was ouer the houshold, and
Shebna the Scribe, and Ioah the sonne of Asaph the Recorder, to
Hezekiah with their clothes rent, and tolde him the wordes of
Rabshakeh.</ab>



</div>