<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-33-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 Gods iudgements against the
enemies of the Church. 13 The priuiledges of the
godly.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to thee that
spoilest, and thou wast not spoiled; and dealest treacherously, and
they dealt not treacherously with thee: when thou shalt cease to
spoile, thou shalt bee spoiled; and when thou shalt make an end to
deale treacherously, they shall deale treacherously with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">O Lord, be
gratious vnto vs, we haue waited for thee: be thou their arme euery
morning, our saluation also in the time of trouble.</ab>
<ab n="3">At the noise of
the tumult the people fled: at the lifting vp of thy selfe the
nations were scattered.</ab>
<ab n="4">And your spoile
shall be gathered like the gathering of the caterpiller: as the
running to and fro of Locusts shall he runne vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="5">The Lord is
exalted: for hee dwelleth on high, he hath filled Zion with
iudgement and righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">And wisedome and
knowledge shall be the stabilitie of thy times, and strength of
saluation: the feare of the Lord is his treasure.<note> Heb. saluations.</note></ab>

<fw>Hypocrites feare.</fw>
<ab n="7">Behold, their
valiant ones shall cry without: the ambassadours of peace shall
weepe bitterly.<note> Or, messengers.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The high wayes lye
waste; the way faring man ceaseth: he hath broken the couenant, he
hath despised the cities, he regardeth no man.</ab>
<ab n="9">The earth mourneth
and languisheth: Lebanon is ashamed and hewen downe: Sharon is like
a wildernes, and Bashan and Carmel shake off their
fruits.<note> Or, withered away.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Now will I rise,
saith the Lord: now will I be exalted, now will I lift vp my
selfe.</ab>
<ab n="11">Yee shall
conceiue chaffe, yee shall bring forth stubble: your breath as fire
shall deuoure you.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the people
shalbe as the burnings of lyme: as thornes cut vp shall they be
burnt in the fire.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Heare yee
that are farre off, what I haue done; and yee that are neere,
acknowledge my might.</ab>
<ab n="14">The sinners in
Zion are afraid, fearefulnesse hath surprised the hypocrites: who
among vs shall dwell with the deuouring fire? who amongst vs shall
dwell with euerlasting burnings?</ab>
<ab n="15">He that walketh
righteously, and speaketh vprightly, hee that despiseth the gaine
of oppressions, that shaketh his hands from holding of bribes, that
stoppeth his eares from hearing of blood, and shutteth his eyes
from seeing euill:<note> Psal.15.2. and 24. 3. , Heb. in righteousnesses. , Heb. vprightnesses. , Or, deceits. , Heb. bloods</note></ab>
<ab n="16">He shall dwell on
high: his place of defence shalbe the munitions of rocks, bread
shalbe giuen him, his waters shall be sure.<note> Heb. heights, or hie places.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Thine eyes shall
see the king in his beauty: they shall behold the land that is very
farre off.<note> Heb the land of farre distances.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Thine heart shall
meditate terrour; Where is the scribe? where is the receiuer? where
is he that counted the towres?<note> 1.Cor.1. 20. , Heb. weigher.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Thou shalt not
see a fierce people, a people of a deeper speech then thou canst
perceiue; of a stammering tongue, that thou canst not
vnderstand.<note> Or, ridiculous.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Looke vpon Zion,
the city of our solemnities: thine eyes shall see Ierusalem a quiet
habitation, a tabernacle that shall not be taken downe, not one of
the stakes thereof shall euer be remoued, neither shall any of the
coardes thereof be broken.</ab>

<fw>Against Idumea.</fw>
<ab n="21">But there the
glorious Lord will be vnto vs a place of broad riuers and streames;
wherein shall goe no galley with oares, neither shall gallant ship
passe thereby.<note> Heb. broad of spaces or hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For the Lord is
our Iudge, the Lord is our Lawgiuer, the Lord is our King, he wil
saue vs.<note> Hebr. statute-maker.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Thy tacklings are
loosed: they could not well strengthen their mast, they could not
spread the saile: then is the praye of a great spoile diuided, the
lame take the praye.<note> Or, they haue forsaken thy tacklings.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the
inhabitant shall not say; I am sicke: the people that dwel therein
shalbe forgiuen their iniquitie.</ab>



</div>