<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 The blessings of Christes
kingdome. 9 Desolation is foreshowen. 15 Restauration is promised
to succeede.</head>

<ab n="1">Behold, a King
shal reigne in righteousnes, and princes shal rule in
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="2">And a man shall be
as an hiding place from the winde, and a couert from the tempest:
as riuers of water in a drie place, as the shadow of a great rocke
in a wearie land.<note> Heb. heauie.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the eyes of
them that see, shall not be dimme; and the eares of them that
heare, shall hearken.</ab>
<ab n="4">The heart also of
the rash shall vnderstand knowledge, and the tongue of the
stammerers shall bee readie to speake plainely.<note> Heb. hastie. , Or, elegantly.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The vile person
shall be no more called liberall, nor the churle sayd to be
bountifull.</ab>
<ab n="6">For the vile
person wil speake villenie, and his heart will worke iniquitie, to
practise hypocrisie, and to vtter errour against the Lord, to make
emptie the soule of the hungry, and hee will cause the drinke of
the thirstie to faile.</ab>
<ab n="7">The instruments
also of the churle are euill: he deuiseth wicked deuices, to
destroy the poore with lying wordes, euen when the needie speaketh
right.<note> Or, when he speaketh against the poore in iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But the liberall
deuiseth liberall things, and by liberall things shall hee
stand.<note> Or, be established.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Rise vp ye
women that are at ease: heare my voice, ye carelesse daughters,
giue eare vnto my speech.</ab>
<ab n="10">Many dayes and
yeeres shall ye be troubled, yee carelesse women: for the vintage
shall faile, the gathering shall not come.<note> Heb. days aboue a yere.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Tremble yee women
that are at ease: be troubled, ye carelesse ones, strip ye and make
ye bare, and gird sackecloth vpon your loynes.</ab>
<ab n="12">They shall lament
for the teats, for the pleasant fieldes, for the fruitfull
vine.<note> Heb. the fields of desire.</note></ab>

<fw>The spoiler spoiled.</fw>
<ab n="13">Upon the land of
my people shall come vp thornes, and briars, yea vpon all the
houses of ioy in the ioyous citie.<note> Or, burning vpon. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Because the
palaces shall be forsaken, the multitude of the citie shall be
left, the forts and towres shall be for dennes for euer, a ioy of
wild asses, a pasture of flockes;<note> Or, clifts and watchtowers.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Untill the spirit
be powred vpon vs from on high, and the wildernesse be a fruitfull
field, and the fruitfull field be counted for a forrest.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then iudgement
shall dwell in the wildernesse, and righteousnesse remaine in the
fruitfull field.<note> Chap.29. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the worke of
righteousnesse shalbe peace, and the effect of righteousnesse,
quietnesse and assurance for euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">And my people
shall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in sure dwellings, and
in quiet resting places:</ab>
<ab n="19">When it shall
haile, comming downe on the forrest; and the citie shall be low in
a low place.<note> Or, and the citie shall be vtterly abased.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Blessed are yee
that sow beside all waters, that send forth thither the feete of
the oxe and the asse.</ab>



</div>