<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Gods mercifull restauration of
Israel. 4 Their triumphant insultation ouer Babel. 24 Gods purpose
against Assyria. 29 Palestina is threatned.</head>

<ab n="1">For the Lord wil
haue mercie on Iacob, and wil yet choose Israel, and set them in
their owne land: and the strangers shalbe ioyned with them, and
they shal cleaue to the house of Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the people
shall take them, and bring them to their place: and the house of
Israel shall possesse them in the land of the Lord, for seruants
and handmaides: and they shall take them captiues, whose captiues
they were, and they shall rule ouer their oppressours.<note> Hebr. that had taken them captiues.</note></ab>

<fw>The tyrants fall.</fw>
<ab n="3">And it shall come
to passe in the day that the Lord shal giue thee rest from thy
sorrow, and from thy feare, and from the hard bondage wherein thou
wast made to serue,</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ That thou
shalt take vp this prouerbe against the king of Babylon, and say;
How hath the oppressour ceased? the golden citie
ceased?<note> Or, Taunting speech. , Or, exactresse of gold.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The Lord hath
broken the staffe of the wicked, and the scepter of the
rulers.</ab>
<ab n="6">He who smote the
people in wrath with a continuall stroke; hee that ruled the
nations in anger, is persecuted and none hindereth.<note> Hebr. A stroke without remoouing.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The whole earth is
at rest and is quiet: they breake foorth into singing.</ab>
<ab n="8">Yea the firre
trees reioyce at thee, and the cedars of Lebanon, saying, Since
thou art layd downe, no feller is come vp against vs.</ab>
<ab n="9">Hell from beneath
is mooued for thee to meet thee at thy comming: it stirreth vp the
dead for thee, euen all the chiefe ones of the earth; it hath
raised vp from their thrones, all the kings of the
nations.<note> Or, the graue. , Hebr. leaders, or great goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">All they shall
speake and say vnto thee; Art thou also become weake as we? art
thou become like vnto vs?</ab>
<ab n="11">Thy pompe is
brought downe to the graue, and the noyse of thy violes: the worme
is spread vnder thee, and the wormes couer thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">How art thou
fallen from heauen, O Lucifer, sonne of the morning? how art thou
cut downe to the ground, which didst weaken the
nations?<note> Or, O daystarre.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For thou hast
said in thine heart; I wil ascend into heauen, I wil exalt my
throne aboue the starres of God: I wil sit also vpon the mount of
the congregation, in the sides of the North.</ab>
<ab n="14">I wil ascend
aboue the heights of the cloudes, I wil bee like the most
High.</ab>
<ab n="15">Yet thou shalt be
brought downe to hel, to the sides of the pit.</ab>
<ab n="16">They that see
thee shal narrowly looke vpon thee, and consider thee, saying; Is
this the man that made the earth to tremble, that did shake
kingdomes?</ab>
<ab n="17">That made the
world as a wildernesse, and destroyed the cities thereof that
opened not the house of his prisoners?<note> Or, Did not let his prisoners loose homeward.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">All the kings of
the nations, euen all of them lie in glory, euery one in his owne
house.</ab>

<fw>Against Assyria, and Moab.</fw>
<ab n="19">But thou art cast
out of thy graue, like an abominable branch: and as the raiment of
those that are slaine, thrust through with a sword, that goe downe
to the stones of the pit, as a carkeis troden vnder feete.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou shalt not be
ioyned with them in buriall, because thou hast destroyed thy land,
and slaine thy people: the seede of euill doers shall neuer be
renowmed.<note> Iob 18. 19. psal.21. 11. and 37. 28. and 109 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Prepare slaughter
for his children for the iniquitie of their fathers, that they doe
not rise nor possesse the land, nor fill the face of the world with
cities.<note> Exo.20. 5. mat.23.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For I will rise
vp against them, sayth the Lord of hostes, and cut off from Babylon
the name, and remnant, and sonne and nephew, sayth the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">I will also make
it a possession for the Bitterne, and pooles of water: and I will
sweepe it with the besome of destruction, sayth the Lord of
hostes.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ The Lord
of hostes hath sworne, saying; Surely as I haue thought, so shall
it come to passe; and as I haue purposed, so shall it
stand:</ab>
<ab n="25">That I will
breake the Assyrian in my land, and vpon my mountaines tread him
vnder foote: then shall his yoke depart from off them, and his
burden depart from off their shoulders.</ab>
<ab n="26">This is the
purpose, that is purposed vpon the whole earth: and this is the
hand that is stretched out vpon all the nations.</ab>
<ab n="27">For the Lord of
hostes hath purposed, and who shall disanull it? and his hand is
stretched out, and who shall turne it backe?<note> 2.Chron. 20.6. iob 9. 12. prou. 21.30. dan. 4.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">In the yeere that
king Ahaz died, was this burden.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Reioyce
not thou whole Palestina, because the rod of him that smote thee is
broken: for out of the serpents roote shall come foorth a
cockatrice, and his fruite shall be a fierie flying
serpent.<note> Or, Adder.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And the first
borne of the poore shall feed, and the needy shall lie downe in
safetie: and I will kill thy root with famine, and he shall slay
thy remnant.</ab>
<ab n="31">Howle, O gate,
crie, O citie, thou whole Palestina art dissolued, for there shal
come from the North a smoke, and none shall bee alone in his
appointed times.<note> Or, he shall not be alone. , Or assemblies.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Assyria, and Moab.</fw>
<ab n="32">What shall one
then answere the messengers of the nation? that the Lord hath
founded Zion, and the poore of his people shall trust in
it.<note> Psal. 87.1, 5. and 102. 17. , Or, betake themselues vnto it.</note></ab>



</div>