<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_44" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-44-44.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIV.</head>
<head>1 God comforteth the Church with his
promises. 7 The vanity of Idols, 9 and folly of Idolmakers. 21 He
exhorteth to prayse God for his redemption and
omnipotency.</head>

<ab n="1">Yet now heare, O
Iacob my seruant, and Israel whom I haue chosen.<note> Cha.41.8. and 43.5. iere.30.10. and 46.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thus sayeth the
Lord that made thee, and formed thee from the wombe, which wil
helpe thee: Feare not, O Iacob, my seruant, and thou Iesurun, whom
I haue chosen.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I will powre
water vpon him that is thirstie, and floods vpon the dry ground: I
will powre my spirit vpon thy seede, and my blessing vpon thine
offspring:<note> Cha. 35.7. ioel 2. 28. ioh.7. 38. acts 2.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And they shall
spring vp as among the grasse, as willowes by the water
courses.</ab>
<ab n="5">One shall say, I
am the Lords: and another shall call himselfe by the name of Iacob:
and another shall subscribe with his hand vnto the Lord, and
surname himselfe by the name of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thus saith the
Lord the king of Israel and his redeemer the Lord of hostes, I am
the first, and I am the last, and besides me there is no
God.<note> Cha.41.4. and 48.12. reuel.1.8, 17 and 22.13.</note></ab>

<fw>Vanitie of Idoles, and
Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="7">And who, as I,
shall call, and shall declare it, and set it in order for me, since
I appointed the ancient people? and the things that are comming,
and shall come? let them shew vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="8">Feare yee not,
neither be afraid: haue not I told thee from that time, and haue
declared it? yee are euen my witnesses. Is there a God besides me?
yea there is no God, I know not any.<note> Chap.45.5. deut.4. 35.39. and 32.39. 1.sam.2.2. , Heb. rocke.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ They that
make a grauen image are all of them vanitie, and their delectable
things shall not profit, and they are their owne witnesses, they
see not, nor know; that they may be ashamed.<note> Heb. desireable. , Psal. 115. 4. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Who hath formed a
God, or moulten a grauen image that is profitable for
nothing?</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, all his
fellowes shall be ashamed: and the workemen, they are of men: let
them all be gathered together, let them stand vp; yet they shal
feare, and they shalbe ashamed together.<note> Psal.49.7. chap.1. 29. and 42. 17. and 45. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The smith with
the tonges both worketh in the coales, and fashioneth it with
hammers, and worketh it with the strength of his armes: yea he is
hungrie, and his strength faileth; hee drinketh no water, and is
faint.<note> Ier. 10.3. wisd. 13.11 , Or, with an axe.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The carpenter
stretcheth out his rule: he maketh it out with the line: he fitteth
it with planes, and he marketh it out with the compasse, and maketh
it after the figure of a man, according to the beautie of a man;
that it may remaine in the house.</ab>
<ab n="14">He heweth him
downe cedars, and taketh the Cypresse and the Oke, which he
strengthneth for himselfe among the trees of the forrest: he
planteth an Ashe, and the raine doth nourish it.<note> Or, taketh courage.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then shall it bee
for a man to burne: for hee will take thereof and warme himselfe;
yea he kindleth it and baketh bread; yea he maketh a God, and
worshippeth it: he maketh it a grauen image, and falleth downe
thereto.</ab>
<ab n="16">He burneth part
thereof in the fire: with part thereof he eateth flesh: he rosteth
rost, and is satisfied: yea hee warmeth himselfe, and saith; Aha, I
am warme, I haue seene the fire.</ab>

<fw>Vanitie of Idoles, and
Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="17">And the residue
thereof he maketh a God, euen his grauen image: hee falleth downe
vnto it, and worshippeth it, and prayeth vnto it, and saith;
Deliuer me, for thou art my God.</ab>
<ab n="18">They haue not
knowen, nor vnderstood: for he hath shut their eyes, that they
cannot see; and their hearts, that they cannot
vnderstand.<note> Heb. dawbed.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And none
considereth in his heart, neither is there knowledge nor
vnderstanding to say; I haue burnt part of it in the fire, yea also
I haue baked bread vpon the coales thereof: I haue rosted flesh and
eaten it; and shall I make the residue thereof an abomination?
shall I fall downe to the stocke of a tree?<note> Heb. setteth to his heart. , Heb. that which comes of a tree.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">He feedeth of
ashes: a deceiued heart hath turned him aside, that he cannot
deliuer his soule, nor say; Is there not a lie in my right
hand?</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Remember
these (O Iacob and Israel) for thou art my seruant: I haue formed
thee: thou art my seruant, O Israel; thou shalt not be forgotten of
me.</ab>
<ab n="22">I haue blotted
out, as a thicke cloude, thy transgressions, and as a a cloud, thy
sinnes: returne vnto me, for I haue redeemed thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">Sing, O yee
heauens; for the Lord hath done it: shout yee lower parts of the
earth: breake forth into singing yee mountaines, O forrest and
euery tree therein: for the Lord hath redeemed Iacob, and glorified
himselfe in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="24">Thus saith the
Lord thy redeemer, and he that formed thee from the wombe; I am the
Lord that maketh all things, that stretcheth forth the heauens
alone, that spreadeth abroad the earth by my selfe:</ab>
<ab n="25">That frustrateth
the tokens of the lyers, and maketh diuiners mad, that turneth
wisemen backward, and maketh their knowledge foolish:</ab>
<ab n="26">That confirmeth
the word of his seruant, and performeth the counsell of his
messengers, that saith to Ierusalem, Thou shalt be inhabited; and
to the cities of Iudah, Yee shall be built, and I will raise vp the
decayed places thereof.<note> Heb. wastes.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">That saith to the
deepe; Be dry, and I will drie vp thy riuers.</ab>
<ab n="28">That saith of
Cyrus, Hee is my shepheard, and shall performe all my pleasure,
euen saying to Ierusalem, Thou shalt be built, and to the Temple,
Thy foundation shalbe laid.<note> 2. Chron. 36. 22. ezr. 1.1. chap. 45.13.</note></ab>



</div>