<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet sheweth the cursed
folly, in trusting to Egypt, and forsaking of God. 6 He exhorteth
to conuersion. 8 Hee sheweth the fall of Assyria.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to them that
go down to Egypt for helpe, and stay on horses, and trust in
charets, because they are many; and in horsemen, because they are
very strong: but they looke not vnto the Holy one of Israel,
neither seeke the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="2">Yet he also is
wise, and will bring euill, and wil not call backe his words: but
will arise against the house of the euill doers, and against the
helpe of them that worke iniquitie.<note> Heb. remooue.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now the Egyptians
are men and not God, and their horses flesh and not spirit: when
the Lord shall stretch out his hand, both he that helpeth shall
fall, and hee that is holpen shall fall downe, and they all shall
faile together.</ab>
<ab n="4">For thus hath the
Lord spoken vnto me; Like as the lyon and the yong lyon roaring on
his pray, when a multitude of shepheards is called foorth against
him, he will not be afraid of their voice, nor abase himselfe for
the noyse of them: so shall the Lord of hostes come downe to fight
for mount Zion, and for the hill thereof.<note> Or, multitude.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">As birds flying,
so wil the Lord of hostes defend Ierusalem, defending also hee will
deliuer it, and passing ouer, he will preserue it.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Turne yee
vnto him from whom the children of Israel haue deeply
reuolted.</ab>
<ab n="7">For in that day
euery man shall cast away his idoles of siluer, and his idoles of
gold, which your owne hands haue made vnto you for a
sinne.<note> Cha.2.20. , Heb. the idoles of his golde.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then shall
the Assyrian fall with the sword, not of a mightie man; and the
sword, not of a meane man, shal deuoure him: but hee shall flee
from the sword, and his young men shall be discomfited.<note> Or, for feare of the sword. , Or, tributarie: hebr. for melting, or tribute.</note></ab>

<fw>Good rulers.</fw>
<ab n="9">And hee shall
passe ouer to his strong holde for feare, and his princes shall be
afraid of the ensigne, sayth the Lord, whose fire is in Zion, and
his fornace in Ierusalem.<note> Or, his strength: heb. rocke shall passe away for feare.</note></ab>



</div>