<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 Gods heauy iudgement vpon
Ierusalem. 7 The vnsatiablenesse of her enemies. 9 The
sencelesnesse, 13 and deepe hypocrisie of the Iewes. 18 A promise
of sanctification to the godly.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to Ariel, to
Ariel the citie where Dauid dwelt: adde yee yeere to yeere; let
them kill sacrifices.<note> Or, oh Ariel that is the lyon of God: Or, of the citie. , Heb. cut off the heads.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Yet I will
distresse Ariel, and there shalbe heauinesse and sorrow; and it
shall be vnto mee as Ariel.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I will campe
against thee round about, and will lay siege against thee with a
mount, and I will raise forts against thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">And thou shalt bee
brought downe, and shalt speake out of the ground, and thy speach
shall be low out of the dust, and thy voyce shalbe as of one that
hath a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and thy speach shall
whisper out of the dust.<note> Heb. peepe or chirpe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer the
multitude of thy strangers shalbe like small dust, and the
multitude of the terrible ones shalbe as chaffe, that passeth away;
yea it shalbe at an instant suddenly.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thou shalt bee
visited of the Lord of hostes with thunder, and with earthquake,
and great noise, with storme and tempest, and the flame of
deuouring fire.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And the
multitude of all the nations that fight against Ariel, euen all
that fight against her and her munition, and that distresse her,
shalbe as a dreame of a night vision.</ab>
<ab n="8">It shall euen be
as when a hungry man dreameth, and behold he eateth; but he
awaketh, and his soule is emptie: or as when a thirstie man
dreameth, and behold he drinketh; but hee awaketh, and behold he is
faint, and his soule hath appetite: so shall the multitude of all
the nations bee, that fight against mount Zion.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Stay your
selues and wonder, cry yee out, and cry: they are drunken, but not
with wine, they stagger, but not with strong drinke.<note> Or, take your pleasure and riot.</note></ab>

<fw>Hypocrites, and rebellious
children.</fw>
<ab n="10">For the Lord hath
powred out vpon you the spirit of deepe sleepe, and hath closed
your eyes: the Prophets and your rulers, the Seers hath hee
couered.<note> Heb. heads.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the vsion of
all is become vnto you, as the wordes of a booke that is sealed,
which men deliuer to one that is learned, saying, Reade this, I
pray thee: and hee saith, I cannot, for it is sealed.<note> Or, letter.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the booke is
deliuered to him that is not learned, saying, Reade this, I pray
thee: and he saith, I am not learned.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Wherefore
the Lord said, Forasmuch as this people draw neere mee with their
mouth, and with their lips doe honour me, but haue remoued their
heart farre from me, and their feare towards mee is taught by the
precept of men:<note> Matth.15. 8. mar.7.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore behold,
I will proceed to do a marueilous worke amongst this people, euen a
marueilous worke and a wonder: for the wisedome of their wise men
shall perish, and the vnderstanding of their prudent men shall be
hid.<note> Heb. I will adde. , Ier.49.7. obad.ver.8. 1.cor.1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Woe vnto them
that seeke deepe to hide their counsell from the Lord, and their
workes are in the darke, and they say, Who seeth vs? and who
knoweth vs?<note> Ecclus.23. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Surely your
turning of things vpside downe shall be esteemed as the potters
clay: for shall the worke say of him that made it, He made me not?
or shall the thing framed, say of him that framed it, He had no
vnderstanding?<note> Isa.45. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Is it not yet a
very litle while, and Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful
field, and the fruitfull field shall be esteemed as a
forrest?</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And in
that day shall the deafe heare the words of the booke, and the eyes
of the blind shall see out of obscuritie, and out of
darkenesse.</ab>
<ab n="19">The meeke also
shall increase their ioy in the Lord, and the poore among men shall
reioice in the holy One of Israel.<note> Heb. shall adde.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For the terrible
one is brought to nought, and the scorner is consumed, and all that
watch for iniquitie are cut off:</ab>
<ab n="21">That make a man
an offendour for a word, and lay a snare for him that reproueth in
the gate, and turne aside the iust for a thing of nought.</ab>

<fw>Hypocrites, and rebellious
children.</fw>
<ab n="22">Therefore thus
saith the Lord who redeemed Abraham, concerning the house of Iacob:
Iacob shall not now be ashamed, neither shall his face now waxe
pale.</ab>
<ab n="23">But when hee
seeth his children the worke of mine hands in the midst of him,
they shall sanctifie my Name, and sanctifie the Holy One of Iacob,
and shall feare the God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="24">They also that
erred in spirit shall come to vnderstanding, and they that
murmured, shall learne doctrine.<note> Hebr. shall know understanding.</note></ab>



</div>