<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 The miserable ouerthrow of Tyre.
17 Their vnhappie returne.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of
Tyre. Howle yee ships of Tarshish, for it is laide waste, so that
there is no house, no entring in: from the land of Chittim it is
reuealed to them.</ab>
<ab n="2">Be still, yee
inhabitants of the yle, thou whom the merchants of Zidon, that
passe ouer the sea, haue replenished.<note> Heb. silent.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And by great
waters the seede of Sihor, the haruest of the riuer is her reuenew,
and she is a mart of nations.</ab>
<ab n="4">Be thou ashamed, O
Zidon; for the sea hath spoken, euen the strength of the sea,
saying; I trauell not, nor bring foorth children, neither doe I
nourish vp yong men, nor bring vp virgines.</ab>
<ab n="5">As at the report
concerning Egypt, so shal they be sorely pained at the report of
Tyre.</ab>
<ab n="6">Passe ye ouer to
Tarshish, howle ye inhabitants of the yle.</ab>
<ab n="7">Is this your
ioyous citie, whose antiquitie is of ancient dayes? her owne feete
shall cary her afarre off to soiourne.<note> Heb. from afarre off.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Tyre.</fw>
<ab n="8">Who hath taken
this counsell against Tyre the crowning citie, whose merchants are
princes, whose traffiquers are the honourable of the earth?</ab>
<ab n="9">The Lord of hostes
hath purposed it, to staine the pride of all glory, and to bring
into contempt all the honorable of the earth.<note> Heb. to pollute.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Passe through thy
land as a riuer O daughter of Tarshish: there is no more
strength.<note> Heb. girdle</note></ab>
<ab n="11">He stretched out
his hand ouer the sea, hee shooke the kingdomes: the Lord hath
giuen a commandement against the merchant citie, to destroy the
strong holdes thereof.<note> Or, concerning a merchant man. Heb. Canaan. , Or, strengths.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And he said, Thou
shalt no more reioice, O thou oppressed virgin, daughter of Zidon:
arise, passe ouer to Chittim, there also shalt thou haue no
rest.</ab>
<ab n="13">Behold, the land
of the Caldeans, this people was not till the Assyrian founded it
for them that dwel in the wildernesse: they set vp the towers
thereof, they raised vp the palaces thereof, and he brought it to
ruine.</ab>
<ab n="14">Howle ye ships of
Tarshish: for your strength is laid waste.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it shall come
to passe in that day, that Tyre shall be forgotten seuentie yeeres
according to the dayes of one king: after the end of seuentie
yeeres shall Tyre sing as an harlot.<note> Heb. it shal be vnto Tyre as the song of an harlot.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Take an harpe,
goe about the city thou harlot, that hast beene forgotten, make
sweet melody, sing many songs, that thou mayest be
remembred.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And it
shall come to passe after the ende of seuentie yeeres, that the
Lord will visite Tyre, and shee shall turne to her hire, and shall
commit fornication with all the kingdomes of the world vpon the
face of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">And her
merchandize and her hire shall be holinesse to the Lord: it shall
not be treasured nor laid vp: for her merchandize shalbe for them
that dwell before the Lord, to eate sufficiently, and for durable
clothing.<note> Heb. olde.</note></ab>



</div>