<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-17-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Syria and Israel are threatned. 6
A remnant shall forsake idolatrie. 9 The rest shalbe plagued for
their impietie. 12 The woe of Israels enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of
Damascus: Behold, Damascus is taken away from being a citie, and it
shalbe a ruinous heape.</ab>
<ab n="2">The cities of
Aroer are forsaken: they shall bee for flockes, which shall lye
downe, and none shall make them afraid.</ab>
<ab n="3">The fortresse also
shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdome from Damascus, and the
remnant of Syria: they shall bee as the glorie of the children of
Israel, saith the Lord of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And in that day it
shall come to passe, that the glory of Iacob shall bee made thinne,
and the fatnesse of his flesh shall waxe leane.</ab>
<ab n="5">And it shall be as
when the haruest-man gathereth the corne, and reapeth the eares
with his arme; and it shalbe as he that gathereth eares in the
valley of Rephaim.</ab>
<ab n="6">(¶ Yet
gleaning-grapes shall be left in it, as the shaking of an Oliue
tree, two or three berries in the toppe of the vppermost bough:
foure or fiue in the out-most fruitfull branches thereof, saith the
Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">At that day shall
a man looke to his Maker, and his eyes shall haue respect to the
Holy one of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee shall not
looke to the altars, the worke of his handes, neither shall respect
that which his fingers haue made, either the groues or the
images.)<note> Or, Sunne-images.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Ethiopia, and Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ In that day
shall his strong cities be as a forsaken bough, and an vppermost
branch, which they left, because of the children of Israel: and
there shalbe desolation.</ab>
<ab n="10">Because thou hast
forgotten the God of thy saluation, and hast not beene mindfull of
the rocke of thy strength: therefore shalt thou plant pleasant
plants, and shalt set it with strange slips.</ab>
<ab n="11">In the day shalt
thou make thy plant to grow, and in the morning shalt thou make thy
seede to flourish: but the haruest shall be a heape in the day of
griefe, and of desperate sorrow.<note> Or, remoued in the day of inheritance, and there shalbe deadly sorrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Woe to the
multitude of many people, which make a noise, like the noise of the
seas; and to the rushing of nations, that make a rushing, like the
rushing of mighty waters.<note> Or, noise. , Or, many.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The nations shall
rush like the rushing of many waters: but God shall rebuke them,
and they shall flee farre off, and shalbe chased as the chaffe of
the mountaines before the wind, and like a rolling thing before the
whirlewind.<note> Or, thistledowne.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And behold at
euening tide trouble, and before the morning he is not: this is the
portion of them that spoile vs, and the lot of them that robbe
vs.</ab>



</div>