<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The great confusion which commeth
by sinne. 9 The impudencie of the people. 12 The oppression and
couetousnesse of the rulers. 16 The iudgements which shall be for
the pride of the women.</head>

<ab n="1">For behold,
the Lord, the Lord of hostes doeth take away from Ierusalem, and
from Iudah, the stay and the staffe, the whole stay of bread, and
the whole stay of water,</ab>
<ab n="2">The mighty
man, and the man of warre; the Iudge and the Prophet, and the
prudent, and the ancient,</ab>

<fw>Of oppression.</fw>
<ab n="3">The captaine
of fiftie, and the honourable man, and the counseller, and the
cunning artificer, and the eloquent oratour.<note> Hebr. A man eminent in countenance. , Or, skilfull of speech.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I will
giue children to bee their Princes, and babes shall rule ouer
them.<note> Eccles. 10. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the
people shall be oppressed, euery one by another, and euery one by
his neighbour: the childe shall behaue himselfe proudly against the
ancient, and the base against the honourable.</ab>
<ab n="6">When a man
shall take hold of his brother of the house of his father, saying,
Thou hast clothing, be thou our ruler, and let this ruine bee vnder
thy hand:</ab>
<ab n="7">In that day
shall he sweare, saying, I will not be an healer: for in my house
is neither bread nor clothing: make me not a ruler of the
people.<note> Hebr. lift vp the hand. , Hebr. binder vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For Ierusalem
is ruined, &amp; Iudah is fallen: because their tongue and their
doings are against the Lord, to prouoke the eyes of his
glorie.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ The
shew of their countenance doeth witnesse against them, and they
declare their sinne as Sodom, they hide it not: woe vnto their
soule, for they haue rewarded euill vnto themselues.<note> Gen. 13. 13. and 18. 21. and 19. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Say yee to the
righteous, that it shall be well with him: for they shall eate the
fruit of their doings.</ab>
<ab n="11">Woe vnto the
wicked, it shall be ill with him: for the reward of his handes
shalbe giuen him.<note> Hebr. done to him.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ As for my
people, children are their oppressours, and women rule ouer them: O
my people, they which lead thee, cause thee to erre, and destroy
the way of thy paths.<note> Or, they which call thee blessed. , Hebr. swallow vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The Lord standeth
vp to plead, and standeth to iudge the people.</ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord will
enter into iudgement with the ancients of his people, and the
Princes thereof: for ye haue eaten vp the Uineyard; the spoile of
the poore is in your houses.<note> Or, burnt.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">What meane yee
that yee beat my people to pieces, and grinde the faces of the
poore, saith the Lord God of hosts?</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Moreouer
the Lord saith; Because the daughters of Zion are hautie, and walke
with stretched forth necks, and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as
they goe, and making a tinkeling with their feet:<note> Hebr. deceiuing with their eyes. , Or, tripping nicely.</note></ab>

<fw>Womens pride.</fw>
<ab n="17">Therefore the Lord
will smite with a scab the crowne of the head of the daughters of
Zion, and the Lord will discouer their secret parts.<note> Heb. make naked.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">In that day the
Lord will take away the brauery of their tinckling ornaments about
their feete, and their caules, and their round tyres like the
Moone.<note> Or, networkes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The chaines, and
the bracelets, and the mufflers,<note> Or, sweetballes. , Or, spangled ornaments.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The bonnets, and
the ornaments of the legges, and the headbands, and the tablets,
and the earerings,<note> Heb. houses of the soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The rings, and
nose-iewels,</ab>
<ab n="22">The changeable
sutes of apparell, and the mantles, and the wimples, and the
crisping pinnes,</ab>
<ab n="23">The glasses, and
the fine linnen, and the hoods, and the vailes.</ab>
<ab n="24">And it shall come
to passe, that in steade of sweete smell, there shall bee stinke;
and in stead of a girdle, a rent; and in stead of well set haire,
baldnesse; and in stead of a stomacher, a girding of sackecloth;
and burning, in stead of beautie.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thy men shall fall
by the sword, and thy mightie in the warre.<note> Heb. might</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And her gates
shall lament and mourne; and she being desolate, shall sit vpon the
ground.<note> Or, emptied: hebr. cleansed.</note></ab>



</div>