<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_59" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-57-59.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-59-60.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LIX.</head>
<head>1 The damnable nature of sinne. 3
The sinnes of the Iewes. 9 Calamitie is for sinne. 16 Saluation is
onely of God. 20 The couenant of the Redeemer.</head>

<ab n="1">Beholde, the Lords
hand is not shortened, that it cannot saue: neither his eare
heauie, that it cannot heare.<note> Num.11.23. chap.50.2.</note></ab>

<fw>The Iewes sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="2">But your
iniquities haue separated betweene you and your God, and your
sinnes haue hid his face from you, that he will not
heare.<note> Or, haue made him hide.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For your hands are
defiled with blood, and your fingers with iniquitie, your lippes
haue spoken lies, your tongue hath muttered
peruersnesse.<note> Chap. 1. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">None calleth for
iustice, nor any pleadeth for trueth: they trust in vanity and
speake lies; they conceiue mischiefe, and bring forth
iniquitie.<note> Iob. 15. 35. psal. 7. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">They hatch
cockatrice egges, and weaue the spiders web: he that eateth of
their egges dieth, and that which is crushed breaketh out into a
viper.<note> Or, adders. , Or, that which is sprinkled is as if there brake out a viper.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Their webbes shall
not become garments, neither shall they couer themselues with their
workes: their workes are workes of iniquitie, and the act of
violence is in their hands.<note> Iob.8.14, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Their feete runne
to euill, and they make haste to shed innocent blood: their
thoughts are thoughts of iniquity, wasting &amp; destruction are in
their paths.<note> Prou.1.15 rom.3.15. , Heb. breaking.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The way of peace
they know not, and there is no iudgement in their goings: they haue
made them crooked pathes; whosoeuer goeth therein, shall not know
peace.<note> Or, right.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Therefore
is iudgement farre from vs, neither doth iustice ouertake vs: we
waite for light, but behold obscuritie, for brightnesse, but we
walke in darknesse.</ab>
<ab n="10">We grope for the
wall like the blind, and we grope as if we had no eies: we stumble
at noone day as in the night, we are in desolate places as dead
men.</ab>
<ab n="11">We roare all like
beares, and mourne sore like doues: we looke for iudgement, but
there is none; for saluation, but it is farre off from vs.</ab>
<ab n="12">For our
transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our sinnes testifie
against vs: for our transgressions are with vs, and as for our
iniquities, we know them:</ab>
<ab n="13">In transgressing
and lying against the Lord, and departing away from our God,
speaking oppression and reuolt, conceiuing and vttering from the
heart words of falshood.</ab>
<ab n="14">And iudgement is
turned away backward, and iustice standeth a farre off: for truth
is fallen in the streete, and equitie cannot enter.</ab>

<fw>The iust is a pray.</fw>
<ab n="15">Yea truth
faileth, and he that departeth from euill maketh himselfe a pray:
and the Lord saw it, and it displeased him, that there was no
iudgement.<note> Or, is accounted mad , Heb. it was euill in his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And hee
saw that there was no man, and wondered that there was no
intercessour. Therefore his arme brought saluation vnto him, and
his righteousnesse, it sustained him.<note> Chap. 63. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For he put on
righteousnesse as a brestplate, and an helmet of saluation vpon his
head; and he put on the garments of vengeance for clothing, and was
clad with zeale as a cloake.<note> Ephes 6.17. 1.thes. 5.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">According to
their deedes accordingly he will repay, furie to his aduersaries,
recompence to his enemies, to the ylands he will repay
recompence.<note> Chap.63. 7. , Heb. recompenses.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">So shall they
feare the name of the Lord from the West, and his glory from the
rising of the sunne: when the enemie shall come in like a flood,
the spirit of the Lord shall lift vp a standard against
him.<note> Reu.12. 15. , Or, put him to flight.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
redeemer shall come to Zion, and vnto them that turne from
transgression in Iacob, saith the Lord.<note> Rom.11. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">As for me, this
is my couenant with them, saith the Lord; My spirit that is vpon
thee, and my words which I haue put in thy mouth, shall not depart
out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of the seede, nor out of the
mouth of thy seedes seed, saith the Lord, from henceforth, and for
euer.</ab>



</div>