<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>The lamentable state of
Moab.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of
Moab: because in the night Ar of Moab is laide waste and brought to
silence; because in the night Kir of Moab is laide waste, and
brought to silence:<note> Or, cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Hee is gone vp to
Baijth, and to Dibon, the high places, to weepe: Moab shall howle
ouer Nebo, and ouer Medeba, on all their heads shalbe baldnesse,
and euery beard cut off.<note> Ier.48.37, 38. ezek.7. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">In their streetes
they shall girde themselues with sackecloth: on the toppes of their
houses, and in their streetes euery one shall howle, weeping
abundantly.<note> Heb. descending into weeping: or, comming downe with weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Heshbon shall
cry, and Elealeh: their voice shalbe heard euen vnto Iahaz:
therefore the armed souldiers of Moab shall crie out, his life
shall be grieuous vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="5">My heart shall cry
out for Moab; his fugitiues shall flee vnto Zoar, an heifer of
three yeeres olde: for by the mounting vp of Luhith with weeping
shall they goe it vp: for in the way of Horonaim, they shall raise
vp a crie of destruction.<note> Or, to the borders thereof euen to Zoar as an heifer. , Iere.48. 5, 34. , Heb. breaking.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For the waters of
Nimrim shall be desolate: for the hay is withered away, the grasse
faileth, there is no greene thing.<note> Heb. desolations.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore the
abundance they haue gotten, and that which they haue laide vp,
shall they cary away to the brooke of the willowes.<note> Or, valley of the Arabians.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For the cry is
gone round about the borders of Moab: the howling thereof vnto
Eglaim, and the howling thereof vnto Beer-Elim.</ab>
<ab n="9">For the waters of
Dimon shalbe full of blood: for I will bring more vpon Dimon, lyons
vpon him that escapeth of Moab, and vpon the remnant of the
land.<note> Heb. additions.</note></ab>



</div>