<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-20-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet lamenteth the inuasion
of Iury by the Persians. 8 He reproueth their humane wisedome and
worldly ioy. 15 Hee prophesieth Shebnaes depriuation, 20 and
Eliakim prefiguring the kingdome of Christ, his
substitution.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of the
valley of vision. What ayleth thee now, that thou art wholly gone
vp to the house toppes?</ab>
<ab n="2">Thou that art full
of stirres, a tumultuous citie, a ioyous citie: thy slaine men are
not slaine with the sword, nor dead in battell.</ab>
<ab n="3">All thy rulers are
fled together, they are bound by the archers: all that are found in
thee are bound together, which haue fled from farre.<note> Heb. of the bow.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore sayd I;
Looke away from me, I will weepe bitterly, labour not to comfort
me; because of the spoiling of the daughter of my
people.<note> Ier.4.19. and 9.1. , Heb. I will be bitter in weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For it is a day of
trouble, and of treading downe, and of perplexitie by the Lord God
of hostes in the valley of vision, breaking downe the walles, and
of crying to the mountaines.</ab>

<fw>Feasting for fasting.</fw>
<ab n="6">And Elam bare the
quiuer with charets of men and horsemen, and Kir vncouered the
shield.<note> Heb. made naked.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And it shall come
to passe that thy choicest valleys shall be full of charets, and
the horsemen shall set themselues in aray at the gate.<note> Heb. the choice of the valleys. , Or, towards.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And he
discouered the couering of Iudah, and thou diddest looke in that
day to the armour of the house of the forrest.</ab>
<ab n="9">Ye haue seene also
the breaches of the citie of Dauid, that they are many: and ye
gathered together the waters of the lower poole.</ab>
<ab n="10">And ye haue
numbred the houses of Ierusalem, and the houses haue yee broken
downe to fortifie the wall.</ab>
<ab n="11">Ye made also a
ditch betweene the two walles, for the water of the olde poole: but
ye haue not looked vnto the maker thereof, neither had respect vnto
him that fashioned it long agoe.</ab>
<ab n="12">And in that day
did the Lord God of hostes call to weeping and to mourning, and to
baldnesse, and to girding with sackecloth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And behold ioy
and gladnesse, slaying oxen and killing sheep, eating flesh, and
drinking wine; let vs eate and drinke, for to morrow we shall
die.<note> Chap. 56. 12. wisd. 2. 6. 1.cor.15. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And it was
reuealed in mine eares by the Lord of hostes; surely this iniquitie
shall not be purged from you, till yee die, sayth the Lord God of
hostes.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Thus sayth
the Lord God of hostes, Goe, get thee vnto this treasurer, euen
vnto Shebna, which is ouer the house, and say;</ab>
<ab n="16">What hast thou
here? And whom hast thou here, that thou hast hewed thee out a
sepulchre here, as hee that heweth him out a sepulchre on high, and
that graueth an habitation for himselfe in a rocke?<note> Or, O hee.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Behold; the Lord
will cary thee away with a mightie captiuitie, and will surely
couer thee.<note> Or, the Lord who couered thee with an excellent couering, and clothed thee gorgeously, v. 18. shall surely, &amp;c. , Heb. the captiuitie of a man.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">He will surely
violently turne and tosse thee, like a ball into a large countrey:
there shalt thou die, and there the charets of thy glory shall be
the shame of thy Lords house.<note> Heb. large of spaces.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And I will driue
thee from thy station, and from thy state shall he pull thee
downe.</ab>

<fw>The key of Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="20">¶ And it
shall come to passe in that day, that I will call my seruant
Eliakim the sonne of Hilkiah:</ab>
<ab n="21">And I will clothe
him with thy robe, and strengthen him with thy girdle, and I wil
commit thy gouernment into his hand, and he shalbe a father to the
inhabitants of Ierusalem, and to the house of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the key of
the house of Dauid will I lay vpon his shoulder: so he shall open
and none shall shut, and he shall shut and none shall
open.<note> Iob 12.14 reue.3.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And I will fasten
him as a naile in asure place, and he shalbe for a glorious throne
to his fathers house.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they shall
hang vpon him all the glory of his fathers house, the offspring and
the issue, all vessels of small quantitie: from the vessels of
cups, euen to all the vessels of flagons.<note> Or, instruments of violes.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">In that day,
sayth the Lord of hostes, shall the naile that is fastened in the
sure place, be remooued, and be cut downe and fall: and the burden
that was vpon it shall bee cut off: for the Lord hath spoken
it.</ab>



</div>