<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_47" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-45-47.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVII.</head>
<head>1 Gods iudgement vpon Babylon and
Caldæa, 6 for their vnmercifulnesse, 7 pride, 10 and
ouerboldnes, 11 shalbe vnresistable.</head>

<ab n="1">Come downe and sit
in the dust: O virgin daughter of Babylon, sit on the ground: there
is no throne, O daughter of the Caldeans: for thou shalt no more be
called tender and delicate.</ab>
<ab n="2">Take the milstones
and grinde meale, vncouer thy lockes: make bare the legge: vncouer
the thigh, passe ouer the riuers.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thy nakednes
shalbe vncouered, yea thy shame shalbe seene: I will take
vengeance, and I will not meet thee as a man.</ab>
<ab n="4">As for our
redeemer, the Lord of hostes is his Name, the Holy one of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">Sit thou silent,
and get thee into darknes, O daughter of the Caldeans: for thou
shalt no more be called the Ladie of kingdomes.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ I was wroth
with my people: I haue polluted mine inheritance, and giuen them
into thine hand: thou didst shew them no mercy; vpon the ancient
hast thou very heauily layed the yoke.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And thou
saydst, I shall bee a Ladie for euer: so that thou didst not lay
these things to thy heart, neither didst remember the later end of
it.<note> Reue.18.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore heare
now this, thou that art giuen to pleasures, that dwellest
carelesly, that sayest in thine heart, I am, and none else besides
mee, I shall not sit as a widow, neither shall I know the losse of
children.</ab>
<ab n="9">But these two
things shall come to thee in a moment in one day; the losse of
children, and widowhood; they shall come vpon thee in their
perfection, for the multitude of thy sorceries, and for the great
abundance of thine inchantments.<note> Chap. 51. 19.</note></ab>

<fw>Vaine sciences.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ For thou
hast trusted in thy wickednesse: thou hast said, None seeth me. Thy
wisedome and thy knowledge, it hath peruerted thee, and thou hast
said in thine heart, I am, and none else besides me.<note> Or, caused thee to turne away.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Therefore
shall euill come vpon thee, thou shalt not know from whence it
riseth: and mischiefe shall fall vpon thee, thou shalt not be able
to put it off: and desolation shall come vpon thee suddenly, which
thou shalt not know.<note> Heb. the morning thereof. , Heb. expiate.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Stand now with
thine inchantments, and with the multitude of thy sorceries,
wherein thou hast laboured from thy youth; if so be thou shalt be
able to profite, if so be thou mayest preuaile.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou art wearied
in the multitude of thy counsels: let now the astrologers, the
starre-gazers, the monethly prognosticators stand vp, and saue thee
from these things that shall come vpon thee.<note> Heb. viewers of the heauens. , Heb. that giue knowledge concerning the moneths.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, they
shall be as stubble: the fire shall burne them, they shall not
deliuer themselues from the power of the flame: there shall not bee
a coale to warme at, nor fire to sit before it.<note> Heb. their soules.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Thus shal they be
vnto thee with whom thou hast laboured, euen thy merchants from thy
youth, they shall wander euery one to his quarter: none shall saue
thee.</ab>



</div>