<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_49" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-48-49.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-49-50.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIX.</head>
<head>1 Christ being sent to the Iewes,
complaineth of them. 5 He is sent to the Gentiles, with gracious
promises. 13 Gods loue is perpetuall to his Church. 18 The ample
restauration of the Church. 24 The powerfull deliuerance out of
captiuity.</head>

<ab n="1">Listen, O yles,
vnto me, and hearken yee people from farre. The Lord hath called
mee from the wombe, from the bowels of my mother hath he made
mention of my name.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he hath made
my mouth like a sharpe sword, in the shadow of his hand hath he hid
me, and made mee a polished shaft; in his quiuer hath hee hid
me,</ab>
<ab n="3">And sayd vnto me;
Thou art my seruant, O Israel, in whom I will be glorified.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then I said; I
haue laboured in vaine, I haue spent my strength for nought, and in
vaine, yet surely my iudgement is with the Lord, and my worke with
my God.<note> Or, my reward.</note></ab>

<fw>Christ appointed.</fw>
<ab n="5">¶ And now,
saith the Lord that formed me from the wombe to be his seruant, to
bring Iacob againe to him; Though Israel be not gathered, yet shall
I be glorious in the eyes of the Lord, and my God shall bee my
strength.<note> Or, that Israel may be gathered to him, and I may &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he said, It is
a light thing that thou shouldest be my seruant to raise vp the
tribes of Iacob, and to restore the preserued of Israel: I will
also giue thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayest be my
saluation, vnto the end of the earth.<note> Or, art thou lighter, then that thou shouldest &amp;c. , Or, desolations. , Chap.42. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thus saith the
Lord the redeemer of Israel, and his holy one, to him whom man
dispiseth, to him whom the nation abhorreth, to a seruant of
rulers; Kings shall see and arise, princes also shall worship,
because of the Lord, that is faithfull, and the holy one of Israel,
and he shall choose thee.<note> Or, to him that is despised in soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Thus saith the
Lord, In an acceptable time haue I heard thee, and in a day of
saluation haue I helped thee: and I will preserue thee, and giue
thee for a couenant of the people, to establish the earth, to cause
to inherite the desolate heritages:<note> 1.Cor.6. 2. , Or, raise vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">That thou mayest
say to the prisoners, Goe forth; to them that are in darkenesse,
Shewe your selues: they shall feede in the wayes, and their
pastures shalbe in all high places.<note> Chap.42. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They shall not
hunger nor thirst, neither shall the heate nor sunne smite them:
for he that hath mercy on them shall lead them, euen by the springs
of water shall he guide them.<note> Reu.7.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I will make
all my mountaines a way, and my high wayes shall be
exalted.</ab>
<ab n="12">Behold, these
shall come from far: and loe, these from the North and from the
West, and these from the land of Sinim.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Sing, O
heauen, and be ioyfull, O earth, and breake forth into singing, O
mountaines: for God hath comforted his people, and will haue mercy
vpon his afflicted.</ab>
<ab n="14">But Zion said,
The Lord hath forsaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me.</ab>
<ab n="15">Can a woman
forget her sucking child, that she should not haue compassion on
the sonne of her wombe? yea they may forget, yet will I not forget
thee.<note> Heb. from hauing compassion.</note></ab>

<fw>Gentiles called.</fw>
<ab n="16">Behold, I haue
grauen thee vpon the palmes of my hands: thy walles are continually
before mee.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thy children shal
make haste, thy destroyers, and they that made thee waste, shall
goe forth of thee.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Lift vp
thine eyes round about, and behold: all these gather themselues
together and come to thee: as I liue, saith the Lord, thou shalt
surely clothe thee with them all, as with an ornament, and bind
them on thee as a bride doeth.<note> Chap. 60. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For thy waste and
thy desolate places, and the land of thy destruction shall euen now
be too narrow by reason of the inhabitants, and they that swallowed
thee vp, shall bee farre away.</ab>
<ab n="20">The children
which thou shalt haue, after thou hast lost the other, shall say
againe in thine eares, The place is too straight for me: giue place
to mee that I may dwell.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then shalt thou
say in thine heart, Who hath begotten me these, seeing I haue lost
my children and am desolate, a captiue and remouing to and fro? and
who hath brought vp these? Beholde, I was left alone, these where
had they beene?</ab>
<ab n="22">Thus saith the
Lord God, Behold, I will lift vp mine hand to the Gentiles, and set
vp my standerd to the people: and they shall bring thy sonnes in
their armes: and thy daughters shal be caried vpon their
shoulders.<note> Hebr. bosome.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And kings shall
be thy nursing fathers, and their queenes thy nursing mothers: they
shall bow downe to thee with their face toward the earth, and licke
vp the dust of thy feete, and thou shalt know that I am the Lord:
for they shall not be ashamed that waite for me.<note> Heb. nourishers. , Heb. Princesses. , Psal.72.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Shall the
pray be taken from the mightie, or the lawfull captiue
deliuered?<note> Hebr. the captiuitie of the iust.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But thus saith
the Lord, Euen the captiues of the mightie shall be taken away, and
the pray of the terrible shall be deliuered: for I will contend
with him that contendeth with thee, and I will saue thy
children.<note> Heb. captiuitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And I will feede
them that oppresse thee, with their owne flesh, and they shall be
drunken with their owne blood, as with sweet wine: and all flesh
shall know that I the Lord am thy Sauiour and thy Redeemer, the
mightie One of Iacob.<note> Reu.14. 20. and 16. 6. , Or, new wine.</note></ab>



</div>