<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 The care of God ouer his vineyard.
7 His chastisements differ from iudgements. 12 The Church of Iewes
and Gentiles.</head>

<ab n="1">In that day the
Lord with his sore and great and strong sworde shall punish
Leuiathan the piercing serpent, euen Leuiathan that crooked
serpent, and hee shall slay the dragon that is in the
Sea.<note> Or, crossing like a barre.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">In that day, sing
yee vnto her; A vineyard of red wine.</ab>
<ab n="3">I the Lord doe
keepe it; I will water it euery moment: lest any hurt it, I will
keepe it night and day.</ab>
<ab n="4">Furie is not in
mee: who would set the briars and thornes against me in battell? I
would goe through them, I would burne them together.<note> Or, march against.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Or let him take
holde of my strength, that he may make peace with me, and he shall
make peace with me.</ab>
<ab n="6">Hee shall cause
them that come of Iacob to take roote: Israel shall blossome and
budde, and fill the face of the world with fruite.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Hath hee
smitten him, as hee smote those that smote him? or is hee slaine
according to the slaughter of them that are slaine by
him?<note> Heb. according to the stroke of those.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">In measure when it
shooteth foorth, thou wilt debate with it: hee stayeth his rough
winde in the day of the East winde.<note> Or, when thou sendest it foorth. , Or, when he remoueth it.</note></ab>

<fw>Iacob purged.</fw>
<ab n="9">By this therefore
shall the iniquitie of Iacob be purged, and this is all the fruit,
to take away his sinne: when he maketh all the stones of the Altar
as chalke stones, that are beaten in sunder, the groues and images
shall not stand vp.<note> Or, Sunne images.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yet the defenced
citie shall be desolate, and the habitation forsaken, and left like
a wildernesse: there shall the calfe feede, and there shall he lie
downe, and consume the branches thereof.</ab>
<ab n="11">When the boughes
thereof are withered, they shall be broken off: the women come and
set them on fire: for it is a people of no vnderstanding: therefore
hee that made them will not haue mercie on them, and hee that
formed them, will shewe them no fauour.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And it
shall come to passe in that day, that the Lord shall beate off from
the chanell of the riuer vnto the streame of Egypt, and ye shall
bee gathered one by one, O ye children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it shall come
to passe in that day, that the great trumpet shall bee blowen, and
they shall come which were ready to perish in the land of Assyria,
and the outcasts in the land of Egypt, and shall worship the Lord
in the holy mount at Ierusalem.</ab>



</div>