<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-17-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 The confusion of Egypt. 11 The
folishnesse of their Princes. 18 The calling of Egypt to the
Church. 23 The couenant of Egypt, Assyria and Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of
Egypt: Behold, the Lord rideth vpon a swift cloude, and shall come
into Egypt, and the idoles of Egypt shalbe moued at his presence,
and the heart of Egypt shall melt in the midst of it.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I will set the
Egyptians against the Egyptians: and they shall fight euery one
against his brother, and euery one against his neighbour; citie
against citie, and kingdome against kingdome.<note> Heb. mingle.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the spirit of
Egypt shall faile in the midst thereof, and I will destroy the
counsell thereof: and they shall seeke to the idoles, and to the
charmers, and to them that haue familiar spirits, and to the
wizards.<note> Heb. shall be emptied. , Heb. swallow vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the Egyptians
will I giue ouer into the hand of a cruell Lord; and a fierce king
shall rule ouer them, saith the Lorde, the Lord of
hostes.<note> Or, shut vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the waters
shall faile from the sea, and the riuer shalbe wasted, and dried
vp.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they shall
turne the riuers farre away, and the brookes of defence shall be
emptied and dried vp: the reeds and flagges shall wither.</ab>

<fw>Earthly helpes.</fw>
<ab n="7">The paper reeds by
the brookes, by the mouth of the brookes, and euery thing sowen by
the brooks shal wither, be driuen away, and be no more.<note> Heb. and shall not be.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The fishers also
shall mourne, and all they that cast angle into the brookes shall
lament, and they that spread nets vpon the waters shall
languish.</ab>
<ab n="9">Moreouer they that
worke in fine flaxe, and they that weaue net-works shall be
confounded.<note> Or, white workes.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And they shall be
broken in the purposes thereof, all that make sluces and ponds for
fish.<note> Heb. foundations. , Heb. of liuing things.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Surely the
princes of Zoan are fooles, the counsell of the wise counsellers of
Pharaoh is become brutish: How say ye vnto Pharaoh, I am the sonne
of the wise, the sonne of ancient kings?</ab>
<ab n="12">Where are they?
Where are thy wise men? and let them tell thee now, and let them
know, what the Lord of hosts hath purposed vpon Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="13">The princes of
Zoan are become fooles, the princes of Noph are deceiued, they haue
also seduced Egypt, euen they that are the stay of the tribes
thereof.<note> Or, gouernours. heb. corners.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord hath
mingled a peruerse spirit in the midst thereof: and they haue
caused Egypt to erre in euery worke thereof, as a drunken man
staggereth in his vomit.<note> Heb. a spirit of peruersities.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Neither shall
there be any worke for Egypt, which the head or taile, branch or
rush may doe.</ab>
<ab n="16">In that day shall
Egypt bee like vnto women: and it shall be afraid and feare,
because of the shaking of the hand of the Lord of hosts, which he
shaketh ouer it.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the land of
Iudah shall bee a terrour vnto Egypt, euery one that maketh mention
thereof, shal be afraid in himselfe, because of the counsell of the
Lord of hosts, which he hath determined against it.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ In that
day shall fiue cities in the land of Egypt speake the language of
Canaan, and sweare to the Lord of hostes: one shalbe called the
citie of destruction.<note> Heb. the lippe. , Or, of Heres: or of the Sunne.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">In that day shall
there be an Altar to the Lord in the midst of the land of Egypt,
and a pillar at the border thereof to the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Isaiah naked.</fw>
<ab n="20">And it shall be
for a signe, and for a witnesse vnto the Lord of hosts in the land
of Egypt: for they shall crie vnto the Lord, because of the
oppressours, and he shal send them a Sauiour and a great One, and
he shall deliuer them.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the Lord
shalbe knowen to Egypt, and the Egyptians shal know the Lord in
that day, and shal do sacrifice and oblation, yea they shall vow a
vowe vnto the Lord, and performe it.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Lord
shall smite Egypt, he shall smite and heale it, and they shall
returne euen to the Lord, and he shalbe intreated of them, and
shall heale them.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ In that
day shall there be a hie way out of Egypt to Assyria, and the
Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria, and
the Egyptians shall serue with the Assyrians.</ab>
<ab n="24">In that day shall
Israel bee the third with Egypt, and with Assyria, euen a blessing
in the midst of the land:</ab>
<ab n="25">Whom the Lord of
hosts shal blesse, saying, Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria
the work of my hands, and Israel mine inheritance.</ab>



</div>