<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_50" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-49-50.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-50-51.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. L.</head>
<head>1 Christ sheweth, that the
dereliction of the Iewes is not to be imputed to him, by his
abilitie to saue, 5 by his obedience in that worke, 7 and by his
confidence in that assistance. 10 An exhortation to trust in God,
and not in our selues.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord, Where is the bill of your mothers diuorcement, whom I haue
put away? or which of my creditours is it to whom I haue sold you?
Behold, for your iniquities haue you solde your selues, and for
your transgressions is your mother put away.</ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore when I
came was there no man? when I called, was there none to answere? Is
my hand shortened at all, that it cannot redeeme? or haue I no
power to deliuer? Beholde, at my rebuke I drie vp the sea: I make
the riuers a wildernes: their fish stinketh, because there is no
water, and dieth for thirst.<note> Num. 11. 23. chap. 59.1. , Exod. 14. 21. , Iosh.3. 16</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I clothe the
heauens with blackenesse, and I make sackcloth their
couering.</ab>
<ab n="4">The Lord God hath
giuen me the tongue of the learned, that I should know how to
speake a worde in season to him that is wearie: hee wakeneth
morning by morning, hee wakeneth mine eare to heare as the
learned.<note> Matth.11. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ The Lord
God hath opened mine eare, and I was not rebellious, neither turned
away backe.<note> Iohn 14. 31. heb. 10. 5. &amp;c. phil. 2.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I gaue my backe to
the smiters, and my cheeks to them that plucked off the haire: I
hidde not my face from shame and spitting.<note> Matth. 26. 67. and 27. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ For the
Lord God will helpe me, therefore shall I not be confounded:
therefore haue I set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall
not bee ashamed.</ab>
<ab n="8">He is neere that
iustifieth me, who will contend with me? let vs stand together: who
is mine aduersarie? let him come neere to me.<note> Rom. 8. 32, 33. , Heb. the master of my cause.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Behold, the Lord
God wil helpe me, who is he that shall condemne mee? Loe, they all
shall waxe olde as a garment: the moth shall eate them vp.</ab>

<fw>Not to feare man.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ Who is
among you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voyce of his
seruant, that walketh in darkenesse and hath no light? let him
trust in the Name of the Lord, and stay vpon his God.</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, all ye
that kindle a fire, that compasse your selues about with sparks:
walke in the light of your fire, and in the sparkes that ye haue
kindled. This shall ye haue of mine hand, yee shall lie downe in
sorrow.<note> Iohn 9.39.</note></ab>



</div>