<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>1 Merodach Baladan sending to visit
Hezekiah because of the wonder, hath notice of his treasures. 3
Isaiah vnderstanding thereof, foretelleth the Babylonian
captiuitie.</head>

<ab n="1">At that time
Merodach Baladan the sonne of Baladan king of Babylon, sent letters
and a present to Hezekiah: for hee had heard that he had bene
sicke, and was recouered.<note> 2.Kin. 20. 12. &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Of Iohn Baptist.</fw>
<ab n="2">And Hezekiah was
glad of them, and shewed them the house of his precious things, the
siluer, and the golde, and the spices, and the precious oyntment,
and all the house of his armour, and all that was found in his
treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion,
that Hezekiah shewed them not.<note> Or, spicery. , Or, iewels. heb. vessels or instruments.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Then came
Isaiah the Prophet vnto King Hezekiah, and sayde vnto him, What
sayd these men? and from whence came they vnto thee? And Hezekiah
said, They are come from a farre countrey vnto me, euen from
Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then said hee,
What haue they seene in thine house? And Hezekiah answered, All
that is in mine house haue they seene: there is nothing among my
treasures, that I haue not shewed them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then sayde Isaiah
to Hezekiah, Heare the word of the Lord of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="6">Behold, the dayes
come, that all that is in thine house, and that which thy fathers
haue laide vp in store, vntill this day, shalbe caried to Babylon:
nothing shalbe left, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">And of thy sonnes
that shall issue from thee, which thou shalt beget, shall they take
away; and they shall bee Eunuches in the palace of the king of
Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then sayde
Hezekiah to Isaiah, Good is the word of the Lord which thou hast
spoken: hee sayd moreouer, For there shalbe peace and trueth in my
dayes.</ab>



</div>