<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_42" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-42-43.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLII.</head>
<head>1 The Office of Christ, graced with
meekenes and constancie. 5 Gods promise vnto him. 10 An exhortation
to praise God for his Gospel. 17 He reproueth the people of
incredulitie.</head>

<ab n="1">Behold my seruant
whome I vphold, mine elect in whom my soule delighteth: I haue put
my Spirit vpon him, he shall bring forth iudgement to the
Gentiles.<note> Mat.12. 18. , Mat.3.17. and 17.5. eph.1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Hee shall not
crie, nor lift vp, nor cause his voyce to bee heard in the
streete.</ab>
<ab n="3">A bruised reed
shall he not breake, and the smoking flaxe shall hee not quench: he
shall bring forth iudgment vnto trueth.<note> Or, dimly burning. , Hebr. quench it.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">He shall not faile
nor be discouraged, till he haue set iudgement in the earth: and
the yles shall waite for his lawe.<note> Heb. broken.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Thus saith
God the Lord, he that created the heauens, and stretched them out,
he that spread foorth the earth and that which commeth out of it,
he that giueth breath vnto the people vpon it, and spirit to them
that walke therein:</ab>
<ab n="6">I the Lord haue
called thee in righteousnes, and wil hold thine hand, and will
keepe thee, and giue thee for a couenant of the people, for a light
of the Gentiles:<note> Chap. 49. 5. luk.2. 32 acts.13.47.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">To open the blind
eyes, to bring out the prisoners from the prison, and them that sit
in darkenesse out of the prison house.<note> Chap.61. 1. , Luk.4. 18 heb.2.14,15 cha.9.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">I am the Lord;
that is my name, and my glory will I not giue to another, neither
my praise to grauen images.<note> Chap.48. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>The Lords silence.</fw>
<ab n="9">Behold, the former
things are come to passe, and new things doe I declare: before they
spring forth I tell you of them.</ab>
<ab n="10">Sing vnto the
Lord a newe song, and his praise from the end of the earth: yee
that goe downe to the sea, and all that is therein; the yles, and
the inhabitants thereof.<note> Hebr. the fulnesse thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Let the wildernes
and the cities thereof lift vp their voyce, the villages that Kedar
doeth inhabite: let the inhabitants of the rocke sing, let them
shoute from the top of the mountaines.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let them giue
glory vnto the Lord, and declare his praise in the Ilands.</ab>
<ab n="13">The Lord shall
goe foorth as a mighty man, he shall stirre vp iealousie like a man
of warre: he shall cry, yea roare; hee shall preuaile against his
enemies.<note> Or, behaue himselfe mightily.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I haue long time
holden my peace, I haue bene still and refrained my selfe: now wil
I cry like a trauailing woman, I will destroy and deuoure at
once.<note> Hebr. swallow or sup vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">I will make waste
mountaines and hilles, and dry vp all their herbes, and I will make
the riuers Ilands, and I will dry vp the pooles.</ab>
<ab n="16">And I will bring
the blinde by a way that they knew not, I will lead them in pathes
that they haue not knowen: I wil make darkenesse light before them,
and crooked things straight. These things will I doe vnto them, and
not forsake them.<note> Hebr. into straightnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ They shall
be turned backe, they shalbe greatly ashamed, that trust in grauen
images, that say to the moulten images; Ye are our
gods.<note> Psal.97.7. chap. 1. 29. and 44. 11. and 45. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Heare ye deafe,
and looke ye blinde that ye may see.</ab>
<ab n="19">Who is blinde,
but my seruant? or deafe, as my messenger that I sent? who is
blinde as he that is perfit, and blinde as the Lords
seruant?</ab>
<ab n="20">Seeing many
things, but thou obseruest not: opening the eares, but he heareth
not.<note> Rom. 2. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The Lord is well
pleased for his righteousnes sake, he will magnifie the Law, and
make it honourable.<note> Or, him.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But this is a
people robbed and spoiled, they are all of them snared in holes,
and they are hid in prison houses: they are for a praye, &amp; none
deliuereth; for a spoile, and none saith, Restore.<note> Or, in snaring all the yong men of them. , Hebr. a treading.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods loue to his.</fw>
<ab n="23">Who among you
will giue eare to this? who will hearken, and heare for the time to
come?<note> Hebr. for the after time.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Who gaue Iacob
for a spoile, and Israel to the robbers? Did not the Lord, hee,
against whom wee haue sinned? For they would not walke in his
wayes, neither were they obedient vnto his Law.</ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore he hath
powred vpon him the furie of his anger, and the strength of
battell: and it hath set him on fire round about, yet hee knew not;
and it burned him, yet hee layed it not to heart.</ab>



</div>