<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Isaiah in a vision of the Lord in
his glory, 5 being terrified, is confirmed for his Message. 9 He
sheweth the obstinacie of the people, vnto their desolation. 13 A
remnant shall bee saued.</head>

<ab n="1">In the yeere
that King Uzziah died, I saw also the Lord sitting vpon a throne,
high and lifted vp, and his traine filled the Temple.<note> Iohn 12. 39,40.41. , Or, the skirts thereof.</note></ab>

<fw>Vncleane lips.</fw>
<ab n="2">Aboue it
stood the Seraphims: each one had sixe wings, with twaine he
couered his face, and with twaine hee couered his feete, and with
twaine hee did flie.</ab>
<ab n="3">And one cryed
vnto another, and sayd; Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of hostes,
the whole earth is full of his glory.<note> Heb. this cried to this. , Reu.4.8. , Heb. his glory is the fulnesse of the whole earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the posts
of the doore moued at the voyce of him that cryed, and the house
was filled with smoke.<note> Heb. thresholds.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then
sayd I; woe is me; for I am vndone, because I am a man of vncleane
lippes, and I dwell in the midst of a people of vncleane lippes:
for mine eyes haue seene the king, the Lord of hostes.<note> Heb. cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then flew one
of the Seraphims vnto mee, hauing a liue-cole in his hand, which
hee had taken with the tongs from off the altar.<note> Heb. and in his hand a liue-coale.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And he laide
it vpon my mouth, and sayd, Loe, this hath touched thy lippes, and
thine iniquitie is taken away, and thy sinne purged.<note> Heb. caused it to touch.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Also I heard
the voyce of the Lord, saying; Whom shall I send, and who will goe
for vs? Then I saide; Heere am I, send me.<note> Gen.1. 26. , Heb. behold me.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And he
sayd, Goe and tell this people; Heare yee indeede, but vnderstand
not: and see yee indeed, but perceiue not.<note> Matth.13. 14. mar.4. 12. luc.8. 10 ioh.12. 40. act.28. 26. rom.11. 8. , Or, without ceasing, &amp;c. Heb. heare yee in hearing, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Make the heart of
this people fat, and make their eares heauy, and shut their eyes:
lest they see with their eyes, and heare with their eares, and
vnderstand with their heart, and conuert and be healed.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then sayd I; Lord,
how long? And hee answered, Untill the cities be wasted without
inhabitant, and the houses without man, and the land be vtterly
desolate,<note> Heb. desolate with desolation.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Lord haue
remoued men farre away, and there be a great forsaking in the midst
of the land.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ But yet in
it shalbe a tenth, and it shall returne, and shall be eaten: as a
Teyle tree, and as an Oke whose substance is in them, when they
cast their leaues: so the holy seede shall be the substance
thereof.<note> Or, when it is returned and hath bin broused. , Or, stocke, or stemme.</note></ab>



</div>