<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_64" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-63-64.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-64-65.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXIV.</head>
<head>1 The Church prayeth for the
illustration of Gods power. 5 Celebrating Gods mercy, it maketh
confession of their naturall corruptions. 9 It complaineth of their
affliction.</head>

<ab n="1">Oh that thou
wouldest rent the heauens, that thou wouldest come down, that the
mountaines might flowe downe at thy presence,</ab>
<ab n="2">As when the
melting fire burneth, the fire causeth the waters to boyle: to make
thy Name knowen to thine aduersaries, that the nations may tremble
at thy presence.<note> Heb. the fire of meltings.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">When thou diddest
terrible things which wee looked not for, thou camest downe, the
mountaines flowed downe at thy presence.</ab>
<ab n="4">For since the
beginning of the world men haue not heard, nor perceiued by the
eare, neither hath the eye seene, O God, besides thee, what hee
hath prepared for him that waiteth for him.<note> 1. Cor. 2. 9. psal. 31. 20. , Or, seene a God besides thee which doeth so for him, &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Mans righteousnesse.</fw>
<ab n="5">Thou meetest him
that reioyceth, and worketh righteousnesse, those that remember
thee in thy wayes: behold, thou art wroth, for we haue sinned: in
those is continuance, and we shall be saued.</ab>
<ab n="6">But we are al as
an vncleane thing, and all our righteousnesses are as filthy
ragges, and we all doe fade as a leafe, and our iniquities like the
wind haue taken vs away.<note> Psal.50. 5,6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And there is none
that calleth vpon thy name, that stirreth vp himselfe to take hold
of thee: for thou hast hid thy face from vs, and hast consumed vs
because of our iniquities.<note> Heb. melted.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But now, O Lord,
thou art our father: we are the clay, and thou our potter, and we
all are the worke of thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Be not
wroth very sore, O Lord, neither remember iniquitie for euer:
behold, see we beseech thee, we are all thy people.<note> Psal.79. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thy holy cities
are a wildernesse, Zion is a wildernesse, Ierusalem a
desolation.</ab>
<ab n="11">Our holy and our
beautifull house, where our fathers praised thee, is burnt vp with
fire, and all our pleasant things are layed waste:</ab>
<ab n="12">Wilt thou
refraine thy selfe for these things, O Lord? wilt thou hold thy
peace, and afflict vs very sore?</ab>



</div>