<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-20-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet, bewayling the
captiuity of his people, seeth in a vision, the fall of Babylon by
the Medes and Persians. 11 Edom, scorning the Prophet, is moued to
repentance. 13 The set time of Arabias calamity.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of the
desert of the sea. As whirlewinds in the South passe thorough; so
it commeth from the desert, from a terrible land.</ab>
<ab n="2">A grieuous vision
is declared vnto me; The treacherous dealer dealeth treacherously,
and the spoiler spoileth: Goe, vp O Elam: besiege, O Media: all the
sighing thereof haue I made to cease.<note> Heb. hard.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore are my
loynes filled with paine, pangs haue taken hold vpon me, as the
pangs of a woman that trauelleth: I was bowed downe at the hearing
of it, I was dismayed at the seeing of it.</ab>
<ab n="4">My heart panted,
fearefulnesse affrighted me: the night of my pleasure hath he
turned into feare vnto me.<note> Or, my minde wandred. , Heb. put.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Prepare the table,
watch in the watch-tower, eate, drinke: arise yee princes, and
anoint the shield.</ab>
<ab n="6">For thus hath the
Lord sayd vnto me; Goe, set a watchman, let him declare what he
seeth.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he saw a
charet with a couple of horsemen, a charet of asses, and a charet
of camels; and hee hearkened diligently with much heede.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he cryed; A
lyon: my Lord, I stand continually vpon the watch-tower in the day
time, and I am set in my ward whole nights.<note> Or, cryed as a lyon. , Abacuc. 2.1. , Or, euery night.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And behold, heere
commeth a charet of men with a couple of horsemen: and he answered
and sayd; Babylon is fallen, is fallen, and all the grauen images
of her Gods he hath broken vnto the ground.<note> Ier.51.8. reu.14.8. and 18.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">O my threshing
and the corne of my floore: that which I haue heard of the Lord of
hostes the God of Israel, haue I declared vnto you.<note> Heb. sonne.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Arabia.</fw>
<ab n="11">¶ The burden
of Dumah. Hee calleth to me out of Seir: Watchman, what of the
night? Watchman, what of the night?</ab>
<ab n="12">The watchman
sayd; The morning commeth, and also the night: if yee will enquire,
enquire yee: returne, come.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ The burden
vpon Arabia. In the forest in Arabia shall yee lodge, O yee
trauelling companies of Dedanim.</ab>
<ab n="14">The inhabitants
of the land of Tema brought water to him that was thirsty, they
preuented with their bread him that fled.<note> Or, bring yee.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For they fled
from the swords, from the drawen sword, and from the bent bow, and
from the grieuousnesse of warre.<note> Or, for feare. Heb. from the face.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For thus hath the
Lord sayd vnto me: Within a yeere, according to the yeeres of an
hireling, and all the glory of Kedar shall faile.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the residue
of the number of archers, the mighty men of the children of Kedar
shalbe diminished: for the Lord God of Israel hath spoken
it.<note> Heb. bowes</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>