<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_56" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-54-56.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-56-57.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LVI.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet exhorteth to
sanctification. 3 He promiseth it shall be generall without respect
of persons. 9 He inueyeth against blinde watchmen.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord, Keepe yee iudgement, and doe iustice: for my saluation is
neere to come, and my righteousnesse to bee reuealed.<note> Or, equity.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Blessed is the man
that doeth this, and the sonne of man that layeth holde on it: that
keepeth the Sabbath from polluting it, and keepeth his hand from
doing any euill.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Neither let
the sonne of the stranger, that hath ioyned himselfe to the Lord,
speake, saying, The Lord hath vtterly separated mee from his
people: neither let the Eunuch say, Behold, I am a drie
tree.</ab>
<ab n="4">For thus saith the
Lord vnto the Eunuches that keep my Sabbaths, and choose the things
that please mee, and take hold of my couenant:</ab>

<fw>Blinde watchmen.</fw>
<ab n="5">Euen vnto them
will I giue in mine house, and within my walles, a place and a name
better then of sonnes and of daughters: I wil giue them an
euerlasting name, that shal not be cut off.</ab>
<ab n="6">Also the sonnes of
the stranger that ioyne themselues to the Lord, to serue him, and
to loue the Name of the Lord, to be his seruants, euery one that
keepeth the Sabbath from polluting it, and taketh hold of my
Couenant:</ab>
<ab n="7">Euen them will I
bring to my holy mountaine, and make them ioyfull in my house of
prayer: their burnt offerings and their sacrifices shall be
accepted vpon mine Altar: for mine house shalbe called an house of
prayer for all people.<note> Chap.2. 2. , Matth.21. 13. mar.11. 17 luke 19. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord God which
gathereth the outcasts of Israel, saith, Yet will I gather others
to him, besides those that are gathered vnto him.<note> Hebr. to his gathered.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ All ye
beasts of the field, come to deuoure, yea all ye beasts in the
forest.</ab>
<ab n="10">His watchmen are
blinde: they are all ignorant, they are all dumbe dogs, they cannot
barke; sleeping, lying downe, louing to slumber.<note> Or, dreaming or talking in their sleepe.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Yea they are
greedy dogges which can neuer haue ynough, and they are shepheards
that cannot vnderstand: they all looke to their owne way, euery one
for his gaine, from his quarter.<note> Heb. strong of appetite. , Heb. Know not to be satisfied.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Come ye, say
they, I wil fetch wine, and we will fill our selues with strong
drinke, and to morrow shal be as this day, and much more
abundant.</ab>



</div>