<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_57" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-56-57.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-57-59.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LVII.</head>
<head>1 The blessed death of the
righteous. 3 God reproueth the Iewes for their whorish idolatry. 13
Hee giueth Euangelicall promises to the penitent.</head>

<ab n="1">The righteous
perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart; and mercifull men are
taken away none considering that the righteous is taken away from
the euill to come.<note> Hebr. men of kindnesse or godlinesse. , Psal.12. 2. mich.7.2. , Or, from that which is euill.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Hee shall enter
into peace: they shall rest in their beds, each one walking in his
vprightnesse.<note> Or, goe in peace. , Or, before him.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ But draw
neere hither, yee sonnes of the sorceresse, the seed of the
adulterer, and the whore.</ab>
<ab n="4">Against whom doe
ye sport your selues? against whom make ye a wide mouth, and draw
out the tongue? are ye not children of transgression, a seede of
falsehood?</ab>

<fw>Gods dwelling.</fw>
<ab n="5">Inflaming your
selues with idoles vnder euery greene tree, slaying the children in
the valleys vnder the cliftes of the rockes?<note> Or, among the okes. , 1.Kin.16. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Among the smooth
stones of the streame is thy portion; they, they are thy lot: euen
to them hast thou powred a drinke offering, thou hast offered a
meate offering. Should I receiue comfort in these?</ab>
<ab n="7">Upon a loftie and
high mountaine hast thou set thy bed: euen thither wentest thou vp
to offer sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="8">Behinde the doores
also and the posts hast thou set vp thy remembrance: for thou hast
discouered thy selfe to an other then mee, and art gone vp: thou
hast enlarged thy bed, and made a couenant with them: thou louedst
their bed where thou sawest it.<note> Or, hewed it for thy selfe larger then theirs. , Or, thou prouidedst roome.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And thou wentest
to the king with oyntment, and didst increase thy perfumes, and
didst send thy messengers farre off, and didst debase thy selfe
euen vnto hell.<note> Or, thou respectedst the King.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thou art wearied
in the greatnesse of thy way; yet saydst thou not, There is no
hope: thou hast found the life of thine hand; therefore thou wast
not grieued.<note> Or, liuing.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And of whom hast
thou bene afraid or feared, that thou hast lyed, and hast not
remembred me, nor layed it to thy heart? haue not I held my peace
euen of old, and thou fearest me not?</ab>
<ab n="12">I will declare
thy righteousnes; and thy workes, for they shall not profit
thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ When thou
criest, let thy companies deliuer thee: but the winde shall cary
them all away; Uanitie shall take them: but hee that putteth his
trust in me, shall possesse the land, and shall inherit my holy
mountaine.</ab>
<ab n="14">And shall say,
Cast yee vp, cast yee vp; prepare the way, take vp the stumbling
blocke out of the way of my people.<note> Chap. 40. 3. and 62. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For thus saith
the High and loftie One that inhabiteth eternitie, whose Name is
Holy; I dwell in the high and holy place: with him also that is of
a contrite and humble spirit, to reuiue the spirit of the humble,
and to reuiue the heart of the contrite ones.</ab>
<ab n="16">For I will not
contend for euer, neither will I be alwayes wroth: for the spirit
should faile before me, and the soules which I haue made.</ab>

<fw>The true fast, and true
Sabbath.</fw>
<ab n="17">For the iniquitie
of his couetousnesse was I wroth, and smote him: I hid me, and was
wroth, and hee went on frowardly in the way of his
heart.<note> Hebr. turning away.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">I haue seene his
wayes, and will heale him: I will leade him also, and restore
comforts vnto him, and to his mourners.</ab>
<ab n="19">I create the
fruite of the lippes; peace, peace to him that is farre off, and to
him that is neere, sayth the Lord, and I will heale him.</ab>
<ab n="20">But the wicked
are like the troubled sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast
vp myre and dirt.</ab>
<ab n="21">There is no
peace, sayth my God, to the wicked.<note> Chap.48. 12.</note></ab>



</div>