<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 In Maher-shalal-hash-baz, hee
prophecieth that Syria and Israel shalbe subdued by Assyria. 5
Iudah likewise for their infidelitie. 9 Gods iudgements shalbe
vnresistable. 11 Comfort shalbe to them that feare God. 19 Great
afflictions to idolaters.</head>


<fw>Against infidelitie.</fw>
<ab n="1">Moreouer the
Lord said vnto mee, Take thee a great roule, and write in it with a
mans penne, concerning Maher-shalal-hash-baz.<note> Hebr. In making speed to the spoile, he hasteneth the pray. Or, make speed, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And I tooke
vnto mee faithfull witnesses to record, Uriah the Priest, and
Zechariah the sonne of Ieberechiah.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I went
vnto the Prophetesse, and shee conceiued and bare a sonne, then
said the Lord to mee, Call his name
Maher-shalal-hash-baz.<note> Hebr. approched vnto.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For before
the childe shall haue knowledge to cry, My father and my mother,
the riches of Damascus, and the spoile of Samaria shalbe taken away
before the king of Assyria.<note> Or, He that is before the King of Assyria shall take away the riches &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ The
Lord spake also vnto me againe, saying,</ab>
<ab n="6">For so much
as this people refuseth the waters of Shiloah that goe softly, and
reioyce in Rezin, and Remaliahs sonne:</ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
behold, the Lord bringeth vp vpon them the waters of the riuer
strong and many, euen the king of Assyria, and all his glory: and
he shall come vp ouer all his channels, and goe ouer all his
bankes.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee shall
passe through Iudah, he shall ouerflow and goe ouer, he shall reach
euen to the necke; and the stretching out of his wings shall fill
the breadth of thy land, O Immanuel.<note> Hebr. The fulnesse of the breadth of thy land shall be the stretching out of his wings.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶
Associate your selues, O ye people, and yee shalbe broken in
pieces; and giue eare all ye of farre countreys: gird your selues,
and ye shalbe broken in pieces; gird your selues, and ye shalbe
broken in pieces.<note> Or, yet.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Take counsell
together, and it shall come to nought: speake the word, and it
shall not stand; for God is with vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ For the
Lord spake thus to me with a strong hand, and instructed me that I
should not walke in the way of this people, saying,<note> Hebr. In strength of hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Say ye not, A
confederacie to all them, to whom this people shall say, A
confederacie; neither feare yee their feare, nor be afraid.</ab>
<ab n="13">Sanctifie the Lord
of hostes himselfe, and let him bee your feare, and let him be your
dread.</ab>

<fw>Seeke God onely.</fw>
<ab n="14">And he shalbe for
a sanctuary; but for a stone of stumbling and for a rocke of
offence to both the houses of Israel, for a ginne, and for a snare
to the inhabitants of Ierusalem.<note> Isa.28.16. luke 2.34. rom.9.33. 1.pet.2.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And many among
them shall stumble and fall, and be broken, and be snared, and be
taken.<note> Matth.21. 44. luke 20.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Binde vp the
Testimonie, seale the Law among my disciples.</ab>
<ab n="17">And I wil wait
vpon the Lord that hideth his face from the house of Iacob, and I
will looke for him.</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold, I, and the
children whom the Lord hath giuen me, are for signes, and for
wonders in Israel: from the Lord of hostes, which dwelleth in mount
Zion.<note> Hebr.2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And when
they shall say vnto you; Seeke vnto them that haue familiar
spirits, and vnto wizards that peepe and that mutter: should not a
people seeke vnto their God? for the liuing, to the dead?</ab>
<ab n="20">To the Law and to
the Testimonie: if they speake not according to this word, it is
because there is no light in them.<note> Heb.2.13. , Heb. no morning.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And they shall
passe through it, hardly bestead and hungry: and it shall come to
passe, that when they shall be hungry, they shall fret themselues,
and curse their King, and their God, and looke vpward.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they shall
looke vnto the earth: and behold trouble and darkenesse, dimnesse
of anguish; and they shall be driuen to darkenesse.</ab>



</div>