<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet threatneth Ephraim for
their pride and drunkennesse. 5 The residue shall be aduanced in
the Kingdom of Christ. 7 He rebuketh their errour. 9 Their
vntowardnes to learne, 14 And their securitie. 16 Christ the sure
foundation is promised. 18 Their security shalbe tried. 23 They are
incited to the consideration of Gods discreet
prouidence.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to the crowne
of pride, to the drunkards of Ephraim, whose glorious beauty is a
fading flowre, which are on the head of the fat valleys of them
that are ouercome with wine.<note> Heb. broken.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Behold, the Lord
hath a mightie and strong one, which as a tempest of haile and a
destroying storme, as a flood of mightie waters ouerflowing, shall
cast downe to the earth with the hand.</ab>
<ab n="3">The crowne of
pride, the drunkards of Ephraim shall be troden vnder
feete.<note> Hebr. with feete.</note></ab>

<fw>The peoples securitie.</fw>
<ab n="4">And the glorious
beautie which is on the head of the fat valley, shall bee a fading
flowre, and as the hastie fruite before the summer: which when he
that looketh vpon it, seeth it, while it is yet in his hand, he
eateth it vp.<note> Heb. swalloweth.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ In that day
shall the Lord of hosts be for a crowne of glory, and for a diademe
of beautie vnto the residue of his people:</ab>
<ab n="6">And for a spirit
of iudgement to him that sitteth in iudgement, and for strength to
them that turne the battell to the gate.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ But they
also haue erred through wine, and through strong drinke are out of
the way: the priest and the prophet haue erred through strong
drinke, they are swallowed vp of wine: they are out of the way
through strong drinke, they erre in vision, they stumble in
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="8">For all tables are
full of vomite and filthinesse, so that there is no place
cleane.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Whome shall
he teach knowledge? and whom shall he make to vnderstand doctrine?
them that are weaned from the milke, and drawen from the
breasts.<note> Hebr. the hearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For precept must
be vpon precept, precept vpon precept, line vpon line, line vpon
line, here a litle, and there a litle.<note> Or, hath bene.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For with
stammering lips and another tongue will he speake to this
people.<note> Heb. stammerings of lippe. , 1.Cor.14. 21. , Or, he hath spoken.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">To whom he said,
This is the rest wherwith ye may cause the weary to rest, and this
is the refreshing, yet they would not heare.</ab>
<ab n="13">But the word of
the Lord was vnto them, precept vpon precept, precept vpon precept,
line vpon line, line vpon line, here a litle and there a litle:
that they might goe and fall backward, and be broken, and snared,
and taken.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Wherefore
heare the worde of the Lord, yee scornefull men, that rule this
people which is in Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="15">Because ye haue
said, Wee haue made a couenant with death, and with hell are we at
agreement, when the ouerflowing scourge shall passe thorow, it
shall not come vnto vs: for wee haue made lies our refuge, and
vnder falsehood haue we hid our selues:</ab>

<fw>The corner stone.</fw>
<ab n="16">¶ Therefore
thus saith the Lord God, Beholde, I lay in Zion for a foundation, a
stone, a tryed stone, a precious corner stone, a sure foundation:
hee that beleeueth, shall not make haste.<note> Psal. 118. 22. matth. 21.42. acts 4.11. 1.pet. 2.6,7,8. rom.9.33. and 10. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Iudgement also
will I lay to the line, and righteousnesse to the plummet: and the
haile shall sweepe away the refuge of lyes, and the waters shall
ouerflow the hiding place.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And your
couenant with death shalbe disanulled, and your agreement with hell
shall not stand; when the ouerflowing scourge shall passe thorough,
then yee shalbe troden downe by it.<note> Heb. a treading downe to it.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">From the time
that it goeth forth, it shall take you: for morning by morning
shall it passe ouer, by day and by night, and it shalbe a vexation,
onely to vnderstand the report.<note> Or, when he shall make you to vnderstand doctrine.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For the bed is
shorter, then that a man can stretch himselfe on it: and the
couering narrower, then that he can wrap himselfe in it.</ab>
<ab n="21">For the Lord
shall rise vp as in mount Perazim, he shalbe wroth as in the valley
of Gibeon, that he may doe his worke, his strange worke; and bring
to passe his act, his strange act.<note> 2. Sam. 5. 20. 1. chro. 14. 13. , Iosh.10. 12. 2.sam. 5.25. 1.chr. 14. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Now therefore be
yee not mockers, lest your bands be made strong: for I haue heard
from the Lord God of hostes a consumption euen determined vpon the
whole earth.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Giue yee
eare, and heare my voyce, hearken and heare my speach.</ab>
<ab n="24">Doth the plowman
plow all day to sow? doth he open and breake the clods of his
ground?</ab>
<ab n="25">When hee hath
made plaine the face thereof, doth he not cast abroad the fitches,
and scatter the cummin, and cast in the principall wheate, and the
appointed barly and the rye in their place?<note> Or, the wheat in the principall place and barley in the appointed place. , Or, spelt. , Heb. border.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For his God doth
instruct him to discretion, and doth teach him.<note> Or, and he bindeth it in such sort as God doth teach him.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">For the fitches
are not threshed with a threshing instrument, neither is a cart
wheele turned about vpon the cummin: but the fitches are beaten out
with a staffe, and the cummin with a rodde.</ab>
<ab n="28">Bread corne is
bruised; because he will not euer be threshing it, nor breake it
with the wheele of his cart, nor bruise it with his
horsemen.</ab>

<fw>Against Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="29">This also commeth
forth from the Lord of hostes, which is wonderfull in counsell, and
excellent in working.</ab>



</div>