<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_37" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-37-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVII.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah mourning, sendeth to
Isaiah to pray for them. 6 Isaiah comforteth them. 8 Sennacherib
going to encounter Tirhakah, sendeth a blasphemous letter to
Hezekiah. 14 Hezekiahs prayer. 21 Isaiah his prophecie of the
pride, and destruction of Sennacherib, and the good of Zion. 36 An
Angel slayeth the Assyrians. 37 Sennacherib is slaine at Nineueh by
his owne sonnes.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe when King Hezekiah heard it, that hee rent his clothes, and
couered himselfe with sackecloth, and went into the house of the
Lord.<note> 2.King. 19. 1, &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>The blasphemie of Rabshakeh.</fw>
<ab n="2">And hee sent
Eliakim, who was ouer the houshold, and Shebna the Scribe, and the
Elders of the Priestes couered with sackecloth, vnto Isaiah the
Prophet the sonne of Amoz.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they sayd vnto
him; Thus sayth Hezekiah, This day is a day of trouble, and of
rebuke, and of blasphemie: for the children are come to the birth,
and there is not strength to bring foorth.<note> Or, prouocation.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">It may be the Lord
thy God will heare the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of Assyria
his master hath sent to reproch the liuing God, and will reprooue
the words which the Lord thy God hath heard: wherefore lift vp thy
prayer for the remnant that is left.<note> Heb. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So the seruants of
King Hezekiah came to Isaiah.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Isaiah
sayd vnto them; Thus shall yee say vnto your master, Thus sayth the
Lord, Be not afraid of the wordes that thou hast heard, wherewith
the seruants of the king of Assyria haue blasphemed me.</ab>
<ab n="7">Behold, I will
send a blast vpon him, and hee shall heare a rumour, and returne to
his owne land, and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his
owne land.<note> Or, put a spirit into him.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ So
Rabshakeh returned and found the king of Assyria warring against
Libnah: for hee had heard that he was departed from
Lachish.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he heard say
concerning Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, Hee is come foorth to make
warre with thee: and when he heard it, he sent messengers to
Hezekiah, saying;</ab>
<ab n="10">Thus shall ye
speake to Hezekiah King of Iudah, saying, Let not thy God in whom
thou trustest deceiue thee, saying, Ierusalem shall not bee giuen
into the hand of the king of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, thou hast
heard what the kings of Assyria haue done to all lands by
destroying them vtterly, and shalt thou be deliuered?</ab>
<ab n="12">Haue the gods of
the nations deliuered them which my fathers haue destroyed, as
Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the children of Eden which were
in Telassar?</ab>
<ab n="13">Where is the king
of Hamath, and the king of Arphad, and the king of the citie of
Sepharuaim, Hena and Iuah?</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
Hezekiah receiued the letter from the hand of the messengers, and
read it, and Hezekiah went vp vnto the house of the Lord, and
spread it before the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Hezekiahs prayer.</fw>
<ab n="15">And Hezekiah
prayed vnto the Lord, saying,</ab>
<ab n="16">O Lord of hostes,
God of Israel, that dwellest betweene the Cherubims, thou art the
God, euen thou alone, of all the kingdomes of the earth, thou hast
made heauen and earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">Encline thine
eare, O Lord, and heare, Open thine eyes, O Lord, and see, and
heare all the wordes of Sennacherib, which hath sent to reproch the
liuing God.</ab>
<ab n="18">Of a trueth,
Lord, the kings of Assyria haue laid waste all the nations and
their countreys,<note> Heb. lands.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And haue cast
their gods into the fire: for they were no gods, but the work of
mens hands, wood and stone: therfore they haue destroyed
them.<note> Heb. giuen</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Now therefore, O
Lord our God, saue vs from his hand, that all the kingdomes of the
earth may knowe, that thou art the Lord, euen thou onely.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then
Isaiah the sonne of Amoz sent vnto Hezekiah, saying, Thus saith the
Lord God of Israel, Wheras thou hast prayed to me against
Sennacherib king of Assyria:</ab>
<ab n="22">This is the worde
which the Lord hath spoken concerning him: The virgin, the daughter
of Zion hath despised thee, and laughed thee to scorne, the
daughter of Ierusalem hath shaken her head at thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">Whom hast thou
reproched and blasphemed? and against whome hast thou exalted thy
voice, and lifted vp thine eyes on high? euen against the Holy One
of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="24">By thy seruants
hast thou reproched the Lord, and hast said, By the multitude of my
charets am I come vp to the height of the mountaines, to the sides
of Lebanon, and I wil cut downe the tall cedars thereof, and the
choise firre trees thereof: and I will enter into the height of his
border, and the forrest of his Carmel.<note> Heb. by the hand of thy seruants. , Heb. the tallnesse of the cedars thereof, and the choise of the firre trees thereof. , Or, the forrest and his fruitfull field.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">I haue digged and
drunke water, and with the sole of my feete haue I dried vp all the
riuers of the besieged places.<note> Or, fenced and closed.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Hast thou not
heard long agoe, how I haue done it, and of ancient times, that I
haue formed it? now haue I brought it to passe, that thou shouldest
be to lay waste defenced cities into ruinous heapes.<note> Or, Hast thou not heard how I haue made it long agoe, and formed it of ancient times? Should I now bring it to be laide waste, and defenced cities to be ruinous heapes?</note></ab>

<fw>Sennacherib slaine.</fw>
<ab n="27">Therefore their
inhabitants were of small power, they were dismayed and confounded:
they were as the grasse of the field, and as the greene herbe, as
the grasse on the house tops, and as corne blasted before it be
growen vp.<note> Heb. short of hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">But I know thy
abode, and thy going out, and thy comming in, and thy rage against
me.<note> Or, sitting.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Because thy rage
against me, and thy tumult is come vp into mine eares: therefore
will I put my hooke in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I
will turne thee backe by the way by which thou camest.</ab>
<ab n="30">And this shall be
a signe vnto thee, Ye shall eate this yeere such as groweth of it
felfe: and the second yeere that which springeth of the same: and
in the third yeere sow ye and reape, and plant vineyards, and eate
the fruit thereof.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the remnant
that is escaped of the house of Iudah, shal againe take roote
downeward, and beare fruite vpward.<note> Heb the escaping of the house of Iudah that remaineth.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For out of
Ierusalem shall goe forth a remnant, and they that escape out of
mount Zion: the zeale of the Lord of hostes shall doe
this.<note> Heb. the escaping. , 2.Kings 19.11. cha. 9.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Therefore thus
saith the Lord concerning the king of Assyria, He shall not come
into this citie, nor shoot an arrow there, nor come before it with
shields, nor cast a banke against it.</ab>
<ab n="34">By the way that
he came, by the same shall he returne, and shall not come into this
citie, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="35">For I will defend
this citie to saue it, for mine owne sake, and for my seruant
Dauids sake.<note> 2.Kings 20.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Then the Angel of
the Lord went forth, and smote in the campe of the Assyrians a
hundred and fourescore and fiue thousand: and when they arose
earely in the morning, behold, they were all dead
corpses.<note> 2.Kings 19. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">¶ So
Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went, and returned, and
dwelt at Nineueh.</ab>
<ab n="38">And it came to
passe as hee was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that
Adramelech and Sharezer his sons smote him with the sword, and they
escaped into the land of Armenia: and Esarhaddon his sonne reigned
in his stead.<note> Heb. Ararat.</note></ab>



</div>