<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_48" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-48-49.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVIII.</head>
<head>1 God, to conuince the people of
their foreknowen obstinacie, reuealed his prophecies. 9 He saueth
them for his owne sake. 12 He exhorteth them to obedience, because
of his power and prouidence. 16 Hee lamenteth their backewardnesse.
20 Hee powerfully deliuereth his out of Babylon.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare yee this, O
house of Iacob, which are called by the name of Israel, and are
come foorth out of the waters of Iudah; which sweare by the Name of
the Lord, and make mention of the God of Israel, but not in trueth
nor in righteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="2">For they call
themselues of the holy city, and stay themselues vpon the God of
Israel, the Lord of hostes is his Name.</ab>

<fw>God trieth his.</fw>
<ab n="3">I haue declared
the former things from the beginning: and they went foorth out of
my mouth, and I shewed them, I did them suddenly, and they came to
passe.</ab>
<ab n="4">Because I knew
that thou art obstinate, and thy necke is an yron sinew, and thy
brow brasse:<note> Heb. hard.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">I haue euen from
the beginning declared it to thee; before it came to passe I shewed
it thee: lest thou shouldest say, Mine idole hath done them, and my
grauen image, and my molten image hath commanded them.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thou hast heard,
see all this, and will not yee declare it? I haue shewed thee new
things from this time, euen hidden things, and thou didst not know
them.</ab>
<ab n="7">They are created
now, and not from the beginning, euen before the day when thou
heardest them not; lest thou shouldest say, Behold, I knew
them.</ab>
<ab n="8">Yea thou heardest
not, yea thou knewest not, yea from that time that thine eare was
not opened: for I knew that thou wouldest deale very treacherously,
and wast called a transgressour from the wombe.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ For my
names sake will I deferre mine anger, and for my praise will I
refraine for thee, that I cut thee not off.</ab>
<ab n="10">Behold, I haue
refined thee, but not with siluer; I haue chosen thee in the
fornace of affliction.<note> Or, for siluer.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For mine owne
sake, euen for mine owne sake will I doe it; for how should my Name
bee polluted? And I will not giue my glory vnto
another.<note> Cha.42.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Hearken
vnto me, O Iacob, and Israel my called; I am hee, I am the first, I
also am the last.<note> Chap. 41.4. and 44.6. reuel.1.17. and 22.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Mine hand also
hath laid the foundation of the earth, and my right hand hath
spanned the heauens: when I call vnto them, they stand vp
together.<note> Or, the palme of my right hand hath spread out.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">All yee assemble
your selues and heare: which among them hath declared these things?
the Lord hath loued him: hee will doe his pleasure on Babylon, and
his arme shall be on the Caldeans.</ab>
<ab n="15">I, euen I haue
spoken, yea I haue called him: I haue brought him, and he shall
make his way prosperous.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Come ye
neere vnto me; heare ye this; I haue not spoken in secret from the
beginning; from the time that it was, there am I; and now the Lord
God and his Spirit hath sent me.</ab>

<fw>Goe from Babylon.</fw>
<ab n="17">Thus saith the
Lord thy redeemer, the holy one of Israel; I am the Lord thy God
which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way that
thou shouldest goe.</ab>
<ab n="18">O that thou
haddest hearkened to my commandements! then had thy peace beene as
a riuer, and thy righteousnesse as the waues of the sea.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thy seede also
had beene as the sand, and the ofspring of thy bowels like the
grauell thereof: his name should not haue beene cut off, nor
destroyed from before me.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Goe yee
forth of Babylon: flee yee from the Caldeans, with a voyce of
singing, declare yee, tell this, vtter it euen to the end of the
earth: say yee; The Lord hath redeemed his seruant
Iacob.<note> Exod. 19. 4.5,6.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And they thirsted
not when he led them through the deserts; he caused the waters to
flow out of the rocke for them: he claue the rocke also, and the
waters gushed out.<note> Exod. 17. 6. num. 20. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">There is no
peace, saith the Lord, vnto the wicked.<note> Chap. 57. 21.</note></ab>



</div>