<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_55" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-54-56.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. LV.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet, with the promises of
Christ, calleth to faith, 6 and to repentance. 8 The happy successe
of them that beleeue.</head>

<ab n="1">Ho, euery one that
thirsteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money: come
ye, buy and eate, yea come, buy wine and milke without money, and
without price.<note> Ioh.7.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore doe yee
spend money for that which is not bread? and your labour for that
which satisfieth not? hearken diligently vnto me, and eate ye that
which is good, and let your soule delight it selfe in
fatnesse.<note> Heb. weigh</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Incline your eare,
and come vnto me: heare, and your soule shall liue, and I will make
an euerlasting couenant with you, euen the sure mercies of
Dauid.<note> Acts 13.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, I haue
giuen him for a witnesse to the people, a leader and commander to
the people.</ab>
<ab n="5">Behold, thou shalt
call a nation that thou knowest not, and nations that knew not
thee, shall runne vnto thee, because of the Lord thy God, and for
the Holy One of Israel, for he hath glorified thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Seeke ye
the Lord, while he may be found, call ye vpon him while he is
neere.</ab>
<ab n="7">Let the wicked
forsake his way, &amp; the vnrighteous man his thoughts: and let
him returne vnto the Lord, and he will haue mercie vpon him, and to
our God, for hee will abundantly pardon.<note> Hebr. the man of iniquitie. , Heb. he wil multiplie to pardon.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods word sure.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ For my
thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your wayes my wayes,
saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">For as the heauens
are higher then the earth, so are my wayes higher then your wayes,
and my thoughts then your thouhts.</ab>
<ab n="10">For as the raine
commeth down, and the snow from heauen, and returneth not thither,
but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring foorth and bud, that it
may giue seed to the sower, and bread to the eater:</ab>
<ab n="11">So shall my word
bee that goeth forth out of my mouth: it shall not returne vnto me
void, but it shall accomplish that which I please, and it shall
prosper in the thing whereto I sent it.</ab>
<ab n="12">For ye shall goe
out with ioy, and bee led foorth with peace: the mountaines and the
hilles shall breake forth before you into singing, and al the trees
of the field shall clap their hands.<note> Cha.35.1</note></ab>
<ab n="13">In stead of the
thorne shall come vp the Firre tree, and in stead of the brier
shall come vp the Myrtle tree, and it shall be to the Lord for a
name, for an euerlasting signe that shall not bee cut off.</ab>



</div>