<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Isaiah prophecieth the comming of
Christs kingdome. 6 Wickednesse is the cause of Gods forsaking. 10
Hee exhorteth to feare, because of the powerfull effects of Gods
Maiestie.</head>

<ab n="1">The word that
Isaiah, the sonne of Amoz, sawe concerning Iudah and
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="2">And it shall
come to passe in the last dayes, that the mountaine of the Lords
house shall be established in the top of the mountaines, and shall
be exalted aboue the hilles; and all nations shall flow vnto
it.<note> Mic 4.1. &amp;c. , Or, prepared.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And many
people shall goe &amp; say; Come yee and let vs go vp to the
mountaine of the Lord, to the house of the God of Iacob, and he
will teach vs of his wayes, and we will walke in his pathes: for
out of Zion shall goe forth the lawe, and the word of the Lord from
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee shall
iudge among the nations, and shall rebuke many people: and they
shall beate their swords into plow-shares, and their speares into
pruning hookes: nation shall not lift vp sword against nation,
neither shall they learne warre any more.<note> Or, sythes.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">O house of
Iacob, come yee, and let vs walke in the light of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶
Therefore thou hast forsaken thy people the house of Iacob; because
they be replenished from the East, and are soothsayers like the
Philistines, and they please themselues in the children of
strangers.<note> Or, more then the East. , Or, abound with the children. &amp;c</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Their land
also is full of siluer and gold, neither is there any end of their
treasures: their land is also full of horses; neither is there any
end of their charets.</ab>
<ab n="8">Their land
also is full of idoles: they worship the worke of their owne hands,
that which their owne fingers haue made.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the meane
man boweth downe, and the great man humbleth himselfe; therefore
forgiue them not.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Enter into
the rocke, and hide thee in the dust, for feare of the Lord, and
for the glory of his Maiestie.</ab>

<fw>Pride threatned.</fw>
<ab n="11">The loftie lookes
of man shalbe humbled, and the hautines of men shalbe bowed downe:
and the Lord alone shalbe exalted in that day.<note> Chap. 5. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For the day of the
Lord of hostes shall bee vpon euery one that is proud and loftie,
and vpon euery one that is lifted vp, and he shalbe brought
low;</ab>
<ab n="13">And vpon all the
Cedars of Lebanon, that are high and lifted vp; and vpon all the
okes of Bashan,</ab>
<ab n="14">And vpon all the
high mountaines, and vpon all the hilles that are lifted
vp,</ab>
<ab n="15">And vpon euery
high tower, and vpon euery fenced wall,</ab>
<ab n="16">And vpon all the
ships of Tarshish, and vpon all pleasant pictures.<note> Hebr. pictures of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the loftinesse
of man shall be bowed downe, and the hautinesse of men shalbe made
low: and the Lord alone shalbe exalted in that day.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the idoles hee
shall vtterly abolish.<note> Or, the idoles shall vtterly passe away.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And they shall goe
into the holes of the rocks, and into the caues of the earth for
feare of the Lord, and for the glory of his Maiestie; when hee
ariseth to shake terribly the earth.<note> Hos. 10.8. luke 23.30. reuel. 6.16. and 9.6. , Hebr. the dust.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">In that day a man
shall cast his idoles of siluer, and his idoles of golde which they
made each one for himselfe to worship, to the moules and to the
battes:<note> Hebr. the idols of his siluer,&amp;c. , Or, which they made for him.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">To go into the
clefts of the rocks, and into the tops of the ragged rockes, for
feare of the Lord, and for the glorie of his Maiestie; when hee
ariseth to shake terribly the earth.</ab>
<ab n="22">Cease ye from man
whose breath is in his nostrels: for wherein is hee to be accounted
of?</ab>



</div>