<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-33-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 The ioyfull flourishing of
Christes Kingdome. 3 The weake are incouraged by the vertues and
priuiledges of the Gospel.</head>

<ab n="1">The wildernesse
and the solitarie place shall be glad for them: and the desert
shall reioyce and blossome as the rose.</ab>

<fw>Iudah inuaded.</fw>
<ab n="2">It shall blossome
abundantly, and reioyce euen with ioy and singing: the glory of
Lebanon shal be giuen vnto it, the excellencie of Carmel and
Sharon: they shall see the glory of the Lord, and the excellencie
of our God.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Strengthen
yee the weake hands, and confirme the feeble knees.<note> Hebr. 12. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Say to them that
are of a fearefull heart; Be strong, feare not: behold, your God
will come with vengeance, euen God with a recompence, he will come
and saue you.<note> Heb. hastie.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then the eyes of
the blind shall be opened, and the eares of the deafe shalbe
vnstopped.<note> Matth.9. 27. and 11. 5. and 12. 22. and 20. 30. and 21. 14. ioh. 9. 6,7. , Matth.11 5. mar. 7. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then shall the
lame man leape as an Hart, and the tongue of the dumbe sing: for in
the wildernesse shall waters breake out, and streames in the
desert.<note> Matth.11 5. and 15. 30. and 21. 14. ioh. 5.8, 9 acts 3.2. and 8.7 and 14.8. , Matth. 9. 32. and 12. 22. and 15. 30. , Ioh.7.38. 39.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the parched
ground shall become a poole, and the thirstie land springs of
water: in the habitation of dragons, where each lay, shalbe grasse
with reeds and rushes.<note> Or, a court for reedes &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And an high way
shalbe there, and away, and it shall be called the way of
holinesse, the vncleane shall not passe ouer it, but it shall be
for those: the wayfaringmen, though fooles, shall not erre
therein.<note> Or, for he shalbe with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">No lyon shalbe
there; nor any rauenous beast shall goe vp thereon, it shall not be
found there: but the redeemed shall walke there.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the ransomed
of the Lord shall returne and come to Zion with songs, and
euerlasting ioy vpon their heads: they shall obtaine ioy and
gladnesse, and sorrow and sighing shall flee away.<note> Chap. 51. 11.</note></ab>



</div>