<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-24-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 The dolefull iudgements of God
vpon the land. 13 A remnant shall ioyfully praise him. 16 God in
his iudgements shall aduance his Kingdome.</head>

<ab n="1">Behold, the Lord
maketh the earth emptie, and maketh it waste, and turneth it vpside
downe, and scattereth abroad the inhabitants thereof.<note> Heb. peruerteth the face thereof.</note></ab>

<fw>Curse for sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="2">And it shall be as
with the people, so with the priest, as with the seruant, so with
his master, as with the maid, so with her mistresse, as with the
buyer, so with the seller, as with the lender, so with the borower,
as with the taker of vsurie, so with the giuer of vsurie to
him.<note> Or, Prince. , Hose.4.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The land shall be
vtterly emptied, and vtterly spoiled: for the Lord hath spoken this
word.</ab>
<ab n="4">The earth mourneth
and fadeth away, the world languisheth and fadeth away, the
haughtie people of the earth doe languish.<note> Heb. the height of the people.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The earth also is
defiled vnder the inhabitants thereof: because they haue
transgressed the lawes, changed the ordinance, broken the
euerlasting couenant.</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore hath the
curse deuoured the earth, and they that dwell therin are desolate:
therefore the inhabitants of the earth are burned, and few men
left.</ab>
<ab n="7">The new wine
mourneth, the vine languisheth, all the merrie hearted doe
sigh.</ab>
<ab n="8">The mirth of
tabrets ceaseth, the noise of them that reioyce, endeth, the ioy of
the harpe ceaseth.<note> Ier.7.37. and 16.9. &amp; 25.10. ezra 26.13. hos.2.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">They shall not
drinke wine with a song, strong drinke shall bee bitter to them
that drinke it.</ab>
<ab n="10">The city of
confusion is broken downe: euery house is shut vp, that no man may
come in.</ab>
<ab n="11">There is a crying
for wine in the streets, all ioy is darkened, the mirth of the land
is gone.</ab>
<ab n="12">In the citie is
left desolation, and the gate is smitten with destruction.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ When thus
it shalbe in the midst of the land among the people: there shall be
as the shaking of an oliue tree, and as the gleaning grapes when
the vintage is done.</ab>
<ab n="14">They shal lift vp
their voice, they shal sing, for the maiesty of the Lord, they
shall crie aloud from the sea.</ab>
<ab n="15">Wherefore,
glorifie ye the Lord in the fires, euen the Name of the Lord God of
Israel in the yles of the Sea.<note> Or, valleyes</note></ab>

<fw>Feare, pit, and snare.</fw>
<ab n="16">¶ From the
vttermost part of the earth haue we heard songs, euen glory to the
righteous: but I said, My leannesse, my leannesse, woe vnto me: the
treacherous dealers haue dealt treacherously, yea the treacherous
dealers haue dealt very treacherously.<note> Heb. wing. , Heb. leannesse to me or my secret to me.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Feare, and the
pit, &amp; the snare are vpon thee, O inhabitant of the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it shall come
to passe, that he who fleeth from the noise of the feare, shall
fall into the pit; and he that commeth vp out of the midst of the
pit, shalbe taken in the snare: for the windowes from on high are
open, and the foundations of the earth doe shake.<note> Iere.48.44.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The earth is
vtterly broken downe, the earth is cleane dissolued, the earth is
moued exceedingly.</ab>
<ab n="20">The earth shall
reele to and fro, like a drunkard, and shall be remooued like a
cottage, and the transgression thereof shall be heauie vpon it, and
it shall fall, and not rise againe.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it shall come
to passe in that day, that the Lord shall punish the hoste of the
high ones that are on high, and the kings of the earth vpon the
earth.<note> Hebr. visite vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And they shalbe
gathered together as prisoners are gathered in the pit, and shall
be shut vp in the prison, and after many dayes shall they bee
visited.<note> Heb. with the gathering of prisoners. , Or, dungeon. , Or, found wanting.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then the Moone
shall be confounded, and the Sunne ashamed, when the Lord of hosts
shall reigne in mount Zion and in Ierusalem, and before his
ancients gloriously.<note> Chap.13. 10. eze.32. 7. ioel 2.31. and 3.15. , Or, there shalbe glory before his ancients.</note></ab>



</div>