<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Moab is exhorted to yeeld
obedience to Christs kingdome. 6 Moab is threatned for her pride. 9
The Prophet bewaileth her. 12 The iudgement of Moab.</head>


<fw>Against Moab, and Damascus.</fw>
<ab n="1">Send ye the lambe
to the ruler of the land from Sela to the wildernesse, vnto the
mount of the daughter of Zion.<note> Or, Petra: Hebr. a rocke.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For it shalbe that
as a wandering bird cast out of the nest: so the daughters of Moab
shalbe at the fordes of Arnon.<note> Or, a nest forsaken.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Take counsell,
execute Iudgement, make thy shadow as the night in the middest of
the nooneday, hide the outcastes, bewray not him that
wandereth.<note> Heb. bring.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Let mine outcasts
dwel with thee, Moab, be thou a couert to them from the face of the
spoiler: for the extortioner is at an end, the spoiler ceaseth, the
oppressours are consumed out of the land.<note> Heb. wringer. , Hebr. the treaders downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And in mercy shall
the throne be established, and hee shal sit vpon it in trueth, in
the tabernacle of Dauid, iudging and seeking iudgement, and hasting
righteousnesse.<note> Or, prepared. , Dan. 7. 14, 27. mic. 4.7. luke 1. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ We haue
heard of the pride of Moab (hee is very proud) euen of his
hautines, and his pride, and his wrath: but his lies shall not be
so.<note> Iere.48. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore shall
Moab howle for Moab, euery one shal howle: for the foundations of
Kir-hareseth shall yee mourne, surely they are
stricken.<note> Iere.48. 20. , Or, mutter.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For the fieldes of
Heshbon languish, and the vine of Sibmah, the lords of the heathen
haue broken downe the principall plants thereof, they are come euen
vnto Iazer, they wandred through the wildernesse, her branches are
stretched out, they are gone ouer the sea.<note> Or, plucked vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Therefore I
wil bewaile with the weeping of Iazer, the Uine of Sibmah I wil
water thee with my teares, O Heshbon, and Elealeh: for the shouting
for thy Summer fruits, and for thy haruest, is fallen.<note> Or, the alarme is fallen vpon, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And gladnesse is
taken away, and ioy out of the plentifull field, and in the
Uineyards there shalbe no singing, neither shal there be shouting:
the treaders shall tread out no wine in their presses; I haue made
their vintage shouting to cease.<note> Iere.48. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore my
bowels shal sound like an harpe for Moab, and mine inward parts for
Kir-haresh.</ab>

<fw>Against Moab, and Damascus.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And it
shal come to passe, when it is seene that Moab is weary on the high
place, that hee shall come to his Sanctuary to pray: but hee shall
not preuaile.</ab>
<ab n="13">This is the word
that the Lord hath spoken concerning Moab since that time.</ab>
<ab n="14">But now the Lord
hath spoken, saying, Within three yeeres, as the yeeres of an
hireling, and the glory of Moab shalbe contemned, with all that
great multitude; and the remnant shall be very small and
feeble.<note> Or, not many.</note></ab>



</div>