<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 The promulgation of the Gospel. 3
The preaching of Iohn Baptist. 9 The preaching of the Apostles. 12
The Prophet by the omnipotencie of God, 18 and his incomparablenes,
26 comforteth the people.</head>

<ab n="1">Comfort ye,
comfort ye my people, sayth your God.</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake ye
comfortably to Ierusalem, and cry vnto her, that her warrefare is
accomplished, that her iniquitie is pardoned: for shee hath
receiued of the Lords hand double for all her sinnes.<note> Heb. to the heart. , Or, appointed time.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ The voyce
of him that cryeth in the wildernesse, Prepare yee the way of the
Lord, make straight in the desert a high way for our
God.<note> Mat.3.3. mark. 1. 3. luke 3. 4. ioh.1.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Euery valley
shalbe exalted, and euery mountaine and hill shalbe made low: and
the crooked shall be made straight, and the rough places
plaine.<note> Or, a straight place. , Or, a plaine place.</note></ab>

<fw>All flesh is grasse.</fw>
<ab n="5">And the glory of
the Lord shall be reuealed, and all flesh shall see it together:
for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.</ab>
<ab n="6">The voyce sayd;
Cry. And hee sayd; What shall I cry? All flesh is grasse, and all
the goodlinesse thereof is as the flowre of the field.<note> Iob.14. 2. psal. 112. and 103.15 iam.1.10. 1. pet.1.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The grasse
withereth, the flowre fadeth; because the spirit of the Lord
bloweth vpon it: surely the people is grasse.</ab>
<ab n="8">The grasse
withereth, the flowre fadeth: but the word of our God shall stand
for euer.<note> Iohn 12.24. 1.pet.1. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ O Zion,
that bringest good tydings, get thee vp into the high mountaine: O
Ierusalem, that bringest good tidings, lift vp thy voyce with
strength, lift it vp, be not afraid: say vnto the cities of Iudah;
Behold your God.<note> Or, O thou that tellest good tidings to Zion. , Or, O thou that tellest good tidings to Ierusalem.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Behold, the Lord
God will come with strong hand, and his arme shall rule for him:
behold, his reward is with him, and his worke before
him.<note> Or, against the strong. , Chap.62. 11. , Or, recompence for his worke.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">He shall feede
his flocke like a shepheard: he shall gather the lambes with his
arme; and carie them in his bosome, and shall gently lead those
that are with yoong.<note> Eze.34. 23. ioh. 10.11. , Or, that giue sucke.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Who hath
measured the waters in the hollow of his hand? and meted out heauen
with the spanne, and comprehended the dust of the earth in a
measure, and weighed the mountaines in scales, and the hilles in a
balance?<note> Heb. a Tierce.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Who hath directed
the spirit of the Lord, or, being his counseller, hath taught
him?<note> Wisd.9. 13. rom.11. 34. 1.cor.2. 16. , Heb. man of his counsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">With whom tooke
he counsell, and who instructed him, and taught him in the path of
iudgement? and taught him knowledge, and shewed to him the way of
vnderstanding?<note> Heb. made him vnderstand. , Heb. vnderstandings.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Behold, the
nations are as a drop of a bucket, and are counted as the small
dust of the balance: behold, hee taketh vp the yles as a very litle
thing.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Lebanon is
not sufficient to burne, nor the beasts thereof sufficient for a
burnt offring.</ab>
<ab n="17">All nations
before him are as nothing, and they are counted to him lesse then
nothing, and vanitie.<note> Dan.4. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ To whom
then will ye liken God? or what likenesse will ye compare vnto
him?<note> Acts 17. 20.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods power, and prouidence for
his.</fw>
<ab n="19">The workeman
melteth a grauen image, and the goldsmith spreadeth it ouer with
golde, and casteth siluer chaines.</ab>
<ab n="20">He that is so
impouerished that he hath no oblation, chooseth a tree that will
not rot; he seeketh vnto him a cunning workeman, to prepare a
grauen image that shall not be mooued.<note> Heb. Is poore of oblation.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Haue yee not
knowen? haue yee not heard? hath it not beene tolde you from the
beginning? haue yee not vnderstood from the foundations of the
earth?</ab>
<ab n="22">It is he that
sitteth vpon the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof
are as grashoppers; that stretcheth out the heauens as a curtaine,
and spreadeth them out as a tent to dwel in:<note> Or, him that sitteth, &amp;c. , Psa.104.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">That bringeth the
princes to nothing; hee maketh the Iudges of the earth as
vanitie.<note> Iob 12.21. psa.107.40.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Yea they shal not
be planted, yea they shall not be sowen, yea their stocke shall not
take roote in the earth: and he shall also blow vpon them, &amp;
they shall wither, and the whirlewinde shall take them away as
stubble.</ab>
<ab n="25">To whom then will
ye liken me, or shal I be equall, saith the Holy One?</ab>
<ab n="26">Lift vp your eyes
on high, and behold who hath created these things, that bringeth
out their host by number: he calleth them all by names, by the
greatnesse of his might, for that hee is strong in power, not one
faileth.</ab>
<ab n="27">Why sayest thou,
O Iacob, and speakest O Israel, My way is hid from the Lord, and my
iudgement is passed ouer from my God?</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Hast thou
not knowen? hast thou not heard, that the euerlasting God, the
Lord, the Creatour of the ends of the earth, fainteth not, neither
is wearie? there is no searching of his vnderstanding.<note> Psa. 147.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">He giueth power
to the faint, and to them that haue no might, he increaseth
strength.</ab>
<ab n="30">Euen the youths
shall faint, and be weary, and the yong men shall vtterly
fall.</ab>
<ab n="31">But they that
waite vpon the Lord, shall renew their strength: they shall mount
vp with wings as Eagles, they shal runne and not be weary, and they
shall walke, and not faint.<note> Heb. change</note></ab>



</div>