<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_43" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-42-43.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIII.</head>
<head>1 The Lord comforteth the Church
with his promises. 8 Hee appealeth to the people for witnesse of
his Omnipotencie. 14 Hee foretelleth them the destruction of
Babylon, 18 and his wonderfull deliuerance of his people. 22 He
reprooueth the people as inexcusable.</head>

<ab n="1">But now thus
sayeth the Lord that created thee, O Iacob, and hee that formed
thee, O Israel; Feare not: for I haue redeemed thee, I haue called
thee by thy name, thou art mine.</ab>
<ab n="2">When thou passest
through the waters, I wil be with thee; and through the riuers,
they shal not ouerflow thee: when thou walkest through the fire,
thou shalt not be burnt; neither shall the flame kindle vpon
thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I am the Lord
thy God, the Holy one of Israel, thy Sauiour: I gaue Egypt for thy
ransome, Ethiopia and Seba for thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Since thou wast
precious in my sight, thou hast bene honourable, and I haue loued
thee: therefore will I giue men for thee, and people for thy
life.<note> Or, person.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Feare not, for I
am with thee: I will bring thy seed from the East, and gather thee
from the West.<note> Chap.44.1. iere.30.10. and 46.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I wil say to the
North, Giue vp; and to the South, Keepe not backe: bring my sonnes
from farre, and my daughters from the ends of the earth;</ab>
<ab n="7">Euen euery one
that is called by my Name: for I haue created him for my glory, I
haue formed him, yea I haue made him.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Bring
foorth the blinde people, that haue eyes; and the deafe that haue
eares.</ab>

<fw>Gods loue to his chosen people.</fw>
<ab n="9">Let all the
nations be gathered together, and let the people be assembled: who
among them can declare this, and shew vs former things? let them
bring foorth their witnesses, that they may be iustified: or let
them heare, and say, It is trueth.<note> Chap.41. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yee are my
witnesses, saith the Lord, and my seruant whom I haue chosen: that
ye may know and beleeue me, and vnderstand that I am he: before me
there was no God formed, neither shall there be after
me.<note> Cha.41.4 and 44.8, , Or, nothing formed of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">I, euen I am the
Lord, and beside me there is no Sauiour.<note> Chap.45. 21. ose.13. 4</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I haue declared,
and haue saued, and I haue shewed, when there was no strange God
among you: therefore yee are my witnesses, saith the Lord, that I
am God.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yea before the
day was, I am hee; and there is none that can deliuer out of my
hand: I will worke, and who shall let it?<note> Heb. turne it backe. , Iob 9. 12. chap.14.17</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Thus sayth
the Lord your Redeemer, the Holy one of Israel; For your sake I
haue sent to Babylon, and haue brought downe all their nobles, and
the Caldeans, whose crie is in the shippes.<note> Heb. barres</note></ab>
<ab n="15">I am the Lord,
your Holy one, the Creatour of Israel, your King.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus sayth the
Lord, which maketh a way in the sea, and a path in the mightie
waters:<note> Exod. 14. , Iosh. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Which bringeth
foorth the charet and horse, the armie and the power: they shall
lie downe together, they shall not rise: they are extinct, they are
quenched as towe.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Remember
yee not the former things, neither consider the things of
olde.</ab>
<ab n="19">Behold, I will
doe a new thing: now it shall spring foorth, shall yee not know it?
I will euen make a way in the wildernesse, and riuers in the
desert.<note> 2.Cor.6. 17. reuel. 21.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The beast of the
field shall honor mee, the dragons and the owles, because I giue
waters in the wildernesse, and riuers in the desert, to giue drinke
to my people, my chosen.<note> Or, ostriches. Hebr. daughters of the owle.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">This people haue
I formed for my selfe, they shall shewe foorth my
praise.<note> Luke 1. 74,75.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ But thou
hast not called vpon me, O Iacob, but thou hast beene wearie of me,
O Israel.</ab>

<fw>Gods loue to his chosen people.</fw>
<ab n="23">Thou hast not
brought mee the small cattell of thy burnt offrings, neither hast
thou honoured mee with thy sacrifices. I haue not caused thee to
serue with an offring, nor wearied thee with incense.<note> Heb. lambs or kids.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Thou hast bought
mee no sweete cane with money, neither hast thou filled mee with
the fat of thy sacrifices: but thou hast made mee to serue with thy
sins, thou hast wearied mee with thine iniquities.<note> Heb. made me drunke: or, abundantly moistened.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">I, euen I am hee
that blotteth out thy transgressions for mine owne sake, and will
not remember thy sinnes.<note> Ezek.36. 22,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Put mee in
remembrance: let vs plead together: declare thou, that thou mayest
bee iustified.</ab>
<ab n="27">Thy first father
hath sinned, and thy teachers haue transgressed against
mee.<note> Heb. interpreters.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore I haue
profaned the princes of the Sanctuarie, and haue giuen Iacob to the
curse, and Israel to reproches.<note> Or, holy princes.</note></ab>



</div>