<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_45" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-45-45.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-45-47.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLV.</head>
<head>1 God calleth Cyrus for his Churches
sake. 5 By his omnipotencie he challengeth obedience. 20 Hee
conuinceth the idoles of vanitie, by his sauing power.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord to his Anointed, to Cyrus whose right hande I haue holden, to
subdue nations before him: and I will loose the loines of kings to
open before him the two leaued gates, and the gates shall not be
shut.<note> Or, strengthened.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I will goe before
thee, and make the crooked places straight, I wil break in pieces
the gates of brasse, and cut in sunder the barres of yron.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I will giue
thee the treasures of darkenesse, &amp; hidden riches of secret
places, that thou mayest know, that I the Lord which call thee by
thy name, am the God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">For Iacob my
seruants sake, and Israel mine elect, I haue euen called thee by
thy name: I haue surnamed thee, though thou hast not knowen
me.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ I am the
Lord, and there is none els, there is no God besides me: I girded
thee, though thou hast not knowen me:<note> Deu.4.35. 39. and 32. 39. chap. 44.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">That they may
knowe from the rising of the Sun, and from the West, that there is
none besides me, I am the Lord, and there is none else.</ab>
<ab n="7">I forme the light,
and create darkenesse: I make peace, and create euill: I the Lord
do all these things.</ab>
<ab n="8">Drop downe, ye
heauens, from aboue, and let the skies powre downe righteousnesse:
let the earth open, and let them bring forth saluation, and let
righteousnesse spring vp together: I the Lord haue created
it.</ab>
<ab n="9">Woe vnto him that
striueth with his maker: Let the potsheard striue with the
potsheards of the earth: shal the clay say to him that fashioneth
it, What makest thou? or thy worke, he hath no hands?<note> Ier.18.6. rom.9.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Woe vnto him that
saith vnto his father, What begettest thou? or to the woman, What
hast thou brought forth?</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus saith the
Lord, the Holy One of Israel, and his maker, Aske me of things to
come concerning my sonnes, and concerning the worke of my hands
command ye me.</ab>

<fw>God onely Lord.</fw>
<ab n="12">I haue made the
earth, and created man vpon it: I, euen my handes haue stretched
out the heauens, and all their hoste haue I commanded.</ab>
<ab n="13">I haue raised him
vp in righteousnesse, and I will direct all his wayes: he shall
build my citie, and hee shall let goe my captiues, not for price
nor reward, saith the Lord of hosts.<note> Or, make straight. , Chron. 36 22. ezra 1.1 cha. 44. 28</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thus saith the
Lord, The labour of Egypt, and merchandise of Ethiopia, and of the
Sabeans, men of stature shall come ouer vnto thee, and they shall
be thine, they shall come after thee, in chaines they shall come
ouer: and they shal fall downe vnto thee, they shal make
supplication vnto thee, saying, Surely God is in thee, and there is
none else, there is no god.</ab>
<ab n="15">Uerely thou art a
God that hidest thy selfe, O God of Israel the Sauiour.</ab>
<ab n="16">They shall be
ashamed, and also confounded all of them: they shall goe to
confusion together that are makers of idoles.<note> Chap.44. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But Israel shall
bee saued in the Lord with an euerlasting saluation: ye shall not
be ashamed nor confounded world without end.</ab>
<ab n="18">For thus saith
the Lord that created the heauens, God himselfe that formed the
earth and made it, hee hath established it, he created it not in
vaine, he formed it to be inhabited, I am the Lord, and there is
none else.</ab>
<ab n="19">I haue not spoken
in secret, in a darke place of the earth: I said not vnto the seed
of Iacob, Seeke ye mee in vaine: I the Lord speake righteousnesse,
I declare things that are right.<note> Deut. 30. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Assemble
your selues and come: draw neere together ye that are escaped of
the nations: they haue no knowledge that set vp the wood of their
grauen image, and pray vnto a god that cannot saue.</ab>
<ab n="21">Tell ye and bring
them neere, yea let them take counsell together, who hath declared
this from ancient time? who hath told it from that time? Haue not I
the Lord ? and there is no God else beside me, a iust God and a
Sauiour, there is none beside me.</ab>
<ab n="22">Looke vnto mee,
and be ye saued all the endes of the earth: for I am God, and there
is none else.</ab>

<fw>God beareth his.</fw>
<ab n="23">I haue sworne by
my selfe: the word is gone out of my mouth in righteousnes, and
shall not returne, that vnto me euery knee shall bowe, euery tongue
shall sweare.<note> Rom. 14. 11. phil.2. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Surely, shall one
say, In the Lord haue I righteousnesse and strength: euen to him
shall men come, and all that are incensed against him, shalbe
ashamed.<note> Or, surely he shall say of me, In the Lord is all righteousnes and strength. Hebr. righteousnesses.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">In the Lord shall
all the seed of Israel be iustified, and shall glory.</ab>



</div>