<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_62" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-61-63.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXII.</head>
<head>1 The feruent desire of the Prophet,
to confirme the Church in Gods promises. 5 The office of the
Ministers, (vnto which they are incited) in preaching the Gospel,
10 and preparing the people thereto.</head>

<ab n="1">For Zions sake,
wil I not hold my peace, and for Ierusalems sake I will not rest,
vntill the righteousnesse thereof goe forth as brightnesse, and the
saluation thereof as a lampe that burneth;</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Gentiles
shall see thy righteousnes, and all Kings thy glory: and thou shalt
be called by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord shall
name.</ab>

<fw>The duetie of Watchmen.</fw>
<ab n="3">Thou shalt also be
a crowne of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royall diademe in
the hand of thy God.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou shalt no more
bee termed, Forsaken; neither shall thy land any more be termed,
Desolate: but thou shalt be called Hephzi-bah, and thy land,
Beulah: for the Lord delighteth in thee, and thy land shalbe
maried.<note> Ose.1.10. 1.pet.2.10. , That is, my delight is in her. , That is, married.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ For as a
yong man marrieth a virgine, so shall thy sonnes marry thee: and as
the bridegrome reioyceth ouer the bride, so shall thy God reioyce
ouer thee.<note> Hebr. with the ioy of the bridegrome.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I haue set
watchmen vpon thy walles, O Ierusalem, which shall neuer hold their
peace day nor night: ye that make mention of the Lord, keepe not
silence:<note> Or, ye that are the Lords remembrancers.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And giue him no
rest till he establish, and till hee make Ierusalem a praise in the
earth.<note> Hebr. silence.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord hath
sworne by his Right hand, and by the arme of his strength, Surely,
I will no more giue thy corne to be meat for thine enemies, and the
sonnes of the stranger shall not drinke thy wine, for the which
thou hast laboured:<note> Hebr. if he giue, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But they that haue
gathered it shall eat it, and praise the Lord, and they that haue
brought it together, shal drinke it in the Courts of my
Holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Goe
through, goe through the gates: prepare you the way of the people:
cast vp, cast vp the high way, gather out the stones, lift vp a
standard for the people.<note> Chap.40. 3. &amp; 57.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, the Lord
hath proclaimed vnto the end of the world, say ye to the daughter
of Zion, Behold, thy saluation commeth; behold, his reward is with
him, and his worke before him.<note> Zach.9.9. matth.21.5. iohn 12.15. , Chap.40. 10. , Or, recompence.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they shall
call them, The holy people: the redeemed of the Lord: and thou
shalt be called, Sought out, a citie not forsaken.</ab>



</div>