<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_58" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-57-59.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LVIII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet being sent to reprooue
hypocrisie, 3 expresseth a counterfeit fast, and a true. 8 He
declareth what promises are due vnto godlinesse, 13 and to the
keeping of the Sabbath.</head>

<ab n="1">Crie aloude, spare
not, lift vp thy voice like a trumpet, and shewe my people their
transgression, &amp; the house of Iacob their sins.<note> Heb. with the throat.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Yet they seeke mee
daily, and delight to know my wayes, as a nation that did
righteousnesse, and forsooke not the ordinance of their God: they
aske of me the ordinances of iustice: they take delight in
approching to God.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Wherefore
haue wee fasted, say they, and thou seest not? wherefore haue wee
afflicted our soule, &amp; thou takest no knowledge? Behold, in the
day of your fast you find pleasure, and exact all your
labours.<note> Or, things wherewith ye grieue others. Heb. griefes.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, yee fast
for strife and debate; and to smite with the fist of wickednesse,
yee shall not fast as yee doe this day, to make your voice to be
heard on high.<note> Or, ye fast not as this day.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Is it such a fast
that I haue chosen? a day for a man to afflict his soule? Is it to
bow down his head as a bulrush, and to spread sackecloth and ashes
vnder him? wilt thou call this a fast, and an acceptable day to the
Lord ?<note> Zech.7.5. , Leuit.16. 29. , Or, to afflict his soule for a day?</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Is not this the
fast that I haue chosen? to loose the bandes of wickednesse, to
vndoe the heauie burdens, and to let the oppressed goe free, and
that ye breake euery yoke?<note> Heb. the bundles of the yoke. , Heb. broken.</note></ab>

<fw>The true fast, and true
Sabbath.</fw>
<ab n="7">Is it not, to
deale thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poore that
are cast out, to thy house? when thou seest the naked, that thou
couer him, and that thou hide not thy selfe from thine owne
flesh?<note> Eze.18.8. , Or, afflicted.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then shall
thy light breake foorth as the morning, and thine health shall
spring foorth speedily: and thy righteousnesse shall goe before
thee, the glory of the Lord shall be thy rereward.<note> Heb. shall gather thee vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then shalt thou
call, and the Lord shall answere; thou shalt cry, and he shal say,
Here I am: if thou take away from the midst of thee the yoke, the
putting forth of the finger, and speaking vanitie:</ab>
<ab n="10">And if thou draw
out thy soule to the hungry, and satisfie the afflicted soule: then
shall thy light rise in obscuritie, and thy darkenesse be as the
noone day.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord shal
guide thee continually, and satisfie thy soule in drought, and make
fat thy bones: and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a
spring of water, whose waters faile not.<note> Hebr. droughts. , Heb. lye, or deceiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they that
shall be of thee, shall builde the olde waste places: thou shalt
raise vp the foundations of many generations; and thou shalt be
called, the repairer of the breach, the restorer of paths to dwell
in.<note> Cha. 61.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ If thou
turne away thy foote from the Sabbath, from doing thy pleasure on
my Holy day, and call the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord,
honourable, and shalt honour him, not doing thine owne wayes, nor
finding thine owne pleasure, nor speaking thine owne
wordes:</ab>
<ab n="14">Then shalt thou
delight thy selfe in the Lord, and I will cause thee to ride vpon
the high places of the earth, and feede thee with the heritage of
Iacob thy father; for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken
it.<note> Deut. 32. 13.</note></ab>



</div>