<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-17-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 God in care of his people will
destroy the Ethiopians. 7 An accesse thereby shall grow vnto the
Church.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to the land
shadowing with wings, which is beyond the riuers of
Ethiopia:</ab>
<ab n="2">That sendeth
ambassadours by the sea, euen in vessels of bulrushes vpon the
waters, saying; Goe yee swift messengers to a nation scattered and
peeled, to a people terrible from their beginning hitherto, a
nation meted out and troden downe; whose land the riuers haue
spoiled.<note> Or, outspread and polished. , Or, a nation that meteth out, and treadeth downe. Heb. a nation of line line, and treading vnderfoote. , Or, whose land the riuers despise.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">All yee
inhabitants of the world, and dwellers on the earth, see yee, when
hee lifteth vp an ensigne on the mountaines; and when he bloweth a
trumpet, heare yee.</ab>
<ab n="4">For so the Lord
sayd vnto me: I will take my rest, and I will consider in my
dwelling place like a cleare heate vpon herbes, and like a cloud of
dew in the heate of haruest.<note> Or, regard my set dwelling. , Or, after raine.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Ethiopia, and Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="5">For afore the
haruest when the bud is perfect, and the sowre grape is ripening in
the flowre; hee shall both cut off the sprigges with pruning
hookes, and take away and cut downe the branches.</ab>
<ab n="6">They shalbe left
together vnto the foules of the mountaines, and to the beasts of
the earth: and the foules shall summer vpon them, and all the
beastes of the earth shall winter vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ In that
time shall the present be brought vnto the Lord of hostes, of a
people scattered and peeled, and from a people terrible from their
beginning hitherto; a nation meted out and troden vnder foote,
whose land the riuers haue spoiled, to the place of the name of the
Lord of hostes, the mount Zion.<note> Or, outspread and polished. &amp;c.</note></ab>



</div>