<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Ahaz, being troubled with feare of
Rezin and Pekah, is comforted by Isaiah. 10 Ahaz, hauing liberty to
choose a signe, and refusing it, hath for a signe, Christ promised.
17 His iudgement is prophecied to come by Assyria.</head>


<fw>Christ promised, and called
Immanuel.</fw>
<ab n="1">And it came
to passe in the dayes of Ahaz the sonne of Iotham, the sonne of
Uzziah king of Iudah, that Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah, the
sonne of Remaliah king of Israel, went vp towards Ierusalem to
warre against it, but could not preuaile against it.<note> 2.kings. 16.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it was
told the house of Dauid, saying, Syria is confederate with Ephraim:
and his heart was moued, and the heart of his people as the trees
of the wood are mooued with the wind.<note> Heb. resteth on Ephraim.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then sayd the
Lord vnto Isaiah; Goe forth now to meete Ahaz, thou, &amp;
Shear-iashub thy sonne, at the end of the conduit of the vpper
poole in the high way of the fullers field.<note> That is, the remnant shal returne. , 2.kings. 18.17. , Or, causeway.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And say vnto
him; Take heede and be quiet: feare not, neither be faint hearted
for the two tailes of these smoking firebrands, for the fierce
anger of Rezin with Syria, and of the sonne of
Remaliah.<note> Heb. let not thy heart be tender.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Because
Syria, Ephraim, and the sonne of Remaliah haue taken euill counsell
against thee, saying;</ab>
<ab n="6">Let vs goe vp
against Iudah and vexe it, and let vs make a breach therein for vs,
and set a king in the midst of it, euen the sonne of
Tabeal.<note> Or, waken.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thus saith
the Lord God; It shall not stand, neither shall it come to
passe.</ab>
<ab n="8">For the head
of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin, and within
threescore and fiue yeeres shall Ephraim be broken, that it be not
a people.<note> Heb. from a people.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the head
of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliahs sonne:
if yee will not beleeue, surely yee shall not be
established.<note> Or, doe yee not beleeue? it is because yee are not stable.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Moreouer
the Lord spake againe vnto Ahaz, saying;<note> Heb. and the Lord added to speak.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Aske thee a signe
of the Lord thy God; aske it either in the depth, or in the height
aboue.<note> Or, make thy petition deepe.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But Ahaz sayd, I
will not aske, neither will I tempt the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he sayd; Heare
yee now, O house of Dauid; Is it a small thing for you to wearie
men, but will yee wearie my God also?</ab>

<fw>Christ promised, and called
Immanuel.</fw>
<ab n="14">Therefore the Lord
himselfe shal giue you a signe: Behold, a Uirgine shall conceiue
and beare a Sonne, and shall call his name Immanuel.<note> Math.1. 23. luc.1. 31. , Or, thou, O Virgin, shalt call.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Butter and hony
shall he eat, that hee may know to refuse the euill, and choose the
good.</ab>
<ab n="16">For before the
childe shall know to refuse the euill and choose the good; the land
that thou abhorrest, shalbe forsaken of both her kings.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ The Lord
shall bring vpon thee and vpon thy people, and vpon thy fathers
house, dayes that haue not come, from the day that Ephraim departed
from Iudah; euen the King of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it shall come
to passe in that day, that the Lord shall hisse for the flie, that
is in the vttermost part of the riuers of Egypt, and for the Bee
that is in the land of Assyria.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they shall
come, and shall rest all of them in the desolate valleys, and in
the holes of the rockes, and vpon all thornes, and vpon all
bushes.<note> Or, comendable trees.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">In the same day
shall the Lord shaue with a rasor that is hired, namely by them
beyond the riuer, by the king of Assyria, the head, and the haire
of the feet: and it shal also consume the beard.<note> 2.King. 19.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And it shall come
to passe in that day, that a man shal nourish a yong cow and two
sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="22">And it shall come
to passe, for the abundance of milke that they shall giue, he shal
eate butter: for butter and hony shall euery one eate, that is left
in the land.<note> Hebr. in the midst of the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And it shall come
to passe in that day, that euery place shalbe, where there were a
thousand Uines at a thousand siluerlings, it shall euen be for
briers and thornes.</ab>
<ab n="24">With arrowes and
with bowes shall men come thither; because all the land shall
become briars and thornes.</ab>
<ab n="25">And on all hilles
that shalbe digged with the mattocke, there shall not come thither
the feare of briars and thornes: but it shall bee for the sending
foorth of oxen, and for the treading of lesser cattell.</ab>



</div>