<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the Parable of a Vineyard,
God excuseth his seuere iudgement. 8 His iudgements vpon
couetousnesse, 11 Vpon lasciuiousnesse, 13 Vpon impietie, 20 and
vpon iniustice. 26 The executioners of Gods
iudgements.</head>

<ab n="1">Now will I
sing to my welbeloued, a song of my beloued touching his vineyard:
my wellbeloued hath a vineyard in a very fruitfull
hill.<note> Iere. 2.21. mat. 21.33. mark.12.1. luke 20.9. , Heb. the horne of the sonne of oyle.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee
fenced it, and gathered out the stones thereof, and planted it with
the choicest vine, and built a towre in the middest of it, and also
made a winepresse therein: and he looked that it should bring
foorth grapes, and it brought foorth wilde grapes.<note> Or, made a wall about it. , Heb. hewed.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And now, O
inhabitants of Ierusalem, and men of Iudah, Iudge, I pray you,
betwixt me and my Uineyard.</ab>
<ab n="4">What could
haue beene done more to my Uineyard, that I haue not done in it?
wherefore when I looked that it should bring foorth grapes, brought
it foorth wilde grapes?</ab>
<ab n="5">And now goe
to; I will tell you what I will doe to my Uineyard, I will take
away the hedge thereof, and it shall be eaten vp; and breake downe
the wall thereof, and it shall be troden downe.<note> Heb. for a treading.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I will
lay it waste; it shall not be pruned, nor digged, but there shall
come vp briars and thornes: I will also command the cloudes, that
they raine no raine vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the
Uineyard of the Lord of hostes is the house of Israel, and the men
of Iudah his pleasant plant: and he looked for iudgement, but
beholde oppression; for righteousnesse, but behold a
crie.<note> Heb. plant of his pleasures. , Heb.a scab.</note></ab>

<fw>Couetousnesse and riot are
threatened.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ Woe
vnto them that ioyne house to house, that lay field to field, till
there be no place, that they may be placed alone in the midst of
the earth.<note> Mich.2.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">In mine eares
said the Lord of hostes, Of a trueth many houses shall be desolate,
euen great and faire without inhabitant.<note> Or, this is in mine eares saith the LORD, &amp;c. , Heb. If not, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yea ten acres of
vineyard shall yeeld one Bath, and the seed of an Homer shall yeeld
an Ephah.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Woe vnto
them that rise vp earely in the morning, that they may follow
strong drink, that continue vntill night, till wine enflame
them.<note> Prou. 23. 29,30. , Or, pursue them.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the harpe and
the viole, the tabret and pipe, and wine are in their feasts: but
they regard not the worke of the Lord, neither consider the
operation of his hands.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Therefore
my people are gone into captiuitie, because they haue no knowledge:
and their honourable men are famished, aud their multitude dried vp
with thirst.<note> Heb. their glory are men of famine.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore hell
hath enlarged her selfe, and opened her mouth without measure: and
their glory, and their multitude, and their pompe, and hee that
reioyceth, shall descend into it.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the meane man
shall bee brought downe, and the mightie man shall be humbled, and
the eyes of the loftie shall be humbled.<note> Isa. 2.9. 11.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But the Lord of
hosts shalbe exalted in iudgement, and God that is holy, shall bee
sanctified in righteousnesse.<note> Or, the holy God. Heb. The God the holy.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Then shall the
lambes feed after their maner, and the waste places of the fat ones
shall strangers eate.</ab>
<ab n="18">Woe vnto them that
draw iniquitie with cords of vanitie, and sinne, as it were with a
cart rope:</ab>
<ab n="19">That say, Let him
make speede, and hasten his worke, that we may see it: and let the
counsell of the holy one of Israel draw nigh and come, that wee may
know it.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Woe vnto
them that call euill good, and good euill, that put darkenes for
light, and light for darkenesse, that put bitter for sweete, and
sweete for bitter.<note> Heb. that say concerning euill, It is good,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Woe vnto them that
are wise in their owne eyes, and prudent in their owne
sight.<note> Prou.3.7. rom. 12.16 , Heb. before their face.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Woe vnto them that
are mightie to drinke wine, and men of strength to mingle strong
drinke.</ab>

<fw>Couetousnesse and riot are
threatened.</fw>
<ab n="23">Which iustifie the
wicked for reward, and take away the righteousnes of the righteous
from him.<note> Prou. 17. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Therfore as the
fire deuoureth the stubble, and the flame consumeth the chaffe, so
their root shall be rottennes, and their blossome shall goe vp as
dust: because they haue cast away the Lawe of the Lord of hosts,
and despised the worde of the Holy One of Israel.<note> Hebr. the tongue of fire.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore is the
anger of the Lord kindled against his people, and he hath stretched
foorth his hande against them, and hath smitten them: and the
hilles did tremble, and their carkeises were torne in the midst of
the streets: for all this, his anger is not turned away, but his
hand is stretched out still.<note> Or as doung. , Cha. 9. 11 16.21. and 10.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And he will
lift vp an ensigne to the nations from farre, and wil hisse vnto
them from the end of the earth: and behold, they shall come with
speed swiftly.</ab>
<ab n="27">None shalbe weary,
nor stumble amongst them: none shall slumber nor sleepe, neither
shall the girdle of their loynes be loosed, nor the latchet of
their shooes be broken.</ab>
<ab n="28">Whose arrowes are
sharpe, and all their bowes bent, their horses hoofs shall bee
counted like flint, and their wheeles like a whirlewind.</ab>
<ab n="29">Their roaring
shalbe like a lyon, they shall roare like yong lions: yea they shal
roare and lay hold of the pray, and shall carie it away safe, and
none shall deliuer it.</ab>
<ab n="30">And in that day
they shall roare against them, like the roaring of the sea: and if
one looke vnto the land, behold darkenesse and sorrow, and the
light is darkened in the heauens therof.<note> Or, distresse. , Or, when it is light it shalbe darke in the destructions thereof.</note></ab>



</div>