<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_41" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLI.</head>
<head>1 God expostulateth with his people,
about his mercies to the Church, 10 about his promises, 21 and
about the vanity of Idoles.</head>


<fw>Gods power, and prouidence for
his.</fw>
<ab n="1">Keepe silence
before me, O ylands, and let the people renew their strength: let
them come neere, then let them speake: let vs come neere together
to iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="2">Who raised vp the
righteous man from the East, called him to his foote, gaue the
nations before him, and made him rule ouer kings? Hee gaue them as
the dust to his sword, and as driuen stuble to his bow.<note> Heb. righteousnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">He pursued them,
and passed safely; euen by the way, that hee had not gone with his
feete.<note> Heb. in peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Who hath wrought
and done it, calling the generations from the beginning? I the Lord
the first, and with the last, I am he.<note> Chap.43.10. and 44.6. and 48.12. reu.1. 17. and 22. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The yles saw it
and feared, the ends of the earth were afraid, drew neere, and
came.</ab>
<ab n="6">They helped euery
one his neighbour, and euery one sayd to his brother, Be of good
courage.<note> Heb. be strong.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So the carpenter
encouraged the goldsmith, and he that smootheth with the hammer him
that smote the anuill, saying; It is ready for the sodering: and he
fastened it with nayles that it should not be moued.<note> Or founder. , Or, the smiting. , Or, saying of the soder, it is good.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But thou Israel,
art my seruant, Iacob whom I haue chosen, the seede of Abraham my
friend.<note> Deut.7.6 and 10. 15. and 14. 2. psal. 135.4. chap.43.1. and 44 1. , 2.Chron. 20.7. iam 2. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thou whom I haue
taken from the ends of the earth, and called thee from the chiefe
men thereof, and sayd vnto thee; Thou art my seruant, I haue chosen
thee, and not cast thee away.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Feare thou
not, for I am with thee: be not dismaied, for I am thy God: I will
strengthen thee, yea I will helpe thee, yea I will vphold thee with
the right hand of my righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, all they
that were incensed against thee, shalbe ashamed and confounded:
they shall be as nothing, and they that striue with thee, shall
perish.<note> Exod. 23. 22. chap. 60.12. Zech.12.3. , Heb. the men of thy strife.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thou shalt seeke
them, and shalt not find them, euen them that contended with thee:
they that warre against thee shalbe as nothing, and as a thing of
nought.<note> Heb. the men of thy contention. , Heb. the men of thy warre.</note></ab>

<fw>What idoles are.</fw>
<ab n="13">For I the Lord
thy God will hold thy right hand, saying vnto thee, Feare not, I
will helpe thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Feare not, thou
worme Iacob, and ye men of Israel: I will helpe thee, saith the
Lord, and thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel.<note> Or, few men.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Behold, I will
make thee a new sharpe threshing instrument hauing teeth: thou
shalt thresh the mountaines, and beate them small, and shalt make
the hilles as chaffe.<note> Hebr. mouthes.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Thou shalt fanne
them, and the winde shall carie them away, and the whirlewinde
shall scatter them: and thou shalt reioyce in the Lord, and shalt
glory in the Holy One of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="17">When the poore
and needie seeke water and there is none, and their tongue faileth
for thirst, I the Lord will heare them, I the God of Israel will
not forsake them.</ab>
<ab n="18">I will open
riuers in hie places, and fountaines in the midst of the valleys: I
will make the wildernesse a poole of water, and the dry land
springs of water.<note> Chap.35. 7. and 44.3. , Psal. 107. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">I will plant in
the wildernes the Cedar, the Shittah tree, and the Myrtle, and the
Oyle tree: I will set in the desert the Firre tree, and the Pine
and the Boxe tree together:</ab>
<ab n="20">That they may
see, and knowe, and consider, and vnderstand together, that the
hand of the Lord hath done this, and the Holy One of Israel hath
created it.</ab>
<ab n="21">Produce your
cause, saith the Lord, bring foorth your strong reasons, saith the
King of Iacob.<note> Heb. cause to come neere.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Let them bring
them foorth, and shew vs what shall happen: let them shew the
former things what they bee, that we may consider them, and know
the latter end of them, or declare vs things for to
come.<note> Heb. set our heart vpon them.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Shewe the things
that are to come hereafter, that wee may knowe that ye are gods:
yea doe good or doe euill, that we may be dismayed, and behold it
together.</ab>
<ab n="24">Behold, ye are of
nothing, and your worke of nought: an abomination is he that
chooseth you.<note> Or, worse then nothing , Or, worse then of a viper.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">I haue raised vp
one from the North, and he shall come: from the rising of the Sunne
shall he call vpon my name, and he shall come vpon princes as vpon
morter, and as the potter treadeth clay.</ab>

<fw>Christs Office.</fw>
<ab n="26">Who hath declared
from the beginning, that we may know? and before time, that we may
say, He is righteous? yea there is none that sheweth, yea there is
none that declareth, yea there is none that heareth your
words.</ab>
<ab n="27">The first shall
say to Zion, Behold, behold them, and I will giue to Ierusalem one
that bringeth good tidings.</ab>
<ab n="28">For I behelde,
and there was no man, euen amongst them, and there was no
counseller, that when I asked of them, could answere a
word.<note> Heb. returne.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Behold, they are
all vanitie, their works are nothing: their moulten images are
winde and confusion.</ab>



</div>