<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_53" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-51-53.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-53-54.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LIII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet complaining of
incredulitie, excuseth the scandall of the crosse, 4 by the
benefite of his passion, 10 and the good successe
thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">Who hath beleeued
our report? and to whom is the arme of the Lord
reuealed?<note> Ioh.12.38. rom.10.16. , Or, doctrine: Heb. hearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For he shall grow
vp before him as a tender plant, and as a root out of a drie
ground: hee hath no forme nor comelinesse: and when wee shall see
him, there is no beautie that we should desire him.</ab>
<ab n="3">He is despised and
reiected of men, a man ofsorrows, and acquainted with griefe: and
we hid as it were our faces from him; hee was despised, and wee
esteemed him not.<note> Chap. 32. 14. mar. 9.12. , Or, he hid as it were his face from vs. Heb. as a hiding of faces from him or from vs.</note></ab>

<fw>Christs passion.</fw>
<ab n="4">¶ Surely he
hath borne our griefes, and caried our sorrowes: yet we did esteeme
him striken, smitten of God, and afflicted.<note> Mat.8.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But he was wounded
for our transgressions, he was bruised for our iniquities: the
chastisement of our peace was vpon him, and with his stripes we are
healed.<note> Or, tormented. , Rom.4. 25 1.cor. 15. 3. , 1. Pet. 2. 24. , Heb. bruise.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">All we like sheepe
haue gone astray: we haue turned euery one to his owne way, and the
Lord hath layd on him the iniquitie of vs all.<note> Heb. hee hath made the iniquitie of vs all to meete on him.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">He was oppressed,
and he was afflicted, yet he opened not his mouth: he is brought as
a lambe to the slaughter, and as a sheepe before her shearers is
dumme, so he openeth not his mouth.<note> Matth.26. 63. and 27. 12. mar. 14. 61. and 15. 6. , Actes 8. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He was taken from
prison, and from iudgement: and who shall declare his generation?
for he was cut off out of the land of the liuing, for the
transgression of my people was he stricken.<note> Or, he was taken away by distresse and iudgement: but &amp;c. , Heb. was the stroke vpon him.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And he made his
graue with the wicked, and with the rich in his death, because he
had done no violence, neither was any deceit in his
mouth.<note> Heb. deathes. , 1.Pet.2. 22. 1.ioh. 3. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Yet it
pleased the Lord to bruise him, he hath put him to griefe: when
thou shalt make his soule an offring for sinne, he shall see his
seede, hee shall prolong his daies, and the pleasure of the Lord
shall prosper in his hand.<note> Or, when his soule shall make an offring.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">He shall see of
the trauell of his soule, and shalbe satisfied: by his knowledge
shall my righteous seruant iustifie many: for hee shall beare their
iniquities.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore will I
diuide him a portion with the great, and he shall diuide the spoile
with the strong: because hee hath powred out his soule vnto death:
and he was numbred with the transgressours, and he bare the sinne
of many, and made intercession for the transgressours.<note> Mar.15. 28. luc.22. 37. , Luc.23.8.</note></ab>



</div>