<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_63" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-61-63.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-63-64.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXIII.</head>
<head>1 Christ sheweth who he is, 2 what
his victory ouer his enemies, 7 and what his mercy toward his
Church. 10 In his iust wrath hee remembreth his free Mercy. 15 The
Church in their prayer, 17 and complaint, professe their
Faith.</head>


<fw>Gods mercies.</fw>
<ab n="1">Who is this that
commeth from Edom, with died garments from Bozrah? this that is
glorious in his apparel, trauelling in the greatnesse of his
strength? I that speake in righteousnesse, mightie to
saue.<note> Hebr. decked.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore art thou
red in thine apparell, and thy garments like him that treadeth in
the winefat?<note> Reu. 19. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I haue troden the
winepresse alone, and of the people there was none with me: for I
will tread them in mine anger, and trample them in my furie, and
their blood shall be sprinkled vpon my garments, and I will staine
all my raiment.</ab>
<ab n="4">For the day of
vengeance is in mine heart, and the yeere of my redeemed is
come.<note> Chap. 34. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And I looked, and
there was none to helpe; and I wondered that there was none to
vphold: therefore mine owne arme brought saluation vnto me, and my
furie, it vpheld me.<note> Chap. 59. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I will tread
downe the people in mine anger, &amp; make them drunke in my furie,
and I will bring downe their strength to the earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ I will
mention the louing kindnesses of the Lord, and the praises of the
Lord, according to all that the Lord hath bestowed on vs; and the
great goodnes towards the house of Israel, which he hath bestowed
on them, according to his mercies, and according to the multitude
of his louing kindnesses.</ab>
<ab n="8">For hee said,
Surely they are my people, children that will not lie: so hee was
their sauiour.</ab>
<ab n="9">In all their
affliction he was afflicted, and the Angel of his presence saued
them: in his loue and in his pitie hee redeemed them, and he bare
them, and caried them all the dayes of olde.<note> Deut.7. 7,8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ But they
rebelled, and vexed his holy spirit: therefore hee was turned to be
their enemie, and he fought against them.<note> Exod. 15. 24. num.14. 11. psal.78. 57. and 95.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then he remembred
the dayes of old, Moses and his people, saying; Where is hee that
brought them vp out of the Sea, with the shepheard of his flocke?
where is hee that put his holy Spirit within him?<note> Exod.14. 30. , Or, shepheards, as Psal.77.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">That led them by
the right hand of Moses with his glorious arme, diuiding the water
before them, to make himselfe an euerlasting name?<note> Exod. 14. 27. iosh. 15.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">That led them
through the deepe as an horse in the wildernesse, that they should
not stumble?</ab>

<fw>God our Father.</fw>
<ab n="14">As a beast goeth
downe into the valley, the Spirit of the Lord caused him to rest:
so diddest thou leade thy people, to make thy selfe a glorious
Name.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Looke
downe from heauen, and behold from the habitation of thy holinesse,
and of thy glory: where is thy zeale and thy strength, the sounding
of thy bowels, and of thy mercies towards me? are they
restrained?<note> Deut. 26. 15. , Or, the multitude.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Doubtlesse thou
art our father, though Abraham be ignorant of vs, and Israel
acknowledge vs not: thou, O Lord art our Father, our Redeemer, thy
Name is from euerlasting.<note> Or, our redeemer, from euerlasting is thy name.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ O Lord,
why hast thou made vs to erre from thy wayes? and hardened our
heart from thy feare? Returne for thy seruants sake, the tribes of
thine inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="18">The people of thy
holinesse haue possessed it but a little while: our aduersaries
haue troden downe thy Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wee are thine,
thou neuer barest rule ouer them, they were not called by thy
Name.<note> Heb. thy name was not called vpon them.</note></ab>



</div>