<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_54" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-53-54.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-54-56.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LIV.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet for the comfort of the
Gentiles, prophesieth the amplitude of their Church. 4 Their
safety, 6 their certaine deliuerance out of affliction, 11 their
faire edification, 15 and their sure preseruation.</head>


<fw>Gods great mercie.</fw>
<ab n="1">Sing O barren thou
that didst not beare; breake forth into singing, and crie aloud
thou that didst not trauell with child: for more are the children
of the desolate then the children of the maried wife, saith the
Lord.<note> Gal.4. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Enlarge the place
of thy tent, and let them stretch forth the curtaines of thine
habitations: spare not, lengthen thy cords, and strengthen thy
stakes.</ab>
<ab n="3">For thou shalt
breake forth on the right hand, and on the left; and thy seed shall
inherite the Gentiles, and make the desolate cities to be
inhabited.</ab>
<ab n="4">Feare not: for
thou shalt not be ashamed: neither be thou confounded, for thou
shalt not be put to shame: for thou shalt forget the shame of thy
youth, and shalt not remember the reproach of thy widowhood any
more.</ab>
<ab n="5">For thy maker is
thine husband, (the Lord of hostes is his name;) and thy redeemer
the holy one of Israel, the God of the whole earth shall he be
called.<note> Luc.1.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For the Lord hath
called thee as a woman forsaken, and grieued in spirit, and a wife
of youth, when thou wast refused, saith thy God.</ab>
<ab n="7">For a small moment
haue I forsaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather
thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">In a litle wrath I
hid my face from thee, for a moment; but with euerlasting kindnesse
will I haue mercie on thee, saith the Lord thy redeemer.</ab>
<ab n="9">For this is as the
waters of Noah vnto me: for as I haue sworne that the waters of
Noah should no more goe ouer the earth; so haue I sworne that I
would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee.<note> Gen.9.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For the
mountaines shall depart, and the hilles be remoued, but my
kindnesse shall not depart from thee, neither shall the couenant of
my peace be remoued, saith the Lord, that hath mercie on
thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Oh thou
afflicted, tossed with tempest and not comforted, behold, I will
lay thy stones with faire colours, and lay thy foundations with
Saphires.<note> 1.Chron. 29.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And I will make
thy windowes of Agates, and thy gates of Carbuncles, and all thy
borders of pleasant stones.</ab>
<ab n="13">And all thy
children shalbe taught of the Lord, and great shalbe the peace of
thy children.<note> Ioh.6. 45.</note></ab>

<fw>Grace offered freely.</fw>
<ab n="14">In righteousnesse
shalt thou be established: thou shalt be farre from oppression, for
thou shalt not feare; &amp; from terrour, for it shall not come
neere thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">Behold, they
shall surely gather together, but not by me: whosoeuer shal gather
together against thee, shall fall for thy sake.</ab>
<ab n="16">Behold, I haue
created the smith that bloweth the coales in the fire, and that
bringeth foorth an instrument for his worke, and I haue created the
waster to destroy.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ No weapon
that is formed against thee, shall prosper, and euery tongue that
shall rise against thee in iudgement, thou shalt condemne. This is
the heritage of the seruants of the Lord, and their righteousnesse
is of me, saith the Lord.</ab>



</div>