<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CIsaiah_38" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Hezekiah hauing receiued a message
of death, by prayer hath his life lengthened. 8 The Sunne goeth
tenne degrees backward, for a signe of that promise. 9 His song of
Thankesgiuing.</head>


<fw>Hezekiah sicke,</fw>
<ab n="1">In those daies was
Hezekiah sicke vnto death: and Isaiah the Prophet the sonne of Amoz
came vnto him, and said vnto him; Thus saith the Lord, Set thine
house in order: for thou shalt die, and not liue.<note> 2.Kin. 21. 2.chron. 32.24. , Hebr. giue charge concerning thy house.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then Hezekiah
turned his face toward the wall, and prayed vnto the Lord,</ab>
<ab n="3">And said, Remember
now, O Lord, I beseech thee, how I haue walked before thee in
trueth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good
in thy sight: and Hezekiah wept sore.<note> Hebr. with great weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then came
the word of the Lord to Isaiah, saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Goe and say to
Hezekiah, Thus saith the Lord, the God of Dauid thy father; I haue
heard thy prayer, I haue seene thy teares: behold, I will adde vnto
thy dayes fifteene yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I will deliuer
thee and this citie, out of the hand of the king of Assyria: and I
will defend this citie.</ab>
<ab n="7">And this shall be
a signe vnto thee from the Lord, that the Lord will doe this thing
that he hath spoken.</ab>
<ab n="8">Behold, I will
bring againe the shadow of the degrees which is gone downe in the
Sunne-diall of Ahaz ten degrees backward: so the Sunne returned ten
degrees, by which degrees it was gone downe.<note> Hebr. degrees by, or with the Sunne.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ The writing
of Hezekiah king of Iudah, when he had bene sicke, and was
recouered of his sicknesse:</ab>
<ab n="10">I saide in the
cutting off of my dayes; I shall goe to the gates of the graue: I
am depriued of the residue of my yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="11">I said, I shal
not see the Lord, euen the Lord in the land of the liuing: I shal
behold man no more with the inhabitants of the world.</ab>
<ab n="12">Mine age is
departed, and is remoued from me as a shepheards tent: I haue cut
off like a weauer my life: he will cut mee off with pining
sicknesse: from day euen to night wilt thou make an end of
me.<note> Or, From the thrum.</note></ab>

<fw>His thankesgiuing.</fw>
<ab n="13">I reckoned till
morning, that as a Lyon so will hee breake all my bones: from day
euen to night wilt thou make an end of me.</ab>
<ab n="14">Like a crane or a
swallow, so did I chatter; I did mourne as a doue: mine eyes faile
with looking vpward: O Lord, I am oppressed, vndertake for
me.<note> Or, ease me.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">What shall I say?
hee hath both spoken vnto mee, and himselfe hath done it: I shall
goe softly, all my yeeres in the bitternesse of my soule.</ab>
<ab n="16">O Lord, by these
things men liue: and in all these things is the life of my spirit,
so wilt thou recouer me, and make me to liue.</ab>
<ab n="17">Behold, for peace
I had great bitternesse, but thou hast in loue to my soule
deliuered it from the pit of corruption: for thou hast cast all my
sinnes behinde thy backe.<note> Or, on my peace came great bitternesse. , Hebr. thou hast loued me from the pit.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For the graue
cannot praise thee, death cannot celebrate thee: they that goe
downe into the pit cannot hope for thy trueth.</ab>
<ab n="19">The liuing, the
liuing, hee shall praise thee, as I doe this day: the father to the
children shall make knowen thy trueth.</ab>
<ab n="20">The Lord was
ready to saue me: therefore we will sing my songs to the stringed
instruments, all the dayes of our life, in the house of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">For Isaiah had
said, Let them take a lumpe of figges, and lay it for a plaister
vpon the boile, and he shall recouer.</ab>
<ab n="22">Hezekiah also had
said, what is the signe, that I shall goe vp to the house of the
Lord ?</ab>



</div>