<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJames_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The creation of Heauen and Earth,
3 of the light, 6 of the firmament, 9 of the earth separated from
the waters, 11 and made fruitfull, 14 of the Sunne, Moone, and
Starres, 20 of fish and fowle, 24 of beasts and cattell, 26 of Man
in the Image of God. 29 Also the appointment of food.</head>

<ab n="1">In the beginning
God created the Heauen, and the Earth.<note> Psal.33.6. and 136.5. acts.14.15. and 17.24. Hebr.11.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the earth was
without forme, and voyd, and darkenesse was vpon the face of the
deepe: and the Spirit of God mooued vpon the face of the
waters.</ab>
<ab n="3">And God said, Let
there be light: and there was light.<note> 2.Cor.4.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And God saw the
light, that it was good: and God diuided the light from the
darkenesse.<note> Hebr. betweene the light and betweene the darkenesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And God called the
light, Day, and the darknesse he called Night: and the euening and
the morning were the first day.<note> Hebr. and the euening was, and the morning was &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And God
said, Let there be a firmament in the midst of the waters: and let
it diuide the waters from the waters.<note> Psal. 136.5. ier.10.12 and 51.15. , Hebr. Expansion.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And God made the
firmament; and diuided the waters, which were vnder the firmament,
from the waters, which were aboue the firmament: and it was
so.</ab>

<fw>The creation of the world.</fw>
<ab n="8">And God called the
firmament, Heauen: and the euening and the morning were the second
day.<note> Ier.51.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And God
said, Let the waters vnder the heauen be gathered together vnto one
place, and let the dry land appeare: and it was so.<note> Psal.33.7. and 136.5. iob.38.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And God called
the drie land, Earth, and the gathering together of the waters
called hee, Seas: and God saw that it was good.</ab>
<ab n="11">And God said, Let
the Earth bring foorth grasse, the herbe yeelding seed, and the
fruit tree, yeelding fruit after his kinde, whose seed is in it
selfe, vpon the earth: and it was so.<note> Heb. tender grasse.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the earth
brought foorth grasse, and herbe yeelding seed after his kinde, and
the tree yeelding fruit, whose seed was in it selfe, after his
kinde: and God saw that it was good.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the euening
and the morning were the third day.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And God
said, Let there bee lights in the firmament of the heauen, to
diuide the day from the night: and let them be for signes and for
seasons, and for dayes and yeeres.<note> Deu.4.19 psal. 136.7. , Hebr. betweene the day and betweene the night.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And let them be
for lights in the firmament of the heauen, to giue light vpon the
earth: and it was so.</ab>
<ab n="16">And God made two
great lights: the greater light to rule the day, and the lesser
light to rule the night: he made the starres also.<note> Hebr. for the rule of the day, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And God set them
in the firmament of the heauen, to giue light vpon the
earth:</ab>

<fw>The creation of man.</fw>
<ab n="18">And to rule ouer
the day, and ouer the night, and to diuide the light from the
darkenesse: and God saw that it was good.<note> Ier.31.35</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the euening
and the morning were the fourth day.</ab>
<ab n="20">And God said, Let
the waters bring foorth aboundantly the mouing creature that hath
life, and foule that may flie aboue the earth in the open firmament
of heauen.<note> 4.Esdr.6. 47. , Or, creeping. , Heb. soule. , Heb. face of the firmament of heauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And God created
great whales, and euery liuing creature that moueth, which the
waters brought forth aboundantly after their kinde, and euery
winged foule after his kinde: and God saw that it was good.</ab>
<ab n="22">And God blessed
them, saying, Be fruitfull, and multiply, and fill the waters in
the Seas, and let foule multiply in the earth.<note> Chap.8.17. and 9.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the euening
and the morning were the fift day.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And God
said, Let the earth bring forth the liuing creature after his
kinde, cattell, and creeping thing, and beast of the earth after
his kinde: and it was so.</ab>
<ab n="25">And God made the
beast of the earth after his kinde, and cattell after their kinde,
and euery thing that creepeth vpon the earth, after his kinde: and
God saw that it was good.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And God
said, Let vs make man in our Image, after our likenesse: and let
them haue dominion ouer the fish of the sea, and ouer the foule of
the aire, and ouer the cattell, and ouer all the earth, and ouer
euery creeping thing that creepeth vpon the earth.<note> Chap.5.1. and 9.6. 1.corin.11. 7. ephes.4. 14. col.3. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">So God created
man in his owne Image, in the Image of God created hee him; male
and female created hee them.<note> Matth.19 4. wisd.2. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And God blessed
them, and God said vnto them, Be fruitfull, and multiply, and
replenish the earth, and subdue it, and haue dominion ouer the fish
of the sea, and ouer the foule of the aire, and ouer euery liuing
thing that mooueth vpon the earth.<note> Chap.9.1. , Heb. creepeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And God
said, Behold, I haue giuen you euery herbe bearing seede, which is
vpon the face of all the earth, and euery tree, in the which is the
fruit of a tree yeelding seed, to you it shall be for
meat:<note> Hebr. feeding seed. , Chap.9.3.</note></ab>

<fw>The first Sabbath.</fw>
<ab n="30">And to euery
beast of the earth, and to euery foule of the aire, and to euery
thing that creepeth vpon the earth, wherein there is life, I haue
giuen euery greene herbe for meat: and it was so.<note> Hebr. a liuing soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And God saw euery
thing that hee had made: and behold, it was very good. And the
euening and the morning were the sixth day.<note> Ecclus.39 16.</note></ab>



</div>