<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJames_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/James-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/James-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>It is not agreeable to Christian
profession to regard the rich, and to despise the poore brethren:
13 rather wee are to be louing, and mercifull: 14 And not to boast
of faith where no deedes are, 17 which is but a dead faith, 19 the
faith of deuils, 21 not of Abraham, 25 and Rahab.</head>

<ab n="1">My brethren,
haue not the faith of our Lord Iesus Christ the Lord of glorie,
with respect of persons.</ab>
<ab n="2">For if there
come vnto your assembly a man with a gold ring, in goodly apparel,
and there come in also a poore man, in vile raiment:<note> Gr. Synagogue.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And yee haue
respect to him that weareth the gay clothing, and say vnto him, Sit
thou here in a good place: and say to the poore, Stand thou there,
or sit here vnder my footstoole:<note> Or, well, or seemely.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Are yee not
then partiall in your selues, and are become iudges of euill
thoughts?</ab>
<ab n="5">Hearken, my
beloued brethren, Hath not God chosen the poore of this world, rich
in faith, and heires of the kingdome, which hee hath promised to
them that loue him?<note> Or, that.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But yee haue
despised the poore. Doe not rich men oppresse you, and draw you
before the Iudgement seats?</ab>
<ab n="7">Doe not they
blaspheme that worthy Name, by the which ye are called?</ab>

<fw>Faith and workes.</fw>
<ab n="8">If ye fulfil
the royall Law, according to the Scripture, Thou shalt loue thy
neighbour as thy selfe, ye doe well.</ab>
<ab n="9">But if ye haue
respect to persons, ye commit sinne, and are conuinced of the Law,
as transgressours.</ab>
<ab n="10">For whosoeuer shall
keepe the whole Law, &amp; yet offend in one point, he is guilty of
all.</ab>
<ab n="11">For he that said,
Doe not commit adultery; sayd also, Do not kill. Now if thou commit
no adultery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a transgressour of
the Law.<note> Or, that Law which said.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So speake ye, and
so doe, as they that shall bee iudged by the Law of
libertie.</ab>
<ab n="13">For he shall haue
iudgement without mercie, that hath shewed no mercy, &amp; mercie
reioyceth against iudgement.<note> Or, glorieth</note></ab>
<ab n="14">What doth it
profit, my brethren, though a man say hee hath faith, and haue not
workes? can faith saue him?</ab>
<ab n="15">If a brother or
sister be naked, and destitute of dayly foode,</ab>
<ab n="16">And one of you say
vnto them, Depart in peace, be you warmed &amp; filled:
notwithstanding ye giue them not those things which are needfull to
the body: what doth it profit?</ab>
<ab n="17">Euen so faith, if
it hath not works, is dead being alone.<note> Gr. by it selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Yea, a man may say,
Thou hast faith, and I haue workes: shew mee thy faith without thy
workes, and I will shew thee my faith by my workes.<note> Some copies reade, by thy workes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Thou beleeuest that
there is one God, thou doest well: the deuils also beleeue, and
tremble.</ab>
<ab n="20">But wilt thou
knowe, O vaine man, that faith without workes is dead?</ab>
<ab n="21">Was not Abraham our
father iustified by works, when hee had offered Isaac his sonne
vpon the altar?</ab>
<ab n="22">Seest thou how
faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made
perfect?<note> Or, thou seest.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the Scripture
was fullfiled which saith, Abraham beleeued God, and it was imputed
vnto him for righteousnes: and he was called the friend of
God.<note> Gen.15.6 rom.4.3. gal.3.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Ye see then, how
that by workes a man is iustified, and not by faith only.</ab>
<ab n="25">Likewise also, was
not Rahab the harlot iustified by works, when she had receiued the
messengers, and had sent them out another way?</ab>

<fw>Of the tongue</fw>
<ab n="26">For as the body
without the spirit is dead, so faith without workes is dead
also.<note> Or, breath.</note></ab>



</div>