<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJames_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hebrews-Chapter-13-13-James.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/James-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>Wee are to reioyce vnder the Crosse,
5 To aske patience of God, 13 And in our trials not to impute our
weakenesse, or sinnes vnto him, 19 but rather to hearken to the
word, to meditate in it, and to doe thereafter. 26 Otherwise men
may seeme, but neuer be truely religious.</head>

<ab n="1">Iames a
seruant of God, and of the Lord Iesus Christ, to the twelue Tribes
which are scattered abroad, greeting.</ab>
<ab n="2">My brethren,
count it all ioy when ye fall into diuers temptations,</ab>
<ab n="3">Knowing this,
that the trying of your faith worketh patience,</ab>
<ab n="4">But let
patience haue her perfect worke, that ye may be perfect, and
entier, wanting nothing.</ab>
<ab n="5">If any of you
lacke wisedome, let him aske of God, that giueth to all men
liberally, and vpbraideth not: and it shalbe giuen him.</ab>
<ab n="6">But let him
aske in faith, nothing wauering: for he that wauereth is like a
waue of the sea, driuen with the wind, and tossed.</ab>
<ab n="7">For let not
that man thinke that he shall receiue any thing of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">A double
minded man is vnstable in all his wayes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Let the
brother of low degree, reioyce in that he is exalted:<note> Or, glory.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But the rich, in
that hee is made low: because as the floure of the grasse he shall
passe away.</ab>

<fw>God tempteth me.</fw>
<ab n="11">For the Sunne is no
sooner risen with a burning heate, but it withereth the grasse; and
the flowre thereof falleth, and the grace of the fashion of it
perisheth: so also shall the rich man fade away in his
wayes.</ab>
<ab n="12">Blessed is the man
that endureth temptation: for when hee is tried, hee shall receiue
the crowne of life, which the Lord hath promised to them that loue
him.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let no man say when
he is tempted, I am tempted of God: for God cannot be tempted with
euill, neither tempteth he any man.<note> Or, euils.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But euery man is
tempted, when hee is drawen away of his owne lust, and
entised.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then when lust hath
conceiued, it bringeth forth sinne: and sinne, when it is finished,
bringeth forth death.</ab>
<ab n="16">Doe not erre, my
beloued brethren.</ab>
<ab n="17">Euery good gift,
and euery perfect gift is from aboue, &amp; commeth downe from the
Father of lights, with whom is no variablenesse, neither shadow of
turning.</ab>
<ab n="18">Of his owne will
begate hee vs, with the word of Trueth, that wee should bee a kinde
of first fruites of his creatures.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherefore my
beloued brethren, let euery man bee swift to heare, slow to speake,
slow to wrath.</ab>
<ab n="20">For the wrath of
man worketh not the righteousnesse of God.</ab>
<ab n="21">Wherefore lay apart
all filthinesse, and superfluitie of naughtinesse, &amp; receiue
with meeknesse the engrafted word, which is able to saue your
soules.</ab>

<fw>Pure religion.</fw>
<ab n="22">But be ye doers of
the word, and not hearers onely, receiuing your owne
selues.</ab>
<ab n="23">For if any be a
hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like vnto a man beholding
his naturall face in a glasse:</ab>
<ab n="24">For hee beholdeth
himselfe, and goeth his way, and straightway forgetteth what maner
of man he was.</ab>
<ab n="25">But who so looketh
into the perfect Law of libertie, and continueth therein, he being
not a forgetfull hearer, but a doer of the worke, this man shall be
blessed in his deed.<note> Or, doing.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">If any man among
you seeme to be religious, &amp; bridleth not his tongue, but
deceiueth his owne heart, this mans religion is vaine.</ab>
<ab n="27">Pure religion and
vndefiled before God and the Father, is this, to visit the
fatherlesse and widowes in their affliction, and to keepe himselfe
vnspotted from the world.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>