<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJames_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/James-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Wicked rich men are to feare Gods
vengeance. 7 We ought to be patient in afflictions, after the
example of the Prophets, and Iob: 12 to forbeare swearing, 13 to
pray in aduersitie, to sing in prosperitie: 16 to acknowledge
mutually our seueral faults, to pray one for another, 19 and to
reduce a straying brother to the trueth.</head>

<ab n="1">Goe to now,
yee rich men, weepe and howle for your miseries that shall come
vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="2">Your riches
are corrupted, and your garments motheaten:</ab>
<ab n="3">Your gold and
siluer is cankered, and the rust of them shall bee a witnesse
against you, and shall eate your flesh as it were fire: ye haue
heaped treasure together for the last dayes.</ab>
<ab n="4">Beholde, the
hire of the labourers which haue reaped downe your fieldes, which
is of you kept backe by fraud, cryeth: and the cryes of them which
haue reaped, are entred into the eares of the Lord of
Sabaoth.</ab>
<ab n="5">Yee haue liued
in pleasure on the earth, and bene wanton: ye haue nourished your
hearts, as in a day of slaughter:</ab>

<fw>Of patience.</fw>
<ab n="6">Yee haue
condemned, and killed the iust, and he doth not resist you.</ab>
<ab n="7">Be patient
therefore, brethren, vnto the comming of the Lord: behold, the
husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath
long patience for it, vntill hee receiue the early and latter
raine.<note> Or, be long patient, or suffer with long patience</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Be yee also
patient; stablish your hearts: for the comming of the Lorde draweth
nigh.</ab>
<ab n="9">Grudge not one
against another, brethren, lest ye be condemned: behold, the Iudge
standeth before the doore.<note> Or, groane, or grieue not.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Take, my brethren,
the Prophets, who haue spoken in the Name of the Lord, for an
example of suffering affliction, and of patience.</ab>
<ab n="11">Beholde, wee count
them happie which endure. Ye haue heard of the patience of Iob, and
haue seene the end of the Lord: that the Lord is very pitifull and
of tender mercie.</ab>
<ab n="12">But aboue all
things, my brethren, sweare not, neither by heauen, neither by the
earth, neither by any other othe: but let your yea, be yea, and
your nay, nay: lest yee fall into condemnation.</ab>
<ab n="13">Is any among you
afflicted? let him pray. Is any merry? let him sing
Psalmes.</ab>
<ab n="14">Is any sicke among
you? let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let them pray
ouer him, anointing him with oyle in the Name of the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="15">And the prayer of
Faith shall saue the sicke, and the Lord shall raise him vp: and if
hee haue committed sinnes, they shall be forgiuen him.</ab>
<ab n="16">Confesse your
faults one to another, and pray one for another, that yee may bee
healed: the effectuall feruent prayer of a righteous man auaileth
much.</ab>
<ab n="17">Elias was a man
subiect to like passions as we are, and he prayed earnestly that it
might not raine: and it rained not on the earth by the space of
three yeeres and sixe monethes.<note> Or, in his prayer.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And hee prayed
againe, and the heauen gaue raine, and the earth brought foorth her
fruit.</ab>
<ab n="19">Brethren, if any of
you doe erre from the trueth, and one conuert him,</ab>
<ab n="20">Let him know, that
hee which conuerteth the sinner from the errour of his way, shall
saue a soule from death, and shall hide a multitude of
sinnes.</ab>



</div>