<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJames_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/James-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 We are not rashly or arrogantly to
reprooue others: 5 but rather to bridle the tongue, a little
member, but a powerfull instrument of much good, and great harme.
13 They who be truely wise, be milde, and peaceable, without
enuying, and strife.</head>

<ab n="1">My brethren,
bee not many masters, knowing that we shall receiue the greater
condemnation.<note> Or, iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For in many
things we offend all. If any man offend not in word, the same is a
perfect man, and able also to bridle the whole body.</ab>
<ab n="3">Behold, we put
bittes in the horses mouthes, that they may obey vs, and we turne
about their whole body.</ab>
<ab n="4">Behold also
the ships, which though they be so great, and are driuen of fierce
windes, yet are they turned about with a very small helme,
whithersoeuer the gouernour listeth.</ab>
<ab n="5">Euen so the
tongue is a little member, and boasteth great things: behold, how
great a matter a litle fire kindleth.<note> Or, wood.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the tongue
is a fire, a world of iniquitie: so is the tongue amongst our
members, that it defileth the whole body, and setteth on fire the
course of nature, and it is set on fire of hell.</ab>
<ab n="7">For euery kind
of beasts, and of birds, and of serpents, and things in the sea, is
tamed, and hath been tamed of mankind.<note> Gr. nature. , Gr. nature of man.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But the tongue
can no man tame, it is an vnruly euill, ful of deadly
poyson.</ab>
<ab n="9">Therewith
blesse wee God, euen the Father: and therewith curse wee men, which
are made after the similitude of God.</ab>
<ab n="10">Out of the same
mouth proceedeth blessing and cursing: my brethren, these things
ought not so to be.</ab>
<ab n="11">Doeth a fountaine
send foorth at the same place sweet water and bitter?<note> Or, hole.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Can
þe figtree, my brethren, beare oliue berries?
either a vine, figs? so can no fountaine both yeeld salt water
&amp; fresh.</ab>
<ab n="13">Who is a wise man
and indued with knowledge amongst you? let him shew out of a good
conuersation his workes with meekenes of wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="14">But if ye haue
bitter enuying and strife in your hearts glory not, and lie not
against the trueth.</ab>

<fw>Pure wisedome.</fw>
<ab n="15">This wisedome
descendeth not from aboue, but is earthly, sensuall,
deuilish.<note> Or, natural</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For where enuying
and strife is, there is confusion, and euery euill
worke.<note> Gr. tumult or vnquietnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But the wisedome
that is from aboue, is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, and
easie to be intreated, full of mercy, and good fruits, without
partialitie, and without hypocrisie.<note> Or, without wrangling.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And the fruit of
righteousnesse is sowen in peace, of them that make peace.</ab>



</div>