<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Noah, with his familie, and the
liuing creatures, enter into the Arke. 17 The beginning, increase,
and continuance of the Flood.</head>

<ab n="1">And the LORD saide
vnto Noah, Come thou and all thy house into the Arke: for thee haue
I seene righteous before me, in this generation.<note> 2.Pet.2.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Of euery cleane
beast thou shalt take to thee by seuens, the male and his female:
and of beastes that are not cleane, by two, the male and his
female.<note> Hebr. seuen seuen.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Of fowles also of
the aire, by seuens, the male &amp; the female; to keepe seed aliue
vpon the face of all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="4">For yet seuen
dayes, and I will cause it to raine vpon the earth, fortie dayes,
and forty nights: and euery liuing substance that I haue made, will
I destroy, frō off the face of the earth.<note> Hebr. blot out.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Noah did
according vnto all that the LORD commanded him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Noah was sixe
hundred yeeres old, when the flood of waters was vpon the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And Noah
went in, and his sonnes, and his wife, and his sonnes wiues with
him, into the Arke, because of the waters of the Flood.</ab>
<ab n="8">Of cleane beasts,
&amp; of beasts that are not cleane, &amp; of fowles, and of euery
thing that creepeth vpon the earth,</ab>
<ab n="9">There went in two
and two vnto Noah into the Arke, the male &amp; the female, as God
had commanded Noah.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe after seuen dayes, that the waters of the Flood were vpon the
earth.<note> Or, on the seuenth day.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ In the
sixe hundredth yeere of Noahs life, in the second moneth, the
seuenteenth day of the moneth, the same day, were al the fountaines
of the great deepe broken vp, and the windowes of heauen were
opened.<note> Or, flood-gates.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the raine was
vpon the earth, fortie dayes, and fortie nights.</ab>
<ab n="13">In the selfe same
day entred Noah, and Sem, and Ham, and Iapheth, the sonnes of Noah,
and Noahs wife, and the three wiues of his sonnes with them, into
the Arke,</ab>

<fw>Noah entreth into the Arke.</fw>
<ab n="14">They, and euery
beast after his kinde, &amp; all the cattell after their kinde: and
euery creeping thing that creepeth vpon the earth after his kinde,
and euery foule after his kinde, euery birde of euery
sort.<note> Heb. wing.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And they went in
vnto Noah into the Arke, two and two of all flesh, wherein is the
breath of life.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they that
went in, went in male and female of all flesh, as God had
commaunded him: and the LORD shut him in.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Flood was
fortie dayes vpon the earth, and the waters increased, and bare vp
the Arke, and it was lift vp aboue the earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the waters
preuailed, and were encreased greatly vpon the earth: and the Arke
went vpon the face of the waters.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the waters
preuailed exceedingly vpon the earth, and all the high hils, that
were vnder the whole heauen, were couered.</ab>
<ab n="20">Fifteene cubits
vpward, did the waters preuaile; and the mountaines were
couered.</ab>
<ab n="21">And all flesh
died, that mooued vpon the earth, both of fowle, &amp; of cattell,
and of beast, and of euery creeping thing that creepeth vpon the
earth, and euery man.<note> Wisd.10. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">All in whose
nosethrils was the breath of life, of all that was in the dry land,
died.<note> Hebr. the breath of the spirit of life.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And euery liuing
substance was destroyed, which was vpon the face of the ground,
both man and cattell, and the creeping things, and the foule of the
heauen; and they were destroyed from the earth: and Noah onely
remained aliue, and they that were with him in the
Arke.<note> Wisd. 10. 4.2. pet.2.5</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the waters
preuailed vpon the earth, an hundred and fifty dayes.</ab>



</div>