<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_42" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-42-43.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLII.</head>
<head>1 Iohanan desireth Ieremiah to
enquire of God, promising obedience to his will. 7 Ieremiah
assureth him of safety in Iudea, 13 and destruction in Egypt. 19 He
reproueth their hypocrisie in requiring of the Lord, that which
they meant not.</head>

<ab n="1">Then all the
captaines of the forces, and Iohanan the sonne of Kareah, and
Iezaniah the sonne of Hoshaiah, and all the people from the least
euen vnto the greatest, came neere,</ab>
<ab n="2">And said vnto
Ieremiah the prophet, Let, we beseech thee, our supplication be
accepted before thee, and pray for vs vnto the Lord thy God, euen
for all this remnant (for we are left but a few of many, as thine
eies do behold vs)<note> Or, let our supplication fall before thee.</note></ab>

<fw>Dissembling hypocrites.</fw>
<ab n="3">That the Lord
thy God may shew vs the way wherein we may walke, and the thing
that we may doe.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then Ieremiah
the prophet sayd vnto them, I haue heard you; behold, I will pray
vnto the Lord your God, according to your words, and it shall come
to passe that whatsoeuer thing the Lord shall answere you, I will
declare it vnto you: I will keepe nothing backe from you.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then they sayd
to Ieremiah, The Lord be a true and faithfull witnesse betweene vs,
if we doe not, euen according to all things for the which the Lord
thy God shall send thee to vs.</ab>
<ab n="6">Whether it be
good, or whether it be euill, we will obey the voice of the Lord
our God, to whom we send thee, that it may be well with vs, when we
obey the voice of the Lord our God.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And it
came to passe after tenne dayes, that the word of the Lord came
vnto Ieremiah.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then called hee
Iohanan the sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces
which were with him, and all the people, from the least, euen to
the greatest,</ab>
<ab n="9">And said vnto
them, Thus saith the Lord, the God of Israel, vnto whom ye sent me
to present your supplication before him:</ab>
<ab n="10">If ye will
still abide in this land, then will I build you, and not pull you
downe, and I will plant you, and not plucke you vp: for I repent
mee of the euill, that I haue done vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="11">Be not afraid
of the king of Babylon, of whom yee are afraid: be not afraid of
him, saith the Lord: for I am with you to saue you, and to deliuer
you from his hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I will shew
mercies vnto you, that he may haue mercy vpon you; and cause you to
returne to your owne land.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ But if
ye say, We will not dwell in this land, neither obey the voice of
the Lord your God,</ab>
<ab n="14">Saying, No, but
we will goe into the land of Egypt, where we shall see no warre,
nor heare the sound of the Trumpet, nor haue hunger of bread, and
there will we dwell:</ab>

<fw>Dissembling hypocrites.</fw>
<ab n="15">(And now
therefore heare the word of the Lord, yee remnant of Iudah, Thus
saith the Lord of hostes the God of Israel, If ye wholly set your
faces to enter into Egypt, and goe to soiourne there:)</ab>
<ab n="16">Then it shall
come to passe, that the sword which yee feared, shall ouertake you
there in the land of Egypt, and the famine whereof yee were afraid,
shall follow close after you in Egypt, and there ye shall
die.<note> Hebr. shall cleaue after you.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">So shall it bee
with all the men that set their faces to goe into Egypt to soiourne
there, they shall die by the sword, by the famine, and by the
pestilence: and none of them shall remaine or escape from the euil
that I will bring vpon them.<note> Hebr. so shall all the men be.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For thus saith
the Lord of hosts the God of Israel, As mine anger and my furie
hath bene powred foorth vpon the inhabitants of Ierusalem: so shall
my furie bee powred foorth vpon you, when yee shall enter into
Egypt: and ye shall be an execration, and an astonishment, and a
curse, and a reproch, and ye shall see this place no more.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ The Lord
hath said concerning you, O ye remnant of Iudah, Goe ye not into
Egypt: know certainly, that I haue admonished you this
day.<note> Hebr. testified against you.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For ye
dissembled in your hearts when ye sent me vnto the Lord your God,
saying, Pray for vs vnto the Lord our God, and according vnto all
that the Lord our God shall say, so declare vnto vs, and we wil doe
it.<note> Or, you haue vsed deceit against your soules.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And now I haue
this day declared it to you, but ye haue not obeied the voice of
the Lord your God, nor any thing for the which he hath sent me vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="22">Now therefore
know certainly, that ye shall die by the sword, by the famine, and
by the pestilence, in the place whither ye desire to go and to
soiourne.</ab>



</div>