<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_52" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-51-52.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-52-52.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-52-52b-Lamentations.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LII.</head>
<head>1 Zedekiah rebelleth. 4 Ierusalem is
besieged and taken. 8 Zedekiahs sonnes killed, and his owne eyes
put out. 12 Nebuzaradan burneth and spoileth the citie. 24 Hee
carieth away the captiues. 32 Euil-merodach aduanceth
Iehoiakim.</head>

<ab n="1">Zedekiah was one
and twentie yeere olde when he began to reigne, and he reigned
eleuen yeeres in Ierusalem, and his mothers name was Hamutal the
daughter of Ieremiah of Libnah.<note> 2.Kings 14.18. , Heb. reigned.</note></ab>

<fw>The Temple, and the citie
spoiled.</fw>
<ab n="2">And hee did that
which was euill in the eyes of the Lord, according to all that
Iehoiakim had done.</ab>
<ab n="3">For through the
anger of the Lord it came to passe in Ierusalem and Iudah, till hee
had cast them out from his presence, that Zedekiah rebelled against
the king of Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And it
came to passe in the ninth yere of his reigne, in the tenth moneth,
in the tenth day of the moneth, that Nebuchad rezzar king of
Babylon came, hee, and all his armie against Ierusalem, and pitched
against it, and built fortes against it round about.<note> 2 Kings 25.1.chap. 39.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So the citie was
besieged vnto the eleuenth yeere of king Zedekiah.</ab>
<ab n="6">And in the
fourth moneth, in the ninth day of the moneth, the famine was sore
in the citie, so that there was no bread for the people of the
land.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then the city
was broken vp, and all the men of warre fled, and went foorth out
of the citie by night, by the way of the gate between the two wals,
which was by the kings garden (now the Caldeans were by the city
round about) and they went by the way of the plaine.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But the
armie of the Caldeans pursued after the king, and ouertooke
Zedekiah in the plaines of Iericho, &amp; all his armie was
scattered from him.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then they tooke
the king, and caried him vp vnto the king of Babylon to Riblah in
the land of Hamath: where he gaue iudgement vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the king of
Babylon slew the sonnes of Zedekiah before his eyes: he slewe also
all the princes of Iudah in Riblah.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then he put out
the eyes of Zedekiah, and the king of Babylon bound him in chaines,
and caried him to Babylon, and put him in prison till the day of
his death.<note> Heb. blinded. , Or, fetters. , Heb. house of the wards.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Now in
the fifth moneth, in the tenth day of the moneth (which was the
nineteenth yeere of Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon) came
Nebuzaradan captaine of the guard, which serued the king of
Babylon, into Ierusalem;<note> Or, chiefe Marshall. Heb. chiefe of the executioners or slaughtermen. And so vers.14. &amp;c. , Heb. stood before.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And burnt the
house of the Lord, and the kings house, and all the houses of
Ierusalem, and all the houses of the great men burnt he with
fire.</ab>

<fw>The Temple, and the citie
spoiled.</fw>
<ab n="14">And all the
armie of the Caldeans that were with the captaine of the guard,
brake downe all the walles of Ierusalem round about.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then
Nebuzaradan the captaine of the guard, caried away captiue certaine
of the poore of the people, and the residue of the people that
remained in the citie, and those that fell away, that fell to the
king of Babylon, and the rest of the multitude.</ab>
<ab n="16">But Nebuzaradan
the captaine of the guard, left certaine of the poore of the land
for Uine-dressers and for husbandmen.</ab>
<ab n="17">Also the
pillars of brasse that were in the house of the Lord, and the
bases, and the brasen sea that was in the house of the Lord, the
Caldeans brake, and caried all the brasse of them to
Babylon.<note> Chap.27. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The cauldrons
also, and the shouels, and the snuffers, and the bolles, and the
spoones, and all the vessels of brasse wherewith they ministred,
tooke they away.<note> Or, instruments to remooue the ashes. , Or, basons.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the basons,
and the firepans, and the bolles, and the cauldrons, and the
candlestickes, and the spoones, and the cuppes; that which was of
golde, in golde, and that which was of siluer, in siluer, tooke the
captaine of the guard away:<note> Or, censers.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The two
pillars, one Sea, and twelue brasen bulles, that were vnder the
bases, which king Solomon had made in the house of the Lord: the
brasse of all these vessels was without weight.<note> Heb. their brasse.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And concerning
the pillars, the height of one pillar was eighteene cubites, and a
fillet of twelue cubites did compasse it, and the thickenesse
thereof was foure fingers: it was hollow.<note> 1.King.7.15. 2.king.25.17. 2.chro.3.15. , Heb. threed</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And a chapiter
of brasse was vpon it, and the height of one chapiter was fiue
cubites, with networke and pomegranates vpon the chapiters round
about, all of brasse: the second pillar also and the pomegranates
were like vnto these.</ab>
<ab n="23">And there were
ninetie and sixe pomegranates on a side, and all the pomegranates
vpon the networke were an hundreth round about.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
captaine of the guard tooke Seraiah the chiefe Priest, and
Zephaniah the second Priest, and the three keepers of the
doore.<note> Heb. threshold.</note></ab>

<fw>The number of the captiues.</fw>
<ab n="25">Hee tooke also
out of the citie an Eunuch, which had the charge of the men of
warre, and seuen men of them that were neere the kings person which
were found in the citie, and the principall Scribe of the host, who
mustered the people of the land, and threescore men of the people
of the land, that were found in the middest of the
citie.<note> Heb. saw the face of the king. , Or, scribe of the captaine of the hoste.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">So Nebuzar-adan
the captaine of the guard tooke them, and brought them to the king
of Babylon to Riblah.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the king of
Babylon smote them, and put them to death in Riblah, in the land of
Hamath: thus Iudah was caried away captiue out of his owne
land.</ab>
<ab n="28">This is the
people whom Nebuchad-rezzar caried away captiue in the seuenth
yeere, three thousand Iewes and three and twentie.</ab>
<ab n="29">In the
eighteenth yeere of Nebuchad-rezzar hee caried away captiue from
Ierusalem eight hundredth, thirtie and two persons.<note> Heb. soules.</note></ab>

<fw>The number of the captiues.</fw>
<ab n="30">In the three
and twentith yeere of Nebuchad-rezzar, Nebuzar-adan the captaine of
the guard, caried away captiue of the Iewes seuen hundreth fortie
and fiue persons: all the persons were foure thousand and sixe
hundreth.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And it
came to passe in the seuen and thirtieth yeere of the captiuitie of
Iehoiakin king of Iudah, in the twelfth moneth, in the fiue and
twentieth day of the moneth, that Euil-merodach king of Babylon, in
the first yeere of his reigne, lifted vp the head of Iehoiakin king
of Iudah, and brought him forth out of prison,</ab>
<ab n="32">And spake
kindly vnto him, and set his throne aboue the throne of the kings
that were with him in Babylon,<note> Heb. good things with him.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And changed his
prison garments: and hee did continually eate bread before him all
the dayes of his life.</ab>
<ab n="34">And for his
diet, there was a continuall diet giuen him of the king of Babylon,
euery day a portion vntill the day of his death, all the dayes of
his life.<note> Heb. the matter of the day in his day.</note></ab>



</div>