<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-38-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>1 Ierusalem is taken. 4 Zedekiah is
made blinde, and sent to Babylon. 8 The city ruinated, 9 the people
captiuated. 11 Nebuchad-rezzars charge for the good vsage of
Ieremiah. 15 Gods promise to Ebed-melech.</head>

<ab n="1">In the ninth
yeere of Zedekiah king of Iudah, in the tenth moneth, came Nebuchad
rezzar king of Babylon, and all his armie against Ierusalem, and
they besieged it.<note> 2.Kin. 25. 1. chap. 52. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And in the
eleuenth yeere of Zedekiah, in the fourth moneth, the ninth day of
the moneth, the citie was broken vp.</ab>
<ab n="3">And all the
princes of the king of Babylon came in, and sate in the middle
gate, euen Nergal-Sharezer, Samgar-Nebo, Sarsechim, Rabsaris,
Nergal-Sharezer, Rabmag, with all the residue of the princes of the
king of Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And it
came to passe, that when Zedekiah the king of Iudah saw them and
all the men of warre, then they fled and went forth out of the
citie by night, by the way of the kings garden, by the gate betwixt
the two walles, and hee went out the way of the plaine.</ab>
<ab n="5">But the Caldeans
armie pursued after them, and ouertooke Zedekiah in the plaines of
Iericho: and when they had taken him, they brought him vp to
Nebuchad-nezzar king of Babylon to Riblah in the land of Hamath,
where he gaue iudgement vpon him.<note> Hebr. spake with him iudgements.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then the king of
Babylon slewe the sonnes of Zedekiah in Riblah before his eyes:
also the king of Babylon slew all the nobles of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="7">Moreouer he put
out Zedekiahs eyes, and bound him with chaines, to cary him to
Babylon.<note> Heb. with two brasen chaines, or fetters.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the
Caldeans burnt the kings house, and the houses of the people with
fire, and brake downe the wals of Ierusalem.</ab>

<fw>Of Ebed-melech.</fw>
<ab n="9">Then Nebuzaradan
the captaine of the guard caried away captiue into Babylon the
remnant of the people that remained in the citie, and those that
fell away, that fell to him, with the rest of the people that
remained.<note> Or, chiefe Marshall. Hebr. chiefe of the executioners or slaughter men. And so verse 10.11, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But Nebuzaradan
the captaine of the guard left of the poore of the people which had
nothing, in the land of Iudah, and gaue them vineyards and fieldes
at the same time.<note> Hebr. in that day.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Now
Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon gaue charge coucerning Ieremiah to
Nebuzaradan the captaine of the guard, saying;<note> Heb. by the hand of.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Take him, and
looke well to him, and doe him no harme, but doe vnto him euen as
he shall say vnto thee.<note> Hebr. set thine eyes vpon him.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">So Nebuzaradan
the captaine of the guard sent, and Nebushasban, Rabsaris, and
Nergal-Sharezer, Rabmag, and all the King of Babylons
Princes:</ab>
<ab n="14">Euen they sent,
and tooke Ieremiah out of the court of the prison, and committed
him vnto Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the sonne of Shaphan, that hee
should carie him home: so hee dwelt among the people.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Now the
word of the Lord came vnto Ieremiah, while hee was shut vp in the
court of the prison, saying;</ab>
<ab n="16">Goe and speake
to Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, saying, Thus sayth the Lord of hostes
the God of Israel, Behold, I will bring my words vpon this citie
for euill, and not for good, and they shall be accomplished in that
day before thee.</ab>
<ab n="17">But I will
deliuer thee in that day, sayth the Lord, and thou shalt not be
giuen into the hand of the men of whom thou art afraid.</ab>
<ab n="18">For I wil
surely deliuer thee, and thou shalt not fall by the sword, but thy
life shall be for a pray vnto thee, because thou hast put thy trust
in me, sayth the Lord.</ab>



</div>