<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_41" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLI.</head>
<head>1 Ishmael, trecherously killing
Gedaliah and others, purposeth with the residue to flie vnto the
Ammonites. 11 Iohanan recouereth the captiues, and mindeth to fly
into Egypt.</head>


<fw>Gedaliah slaine.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe in the seuenth moneth, that Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah
the sonne of Elishamah of the seede royall, and the princes of the
king, euen tenne men with him, came vnto Gedaliah the sonne of
Ahikam to Mizpah, and there they did eate bread together in
Mizpah.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then arose
Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah, and the ten men that were with him,
and smote Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the sonne of Shaphan with the
sword, and slew him, whome the king of Babylon had made gouernour
ouer the land.</ab>
<ab n="3">Ishmael also
slew all the Iewes that were with him, euen with Gedaliah at
Mizpah, and the Caldeans that were found there, and the men of
warre.</ab>
<ab n="4">And it came to
passe the second day after he had slaine Gedaliah, and no man knew
it,</ab>
<ab n="5">That there came
certaine from Shechem, from Shiloh, and from Samaria, euen
fourescore men, hauing their beards shauen, and their clothes rent,
and hauing cut themselues, with offerings and incense in their
hand, to bring them to the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Ishmael the
sonne of Nethaniah went foorth from Mizpah to meete them, weeping
all along as hee went: and it came to passe as hee met them, he
said vnto them, Come to Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam.<note> Heb. in going and weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And it was so
when they came into the midst of the citie, that Ishmael the sonne
of Nethaniah slew them, and cast them into the midst of the pit,
he, and the men that were with him.</ab>
<ab n="8">But ten men were
found among them, that said vnto Ishmael, Slay vs not: for we haue
treasures in the field, of wheate, and of barley, and of oyle, and
of hony: so he forbare, and slewe them not among their
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now the pit
wherein Ishmael had cast all the dead bodies of the men (whom he
had slaine because of Gedaliah) was it, which Asa the king had
made, for feare of Baasha king of Israel, and Ishmael the sonne of
Nethaniah filled it with them that were slaine.<note> Or, neere Gedaliah, heb. by the hand or by the side of Gedaliah.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then Ishmael
caried away captiue all the residue of the people, that were in
Mizpah, euen the kings daughters, and al the people that remained
in Mizpah, whom Nebuzaradan the captaine of the guard had committed
to Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam, and Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah
caried them away captiue, and departed to goe ouer to the
Ammonites.</ab>

<fw>Ishmael escapeth.</fw>
<ab n="11">¶ But when
Iohanan the sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces
that were with him, heard of all the euill that Ishmael the sonne
of Nethaniah had done,</ab>
<ab n="12">Then they tooke
all the men, and went to fight with Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah,
and found him by the great waters that are in Gibeon.</ab>
<ab n="13">Now it came to
passe that when al the people which were with Ishmael, sawe Iohanan
the sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces, that were
with him, then they were glad.</ab>
<ab n="14">So all the
people that Ishmael had caried away captiue from Mizpah cast about
and returned, and went vnto Iohanan the sonne of Kareah.</ab>
<ab n="15">But Ishmael the
sonne of Nethaniah escaped from Iohanan with eight men, and went to
the Ammonites.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then tooke
Iohanan the sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces
that were with him, all the remnant of the people whom he had
recouered from Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah, from Mizpah (after
that he had slaine Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam,) euen mighty men
of warre, and the women, and the children, and the eunuches whom he
had brought againe from Gibeon.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they
departed and dwelt in the habitation of Chimham, which is by
Bethlehem, to goe to enter into Egypt,</ab>
<ab n="18">Because of the
Caldeans: for they were afraid of them, because Ishmael the sonne
of Nethaniah had slaine Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam, whom the king
of Babylon made gouernour in the land.</ab>



</div>