<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_48" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-48-49.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVIII.</head>
<head>1 Ioseph with his sonnes visiteth
his sicke father. 2 Iacob strengtheneth himselfe to blesse them. 3
He repeateth the promise. 5 He taketh Ephraim and Manasseh as his
owne. 7 Hee telleth him of his mothers graue. 9 Hee blesseth
Ephraim and Manasseh. 17 Hee preferreth the yonger before the
elder. 21 He prophesieth their returne to Canaan.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after these things, that one told Ioseph, Behold, thy father
is sicke: and he tooke with him his two sonnes, Manasseh and
Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="2">And one told
Iacob, and said, Behold, thy sonne Ioseph commeth vnto thee: and
Israel strengthened himselfe, and sate vpon the bed.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Iacob saide
vnto Ioseph, God Almightie appeared vnto mee at Luz in the land of
Canaan, and blessed mee,<note> Chap. 28. 13. &amp; 35.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And said vnto me,
Behold, I wil make thee fruitfull, and multiplie thee, and I will
make of thee a multitude of people, and will giue this land to thy
seede after thee, for an euerlasting possession.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And now
thy two sonnes, Ephraim and Manasseh, which were borne vnto thee in
the land of Egypt, before I came vnto thee into Egypt, are mine: as
Reuben and Simeon, they shalbe mine.<note> Chap. 41. 50. iosh. 13.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And thy issue
which thou begettest after them, shall be thine, and shall be
called after the name of their brethren in their
inheritance.</ab>

<fw>Iacob blesseth Iosephs sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="7">And as for me,
when I came from Padan, Rachel died by me in the land of Canaan, in
the way, when yet there was but a little way to come vnto Ephrath:
and I buried her there in the way of Ephrath, the same is
Bethlehem.<note> Gen.35. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Israel
behelde Iosephs sonnes, and said, Who are these?</ab>
<ab n="9">And Ioseph said
vnto his father, They are my sonnes, whom God hath giuen me in this
place: and he said, Bring them, I pray thee, vnto me, and I will
blesse them.</ab>
<ab n="10">(Now the eyes of
Israel were dimme for age, so that he could not see,) and hee
brought them neere vnto him, and he kissed them, and imbraced
them.<note> Heb. heauy</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Israel said
vnto Ioseph, I had not thought to see thy face: and loe, God hath
shewed me also thy seed.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Ioseph
brought them out from betweene his knees, and hee bowed himselfe
with his face to the earth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Ioseph tooke
them both, Ephraim in his right hand, toward Israels left hand, and
Manasseh in his left hand towards Israels right hand, and brought
them neere vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Israel
stretched out his right hand, and layd it vpon Ephraims head who
was the yonger; and his left hand vpon Manassehs head, guiding his
hands wittingly: for Manasseh was the first borne.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And he
blessed Ioseph and said, God before whom my fathers Abraham and
Isaac did walke, the God which fedde mee all my life long vnto this
day,<note> Hebr.11. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The Angel which
redeemed mee from all euill, blesse the laddes, and let my name be
named on them, and the name of my fathers Abraham and Isaac, and
let them grow into a multitude in the midst of the
earth.<note> Hebr. as fishes doe increase.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And when Ioseph
saw that his father laide his right hand vpon the head of Ephraim,
it displeased him: and he held vp his fathers hand, to remoue it
from Ephraims head, vnto Manassehs head.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Ioseph saide
vnto his father, Not so my father: for this is the first borne; put
thy right hand vpon his head.</ab>

<fw>Iacob blesseth his sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="19">And his father
refused, and said, I know it, my sonne, I know it: he also shall
become a people, and he also shall be great: but truely his yonger
brother shall be greater then he; and his seede shall become a
multitude of nations.<note> Hebr: fulnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And he blessed
them that day, saying, In thee shall Israel blesse, saying, God
make thee as Ephraim, and as Manasseh: and he set Ephraim before
Manasseh.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Israel saide
vnto Ioseph, Behold, I die: but God shall be with you, and bring
you againe vnto the land of your fathers.</ab>
<ab n="22">Moreouer I haue
giuen to thee one portion aboue thy brethren, which I tooke out of
the hand of the Amorite with my sword, and with my bow.</ab>



</div>