<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Hananiah prophecieth falsely the
returne of the vessels and of Ieconiah. 5 Ieremiah wishing it to be
true, sheweth that the euent will declare who are true Prophets. 10
Hananiah breaketh Ieremiahs yoke. 12 Ieremiah telleth of an yron
yoke, 15 and foretelleth Hananiahs death.</head>


<fw>Hananiah.</fw>
<ab n="1">And it came to
passe the same yeere, in the beginning of the reigne of Zedekiah
king of Iudah, in the fourth yeere, and in the fift moneth, that
Hananiah the sonne of Azur the prophet, which was of Gibeon, spake
vnto mee in the house of the Lord, in the presence of the priests
and of all the people, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus speaketh
the Lord of hostes, the God of Israel, saying; I haue broken the
yoke of the king of Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="3">Within two full
yeeres will I bring againe into this place all the vessels of the
Lords house, that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon tooke away from
this place, and caried them to Babylon.<note> Heb. two yeeres of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I will bring
againe to this place Ieconiah the sonne of Iehoiakim king of Iudah,
with all the captiues of Iudah, that went into Babylon, saith the
Lord, for I will breake the yoke of the king of
Babylon.<note> Heb. captiuity.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then the
prophet Ieremiah said vnto the prophet Hananiah in the presence of
the priests, and in the presence of all the people, that stood in
the house of the Lord,</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen the prophet
Ieremiah said; Amen: the Lord doe so, the Lord performe the words
which thou hast prophecied, to bring againe the vessels of the
Lords house, and all that is caried away captiue from Babylon into
this place.</ab>
<ab n="7">Neuerthelesse,
heare thou now this word that I speake in thine eares, and in the
eares of all the people.</ab>
<ab n="8">The prophets
that haue beene before mee, and before thee of old, prophecied both
against many countries, and against great kingdoms, of warre, and
of euill, and of pestilence.</ab>
<ab n="9">The prophet
which prophecieth of peace, when the word of the prophet shall come
to passe, then shall the prophet be knowen, that the Lord hath
truely sent him.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Then
Hananiah the prophet tooke the yoke from off the prophet Ieremiahs
necke, and brake it.<note> Chap.27. 2.</note></ab>

<fw>Yokes of iron.</fw>
<ab n="11">And Hananiah
spake in the presence of all the people, saying; Thus saith the
Lord, Euen so will I breake the yoke of Nebuchadnezzer king of
Babylon from the necke of all nations within the space of two full
yeeres: and the Prophet Ieremiah went his way.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then the
word of the Lord came vnto Ieremiah the Prophet (after that
Hananiah the prophet had broken the yoke from off the necke of the
Prophet Ieremiah) saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Goe, and tell
Hananiah, saying, Thus saith the Lord, Thou hast broken the yokes
of wood, but thou shalt make for them yokes of yron.</ab>
<ab n="14">For thus saith
the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, I haue put a yoke of yron
vpon the neck of all these nations, that they may serue
Nebuchad-nezzar king of Babylon, and they shall serue him, and I
haue giuen him the beasts of the field also.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then
said the Prophet Ieremiah vnto Hananiah the prophet, Heare nowe
Hananiah: the Lord hath not sent thee, but thou makest this people
to trust in a lye.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore thus
saith the Lord, Beholde, I will cast thee from off the face of the
earth: this yeere thou shalt die, because thou hast taught
rebellion against the Lord.<note> Deut.13. 5. chap.29. 32. , Heb. reuolt.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">So Hananiah the
prophet died the same yeere, in the seuenth moneth.</ab>



</div>