<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 In the Type of a linnen girdle,
hidden at Euphrates, God prefigureth the destruction of his people.
12 Vnder the parable of the bottles filled with wine, he
foretelleth their drunkennesse in miserie. 15 He exhorteth to
preuent their future iudgements. 22 He sheweth their abominations
are the cause thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord vnto me; Goe and get thee a linen girdle, and put it vpon thy
loynes, and put it not in water.</ab>
<ab n="2">So I got a
girdle, according to the word of the Lord, and put it on my
loines.</ab>

<fw>The linnen girdle, and wine
bottles.</fw>
<ab n="3">And the word of
the Lord came vnto me the second time, saying;</ab>
<ab n="4">Take the girdle
that thou hast got, which is vpon thy loines, and arise, goe to
Euphrates, and hide it there in a hole of the rocke.</ab>
<ab n="5">So I went and
hid it by Euphrates, as the Lord commaunded mee.</ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe after many daies, that the Lord saide vnto me; Arise, goe to
Euphrates, and take the girdle from thence, which I commaunded thee
to hide there.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then I went to
Euphrates and digged, and tooke the girdle from the place where I
had hid it, and behold, the girdle was marred, it was profitable
for nothing.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then the word of
the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="9">Thus saith the
Lord; After this maner will I marre the pride of Iudah, and the
great pride of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="10">This euill
people which refuse to heare my words, which walke in the
imagination of their heart, and walke after other Gods to serue
them and to worship them, shall euen be as this girdle, which is
good for nothing.<note> Or, stubburnnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For as the
girdle cleaueth to the loines of a man: so haue I caused to cleaue
vnto me the whole house of Israel, and the whole house of Iudah,
saith the Lord; that they might bee vnto me for a people, and for a
name, and for a praise, and for a glory: but they would not
heare.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶
Therefore thou shalt speake vnto them this word; Thus saith the
Lord God of Israel; Euerie botle shalbe filled with wine: and they
shall say vnto thee; Doe we not certainly know, that euery botle
shall be filled with wine?</ab>
<ab n="13">Then shalt thou
say vnto them; Thus saith the Lord; Behold, I will fill all the
inhabitants of this land, euen the kings that sit vpon Dauids
throne, and the priests and the prophets, and all the inhabitants
of Ierusalem with drunkennesse.</ab>
<ab n="14">And I will dash
them one against another, euen the fathers and the sonnes together,
saith the Lord: I wil not pitie nor spare, nor haue mercie, but
destroy them.<note> Heb. a man against his brother. , Heb. from destroying them.</note></ab>

<fw>Custome in euill.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ Heare ye
and giue eare, bee not proud: for the Lord hath spoken.</ab>
<ab n="16">Giue glory to
the Lord your God before he cause darknesse, and before your feet
stumble vpon the darke mountaines, and while yee looke for light,
he turne it into the shadowe of death, and make it grosse
darkenesse.<note> Isa.8. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But if ye will
not heare it, my soule shall weepe in secret places for your pride,
and mine eye shall weepe sore, and run downe with teares, because
the Lords flocke is caried away captiue.<note> Lamen.1. 2.16. and 2.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Say vnto the
king, and to the queene, Humble your selues, sit downe, for your
principalities shall come downe, euen the crowne of your
glory.<note> Or, head-tires.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The cities of
the South shall bee shut vp, and none shall open them, Iudah shall
be caried away captiue all of it, it shall bee wholly caried away
captiue.</ab>
<ab n="20">Lift vp your
eyes, and beholde them that come from the North, where is the
flocke that was giuen thee, thy beautifull flocke?</ab>
<ab n="21">What wilt thou
say when he shall punish thee (for thou hast taught them to be
captaines and as chiefe ouer thee) shall not sorrowes take thee as
a woman in trauaile?<note> Hebr. visit vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And if
thou say in thine heart, Wherefore come these things vpon me? for
the greatnesse of thine iniquitie are thy skirts discouered, and
thy heeles made bare.<note> Cha.5. 19 and 16. 10. , Or, shall be violently taken away.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Can the
Ethiopian change his skinne? or the leopard his spots? then may ye
also doe good, that are accustomed to doe euill.<note> Heb. taught.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Therefore will
I scatter them as the stubble that passeth away by the winde of the
wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="25">This is thy
lot, the portion of thy measures from me, saith the Lord, because
thou hast forgotten mee, and trusted in falshood.</ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore will
I discouer thy skirts vpon thy face, that thy shame may
appeare.</ab>
<ab n="27">I haue seene
thine adulteries, and thy neighings, the lewdnesse of thy whordome,
and thine abominations on the hils in the fields: woe vnto thee, O
Ierusalem, wilt thou not bee made cleane? when shall it once
be?<note> Heb. after when yet?</note></ab>



</div>