<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 The captiuitie of Iudah for her
sinne. 5 Trust in man is cursed, 7 in God is blessed. 9 The
deceitfull heart cannot deceiue God. 12 The saluation of God. 15
The Prophet complaineth of the mockers of his prophecie. 19 He is
sent to renew the couenant in hallowing the Sabbath.</head>

<ab n="1">The sinne of
Iudah is written with a pen of yron, and with the point of a
diamond; it is grauen vpon the table of their heart, and vpon the
hornes of your altars:<note> Iob.19. 24. , Heb. naile:</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Whilest their
children remember their altars and their groues by the greene trees
vpon the high hilles.<note> Iudg.3.7. Isai.1.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">O my mountaine,
in the field I will giue thy substance, and all thy treasures to
the spoile, and thy high places for sinne, throughout all thy
borders.<note> Chap.15. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And thou, euen
thy selfe shalt discontinue from thine heritage that I gaue thee,
and I will cause thee to serue thine enemies in the land which thou
knowest not: for yee haue kindled a fire in mine anger, which shall
burne for euer.<note> Heb. in thy selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Thus
saith the Lord; Cursed be the man that trusteth in man, and maketh
flesh his arme, and whose heart departeth from the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">For hee shall be
like the heath in the desert, and shall not see when good commeth,
but shall inhabite the parched places in the wildernesse, in a salt
land and not inhabited.</ab>
<ab n="7">Blessed is the
man that trusteth in the Lord, and whose hope the Lord
is.<note> Psal.2.12. and 34.10. and 125.1. prou.16. 20. isa.30. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For he shall be
as a tree planted by the waters, and that spreadeth out her rootes
by the riuer, and shall not see when heate commeth, but her leafe
shall be greene, and shall not be carefull in the yeere of drought,
neither shall cease from yeelding fruit.<note> Psal.1.3. , Or, restraint.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ The heart
is deceitfull aboue all things, and desperately wicked, who can
know it?</ab>
<ab n="10">I the Lord
search the heart, I try the reines, euen to giue euery man
according to his waies, and according to the fruit of his
doings.<note> 2.Sam.16. 7. psal.7.10. chap.11.20 and 20. 12.</note></ab>

<fw>The obseruation of the Sabbath
day.</fw>
<ab n="11">As the partrich
sitteth on egges, and hatcheth them not: so he that getteth riches
and not by right, shall leaue them in the midst of his dayes, and
at his end shall be a foole.<note> Or, gathereth young which shee hath not brought forth.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ A
glorious high throne from the beginning, is the place of our
Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="13">O Lord, the
hope of Israel, all that forsake thee shall be ashamed, and they
that depart from me shall bee written in the earth, because they
haue forsaken the Lord the fountaine of liuing waters.<note> Psal.73. 25. isa.1.28 , Chap.2.3</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Heale me, O
Lord, and I shall be healed: saue me, and I shalbe saued: for thou
art my praise.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Behold,
they say vnto mee, Where is the word of the Lord ? let it come
now.<note> Isa.5.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">As for me, I
haue not hastened from being a pastour to follow thee, neither haue
I desired the wofull day, thou knowest: that which came out of my
lips, was right before thee.<note> Heb. after thee. , Chap.1.4, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Be not a
terrour vnto me, thou art my hope in the day of euill.</ab>
<ab n="18">Let them bee
confounded that persecute me, but let not me be confounded: let
them be dismayed, but let not me be dismayed: bring vpon them the
day of euill, and destroy them with double destruction.<note> Psal.35.4 and 40.15. , Heb. break them with a double breach. , Cha.11.20</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Thus
sayd the Lord vnto me, Go and stand in the gate of the children of
the people, whereby the kings of Iudah come in, and by the which
they goe out, and in all the gates of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="20">And say vnto
them, Heare ye the word of the Lord, ye kings of Iudah, and all
Iudah, and all the inhabitants of Ierusalem, that enter in by these
gates.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thus saith the
Lord, Take heed to your selues, and beare no burden on the Sabbath
day, nor bring it in by the gates of Ierusalem.<note> Nehe.13. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Neither carie
forth a burden out of your houses on the Sabbath day, neither doe
ye any worke, but hallowe ye the Sabbath day, as I commanded your
fathers.<note> Exo.20.8. and 23. 12. and 31. 13. exe.20. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But they obeyed
not, neither inclined their eare, but made their necke stiffe, that
they might not heare nor receiue instruction.</ab>

<fw>The obseruation of the Sabbath
day.</fw>
<ab n="24">And it shall
come to passe, if yee diligently hearken vnto me, saith the Lord,
to bring in no burden through the gates of this citie on the
Sabbath day, but hallow the Sabbath day, to doe no worke
therein:</ab>
<ab n="25">Then shall
there enter into the gates of this citie kings and princes sitting
vpon the throne of Dauid, riding in charets and on horses, they and
their princes, the men of Iudah and the inhabitants of Ierusalem:
and this citie shall remaine for euer.<note> Cha. 22.8</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And they shall
come from the cities of Iudah, and from the places about Ierusalem,
and from the lande of Beniamin, and from the plaine and from the
mountaines, and from the South, bringing burnt offerings, and
sacrifices, and meate offerings, and incense, and bringing
sacrifices of praise vnto the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="27">But if you will
not hearken vnto me to hallow the Sabbath day, and not to beare a
burden, euen entring in at the gates of Ierusalem on the Sabbath
day: then will I kindle a fire in the gates thereof, and it shall
deuoure the palaces of Ierusalem, and it shall not be
quenched.</ab>



</div>