<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-31-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 The restauration of Israel. 10 The
publication thereof. 15 Rahel mourning is comforted. 18 Ephraim
repenting is brought home againe. 22 Christ is promised. 27 His
care ouer the Church. 31 His new couenant. 35 The stability, 38 and
amplitude of the Church.</head>


<fw>Euerlasting loue.</fw>
<ab n="1">At the same
time, saith the Lord, wil I be the God of all the families of
Israel, &amp; they shalbe my people.</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord; The people which were left of the sword found grace in the
wildernesse, euen Israel, when I went to cause him to rest.</ab>
<ab n="3">The Lord hath
appeared of old vnto mee, saying; Yea I haue loued thee with an
euerlasting loue: therefore with louing kindnesse haue I drawen
thee.<note> Heb. from a farre. , Or, haue I extended louing kindnesse vnto thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Againe I will
build thee, and thou shalt be built, O virgine of Israel, thou
shalt againe be adorned with thy tabrets, and shalt goe forth in
the daunces of them that make merry.<note> Exod. 15. 20. iudg.11. 34. , Or, timbrels.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou shalt yet
plant vines vpon the mountaines of Samaria, the planters shall
plant, and shall eate them as common things.<note> Heb prophane them.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For there shall
be a day, that the watchmen vpon the mount Ephraim shall cry; Arise
yee, and let vs goe vp to Zion vnto the Lord our God.</ab>
<ab n="7">For thus saith
the Lord, Sing with gladnesse for Iacob, and shout among the chiefe
of the nations: publish yee, praise yee, and say; O Lord saue thy
people the remnant of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">Behold, I will
bring them from the North countrey, and gather them from the coasts
of the earth, and with them the blind and the lame, the woman with
child, and her that trauelleth with child together, a great company
shall returne thither.</ab>
<ab n="9">They shall come
with weeping, and with supplications will I leade them: I will
cause them to walke by the riuers of waters, in a straight way
wherein they shall not stumble: for I am a father to Israel, and
Ephraim is my first borne.<note> Or, fauours. , Exod.4. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Heare
the word of the Lord, O yee nations, and declare it in the iles
afarre off, and say; Hee that scattered Israel will gather him, and
keepe him as a shepheard doth his flocke.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the Lord
hath redeemed Iacob, and ransomed him from the hand of him that was
stronger then hee.</ab>

<fw>Christ promised.</fw>
<ab n="12">Therefore they
shall come and sing in the height of Zion, and shall flow together
to the goodnesse of the Lord, for wheate, and for wine, and for
oyle, and for the young of the flocke and of the herd: and their
soule shall be as a watered garden, and they shall not sorrow any
more at all.<note> Isai.58.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Then shall the
virgine reioyce in the daunce, both yoong men and old together: for
I will turne their mourning into ioy, and will comfort them, and
make them reioyce from their sorrow.</ab>
<ab n="14">And I will
satiate the soule of the priests with fatnesse, and my people shall
be satisfied with goodnesse, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Thus
saith the Lord; A voyce was heard in Ramah, lamentation and bitter
weeping: Rahel weeping for her children, refused to be comforted
for her children, because they were not.<note> Matth.2.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Thus saith the
Lord; Refraine thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from teares:
for thy worke shall be rewarded, saith the Lord, and they shall
come againe from the land of the enemie.</ab>
<ab n="17">And there is
hope in thine end, saith the Lord, that thy children shall come
againe to their owne border.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ I haue
surely heard Ephraim bemoaning himselfe thus, Thou hast chastised
me, and I was chastised, as a bullocke vnaccustomed to the yoke:
turne thou me, and I shall be turned; thou art the Lord my
God.</ab>
<ab n="19">Surely after
that I was turned, I repented; and after that I was instructed, I
smote vpon my thigh: I was ashamed, yea euen confounded, because I
did beare the reproch of my youth.<note> Deut.30. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Is Ephraim my
deare sonne? is he a pleasant child? for since I spake against him,
I doe earnestly remember him still: therefore my bowels are
troubled for him; I will surely haue mercy vpon him, saith the
Lord.<note> Heb. sound.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Set thee vp
way-markes; make thee high heaps: set thine heart toward the high
way, euen the way which thou wentest: turne againe, O virgine of
Israel, turne againe to these thy cities.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ How long
wilt thou go about, O thou backsliding daughter? for the Lord hath
created a new thing in the earth: A woman shall compasse a
man.</ab>

<fw>A new Couenant, and
euerlasting.</fw>
<ab n="23">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts the God of Israel, As yet they shall vse this speech
in the land of Iudah, and in the cities thereof, when I shall bring
againe their captiuitie, The Lord blesse thee, O habitation of
iustice, and mountaine of holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="24">And there shall
dwell in Iudah it selfe, and in all the cities thereof together,
husbandmen, and they that goe forth with flocks.</ab>
<ab n="25">For I haue
satiated the wearie soule, and I haue replenished euery sorowfull
soule.</ab>
<ab n="26">Upon this I
awaked and beheld, and my sleepe was sweete vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Behold,
the dayes come, saith the Lord, that I will sow the house of
Israel, and the house of Iudah with the seed of man, and with the
seed of beast.</ab>
<ab n="28">And it shall
come to passe, that like as I haue watched ouer them, to plucke vp
and to breake downe, and to throw downe, and to destroy, and to
afflict: so will I watch ouer them, to build and to plant, saith
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">In those dayes
they shall say no more, The fathers haue eaten a sowre grape, and
the childrens teeth are set on edge.<note> Eze.18.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But euery one
shall die for his owne iniquitie, euery man that eateth the sowre
grape, his teeth shall be set on edge.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Behold,
the dayes come, saith the Lord, that I will make a newe couenant
with the house of Israel, and with the house of Iudah.<note> Heb.8.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Not according
to the couenant that I made with their fathers in the day that I
tooke them by the hand, to bring them out of the land of Egypt,
which my couenant they brake, although I was an husband vnto them,
saith the Lord.<note> Or, should I haue continued a husband vnto them?</note></ab>
<ab n="33">But this shall
be the couenant, that I will make with the house of Israel, After
those dayes, saith the Lord, I will put my law in their inward
parts, and write it in their hearts, and wil be their God, and they
shall be my people.<note> Chap.24. 7. and 32. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And they shall
teach no more euery man his neighbour, and euery man his brother,
saying, Know the Lord: for they shall all know mee, from the least
of them vnto the greatest of them, saith the Lord; for I will
forgiue their iniquitie, and I will remember their sinne no
more.<note> Isa.54.17 ioh.6.45. , Chap. 33. 8. mic.7.18 acts 10.43.</note></ab>

<fw>A new Couenant, and
euerlasting.</fw>
<ab n="35">¶ Thus
saith the Lord which giueth the Sunne for a light by day, and the
ordinances of the moone and of the starres for a light by night,
which diuideth the sea when the waues thereof roare, the Lord of
hosts is his name.<note> Gen.1.16 , Isa.51.15</note></ab>
<ab n="36">If those
ordinances depart from before me, saith the Lord, then the seed of
Israel also shall cease from being a nation before me for
euer.<note> Isa.54.9. chap.33.20</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Thus saith the
Lord, If heauen aboue can bee measured, and the foundations of the
earth searched out beneath, I will also cast off all the seed of
Israel for all that they haue done, saith the Lord.<note> Chap.33. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">¶ Behold,
the dayes come, saith the Lord, that the citie shall be built to
the Lord from the tower of Hananeel vnto the gate of the
corner.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the
measuring line shall yet goe forth ouer against it, vpon the hill
Gareb, and shall compasse about to Goath.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the whole
valley of the dead bodies, and of the ashes, and all the fields
vnto the brooke of Kidron, vnto the corner of the horse gate
towards the East, shalbe holy vnto the Lord, it shall not be
plucked vp, nor throwen downe any more for euer.</ab>



</div>