<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_48" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-48-48.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-48-49.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVIII.</head>
<head>1 The iudgement of Moab, 7 for their
pride, 11 for their securitie, 14 for their carnall confidence, 26
&amp; for their contempt of God and his people. 47 The restauration
of Moab.</head>

<ab n="1">Against Moab
thus sayth the Lord of hostes, the God of Israel, Woe vnto Nebo,
for it is spoiled: Kiriathaim is confounded and taken. Misgab is
confounded and dismayed.<note> Or, the hie place.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">There shall bee
no more prayse of Moab: in Heshbon they haue deuised euill against
it; come and let vs cut it off from being a nation; also thou shalt
bee cut downe, O Madmen, the sword shall pursue thee.<note> Or, bee brought to silence. , Heb. goe after thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">A voice of
crying shall be from Horonaim; Spoiling &amp; great
destruction.</ab>
<ab n="4">Moab is
destroyed, her little ones haue caused a crie to be heard.</ab>
<ab n="5">For in the going
vp of Luhith continuall weeping shall go vp; for in the going downe
of Horonaim the enemies haue heard a crie of
destruction.<note> Heb. weeping with weeping. , Isai.15.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Flee, saue your
liues, and be like the heath in the wildernesse.<note> Or, a naked tree. , Cha.17.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ For
because thou hast trusted in thy workes, and in thy treasures, thou
shalt also be taken, and Chemosh shall goe foorth into captiuitie
with his priests and his princes together.<note> Cha.49.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the spoyler
shall come vpon euery citie, and no citie shall escape: the valley
also shal perish, &amp; the plaine shall be destroyed, as
þe Lord hath spoken.</ab>
<ab n="9">Giue wings vnto
Moab, that it may flee and get away: for the cities thereof shalbe
desolate, without any to dwell therein.</ab>
<ab n="10">Cursed be he
that doeth the worke of the Lord deceitfully, and cursed be he that
keepeth backe his sword from blood.<note> Or, negligently.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Moab
hath bene at ease from his youth, and hee hath setled on his lees,
and hath not been emptied from vessell to vessell, neither hath he
gone into captiuitie: therefore his taste remained in him, and his
sent is not changed.<note> Heb. stood.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Therfore
behold, the dayes come, sayth the Lord, that I will send vnto him
wanderers that shall cause him to wander, and shall emptie his
vessels, and breake their bottles.</ab>

<fw>Moabs securitie, and pride.</fw>
<ab n="13">And Moab shall
bee ashamed of Chemosh, as the house of Israel was ashamed of
Bethel their confidence.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ How say
yee, We are mightie and strong men for the warre?<note> 1. Kings 12.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Moab is spoiled
and gone vp out of her cities, and his chosen yong men are gone
downe to the slaughter, sayth the King, whose Name is the Lord of
hostes.<note> Heb. the choice of.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The calamitie
of Moab is neere to come, and his affliction hasteth fast.</ab>
<ab n="17">All yee that
are about him bemoane him, and all yee that know his Name, say, How
is the strong staffe broken, and the beautifull rod!</ab>
<ab n="18">Thou daughter
that doest inhabit Dibon, come downe from thy glory, and sit in
thirst; for the spoiler of Moab shall come vpon thee, and he shall
destroy thy strong holdes.</ab>
<ab n="19">O inhabitant of
Aroer, stand by the way and espie, aske him that fleeth, and her
that escapeth, and say, What is done?<note> Heb. inhabitresse.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Moab is
confounded, for it is broken downe: howle and cry, tell ye it in
Arnon, that Moab is spoiled,<note> Isai. 16.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And iudgement
is come vpon the plaine countrey, vpon Holon, and vpon Iahazah, and
vpon Mephaath,</ab>
<ab n="22">And vpon Dibon,
and vpon Nebo, and vpon Beth-diblathaim,</ab>
<ab n="23">And vpon
Kiriathaim, and vpon Beth-Gamul, and vpon Beth-meon,</ab>
<ab n="24">And vpon
Kerioth, and vpon Bozrah, and vpon all the cities of the land of
Moab farre or neere.</ab>
<ab n="25">The horne of
Moab is cut off, &amp; his arme is broken, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Make ye
him drunken: for hee magnified himselfe against the Lord: Moab also
shall wallow in his vomit, and he also shalbe in derision.</ab>
<ab n="27">For was not
Israel a derision vnto thee? was hee found among theeues? for since
thou spakest of him, thou skippedst for ioy.<note> Or, moouedst thy selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">O yee that
dwell in Moab, leaue the cities and dwell in the rocke, and be like
the doue that maketh her nest in the sides of the holes
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="29">We haue heard
the pride of Moab, (he is exceeding proud) his loftinesse and his
arrogancie, and his pride, and the hautinesse of his
heart.<note> Isai. 16.6. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">I knowe his
wrath, sayeth the Lord, but it shall not be so, his lyes shall not
so effect it.<note> Or, those on whom hee stayeth (heb. his barres) do not right.</note></ab>

<fw>Feare, pit, and snare.</fw>
<ab n="31">Therefore will
I howle for Moab, and I will cry out for all Moab, mine heart shall
mourne for the men of Kir-heres.</ab>
<ab n="32">O vine of
Sibmah, I wil weepe for thee, with the weeping of Iazer; thy plants
are gone ouer the sea, they reach euen to the sea of Iazer, the
spoiler is fallen vpon thy summer fruits, and vpon thy
vintage.</ab>
<ab n="33">And ioy and
gladnesse is taken from the plentifull field, and from the land of
Moab, and I haue caused wine to faile from the winepresses, none
shall tread with shouting, their showting shall be no
showting.<note> Isai. 16.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">From the cry of
Heshbon euen vnto Elealeh, and euen vnto Iahaz haue they vttered
their voyce, from Zoar euen vnto Horonaim as an heifer of three
yeeres old: for the waters also of Nimrim shall be
desolate.<note> Isai. 15. 5,6. , Heb. desolations.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Moreouer, I
will cause to cease in Moab, saith the Lord, him that offereth in
the high places, and him that burneth incense to his Gods.</ab>
<ab n="36">Therefore mine
heart shall sound for Moab like pipes, and mine heart shall sound
like pipes for the men of Kir-heres: because the riches that hee
hath gotten is perished.</ab>
<ab n="37">For euery head
shall be bald, and euery beard clipt: vpon all the hands shall be
cuttings, and vpon the loines sackcloth.<note> Isai. 15. 2,3. , Heb. diminished.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">There shall be
lamentation generally vpon all the house toppes of Moab, and in the
streetes thereof: for I haue broken Moab like a vessell, wherin is
no pleasure, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="39">They shall
howle, saying; How is it broken downe? how hath Moab turned the
backe with shame? so shall Moab be a derision, and a dismaying to
all them about him.<note> Heb. necke.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">For thus saith
the Lord, Behold, hee shall fly as an eagle, and shall spread his
wings ouer Maob.</ab>
<ab n="41">Kerioth is
taken, and the strong holds are surprised, &amp; the mighty mens
hearts in Moab at that day shall be as the heart of a woman in her
pangs.<note> Or, the cities.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And Moab shall
be destroyed from being a people, because he hath magnified
himselfe against the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="43">Feare, and the
pit, and the snare shall be vpon thee, O inhabitant of Moab, saith
the Lord.<note> Isai. 24. 17,18.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Ammon.</fw>
<ab n="44">Hee that fleeth
from the feare shall fall into the pit, and he that getteth vp out
of the pit shall be taken in the snare: for I will bring vpon it,
euen vpon Moab, the yeere of their visitation, saith the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="45">They that fled,
stood vnder the shadow of Heshbon, because of the force: but a fire
shall come forth out of Heshbon, and a flame from the middest of
Sihon, and shall deuoure the corner of Moab, and the crowne of the
head of the tumultuous ones.<note> Num. 21. 28. , Heb. children of noise.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">Woe be vnto
thee, O Moab, the people of Chemosh perisheth: for thy sonnes are
taken captiues, and thy daughters captiues.<note> Heb. in captiuitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">¶ Yet will
I bring againe the captiuitie of Moab in the later dayes, saith the
Lord. Thus farre is the iudgement of Moab.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>