<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 The Butler and Baker of Pharaoh in
prison. 4 Ioseph hath charge of them. 5 He interpreteth their
dreames. 20 They come to passe according to his interpretation. 23
The ingratitude of the Butler.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after these things, that the Butler of the King of Egypt, and
his Baker, had offended their lord the King of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Pharaoh was
wroth against two of his officers, against the chiefe of the
Butlers, and against the chiefe of the Bakers.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he put them
in ward in the house of the captaine of the guard, into the prison,
the place where Ioseph was bound.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the captaine
of the guard charged Ioseph with them, and he serued them, and they
continued a season in warde.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And they
dreamed a dreame both of them, each man his dreame in one night,
each man according to the interpretation of his dreame, the Butler
and the Baker of the king of Egypt, which were bound in the
prison.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Ioseph came
in vnto them in the morning, and looked vpon them, and behold, they
were sad.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he asked
Pharaohs officers that were with him in the warde of his lords
house, saying, wherefore looke ye so sadly to day?<note> Heb. are your faces euill?</note></ab>

<fw>He interpreteth seuerall
dreames.</fw>
<ab n="8">And they said
vnto him, we haue dreamed a dreame, and there is no interpreter of
it. And Ioseph said vnto them, Doe not interpretations belong to
God? tell me them, I pray you.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the chiefe
Butler tolde his dreame to Ioseph, and said to him; In my dreame,
beholde, a vine was before mee:</ab>
<ab n="10">And in the vine
were three branches, and it was as though it budded, and her
blossoms shot foorth; and the clusters thereof brought forth ripe
grapes.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Pharaohs cup
was in my hand, and I tooke the grapes and pressed them into
Pharaohs cup: and I gaue the cup into Pharaohs hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Ioseph said
vnto him, This is the interpretation of it: the three branches are
three dayes,</ab>
<ab n="13">Yet within three
dayes shall Pharaoh lift vp thine head, and restore thee vnto thy
place, and thou shalt deliuer Pharaohs cup into his hand, after the
former manner when thou wast his Butler.<note> Or, reckon.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But thinke on
me, when it shall be well with thee, and shew kindenesse, I pray
thee, vnto mee, and make mention of me vnto Pharaoh, and bring me
out of this house.<note> Hebr. Remember mee with thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For indeed I was
stollen away out of the land of the Hebrewes: and here also haue I
done nothing, that they should put me into the dungeon.</ab>
<ab n="16">When the chiefe
Baker saw, that the interpretation was good, he said vnto Ioseph, I
also was in my dreame, and behold, I had three white baskets on my
head.<note> Or, full of holes.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And in the
vppermost basket there was of all maner of bake-meats for Pharaoh,
and the birds did eat them out of the basket vpon my
head.<note> Hebr. meat of Pharaoh, the worke of a baker, or cooke.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Ioseph
answered, and said, This is the interpretation thereof: the three
baskets are three dayes:</ab>
<ab n="19">Yet within three
dayes shall Pharaoh lift vp thy head from off thee, and shall hang
thee on a tree, and the birds shall eate thy flesh from off
thee.<note> Or, reckon thee, and take thy office from thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And it
came to passe the third day, which was Pharaohs birth day, that hee
made a feast vnto all his seruaunts: and he lifted vp by the head
of the chiefe Butler, and of the chiefe Baker among his
seruants.<note> Or, reckoned.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And he restored
the chiefe Butler vnto his Butlership againe, and hee gaue the cup
into Pharaohs hand.</ab>
<ab n="22">But he hanged
the chiefe Baker, as Ioseph had interpreted to them.</ab>

<fw>He interpreteth seuerall
dreames.</fw>
<ab n="23">Yet did not the
chiefe Butler remember Ioseph, but forgate him.</ab>



</div>