<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Zedekiah sendeth to Ieremiah to
inquire the euent of Nebuchadrezzars warre. 3 Ieremiah foretelleth
a hard siege and miserable captiuitie. 8 He counselleth the people
to fall to the Caldeans, 11 and vpbraideth the kings
house.</head>

<ab n="1">The word which
came vnto Ieremiah from the Lord, when king Zedekiah sent vnto him
Pashur the sonne of Melchiah, and Zephaniah the sonne of Maaseiah
the priest, saying;</ab>

<fw>Life, and death.</fw>
<ab n="2">Enquire, I pray
thee, of the Lord for vs (for Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon
maketh warre against vs) if so be that the Lord will deale with vs,
according to all his wondrous workes, that he may goe vp from
vs.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Then
saide Ieremiah vnto them. Thus shall yee say to Zedekiah,</ab>
<ab n="4">Thus saith the
Lord God of Israel; Behold, I will turne backe the weapons of warre
that are in your hands, wherewith yee fight against the king of
Babylon, and against the Caldeans, which besiege you without the
walles, and I will assemble them into the middest of this
citie.</ab>
<ab n="5">And I myselfe
will fight against you with an out stretched hand, and with a
strong arme, euen in anger, and in furie, and in great
wrath.<note> Exod. 6.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I will smite
the inhabitants of this citie both man and beast: they shall die of
a great pestilence.</ab>
<ab n="7">And afterward,
saith the Lord, I will deliuer Zedekiah king of Iudah, and his
seruants, and the people, and such as are left in this citie from
the pestilence, from the sword, and from the famine, into the hand
of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of their
enemies, and into the hand of those that seeke their life, and and
he shall smite them with the edge of the sword: hee shall not spare
them, neither haue pitie, nor haue mercy.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And vnto
this people thou shalt say; Thus saith the Lord; Behold, I set
before you the way of life, and the way of death.</ab>
<ab n="9">He that abideth
in this citie, shall die by the sword, and by the famine, and by
the pestilence: but he that goeth out, and falleth to the Caldeans,
that besiege you, he shall liue, and his life shall be vnto him,
for a pray.<note> Chap. 38. 2. , Chap. 39. 18. and 45. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For I haue set
my face against this citie for euill and not for good, saith the
Lord; it shall be giuen into the hand of the king of Babylon, and
he shall burne it with fire.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
touching the house of the king of Iudah, say; Heare yee the word of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">Oh house of
Dauid, thus saith the Lord, Execute iudgement in the morning, and
deliuer him that is spoiled, out of the hand of the oppressour,
lest my furie goe out like fire, and burne, that none can quench
it, because of the euill of your doings.<note> Chap.22. 2. , Heb. iudge.</note></ab>

<fw>The Kings duetie, and
prosperitie.</fw>
<ab n="13">Behold, I am
against thee, O inhabitant of the valley, and rocke of the plaine,
saith the Lord, which say, Who shall come downe against vs? or who
shall enter into our habitations?<note> Heb. inhabitresse.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But I will
punish you according to the fruit of your doings, saith the Lord:
and I will kindle a fire in the forrest thereof, and it shall
deuoure all things round about it.<note> Heb. visite vpon. , Pro.1.31.</note></ab>



</div>