<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>Ieremiah by promises and
threatnings, exhorteth to repentance. 8 Hee is therefore
apprehended, 10 and arraigned: 11 His apologie: 16 He is quit in
iudgement, by the example of Micah, 20 and of Vrijah, 24 and by the
care of Ahikam.</head>

<ab n="1">In the beginning
of the reigne of Iehoiakim the sonne of Iosiah king of Iudah, came
this word from the Lord, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord, Stand in the Court of the Lords house, and speake vnto all
the cities of Iudah, which come to worship in the Lords house, all
the wordes that I command thee to speake vnto them: diminish not a
word;<note> Acts.20. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">If so bee they
will hearken, and turne euery man from his euill way, that I may
repent me of the euil which I purpose to doe vnto them, because of
the euil of their doings.<note> Chap.18. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And thou shalt
say vnto them, Thus saith the Lord; If yee will not hearken to mee
to walke in my Law, which I haue set before you,</ab>
<ab n="5">To hearken to
the wordes of my seruants the Prophets, whom I sent vnto you, both
rising vp early and sending them, (but ye haue not
hearkned:)</ab>
<ab n="6">Then wil I make
this house like Shiloh, and wil make this city a curse to all the
nations of the earth.<note> 1.Sam.4. 12. chap.7. 12,14. psal. 78.60.</note></ab>

<fw>The Prophet taken.</fw>
<ab n="7">So the priests
and the prophets, and all the people heard Ieremiah speaking these
wordes in the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Now it
came to passe when Ieremiah had made an ende of speaking all that
the Lord had commanded him to speake vnto all the people, that the
priests and the prophets, and all the people tooke him, saying;
Thou shalt surely die.</ab>
<ab n="9">Why hast thou
prophecied in the Name of the Lord, saying, This house shalbe like
Shiloh, and this city shalbe desolate without an inhabitant? And
all the people were gathered against Ieremiah in the house of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ When the
Princes of Iudah heard these things, then they came vp from the
kings house vnto the house of the Lord, and sate downe in the
entrie of the new gate of the Lords house.<note> Or, at the doore.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then spake the
priests and the prophets vnto the Princes, and to all the people,
saying; This man is worthy to die, for he hath prophecied against
this citie, as yee haue heard with your eares.<note> Hebr. the iudgement of death is for this man.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then
spake Ieremiah vnto all the Princes, and to all the people, saying,
The Lord sent me to prophecie against this house, and against this
citie, all the wordes that yee haue heard.</ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore nowe
amend your wayes, and your doings, and obey the voice of the Lord
your God, and the Lord will repent him of the euill that he hath
pronounced against you.<note> Chap.7.3. , Verse 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">As for mee,
behold, I am in your hand: doe with mee as seemeth good and meet
vnto you.<note> Hebr. as it is good and right in your eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But know ye for
certaine, That if ye put mee to death, ye shall surely bring
innocent blood vpon your selues, and vpon this citie, and vpon the
inhabitants thereof: for of a trueth the Lord hath sent mee vnto
you, to speake all these words in your eares.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then
said the Princes, and all the people, vnto the priests, and to the
prophets; This man is not worthy to die: for hee hath spoken to vs
in the Name of the Lord our God.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then rose vp
certaine of the Elders of the land, and spake to all the assembly
of the people, saying;</ab>

<fw>Vrijah slaine.</fw>
<ab n="18">Micah the
Morashite prophecied in the dayes of Hezekiah king of Iudah, and
spake to all the people of Iudah, saying; Thus saith the Lord of
hostes, Zion shall be plowed like a field, and Ierusalem shall
become heapes, and the mountaine of the house, the hie places of a
forrest.<note> Mic.1.1. and 3. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Did Hezekiah
King of Iudah and all Iudah put him at all to death? did hee not
feare the Lord, and besought the Lord, and the Lord repented him of
the euill which he had pronounced against them? thus might wee
procure great euill against our soules.<note> Heb. the face of the LORD.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And there was
also a man that prophecied in the Name of the Lord, Urijah the
sonne of Shemaiah of Kiriath-iearim, who prophecied against this
citie and against this land, according to all the words of
Ieremiah.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when
Iehoiakim the king with all his mightie men, and all the princes
heard his wordes, the king sought to put him to death; but when
Urijah heard it, he was afraid and fled, and went into
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Iehoiakim
the king sent men into Egypt, namely Elnathan the sonne of Achbor,
and certeine men with him, into Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they fet
foorth Urijah out of Egypt, and brought him vnto Iehoiakim the
king, who slewe him with the sword, and cast his dead body into the
graues of the common people.<note> Heb. sons of the people.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Neuerthelesse,
the hand of Ahikam, the sonne of Shaphan, was with Ieremiah, that
they should not giue him into the hand of the people, to put him to
death.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>