<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah is sent to call for true
repentance, to preuent the Iewes captiuitie. 8 He reiecteth their
vaine confidence, 12 by the example of Shiloh. 17 He threatneth
them for their idolatrie. 21 Hee reiecteth the sacrifices of the
disobedient. 29 He exhorteth to mourne for their abominations in
Tophet, 32 and the iudgements for the same.</head>


<fw>Vaine trust.</fw>
<ab n="1">The word that
came to Ieremiah from the Lord, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Stand in the gate
of the Lords house, and proclaime there this word, and say, Heare
the word of the Lord, all ye of Iudah, that enter in at these gates
to worship the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thus saith the
Lord of hostes the God of Israel; Amend your wayes, and your
doings, and I will cause you to dwell in this place.<note> Chap.26. 13. and 18. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Trust ye not in
lying words, saying, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the
Lord, the Temple of the Lord are these.</ab>
<ab n="5">For if ye
throughly amend your waies and your doings, if you throughly
execute iudgement betweene a man and his neighbour:</ab>
<ab n="6">If ye oppresse
not the stranger, the fatherlesse and the widow, and shed not
innocent blood in this place, neither walke after other gods to
your hurt:</ab>
<ab n="7">Then will I cause
you to dwell in this place, in the land that I gaue to your
fathers, for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Behold, ye
trust in lying words, that cannot profit.</ab>
<ab n="9">Will ye steale,
murther, and commit adulterie, and sweare falsly, and burne incense
vnto Baal, and walke after other gods, whom ye know not;</ab>
<ab n="10">And come and
stand before me in this house, which is called by my Name, and say,
We are deliuered, to do all these abominations?<note> Hebr. whereupon my Name is called.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Is this house,
which is called by my Name, become a denne of robbers in your eies?
Behold, euen I haue seen it, saith the Lord.<note> Isai. 56.7. , Matth. 21. 13. mar. 11. 17. luke 19. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But goe yee now
vnto my place which was in Shiloh, where I set my Name at the
first, and see what I did to it, for the wickednesse of my people
Israel.<note> 1.Sam.4. 11. psal.78. 60. chap. 26.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And now because
ye haue done all these workes, saith the Lord, and I spake vnto
you, rising vp earely, and speaking, but ye heard not; and I called
you, but ye answered not:<note> Pro. 1.24. isa. 65.12. and 66.4.</note></ab>

<fw>Obey Gods voice.</fw>
<ab n="14">Therefore will I
doe vnto this house, which is called by my Name, wherein yee trust,
and vnto the place which I gaue to you, and to your fathers, as I
haue done to Shiloh.<note> 1.Sam.4.11. psal.78.60. and 132.6. chap.26.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And I will cast
you out of my sight, as I haue cast out all your brethren, euen the
whole seed of Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore pray
not thou for this people, neither lift vp cry nor prayer for them,
neither make intercession to me, for I will not heare
thee.<note> Chap.12.14. and 14. 11. exod. 32.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Seest
thou not what they doe in the cities of Iudah, and in the streets
of Ierusalem?</ab>
<ab n="18">The children
gather wood, and the fathers kindle the fire, &amp; the women knead
their dough to make cakes to the Queene of heauen, and to powre out
drinke offerings vnto other gods, that they may prouoke me to
anger.<note> Chap. 44. 19. , Or, frame, or workmanship of heauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Doe they prouoke
mee to anger, saith the Lord ? Doe they not prouoke themselues to
the confusion of their owne faces?</ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God, Behold, mine anger and my furie shalbe powred
out vpon this place, vpon man &amp; vpon beast, and vpon the trees
of the field, and vpon the fruit of the ground, and it shall burne,
and shall not be quenched.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Thus
saith the Lord of hosts the God of Israel, Put your burnt offrings
vnto your sacrifices, &amp; eate flesh.<note> Isa.1.11. chap 6.20. amos 5.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For I spake not
vnto your fathers, nor commanded them in the day that I brought
them out of the land of Egypt, concerning burnt offerings or
sacrifices.<note> Hebr. concerning the matter of.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But this thing
commaunded I them, saying, Obey my voice, and I wil be your God,
and ye shalbe my people: and walke ye in all the wayes that I haue
commanded you, that it may be well vnto you.<note> Deut. 6.3. , Exod. 19. 5. leuit.26. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But they
hearkened not, nor inclined their eare, but walked in the counsels
and in the imagination of their euill heart, and went backward, and
not forward.<note> Or, stubburnnesse. , Hebr. were.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Since the day
that your fathers came forth out of the land of Egypt vnto this
day, I haue euen sent vnto you all my seruants the Prophets, daily
rising vp early, and sending them.<note> 1.Chron. 36.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Yet they
hearkned not vnto me, nor inclined their eare, but hardened their
neck, they did worse then their fathers.<note> Chap.16. 12.</note></ab>

<fw>Stubborne people.</fw>
<ab n="27">Therefore thou
shalt speake all these wordes vnto them, but they will not hearken
to thee: thou shalt also call vnto them, but they will not answere
thee.</ab>
<ab n="28">But thou shalt
say vnto them; This is a nation, that obeyeth not the voyce of the
Lord their God, nor receiueth correction: trueth is perished, and
is cut off from their mouth.<note> Or, instruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Cut off
thine haire, O Ierusalem, and cast it away, and take vp a
lamentation on high places, for the Lord hath reiected, and
forsaken the generation of his wrath.</ab>
<ab n="30">For the children
of Iudah haue done euill in my sight, saith the Lord: they haue set
their abominations in the house which is called by my Name, to
pollute it.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they haue
built the high places of Tophet which is in the valley of the sonne
of Hinnom, to burne their sonnes and their daughters in the fire,
which I commanded them not, neither came it into my
heart.<note> 2.Kings 23.10. chap. 19.5. , Heb. came it vpon my heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ Therefore
behold, the dayes come, saith the Lord, that it shall no more be
called Tophet, nor the valley of the sonne of Hinnom, but the
valley of slaughter: for they shall bury in Tophet, till there be
no place.<note> Cha. 19.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the
carkeises of this people shall be meate for the fowles of the
heauen, and for the beasts of the earth, and none shall fray them
away.<note> Chap.34.20. and .16.4. psal. 79.2</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Then will I
cause to cease from the cities of Iudah, and from the streets of
Ierusalem, the voice of mirth and the voice of gladnesse, the voice
of the bridegroome, and the voice of the bride: for the land shall
be desolate.<note> Isa.24.7. chap.16.9. and 25.10. and .33.11. eze.26.13. ose.2.11.</note></ab>



</div>