<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_37" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-36-37.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-37-38.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVII.</head>
<head>2 Ioseph is hated of his brethren. 5
His two dreames. 13 Iacob sendeth him to visite his brethren. 18
His brethren conspire his death. 21 Reuben saueth him. 26 They sell
him to the Ishmeelites. 31 His father, deceiued by the bloodie
coat, mourneth for him. 36 Hee is sold to Potiphar in
Egypt.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iacob dwelt
in the land wherein his father was a stranger, in the land of
Canaan.<note> Heb. of his fathers soiournings.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">These are the
generations of Iacob: Ioseph being seuenteene yeeres old, was
feeding the flocke with his brethren, and the lad was with the
sonnes of Bilhah, and with the sonnes of Zilpah, his fathers wiues:
and Ioseph brought vnto his father their euill report.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now Israel loued
Ioseph more then all his children, because he was the sonne of his
old age: and he made him a coat of many colours.<note> Or, peeces.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when his
brethren saw that their father loued him more then all his
brethren, they hated him, and could not speake peaceably vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And Ioseph
dreamed a dreame, and he told it his brethren, and they hated him
yet the more.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he said vnto
them, Heare, I pray you, this dreame which I haue dreamed.</ab>

<fw>Iosephs dreames.</fw>
<ab n="7">For beholde, wee
were binding sheaues in the field, and loe, my sheafe arose, and
also stood vpright; and behold, your sheaues stood round about, and
made obeisance to my sheafe.</ab>
<ab n="8">And his brethren
saide to him, Shalt thou indeed reigne ouer vs? or shalt thou
indeed haue dominion ouer vs? and they hated him yet the more, for
his dreames, and for his words.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And hee
dreamed yet another dreame, and told it his brethren, and said,
Behold, I haue dreamed a dreame more: and behold, the sunne and the
moone, and the eleuen starres made obeisance to me.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he told it
to his father, and to his brethren: and his father rebuked him, and
said vnto him, What is this dreame that thou hast dreamed? shal I,
and thy mother, and thy brethren indeed come to bow downe our
selues to thee, to the earth?</ab>
<ab n="11">And his brethren
enuied him: but his father obserued the saying.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And his
brethren went to feed their fathers flocke in Shechem.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Israel saide
vnto Ioseph, Doe not thy brethren feed the flocke in Shechem? Come,
and I will send thee vnto them: &amp; he said to him, Here am
I.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he said to
him, Goe, I pray thee, see whether it bee well with thy brethren,
and well with the flockes, and bring me word againe: so hee sent
him out of the vale of Hebron, and he came to Shechem.<note> Hebr. see the peace of thy brethren &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And a
certaine man found him, and behold, hee was wandring in the field,
and the man asked him, saying, What seekest thou?</ab>
<ab n="16">And he said, I
seeke my brethren: tell me, I pray thee, where they feede their
flockes.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the man
said, They are departed hence: for I heard them say, Let vs goe to
Dothan. And Ioseph went after his brethren, and found them in
Dothan.</ab>
<ab n="18">And when they
saw him a farre off, euen before he came neere vnto them, they
conspired against him, to slay him.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they said
one to another, Behold, this dreamer commeth.<note> Hebr. master of dreames.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Come now
therefore, and let vs slay him, and cast him into some pit, and we
will say, Some euill beast hath deuoured him: and we shall see what
will become of his dreames.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Reuben heard
it, and he deliuered him out of their hands, and said; Let vs not
kill him.<note> Chap. 42. 22.</note></ab>

<fw>Ioseph is sold.</fw>
<ab n="22">And Reuben saide
vnto them, Shed no blood, but cast him into this pit that is in the
wildernesse, and lay no hand vpon him; that he might rid him out of
their hands, to deliuer him to his father againe.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And it
came to passe when Ioseph was come vnto his brethren, that they
stript Ioseph out of his coate, his coat of many colours that was
on him.<note> Or, pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And they tooke
him and cast him into a pit: and the pit was emptie, there was no
water in it.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they sate
downe to eat bread: and they lift vp their eyes and looked, and
behold, a company of Ishmeelites came from Gilead, with their
camels, bearing spicery, &amp; baulme, and myrrhe, going to cary it
downe to Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Iudah saide
vnto his brethren, What profit is it if we slay our brother, and
conceale his blood?</ab>
<ab n="27">Come, and let vs
sell him to the Ishmeelites, and let not our hand bee vpon him: for
he is our brother, and our flesh; and his brethren were
content.<note> Hebr. hearkened.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Then there
passed by Midianites merchant men, and they drew and lift vp Ioseph
out of the pit, and sold Ioseph to the Ishmeelites for twentie
pieces of siluer: and they brought Ioseph into Egypt.<note> Psal 105. 17. wis. 10. 13. acts.7. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And
Reuben returned vnto the pit, and behold, Ioseph was not in the
pit: and he rent his clothes.</ab>
<ab n="30">And hee returned
vnto his brethren and said, The childe is not, and I, whither shall
I goe?</ab>
<ab n="31">And they tooke
Iosephs coat, and killed a kid of the goats, and dipped the coat in
the blood.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they sent
the coat of many colours, and they brought it to their father, and
said, This haue we found: know now whether it bee thy sonnes coat
or no.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he knew it,
and said, It is my sonnes coat: an euil beast hath deuoured him;
Ioseph is without doubt rent in pieces.<note> Chap. 44. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And Iacob rent
his clothes, and put sackcloth vpon his loines, &amp; mourned for
his sonne many dayes.</ab>
<ab n="35">And all his
sonnes, and all his daughters rose vp to comfort him: but he
refused to be comforted: and he said, For I will goe downe into the
graue vnto my sonne, mourning; thus his father wept for
him.</ab>

<fw>Iudahs marriage:</fw>
<ab n="36">And the
Medanites sold him into Egypt vnto Potiphar, an officer of
Pharaohs, and captaine of the guard.<note> Hebr. Eunuch. But the word doeth signifie not only Eunuches, but also Chamberlaines, Courtiers, and Officers. , Heb. chiefe of the slaughter men, or executioners. , Or, chiefe Marshall.</note></ab>



</div>