<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_49" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-48-49.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-49-49.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-49-50.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIX.</head>
<head>1 The iudgement of the Ammonites. 6
Their restauration. 7 The iudgement of Edom, 23 of Damascus, 28 of
Kedar, 30 of Hazor, 34 and of Elam. 39 The restauration of
Elam.</head>

<ab n="1">Concerning the
Ammonites, thus sayth the Lord; hath Israel no sonnes? Hath he no
heire? Why then doth their king inherit God, and his people dwell
in his cities?<note> Or, against. , Or, Melcom. , Amos 1. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Therfore behold,
the dayes come, saith the Lord, that I will cause an alarme of
warre to be heard in Rabbah of the Ammonites, and it shall be a
desolate heape, and her daughters shall be burnt with fire: then
shall Israel be heire vnto them that were his heires, saith the
Lord.<note> Amos. 1. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Howle, O
Heshbon, for Ai is spoiled: cry yee daughters of Rabbah, gird yee
with sackcloth: lament and runne to and fro by the hedges: for
their king shall goe into captiuitie: and his priests and his
princes together.<note> Or, Melcom. , Chap.48. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Wherfore
gloriest thou in the valleys, thy flowing valley, O backsliding
daughter? That trusted in her treasures, saying; Who shall come
vnto mee?<note> Or, thy valley floweth away.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Behold, I will
bring a feare vpon thee, saith the Lord God of hostes, from all
those that be about thee, and yee shall be driuen out euery man
right forth, and none shal gather vp him that wandereth.</ab>
<ab n="6">And afterward I
will bring againe the captiuitie of the children of Ammon, saith
the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Against Edom, and Damascus.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶
Concerning Edom thus saith the Lord of hosts, Is wisedome no more
in Teman? is counsell perished from the prudent? is their wisedom
vanished?<note> Obad.ver.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Flee ye, turne
backe, dwell deepe, O inhabitants of Dedan: for I will bring the
calamitie of Esau vpon him, the time that I will visite
him.<note> Or, they are turned backe.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">If grape
gatherers come to thee, would they not leaue some gleaning grapes?
If theeues by night, they will destroy till they haue
enough.<note> Obad. ver. 5. , Heb. their sufficiencie.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But I haue made
Esau bare, I haue vncouered his secret places, and he shall not be
able to hide himselfe: his seed is spoiled, and his brethren and
his neighbours, and he is not.</ab>
<ab n="11">Leaue thy
fatherlesse children, I will preserue them aliue: and let thy
widowes trust in me.</ab>
<ab n="12">For thus saith
the Lord, Behold, they whose iudgement was not to drinke of the
cup, haue assuredly drunken, and art thou he that shall altogether
go vnpunished? thou shalt not go vnpunished, but thou shalt surely
drinke of it.</ab>
<ab n="13">For I haue
sworne by my selfe, saith the Lord, that Bozrah shall become a
desolation, a reproch, a waste, and a curse, and all the cities
thereof shall be perpetuall wastes.</ab>
<ab n="14">I haue heard a
rumor from the Lord, &amp; an ambassadour is sent vnto the heathen,
saying, Gather ye together &amp; come against her, &amp; rise vp to
the battell.<note> Obad.ver.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For lo, I wil
make thee smal among the heathen, and despised among men.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thy
terriblenesse hath deceiued thee, and the pride of thine heart, O
thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rocke, that holdest the
height of the hill: thogh thou shouldest make thy nest as high as
the eagle, I will bring thee downe from thence, saith the
Lord.<note> Obad. ver. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Also Edom
shalbe a desolation: euery one þt goeth by it
shalbe astonished, and shall hisse at all the plagues
thereof,<note> Chap. 50 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">As in the
ouerthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah, and the neighbour cities thereof,
saith the Lord: no man shall abide there, neither shall a sonne of
man dwell in it.<note> Gen. 19. 25. chap. 50 40.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Edom, and Damascus.</fw>
<ab n="19">Behold, he shal
come vp like a lyon from the swelling of Iordane against the
habitation of the strong: but I wil suddenly make him runne away
from her, and who is a chosen man that I may appoynt ouer her? For
who is like mee? And who will appoint me the time? Who is that
shepheard that will stand before mee?<note> Or, conuent me in iudgement. , Iob. 21.1. chap. 50. 44,45.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Therfore heare
the counsell of the Lord, that he hath taken against Edom, &amp;
his purposes that hee hath purposed against the inhabitants of
Teman: surely the least of the flocke shall draw them out: surely
hee shall make their habitations desolate with them.</ab>
<ab n="21">The earth is
moued at the noise of their fall: at the crie, the noise thereof
was heard in the red Sea.<note> Heb. weedie Sea.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Behold, he
shall come vp and flie as the eagle, and spread his wings ouer
Bozrah: and at that day shall the heart of the mightie men of Edom,
be as the heart of a woman in her pangs.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶
Concerning Damascus, Hamath is confounded, &amp; Arpad, for they
haue heard euil tidings, they are faint hearted, there is sorrow on
the sea, it can not be quiet.<note> Heb. melted. , Or, as on the Sea.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Damascus is
waxed feeble, and turneth her selfe to flee, and feare hath seised
on her: anguish and sorrowes haue taken her as a woman in
trauell.</ab>
<ab n="25">How is the
citie of praise not left, the citie of my ioy?</ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore her
yong men shal fall in her streets, and all the men of warre shall
bee cut off in that day, saith the Lord of hosts.</ab>
<ab n="27">And I will
kindle a fire in the wall of Damascus, and it shal consume the
palaces of Ben-hadad.<note> Amos 1.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶
Concerning Kedar, and concerning the kingdoms of Hazor, which
Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon shall smite, Thus saith the Lord:
Arise ye, goe vp to Kedar, and spoile the men of the East.</ab>
<ab n="29">Their tents and
their flocks shall they take away: they shal take to themselues
their curtaines and all their vessels, and their camels, and they
shal crie vnto them, Feare is on euery side.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Flee,
get you farre off, dwell deepe, O ye inhabitants of Hazor, saith
the Lord: for Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon hath taken counsel
against you, and hath conceiued a purpose against you.<note> Verse 8. , Heb. flit greatly.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Arise, get you
vp vnto the wealthy nation that dwelleth without care, saith the
Lord, which haue neither gates nor barres, which dwell
alone.<note> Or, that is at ease.</note></ab>

<fw>Against Elam.</fw>
<ab n="32">And their
camels shall be a bootie, and the multitude of their cattell a
spoile, and I will scatter into all winds them that are in the
vtmost corners, and I will bring their calamitie from all sides
thereof, saith the Lord.<note> Heb. cut off into corners, or that haue the corners of their haire polled.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And Hazor shall
be a dwelling for dragons, and a desolation for euer; there shall
no man abide there, nor any sonne of man dwell in it.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ The word
of the Lord that came to Ieremiah the Prophet against Elam in the
beginning of the reigne of Zedekiah king of Iudah, saying,</ab>
<ab n="35">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, Behold, I will breake the bow of Elam, the chiefe of
their might.</ab>
<ab n="36">And vpon Elam
will I bring the foure windes from the foure quarters of heauen,
and will scatter them towards all those windes, and there shall be
no nation, whither the outcasts of Elam shall not come.</ab>
<ab n="37">For I will
cause Elam to bee dismayed before their enemies, and before them
that seeke their life: and I will bring euill vpon them, euen my
fierce anger, saith the Lord, and I will send the sword after them,
till I haue consumed them.</ab>
<ab n="38">And I will set
my throne in Elam, and will destroy from thence the king and the
princes, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ But it
shall come to passe in the later daies, that I wil bring againe the
captiuitie of Elam, saith the Lord.<note> Chap. 49. 6. and 48. 47.</note></ab>



</div>