<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Abraham is tempted to offer Isaac.
3 Hee giueth proofe of his faith and obedience. 11 The Angel
stayeth him. 13 Isaac is exchanged with a ramme. 14 The place is
called Iehouah-ijreh. 15 Abraham is blessed againe. 20 The
generation of Nahor vnto Rebekah.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after these things, that God did tempt Abraham, and said vnto
him, Abraham. And hee said, Beholde, heere I am.<note> Hebr.11. 17. , Hebr. Behold me.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he said, Take
now thy sonne, thine onely sonne Isaac, whom thou louest, and get
thee into the land of Moriah: and offer him there for a burnt
offering vpon one of the Mountaines which I will tell thee
of.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
Abraham rose vp earely in the morning, and sadled his asse, and
tooke two of his yong men with him, and Isaac his sonne, and claue
the wood for the burnt offering, and rose vp, and went vnto the
place of which God had told him.</ab>

<fw>Isaac spared.</fw>
<ab n="4">Then on the third
day Abraham lift vp his eyes, and saw the place afarre off.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Abraham said
vnto his yong men, Abide you here with the asse, and I and the lad
will goe yonder and worship, and come againe to you.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Abraham tooke
the wood of the burnt offering, and layd it vpon Isaac his sonne:
and he tooke the fire in his hand, and a knife: and they went both
of them together.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Isaac spake
vnto Abraham his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am
I, my sonne. And hee said, Behold the fire and wood: but where is
the lambe for a burnt offring?<note> Hebr. behold me. , Or, kidde.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Abraham said,
My sonne, God will prouide himselfe a lambe for a burnt offering:
so they went both of them together.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they came to
the place which God had tolde him of, and Abraham built an Altar
there, and layd the wood in order, and bound Isaac his sonne, and
layde him on the Altar vpon the wood.<note> Iam.2.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Abraham
stretched foorth his hand, and tooke the knife to slay his
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Angel of
the LORD called vnto him out of heauen, and said, Abraham, Abraham.
And he said, Here am I.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he said, Lay
not thine hand vpon the lad, neither do thou any thing vnto him:
for now I know that thou fearest God, seeing thou hast not
withhelde thy sonne, thine onely sonne from mee.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Abraham
lifted vp his eyes, and looked, and beholde, behinde him a Ramme
caught in a thicket by his hornes: And Abraham went and tooke the
Ramme, and offered him vp for a burnt offering, in the stead of his
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Abraham
called the name of that place Iehouah-ijreh, as it is said to this
day, In the Mount of the LORD it shalbe seene.<note> That is, The LORD will see, or, prouide.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And the
Angel of the LORD called vnto Abraham out of heauen the second
time,</ab>
<ab n="16">And said, By my
selfe haue I sworne, saith the LORD, for because thou hast done
this thing, and hast not withheld thy sonne, thine onely
sonne,<note> Psal. 105. 9. ecclus. 44.21. luke 1.73. Hebr.6.13.</note></ab>

<fw>Sarahs death.</fw>
<ab n="17">That in blessing
I will blesse thee, and in multiplying, I will multiply thy seed as
the starres of the heauen, and as the sand which is vpon the sea
shore, and thy seed shall possesse the gate of his
enemies.<note> Heb. lippe.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And in thy seed
shall all the nations of the earth be blessed, because thou hast
obeyed my voice.<note> Chap.12. 3. and 18. 18. ecclus.44.22. acts. 3.25. galat. 3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">So Abraham
returned vnto his yong men, and they rose vp, and went together to
Beer-sheba, and Abraham dwelt at Beer-sheba.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And it
came to passe after these things, that it was told Abraham, saying,
Behold Milcah, shee hath also borne children vnto thy brother
Nahor,</ab>
<ab n="21">Huz his first
borne, and Buz his brother, and Kemuel the father of Aram,</ab>
<ab n="22">And Chesed, and
Hazo, and Pildash, and Iidlaph, and Bethuel.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Bethuel
begate Rebekah: these eight Milcah did beare to Nahor, Abrahams
brother.<note> Called Rom.9.10. Rebecca.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And his
concubine whose name was Reumah, she bare also Tebah, and Gaham,
and Thahash, and Maachah.</ab>



</div>