<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_47" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-46-47.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-47-47.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-47-48.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVII.</head>
<head>1 Ioseph presenteth fiue of his
brethren, 7 and his father, before Pharaoh. 11 Hee giueth them
habitation and maintenance. 13 He getteth all the Egyptians money,
16 their cattell, 18 their lands to Pharaoh. 22 The Priestes land
was not bought. 23 Hee letteth the land to them for a fift part. 28
Iacobs age. 29 Hee sweareth Ioseph to burie him with his
fathers.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Ioseph came
and tolde Pharaoh, and saide, My father and my brethren, and their
flockes, and their heards, and all that they haue, are come out of
the land of Canaan: and behold, they are in the land of
Goshen.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee tooke
some of his brethren, euen fiue men, &amp; presented them vnto
Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Pharaoh said
vnto his brethren, What is your occupation? And they said vnto
Pharaoh, Thy seruants are shepheards, both wee and also our
fathers.</ab>

<fw>Iacob and Pharaoh.</fw>
<ab n="4">They said
moreouer vnto Pharaoh, For to soiourne in the land are we come: for
thy seruants haue no pasture for their flockes, for the famine is
sore in the land of Canaan: now therefore we pray thee, let thy
seruants dwel in the land of Goshen.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Pharaoh spake
vnto Ioseph, saying, Thy father and thy brethren are come vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">The land of Egypt
is before thee: in the best of the land make thy father and
brethren to dwell, in the lande of Goshen let them dwell: and if
thou knowest any man of actiuitie amongst them, then make them
rulers ouer my cattell.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Ioseph
brought in Iacob his father, and set him before Pharaoh: and Iacob
blessed Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Pharaoh said
vnto Iacob, How old art thou?<note> Heb. how many are the dayes of the yeeres of thy life?</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Iacob said
vnto Pharaoh, The dayes of the yeeres of my pilgrimage are an
hundred &amp; thirtie yeres: few and euill haue the dayes of the
yeeres of my life bene, and haue not attained vnto the dayes of the
yeeres of the life of my fathers, in the dayes of their
pilgrimage.<note> Heb.11. 9,13.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Iacob
blessed Pharaoh, and went out from before Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
Ioseph placed his father, and his brethren, and gaue them a
possession in the land of Egypt, in the best of the land, in the
land of Rameses, as Pharaoh had commanded.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Ioseph
nourished his father and his brethren, and all his fathers houshold
with bread, according to their families.<note> Or, as a litle childe is nourished. Heb. according to the little ones.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And there
was no bread in all the land: for the famine was very sore, so that
the land of Egypt and all the land of Canaan fainted by reason of
the famine.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Ioseph
gathered vp all the money that was found in the land of Egypt, and
in the land of Canaan, for the corne which they bought: and Ioseph
brought the money into Pharaohs house.</ab>
<ab n="15">And when money
failed in the land of Egypt, and in the land of Canaan, all the
Egyptians came vnto Ioseph, and said, Giue vs bread: for why should
we die in thy presence? for the money faileth.</ab>

<fw>Lands sold.</fw>
<ab n="16">And Ioseph said,
Giue your cattell: and I will giue you for your catell, if money
faile.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they brought
their cattel vnto Ioseph: and Ioseph gaue them bread in exchange
for horses, and for the flockes, and for the cattell of the heards,
and for the asses, and he fed them with bread, for all their
cattel, for that yeere.<note> Heb. led them.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">When that yeere
was ended, they came vnto him the second yeere, and said vnto him,
We will not hide it from my lord, how that our money is spent, my
lord also had our heards of cattell: there is not ought left in the
sight of my lord, but our bodies, and our lands.</ab>
<ab n="19">Wherfore shall
we die before thine eyes, both we, and our land? buy vs and our
land for bread, and we and our land will be seruants vnto Pharaoh:
and giue vs seede that we may liue and not die, that the land be
not desolate.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Ioseph
bought all the land of Egypt for Pharaoh: for the Egyptians sold
euery man his field, because the famine preuailed ouer them: so the
land became Pharaohs.</ab>
<ab n="21">And as for the
people, he remoued them to cities from one end of the borders of
Egypt, euen to the other ende thereof.</ab>
<ab n="22">Onely the land
of the Priests bought he not: for the priests had a portion
assigned them of Pharaoh, and did eate their portion which Pharaoh
gaue them: wherefore they solde not their lands.<note> Or, Princes</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then Ioseph said
vnto the people, Behold, I haue bought you this day, and your land
for Pharaoh: Loe, here is seed for you, and ye shall sow the
land.</ab>
<ab n="24">And it shall
come to passe in the increase, that you shall giue the fift part
vnto Pharaoh, and foure parts shall be your owne, for seed of the
field, and for your food, and for them of your households, and for
food for your litle ones.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they said,
Thou hast saued our liues: let vs find grace in the sight of my
lord, and we will be Pharaohs seruants.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Ioseph made
it a law ouer the land of Egypt vnto this day, that Pharaoh should
haue the fift part: except the land of the priests onely, which
became not Pharaohs.<note> Or, Princes</note></ab>

<fw>Iacob blesseth Iosephs sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ And
Israel dwelt in the land of Egypt in the countrey of Goshen, and
they had possessions therein, and grew, and multiplied
exceedingly.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Iacob liued
in the land of Egypt seuenteene yeres: so the whole age of Iacob
was an hundred fourtie and seuen yeeres.<note> Hebr. the dayes of the yeeres of his life.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And the time
drew nigh that Israel must die, and he called his sonne Ioseph, and
said vnto him, If now I haue found grace in thy sight, put, I pray
thee, thy hand vnder my thigh, and deale kindly and truely with
mee, bury me not, I pray thee, in Egypt.<note> Chap. 24.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But I will lie
with my fathers, and thou shalt carie mee out of Egypt, and bury me
in their burying place: and he said, I will doe as thou hast
said.</ab>
<ab n="31">And he said,
Sweare vnto mee: and he sware vnto him. And Israel bowed himselfe
vpon the beds head.<note> Heb.11. 21.</note></ab>



</div>