<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The calamity of the Iewes, both
dead and aliue. 4 Hee vpbraideth their foolish, and shamelesse
impenitencie. 13 Hee sheweth their grieuous iudgment, 18 and
bewaileth their desperate estate.</head>

<ab n="1">At that time,
sayeth the Lord, they shall bring out the bones of the kings of
Iudah, and the bones of his princes, and the bones of the Priests,
and the bones of the Prophets, and the bones of the inhabitants of
Ierusalem out of their graues.</ab>

<fw>Couetousnes in all.</fw>
<ab n="2">And they shall
spread them before the Sunne, and the Moone, and all the hoste of
heauen whom they haue loued, and whom they haue serued, and after
whom they haue walked, and whom they haue sought, and whom they
haue worshipped: they shall not be gathered, nor be buried, they
shall be for doung, vpon the face of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="3">And death shall
bee chosen rather then life, by all the residue of them that
remaine of this euill family, which remaine in all the places
whither I haue driuen them, saith the Lord of hosts.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Moreouer
thou shalt say vnto them, Thus saith the Lord, Shall they fall, and
not arise? shall hee turne away, and not returne?</ab>
<ab n="5">Why then is this
people of Ierusalem slidden backe, by a perpetual backesliding?
they hold fast deceit, they refuse to returne.</ab>
<ab n="6">I hearkened and
heard, but they spake not aright: no man repented him of his
wickednesse, saying, What haue I done? euery one turned to his
course, as the horse rusheth into the battell.</ab>
<ab n="7">Yea the Storke in
the heauen knoweth her appointed times, and the turtle, and the
crane, and the swallow obserue the time of their coming; but my
people know not the iudgement of the Lord.<note> Isai. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">How doe ye say,
We are wise, and the Law of the Lord is with vs? Loe, certainly, in
vaine made he it, the pen of the scribes is in vaine.<note> Or, the false penne of the scribes worketh for falshood.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The wise men are
ashamed, they are dismayed and taken; loe, they haue reiected the
word of the Lord, and what wisedome is in them?<note> Cha. 6.15. , Or, haue they beene ashamed, &amp;c. , Heb. the wisedome of what thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Therfore will I
giue their wiues vnto others, &amp; their fields to them that shall
inherite them: for euery one from the least euen vnto the greatest
is giuen to couetousnes, from the Prophet euen vnto the priest,
euery one dealeth falsly.<note> Isai.56.11 chap. 6.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For they haue
healed the hurt of the daughter of my people slightly, saying,
Peace, peace, when there is no peace.<note> Cha. 6.14. , Eze. 13. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Were they
ashamed when they had committed abomination? nay, they were not at
all ashamed, neither could they blush: therefore shall they fall
among them that fal, in the time of their visitation they shall be
cast downe, saith the Lord.<note> Chap. 3.3. and 6.15.</note></ab>

<fw>The Prophets sorow for the
people.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ I will
surely consume them, saith the Lord; there shalbe no grapes on the
vine, nor figges on the figtree, and the leafe shall fade, and the
things that I haue giuen them, shall passe away from
them.<note> Or, in gathering I will consume. , Isai. 5.1. &amp;c. , Matth.21. 19. luke 13.6. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Why doe wee sit
still? assemble your selues, and let vs enter into the defenced
cities, and let vs be silent there: for the Lord our God hath put
vs to silence, and giuen vs waters of gall to drink, because we
haue sinned against the Lord.<note> Cha.9.15. dan. 23.15. , Or, poyson.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">We looked for
peace, but no good came: and for a time of health, and behold
trouble.<note> Chap. 14. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The snorting of
his horses was heard from Dan: the whole land trembled at the sound
of the neighing of his strong ones, for they are come and haue
deuoured the land, and all that is in it, the citie, and those that
dwell therein.<note> Cha.4.15. , Hebr. the fulnesse therof.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For behold, I
wil send serpents, cockatrices among you, which will not be
charmed, and they shall bite you; saith the Lord.<note> Psal. 58. 5,6.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ When I
would comfort my selfe against sorrow, my heart is faint in
me.<note> Heb. vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Behold the voice
of the crie of the daughter of my people because of them that dwel
in a farre countrey: Is not the Lord in Zion? is not her king in
her? why haue they prouoked me to anger with their grauen images,
and with strange vanities?<note> Heb. because of the countrey of them that are farre off.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The haruest is
past, the summer is ended, and we are not saued.</ab>
<ab n="21">For the hurt of
the daughter of my people am I hurt, I am blacke: astonishment hath
taken hold on me.</ab>
<ab n="22">Is there no
balme in Gilead? is there no physician there? why then is not the
health of the daughter of my people recouered?<note> Chap. 46. 11. , Heb. gone vp.</note></ab>



</div>