<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_43" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-42-43.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIII.</head>
<head>1 Iohanan, discrediting Ieremiahs
prophecie, carieth Ieremiah and others into Egypt. 8 Ieremiah
prophecieth by a type the conquest of Egypt, by the
Babylonians.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe that whē Ieremiah had made an end of speaking vnto all
the people, al the words of the Lord their God, for which the Lord
their God had sent him to them, euen all these words;</ab>

<fw>Threatnings for their
disobedience.</fw>
<ab n="2">Then spake
Azariah the sonne of Hoshaiah, and Iohanan the sonne of Kareah, and
all the proud men, saying vnto Ieremiah, Thou speakest falsly: the
Lord our God hath not sent thee to say, Goe not into Egypt, to
soiourne there.</ab>
<ab n="3">But Baruch the
sonne of Neriah setteth thee on against vs, for to deliuer vs into
the hand of the Caldeans, that they might put vs to death, and
carie vs away captiues into Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="4">So Iohanan the
sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces, and all the
people, obeied not the voice of the Lord, to dwell in the land of
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="5">But Iohanan the
sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces, tooke all the
remnant of Iudah, that were returned from all nations whither they
had bene driuen, to dwell in the land of Iudah,</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen men, and
women, and children, and the kings daughters, and euery person that
Nebuzaradan the captaine of the guard had left with Gedaliah the
sonne of Ahikam, the sonne of Shaphan, and Ieremiah the Prophet,
and Baruch the sonne of Neriah.</ab>
<ab n="7">So they came
into the land of Egypt: for they obeyed not the voyce of the Lord,
thus came they euen to Tahpanhes.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then came
the word of the Lord vnto Ieremiah in Tahpanhes, saying;</ab>
<ab n="9">Take great
stones in thine hand, and hide them in the clay in the bricke kill,
which is at the entry of Pharaohs house in Tahpanhes, in the sight
of the men of Iudah:</ab>
<ab n="10">And say vnto
them, Thus saieth the Lord of hosts the God of Israel; Beholde, I
will send and take Nebuchadrezzar the king of Babylon my seruant,
and will set his throne vpon these stones that I haue hidde, and
hee shall spread his royall pauilion ouer them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when he
commeth, hee shall smite the land of Egypt, and deliuer such as are
for death, to death; and such as are for captiuitie to captiuitie;
and such as are for the sword, to the sword.<note> Chap.15.2 zach.11.2.</note></ab>

<fw>Threatnings for their
disobedience.</fw>
<ab n="12">And I wil
kindle a fire in the houses of the gods of Egypt, and hee shall
burne them, and carry them away captiues, and hee shall aray
himselfe with the land of Egypt, as a shepheard putteth on his
garment, and hee shall goe forth from thence in peace.</ab>
<ab n="13">He shall breake
also the images of Beth-shemesh that is in the land of Egypt, and
the houses of the gods of the Egyptians shall he burne with
fire.<note> Heb. statues, or standing images. , Or, The house of the Sunne.</note></ab>



</div>