<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_38" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-37-38.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-38-38.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-38-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah by a false suggestion is
put into the dungeon of Malchiah. 7 Ebed-melech, by suite, getteth
him some inlargement. 14 Vpon secret conference, he counsaileth the
king by yeelding to saue his life. 24 By the kings instructions, he
concealeth the conference from the Princes.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Shephatiah
the sonne of Mattan, and Gedaliah the sonne of Pashur and Iucal the
sonne of Shelemiah, &amp; Pashur the sonne of Malchiah heard the
words that Ieremiah had spoken vnto all the people, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord, He that remaineth in this citie, shall die by the sword, by
the famine, and by the pestilence, but he that goeth forth to the
Caldeans, shall liue: for he shall haue his life for a pray, and
shall liue.<note> Cha.21.9</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thus saith the
Lord, This citie shall surely be giuen into the hand of the king of
Babylons armie, which shall take it.</ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore the
princes sayd vnto the king, We beseech thee let this man be put to
death: for thus he weakeneth the hands of the men of warre that
remaine in this citie, and the hands of all the people, in speaking
such words vnto them: for this man seeketh not the welfare of this
people, but the hurt.<note> Heb. peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then Zedekiah
the king sayd, Behold, he is in your hand; for the king is not he
that can do any thing against you.</ab>

<fw>The king talketh with Ieremiah.</fw>
<ab n="6">Then tooke they
Ieremiah, and cast him into the dungeon of Malchiah the sonne of
Hammelech that was in the court of the prison: and they let downe
Ieremiah with cords: and in the dungeon there was no water, but
mire: so Ieremiah sunke in the mire.<note> Or, of the king.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Now when
Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, one of þe eunuches which
was in the kings house, heard that they had put Ieremiah in the
dungeon (the king then sitting in the gate of Beniamin)</ab>
<ab n="8">Ebed-melech went
foorth out of the kings house, and spake to the king,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="9">My lord the
king, these men haue done euill in all that they haue done to
Ieremiah the Prophet, whom they haue cast into the dungeon, and he
is like to die for hunger in the place where he is, for there is no
more bread in the city.<note> Hebr. he will die.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then the king
commanded Ebed-melech the Ethiopian, saying, Take from hence
thirtie men with thee, and take vp Ieremiah the Prophet out of the
dungeon before he die.<note> Hebr. in thine hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">So Ebed-melech
tooke the men with him, and went into the house of the king vnder
the treasurie, and tooke thence old cast cloutes, and old rotten
ragges, and let them downe by cordes into the dungeon to
Ieremiah.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Ebed-melech
the Ethiopian said vnto Ieremiah, Put now these old cast cloutes
and rotten ragges vnder thine arme-holes, vnder the cordes. And
Ieremiah did so.</ab>
<ab n="13">So they drew vp
Ieremiah with cordes, and tooke him vp out of the dungeon, and
Ieremiah remained in the court of the prison.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then
Zedekiah the king sent, and tooke Ieremiah the Prophet vnto him
into the third entrie that is in the house of the Lord, and the
king said vnto Ieremiah, I will aske thee a thing: hide nothing
from me.<note> Or principall.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then Ieremiah
said vnto Zedekiah, If I declare it vnto thee, wilt thou not surely
put me to death? and if I giue thee counsell, wilt thou not hearken
vnto me?</ab>
<ab n="16">So the king
sware secretly vnto Ieremiah, saying, As the Lord liueth that made
vs this soule, I wil not put thee to death, neither will I giue
thee into the hand of these men that seeke thy life.</ab>

<fw>The king talketh with Ieremiah.</fw>
<ab n="17">Then said
Ieremiah vnto Zedekiah, Thus saith the Lord the God of hostes, the
God of Israel, If thou wilt assuredly goe foorth vnto the king of
Babylons Princes, then thy soule shall liue, and this Citie shall
not be burnt with fire, and thou shalt liue, and thine
house.</ab>
<ab n="18">But if thou
wilt not goe foorth to the king of Babylons Princes, then shall
this City be giuen into the hand of the Caldeans, and they shall
burne it with fire, and thou shalt not escape out of their
hand.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Zedekiah
the king said vnto Ieremiah, I am afraid of the Iewes that are
fallen to the Caldeans, lest they deliuer mee into their hand, and
they mocke me.</ab>
<ab n="20">But Ieremiah
said, They shall not deliuer thee: obey, I beseech thee, the voyce
of the Lord, which I speake vnto thee: so it shall be well vnto
thee, and thy soule shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="21">But if thou
refuse to goe foorth, this is the word that the Lord hath shewed
me.</ab>
<ab n="22">And behold, all
the women that are left in the king of Iudahs house, shalbe brought
forth to the king of Babylons Princes, and those women shall say,
Thy friends haue set thee on, and haue preuailed against thee: thy
feet are sunke in the mire, and they are turned away
backe.<note> Hebr. men of thy peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">So they shall
bring out all thy wiues, and thy children to the Caldeans, and thou
shalt not escape out of their hand, but shalt be taken by the hand
of the King of Babylon: and thou shalt cause this citie to be burnt
with fire.<note> Hebr. thou shalt burne, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Then
said Zedekiah vnto Ieremiah, Let no man know of these words, and
thou shalt not die.</ab>
<ab n="25">But if the
Princes heare that I haue talked with thee, and they come vnto
thee, and say vnto thee, Declare vnto vs now what thou hast said
vnto the king; hide it not from vs, and wee wil not put thee to
death; also what the king said vnto thee:</ab>
<ab n="26">Then thou shalt
say vnto them, I presented my supplication before the king, that he
would not cause me to returne to Ionathans house to die
there.</ab>

<fw>Zedekiah taken.</fw>
<ab n="27">Then came all
the Princes vnto Ieremiah, and asked him, and he told them
according to all these words, that the king had commanded: so they
left off speaking with him, for the matter was not
perceiued.<note> Hebr. they were silent from him.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">So Ieremiah
abode in the court of the prison, vntill the day that Ierusalem was
taken, and hee was there when Ierusalem was taken.</ab>



</div>