<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_38" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-37-38.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Iudah begetteth Er, Onan, and
Shelah. 6 Er marrieth Tamar. 8 The trespasse of Onan. 11 Tamar
stayeth for Shelah. 13 She deceiueth Iudah. 27 She beareth twinnes,
Pharez and Zarah.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe at that time, that Iudah went downe from his brethren, and
turned in to a certaine Adullamite, whose name was Hirah:</ab>
<ab n="2">And Iudah saw
there a daughter of a certaine Canaanite, whose name was Shuah: and
he tooke her, and went in vnto her.<note> 1.Chron. 2.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And she conceiued
&amp; bare a sonne, and he called his name Er.</ab>
<ab n="4">And shee
conceiued againe, and bare a sonne, and shee called his name,
Onan.<note> Num. 26. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And she yet
againe conceiued and bare a sonne, and called his name Shelah: and
hee was at Chezib, when shee bare him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Iudah tooke a
wife for Er his first borne, whose name was Tamar.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Er, Iudahs
first borne was wicked in the sight of the LORD, and the LORD slew
him.<note> Num. 26. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Iudah said
vnto Onan, Goe in vnto thy brothers wife, and marrie her, and raise
vp seed to thy brother.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Onan knew
that the seed should not be his; and it came to passe when hee went
in vnto his brothers wife, that hee spilled it on the ground, least
that hee should giue seed to his brother.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the thing
which he did, displeased the LORD: wherefore hee slew him
also.<note> Hebr. was euill in the eyes of the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then said Iudah
to Tamar his daughter in law, Remaine a widow at thy fathers house,
til Shelah my sonne be growen: (for he said, Lest peraduenture he
die also as his brethren did) and Tamar went and dwelt in her
fathers house.</ab>

<fw>His incest.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And in
processe of time, the daughter of Shuah Iudahs wife died: and Iudah
was comforted, and went vp vnto his sheepe-shearers to Timnath, he
and his friend Hirah the Adullamite.<note> Hebr. The dayes were multiplied.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And it was told
Lamar, saying, Behold, thy father in law goeth vp to Timnath to
sheare his sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="14">And shee put her
widowes garments off from her, and couered her with a vaile, and
wrapped her selfe, and sate in an open place, which is by the way
to Timnath: for shee sawe that Shelah was growen, and she was not
giuen vnto him to wife.<note> Heb. the doore of eyes, or, of Enaijm.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">When Iudah saw
her, he thought her to be an harlot: because she had couered her
face.</ab>
<ab n="16">And hee turned
vnto her by the way, and said, Goe to, I pray thee, let me come in
vnto thee: (for he knew not that she was his daughter in law) and
she said, what wilt thou giue mee, that thou mayest come in vnto
me?</ab>
<ab n="17">And hee said, I
will send thee a kid from the flocke: and shee saide, Wilt thou
giue mee a pledge, till thou send it?<note> Heb. a kid of the goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And he said,
What pledge shall I giue thee? And she said, Thy signet, and thy
bracelets, and thy staffe, that is in thine hand: and he gaue it
her, &amp; came in vnto her, and she conceived by him.</ab>
<ab n="19">And shee arose
and went away, and laid by her vaile from her, and put on the
garments of her widowhood.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Iudah sent
the kidde by the hand of his friend the Adullamite, to receive his
pledge from the womans hand: but he found her not.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then hee asked
the men of that place, saying, where is the harlot, that was openly
by the way side? And they said, There was no harlot in this
place.<note> Or, in Enaijm.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And he returned
to Iudah, and said, I cannot finde her: and also the men of the
place said, That there was no harlot in this place.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Iudah said,
Let her take it to her, lest we bee shamed: behold, I sent this
kidde, and thou hast not found her.<note> Heb. become a contempt.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And it
came to passe about three moneths after, that it was tolde Iudah,
saying, Tamar thy daughter in law hath played the harlot, and also
behold, she is with child by whoredom: and Iudah said, Bring her
foorth, and let her be burnt.</ab>

<fw>Ioseph in Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="25">When she was
brought forth, she sent to her father in law, saying, By the man
whose these are, am I with child: and shee said, Discerne, I pray
thee, whose are these, the signet, and bracelets, and
staffe.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Iudah
acknowledged them, and said, She hath bin more righteous then I:
because that I gaue her not to Shelah my sonne: and he knew her
againe no more.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And it
came to passe in the time of her trauaile, that beholde, twinnes
were in her wombe.</ab>
<ab n="28">And it came to
passe when shee trauailed, that the one put out his hand, and the
midwife tooke and bound vpon his hand a skarlet threed, saying,
This came out first.</ab>
<ab n="29">And it came to
passe as he drewe backe his hand, that behold, his brother came
out: and she said, how hast thou broken foorth? this breach bee
vpon thee: Therefore his name was called Pharez.<note> Or, wherefore hast thou made this breach against thee? , That is, a breach. , 1 Chron. 2.4. matt. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And afterward
came out his brother that had the skarlet threed vpon his hand, and
his name was called Zarah.</ab>



</div>