<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Abraham soiourneth at Gerar, 2
denieth his wife, and loseth her. 3 Abimelech is reproued for her
in a dreame. 9 He rebuketh Abraham, 14 restoreth Sarah, 16 and
reprooueth her. 17 Hee is healed by Abrahams prayer.</head>

<ab n="1">And Abraham
iourneyed from thence, toward the South-Countrey, and dwelled
betweene Cadesh and Shur, and soiourned in Gerar.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Abraham said
of Sarah his wife, She is my sister: And Abimelech King of Gerar
sent, and tooke Sarah.</ab>
<ab n="3">But God came to
Abimelech in a dreame by night, and said to him, Behold, thou art
but a dead man, for the woman which thou hast taken: for shee is a
mans wife.<note> Heb. married to an husband.</note></ab>

<fw>Abraham in Gerar.</fw>
<ab n="4">But Abimelech had
not come neere her: and he said, LORD, wilt thou slay also a
righteous nation?</ab>
<ab n="5">Said he not vnto
me, She is my sister? and she, euen she herselfe said, Hee is my
brother: in the integritie of my heart, and innocencie of my hands
haue I done this.<note> Or, simplicitie or sinceritie.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And God saide
vnto him in a dreame, Yea, I know that thou didst this in the
integritie of thy heart: for I also withheld thee from sinning
against mee, therefore suffered I thee not to touch her.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
restore the man his wife: for he is a Prophet, and he shal pray for
thee, and thou shalt liue: and if thou restore her not, know thou
that thou shalt surely die, thou, and all that are thine.</ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore
Abimelech rose earely in the morning, and called all his seruants,
and told all these things in their eares: and the men were sore
afraid.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then Abimelech
called Abraham, and said vnto him, What hast thou done vnto vs? and
what haue I offended thee, that thou hast brought on me, and on my
kingdome a great sinne? thou hast done deeds vnto mee that ought
not to be done.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Abimelech
said vnto Abraham, What sawest thou, that thou hast done this
thing?</ab>
<ab n="11">And Abraham
said, Because I thought, Surely the feare of God is not in this
place: and they will slay mee for my wiues sake.</ab>
<ab n="12">And yet indeed
shee is my sister: she is the daughter of my father, but not the
daughter of my mother; and shee became my wife.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it came to
passe when God caused me to wander from my fathers house, that I
said vnto her, This is thy kindnesse which thou shalt shew vnto me;
at euery place whither wee shall come, say of me, He is my
brother.<note> Chap.12. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Abimelech
tooke sheepe and oxen, and men-seruants, and women seruants, and
gaue them vnto Abraham, and restored him Sarah his wife.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Abimelech
said, Behold, my land is before thee; dwel where it pleaseth
thee.<note> Heb. as is good in thine eyes.</note></ab>

<fw>Isaac is borne.</fw>
<ab n="16">And vnto Sarah
hee said, Behold, I haue giuen thy brother a thousand pieces of
siluer: behold, he is to thee a couering of the eyes, vnto all that
are with thee, and with all other: thus shee was reproued.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ So
Abraham prayed vnto God: and God healed Abimelech, and his wife,
and his maid-seruants, and they bare children.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the LORD had
fast closed vp all the wombes of the house of Abimelech, because of
Sarah Abrahams wife.</ab>



</div>