<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the type of bonds and yokes,
hee prophecieth the subduing of the neighbour kings vnto
Nebuchad-nezzar. 8 Hee exhorteth them to yeeld, and not to beleeue
the false prophets. 12 The like hee doeth to Zedekiah. 19 He
foretelleth the remnant of the vessels shall be caried to Babylon,
and there continue vntill the day of visitation.</head>

<ab n="1">In the beginning
of the reigne of Iehoiakim the sonne of Iosiah King of Iudah, came
this worde vnto Ieremiah from the Lord, saying,</ab>

<fw>Babels yoke.</fw>
<ab n="2">Thus sayth the
Lord to me, Make thee bonds and yokes, and put them vpon thy
necke.</ab>
<ab n="3">And send them to
the king of Edom, and to the king of Moab, and to the king of the
Ammonites, and to the king of Tyrus, and to the king of Zidon, by
the hand of the messengers which come to Ierusalem vnto Zedekiah
king of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="4">And command them
to say vnto their masters, Thus saith the Lord of hosts the God of
Israel, Thus shall ye say vnto your masters:<note> Or, concerning their masters, saying.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">I haue made the
earth, the man and the beast that are vpon the ground, by my great
power, and by my outstretched arme, and haue giuen it vnto whom it
seemed meet vnto me.<note> Dan.4. 14,22.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And now haue I
giuen all these landes into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of
Babylon my seruant, and the beasts of the field haue I giuen him
also to serue him.<note> Cha.25.9. and 43.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And all nations
shall serue him and his sonne, and his sonnes sonne, vntill the
very time of his land come: and then many nations and great kings
shall serue themselues of him.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it shall
come to passe, that the nation and kingdome which will not serue
the same Nebuchad-nezzar the king of Babylon, and that will not put
their necke vnder the yoke of the king of Babylon, that nation will
I punish, sayth the Lord, with the sword, and with the famine, and
with the pestilence, vntill I haue consumed them by his
hand.</ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore
hearken not ye to your prophets, nor to your diuiners, nor to your
dreamers, nor to your inchanters, nor to your sorcerers, which
speak vnto you, saying; Ye shall not serue the king of
Babylon:<note> Hebr. dreames.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For they
prophecie a lie vnto you, to remooue you farre from your land, and
that I should driue you out, and ye should perish.</ab>
<ab n="11">But the nations
that bring their necke vnder the yoke of the king of Babylon, and
serue him, those will I let remaine still in their owne land, sayth
the Lord, and they shall till it, and dwell therein.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ I spake
also to Zedekiah king of Iudah according to all these wordes,
saying, Bring your neckes vnder the yoke of the king of Babylon,
and serue him and his people, and liue.</ab>

<fw>Lying prophets.</fw>
<ab n="13">Why will yee
die, thou and thy people, by the sword, by the famine, and by the
pestilence, as the Lord hath spoken against the nation that will
not serue the king of Babylon?</ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore
hearken not vnto the words of the prophets, that speake vnto you,
saying; Yee shall not serue the king of Babylon: for they prophecie
a lie vnto you.<note> Chap. 14. 14. and 23. 21. and 29. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For I haue not
sent them, saith the Lord, yet they prophecie a lye in my name,
that I might driue you out, &amp; that yee might perish, ye, and
the prophets that prophecie vnto you.<note> Heb. in a lie, or lyingly.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Also I spake to
the priests, and to all this people, saying; Thus saith the Lord,
Hearken not to the words of your prophets, that prophecie vnto you,
saying; Behold, the vessels of the Lords house shall now shortly be
brought againe from Babylon; for they prophecie a lie vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hearken not
vnto them: serue the king of Babylon, and liue: wherefore should
this citie be laid waste?</ab>
<ab n="18">But if they be
prophets, and if the word of the Lord be with them, let them nowe
make intercession to the Lord of hostes, that the vessels which are
left in the house of the Lord, and in the house of the king of
Iudah, and at Ierusalem, goe not to Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ For thus
saith the Lord of hostes concerning the pillars, and concerning the
sea, and concerning the bases, and concerning the residue of the
vessels that remaine in this citie,</ab>
<ab n="20">Which
Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon tooke not, when he caried away
captiue Ieconiah the sonne of Iehoiakim king of Iudah, from
Ierusalem to Babylon, and all the nobles of Iudah and
Ierusalem:<note> 2.Kings 24.14, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Yea thus saith
the Lord of hostes the God of Israel, concerning the vessels that
remaine in the house of the Lord, and in the house of the king of
Iudah and of Ierusalem;</ab>
<ab n="22">They shall be
caried to Babylon, and there shall they be vntill the day that I
visit them, saith the Lord: then will I bring them vp, and restore
them to this place.<note> 2.Kings 25.13. 2.chron.36. 18. , 2.Chron.36.22. cha. 29.10.</note></ab>



</div>