<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 God hauing shewed his former
kindnesse, expostulateth with the Iewes, their causelesse reuolt, 9
beyond any example. 14 They are the causes of their owne
calamities. 20 The sinnes of Iudah. 31 Her confidence is
reiected.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer, the
word of the Lord came to me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Goe, and crie in
the eares of Ierusalem, saying; Thus sayth the Lord, I remember
thee, the kindnesse of thy youth, the loue of thine espousals, when
thou wentest after me in the wildernesse, in a land that was not
sowen.<note> Or, for thy sake. , Eze.16.8. cha. 12. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Israel was
holinesse vnto the Lord, and the first fruites of his increase: all
that deuoure him, shall offend, euill shall come vpon them, sayth
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">Heare ye the word
of the Lord, O house of Iacob, and all the families of the house of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Thus sayth
the Lord, What iniquitie haue your fathers found in me, that they
are gone farre from mee, and haue walked after vanitie, and are
become vaine?</ab>
<ab n="6">Neither sayd
they, Where is the Lord that brought vs vp out of the land of
Egypt? that led vs through the wildernesse, through a land of
deserts and of pittes, through a land of drought, and of the shadow
of death, through a land that no man passed thorow, and where no
man dwelt.<note> Isai.63.9, 11,13. ose. 13.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And I brought you
into a plentifull countrey, to eate the fruit thereof, and the
goodnesse thereof; but when ye entred yee defiled my land, and made
mine heritage an abomination.<note> Psal.78. 58. and 106.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The Priests said
not, Where is the Lord ? and they that handle the Law knew me not:
the pastours also transgressed against mee, and the Prophets
prophecied by Baal, and walked after things that doe not
profit.<note> Rom.2.20</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Wherefore,
I will yet pleade with you, sayth the Lord, and with your childrens
children will I pleade.</ab>

<fw>The backsliding of Gods people.</fw>
<ab n="10">For passe ouer
the yles of Chittim, and see; and send vnto Kedar and consider
diligently, and see if there be such a thing.<note> Or, ouer to.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Hath a nation
changed their Gods, which are yet no Gods? but my people haue
changed their glory, for that which doth not profit.<note> Cha. 16.20</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Be astonished, O
yee heauens, at this, and be horribly afraid, be yee very desolate,
saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">For my people
haue committed two euils: they haue forsaken me, the fountaine of
liuing waters, and hewed them out cisternes, broken cisternes that
can hold no water.<note> Chap. 17. 13. &amp; 18.14 psal.36.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Is Israel
a seruant? is he a home-borne slaue? why is he spoiled?<note> Heb. become a spoile.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The young lyons
roared vpon him and yelled, and they made his land waste: his
cities are burnt without inhabitant.<note> Heb. gaue out their voyce.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Also the
children of Noph and Tahapanes haue broken the crowne of thy
head.<note> Or, feede on thy crown, deut. 33.12 Isai. 8.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Hast thou not
procured this vnto thy selfe, in that thou hast forsaken the Lord
thy God, when he led thee by the way?</ab>
<ab n="18">And now what
hast thou to doe in the way of Egypt, to drinke the waters of
Sihor? Or what hast thou to doe in the way of Assyria, to drinke
the waters of the riuer?</ab>
<ab n="19">Thine owne
wickednesse shall correct thee, and thy backslidings shall reproue
thee: know therefore and see, that it is an euill thing and bitter
that thou hast forsaken the Lord thy God, and that my feare is not
in thee, saith the Lord GOD of Hostes.<note> Isai.3.9. os.5.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ For of
old time I haue broken thy yoke, and burst thy bands, and thou
saidst; I will not transgresse: when vpon euery high hill, and
vnder euery greene tree thou wandrest, playing the
harlot.<note> Or, serue. , Isai. 57.5,7. , Ier.3.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Yet I had
planted thee a noble vine, wholy a right seede: How then art thou
turned into the degenerate plant of a strange vine vnto
me?<note> Matth.21.23. mar.12.1. luc.20.9. , Exod.15.17. psal.44.3. and 80.9. Isai.5.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For though thou
wash thee with nitre, and take thee much sope, yet thine iniquitie
is marked before me, saith the Lord GOD.<note> Iob. 9.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">How canst thou
say, I am not polluted, I haue not gone after Baalim? see thy way
in the valley, know what thou hast done: thou art a swift
dromedarie trauersing her wayes.<note> Or, O swift dromedarie.</note></ab>

<fw>The backsliding of Gods people.</fw>
<ab n="24">A wild asse vsed
to the wildernesse, that snuffeth vp the wind at her pleasure, in
her occasion who can turne her away? all they that seeke her will
not wearie themselues, in her moneth they shall find
her.<note> Or, O wild asse &amp;c. , Heb. taught , Heb. the desire of her heart. , Or, reuerse it.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Withhold thy
foote from being vnshod, and thy throte from thirst: but thou
saidst, There is no hope. No, for I haue loued strangers, and after
them will I goe.<note> Or, is the case desperate?</note></ab>
<ab n="26">As the thiefe is
ashamed, when he is found: so is the house of Israel ashamed, they,
their kings, their princes, and their priests, &amp; their
prophets,</ab>
<ab n="27">Saying to a
stocke; Thou art my father, and to a stone; Thou hast brought me
forth: for they haue turned their backe vnto me, and not their
face: but in the time of their trouble, they will say; Arise and
saue vs.<note> Or, begotten me. , Heb. the hinder part part of the necke. , Isai. 26. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">But where are
thy Gods that thou hast made thee? let them arise if they can saue
thee in the time of thy trouble: for according to the number of thy
cities, are thy Gods, O Iudah.<note> Isai. 45. 20. , Heb. euill. , Chap. 11. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Wherefore will
yee plead with me? yee all haue transgressed against me, saith the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="30">In vaine haue I
smitten your children, they receiued no correction: your owne sword
hath deuoured your prophets, like a destroying lyon.<note> IsaiI.9. 13. cha. 5. 3 , Matth.23. 29. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ O
generation, see yee the word of the Lord: haue I beene a
wildernesse vnto Israel? a land of darkenesse? wherefore say my
people; We are Lords, we will come no more vnto thee?<note> Chap.2.5 , Heb. we haue dominion.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Can a maide
forget her ornaments, or a bride her attire? yet my people haue
forgotten me dayes without number.</ab>
<ab n="33">Why trimmest
thou thy way to seeke loue? therefore hast thou also taught the
wicked ones thy wayes.</ab>
<ab n="34">Also in thy
skirts is found the blood of the soules of the poore innocents: I
haue not found it by secret search, but vpon all these.<note> Heb. digging.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Yet thou sayest;
Because I am innocent, surely his anger shall turne from me:
behold, I will plead with thee, because thou sayest, I haue not
sinned.</ab>
<ab n="36">Why gaddest thou
about so much to change thy way? thou also shalt bee ashamed of
Egypt, as thou wast ashamed of Assyria.</ab>

<fw>God calleth to repentance.</fw>
<ab n="37">Yea thou shalt
goe forth from him, and thine hands vpon thine head: for the Lord
hath reiected thy confidences, and thou shalt not prosper in
them.</ab>



</div>