<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-34-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah prophecieth the
captiuitie of Zedekiah, and the Citie. 8 The Princes and the people
hauing dismissed their bondseruants, contrary to the Couenant of
God, reassume them. 12 Ieremiah for their disobedience, giueth them
and Zedekiah, into the hands of their enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">The word which
came vnto Ieremiah frō the Lord (when Nebuchad-nezzar king of
Babylon and all his armie, and all the kingdomes of the earth of
his dominion, and all the people fought against Ierusalem and
against all the cities thereof) saying,<note> 2.Kings 25.1, &amp;c. chap. 52. , Heb. the dominion of his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord, the God of Israel, Go, and speake to Zedekiah king of Iudah,
and tell him, Thus saith the Lord, Behold, I will giue this citie
into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shal burne it with
fire.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thou shalt
not escape out of his hand, but shalt surely be taken, and
deliuered into his hand, and thine eyes shall behold the eyes of
the king of Babylon, and he shall speake with thee mouth to mouth,
and thou shalt goe to Babylon.<note> Chap. 32. 4. , Heb. his mouth shall speake to thy mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Yet heare the
word of the Lord, O Zedekiah king of Iudah: Thus saith the Lord of
thee, Thou shalt not die by the sword:</ab>
<ab n="5">But thou shalt
die in peace, and with the burnings of thy fathers the former kings
which were before thee, so shall they burne odours for thee, and
they will lament thee, saying, Ah Lord; for I haue pronounced the
word, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Ieremiah
the Prophet spake all these words vnto Zedekiah king of Iudah in
Ierusalem;</ab>
<ab n="7">When the king of
Babylons armie fought against Ierusalem, and against all the cities
of Iudah that were left, against Lachish, and against Azekah: for
these defenced cities remained of the cities of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ This is
the word that came vnto Ieremiah from the Lord, after that the king
Zedekiah had made a couenant with all the people which were at
Ierusalem to proclaime liberty vnto them,<note> Exo.21.2.</note></ab>

<fw>Captiuitie is threatened.</fw>
<ab n="9">That euery man
should let his man seruant, and euery man his maide seruant, being
an Hebrewe, or an Hebrewesse, goe free, that none should serue
himselfe of them, to wit, of a Iew his brother.</ab>
<ab n="10">Now when all
the princes and all the people which had entred into the couenant,
heard that euery one should let his man seruant, and euery one his
maid seruant goe free, that none should serue themselues of them
any more, then they obeyed and let them goe.</ab>
<ab n="11">But afterwards
they turned, and caused the seruants and the handmaids whom they
had let goe free, to returne, and brought them into subiection for
seruants and for handmaids.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶
Therefore the worde of the Lord came to Ieremiah, from the Lord,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Thus saith the
Lord the God of Israel, I made a couenant with your fathers in the
day that I brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, out of the
house of bondmen, saying,</ab>
<ab n="14">At the end of
seuen yeeres, let ye go euery man his brother an Hebrew which hath
bene sold vnto thee: and when he hath serued thee sixe yeeres, thou
shalt let him goe free from thee, but your fathers hearkened not
vnto me, neither inclined their eare.<note> Exo.21.2 deut. 15. 12 , Or, hath sold himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And ye were now
turned, and had done right in my sight, in proclaiming libertie
euery man to his neighbour, and ye had made a couenant before me in
the house, which is called by my Name.<note> Heb. to day , Heb. wherupon my name is called.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But yee turned
and polluted my Name, and caused euery man his seruant, and euery
man his handmaide, whome yee had set at libertie at their pleasure,
to returne; and brought them into subiection, to bee vnto you for
seruants and for handmaids.</ab>
<ab n="17">Therfore thus
saith the Lord, Ye haue not hearkened vnto me, in proclaiming
libertie euery one to his brother, and euery man to his neighbour:
behold, I proclaime a libertie for you, saith the Lord, to the
sword, to the pestilence, and to the famine, and I wil make you to
be remoued into all the kingdomes of the earth.<note> Heb. for a remouing. , Deut. 28. 64. chap.29 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And I wil giue
the men that haue transgressed my couenant, which haue not
performed the wordes of the couenant which they had made before
mee, when they cut the calfe in twaine, and passed betweene the
parts thereof,</ab>

<fw>The obedience of the
Rechabites.</fw>
<ab n="19">The princes of
Iudah and the princes of Ierusalem, the eunuches, and the priests,
and all the people of the land which passed betweene the parts of
the calfe,</ab>
<ab n="20">I will euen
giue them into the hande of their enemies, and into the hand of
them that seeke their life, and their dead bodies shall bee for
meate vnto the foules of the heauen, and to the beasts of the
earth.<note> Chap.7. 33. and 16. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Zedekiah
king of Iudah, and his Princes will I giue into the hand of their
enemies, and into the hand of them that seeke their life and into
the hand of the king of Babylons armie, which are gone vp from
you.</ab>
<ab n="22">Behold, I will
command, saith the Lord, and cause them to returne to this citie,
and they shall fight against it, and take it, and burne it with
fire, and I will make the cities of Iudah a desolation without an
inhabitant.</ab>



</div>