<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Baruch-Chapter-4-5-Letter-of-Jeremiah.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Letter-of-Jeremiah-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Letter-of-Jeremiah-Chapter-1-1b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The cause of the captiuity is
their sinne. 3 The place whereto they were caried, is Babylon: the
vanitie of whose idols and idolatry are set foorth at large in this
Chapter.</head>

<ab n="1">A copy
of an Epistle which Ieremie sent vnto them which were to be led
captiues into Babylon, by the king of the Babylonians, to certifie
them as it was commanded him of God.</ab>
<ab n="2">Because
of þ<note/> sinnes which ye haue committed before God, ye
shall be led away captiues vnto Babylon by Nabuchodonosor king of
the Babylonians.</ab>
<ab n="3">So when
ye be come vnto Babylon, ye shal remaine there many yeeres, and for
a long season, namely seuen generations: and after that I will
bring you away peaceably from thence.</ab>
<ab n="4">Now
shal ye see in Babylon gods of siluer, and of gold, and of wood,
borne vpon shoulders, which cause the nations to feare.<note> Esai.44.8, 9,10. and 46. 5,7. psal.115.4. wis.13.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Beware
therefore that yee in no wise be like to strangers, neither be yee
afraid of them, when yee see the multitude before them, and behinde
them, worshipping them.</ab>
<ab n="6">But say
yee in your hearts, O Lord, we must worship thee.</ab>
<ab n="7">For
mine Angel is with you, and I my selfe caring for your
soules.</ab>
<ab n="8">As for
their tongue, it is polished by the workeman, and they themselues
are guilded and laid ouer with siluer, yet are they but false and
cannot speake.</ab>
<ab n="9">And
taking golde, as it were for a virgine that loues to go gay, they
make crownes for the heads of their gods.</ab>
<ab n="10">Sometimes
also the Priests conuey from their gods golde and siluer, and
bestow it vpon themselues.</ab>
<ab n="11">Yea
they will giue thereof to the common harlots, and decke them as men
with garments [being] gods of siluer, and gods of gold, and
wood.<note> Or, which prostitute themselues openly.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Yet
cannot these gods saue themselues from rust and moths, though they
be couered with purple raiment.</ab>
<ab n="13">They
wipe their faces because of the dust of the Temple, when there is
much vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he
that cannot put to death one that offendeth him, holdeth a scepter
as though hee were a iudge of the countrey.</ab>
<ab n="15">Hee
hath also in his right hand a dagger, and an axe: but cannot
deliuer himselfe from warre and theeues.</ab>
<ab n="16">Whereby
they are knowen not to bee gods, therefore feare them not.</ab>
<ab n="17">For
like as a vessell that a man vseth, is nothing worth when it is
broken: euen so it is with their gods: when they be set vp in the
Temple, their eyes be full of dust, thorow the feet of them that
come in.</ab>
<ab n="18">And as
the doores are made sure on euery side, vpon him that offendeth the
king, as being committed to suffer death: euen so the priests make
fast their temples, with doores, with lockes and barres, lest their
gods bee spoiled with robbers.<note> Or, courts.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">They
light them candles, yea, more then for themselues, whereof they
cannot see one.</ab>
<ab n="20">They
are as one of the beames of the temple, yet they say, their hearts
are gnawed vpon by things creeping out of the earth, &amp; when
they eate them and their clothes, they feele it not.<note> Gr. licked.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Their
faces are blacked, thorow the smoke that comes out of the
temple.</ab>
<ab n="22">Upon
their bodies and heads, sit battes, swallowes, and birds, and the
cats also.</ab>
<ab n="23">By
this you may know that they are no gods: therefore feare them
not.</ab>
<ab n="24">Notwithstanding
the gold that is about them, to make them beautifull, except they
wipe off the rust they will not shine: for neither when they were
molten did they feele it.</ab>
<ab n="25">The
things wherein there is no breath, are bought for a most hie
price.<note> Or, any price.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">They
are borne vpon shoulders, hauing no feete, whereby they declare
vnto men that they be nothing worth.<note> Esa.46.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">They
also that serue them, are ashamed: for if they fall to the ground
at any time, they cannot rise vp againe of themselues: neither if
one set them upright can they moue of themselues: neither if they
be bowed downe, can they make themselues streight: but they set
gifts before them as vnto dead men.<note> Or, offrings</note></ab>
<ab n="28">As for
the things that are sacrificed vnto them, their priests sell and
abuse: in like maner their wiues lay vp part thereof in salt: but
vnto the poore and impotent, they giue nothing of it.<note> Or, spend.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Menstruous
women, and women in childbed eate their sacrifices: by these things
ye may know that they are no gods: feare them not.<note> Leu.12.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">For
how can they be called gods? because women set meate before the
gods of siluer, gold, and wood.</ab>
<ab n="31">And
the priests sit in their temples, hauing their clothes rent, and
their heads and beards shauen, and nothing vpon their
heads.</ab>
<ab n="32">They
roare and crie before their gods: as men doe at the feast when one
is dead.</ab>
<ab n="33">The
priestes also take off their garments, and clothe their wiues and
children.</ab>
<ab n="34">Whether
it be euill that one doth vnto them, or good: they are not able to
recompense it: they can neither set vp a king, nor put him
downe.</ab>
<ab n="35">In
like maner, they can neither giue riches nor money: though a man
make a vowe vnto them, and keepe it not, they will not require
it.</ab>
<ab n="36">They
can saue no man from death, neither deliuer the weake from the
mightie.</ab>
<ab n="37">They
cannot restore a blind man to his sight, nor helpe any man in his
distresse.</ab>
<ab n="38">They
can shew no mercie to the widow: nor doe good to the
fatherlesse.</ab>
<ab n="39">Their
gods of wood, and which are ouerlaid with gold, and siluer, are
like the stones that be hewen out of the mountaine: they that
worship them shall be confounded.</ab>
<ab n="40">How
should a man then thinke and say that they are gods? when euen the
Chaldeans thēselues dishonor them.</ab>
<ab n="41">Who if
they shall see one dumbe that cannot speake, they bring him and
intreate Bel that he may speake, as though he were able to
vnderstand.<note> Or, bid him call vpon Bel.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">Yet
they cannot vnderstand this themselues, and leaue them: for they
haue no knowledge.<note> Or, sence.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">The
women also with cordes aboue them, sitting in the wayes, burne
branne for perfume: but if any of them drawen by some that passeth
by, lie with him, she reproacheth her fellow that she was not
thought as worthy as her selfe, nor her cord broken.</ab>
<ab n="44">Whatsoeuer
is done among them is false: how may it then be thought or said
that they are gods?</ab>
<ab n="45">They
are made of carpenters, and goldsmiths, they can be nothing else,
then the workman will haue them to be.</ab>
<ab n="46">And
they themselues that made them, can neuer continue long, how should
then the things that are made of them, be gods?</ab>
<ab n="47">For
they left lies and reproaches to them that come after.</ab>
<ab n="48">For
when there commeth any warre or plague vpon them, the priests
consult with themselues, where they may be hidden with
them.</ab>
<ab n="49">How
then cannot men perceiue, that they be no gods, which can neither
saue themselues from warre nor from plague?</ab>
<ab n="50">For
seeing they be but of wood, and ouerlaide with siluer and gold: it
shall be knowen heereafter that they are false.<note> Psal 115. 4. wisdom. 13.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And it
shall manifestly appeare to all nations and kings, that they are no
gods: but the workes of mens hands, and that there is no worke of
God in them.</ab>
<ab n="52">Who
then may not know that they are no gods?</ab>
<ab n="53">For
neither can they set vp a king in the land, nor giue raine vnto
men.</ab>
<ab n="54">Neither
can they iudge their owne cause, nor redresse a wrong being vnable:
for they are as crowes between heauen and earth.</ab>
<ab n="55">Whereupon
when fire falleth vpon the house of gods of wood, or layd ouer with
gold or siluer, their priests will fly away, &amp; escape: but they
themselues shall be burnt asunder like beames.</ab>
<ab n="56">Moreouer
they cannot withstand any king or enemies: how can it then be
thought or said that they be gods?</ab>
<ab n="57">Neither
are those gods of wood, and layd ouer with siluer or gold able to
escape either from theeues or robbers.</ab>
<ab n="58">Whose
gold, and siluer, and garments wherwith they are clothed, they that
are strong doe take, and goe away withall: neither are they able to
helpe themselues.</ab>
<ab n="59">Therefore
it is better to be a king that sheweth his power, or else a
profitable vessell in an house, which the owner shall haue vse of,
then such false gods: or to be a doore in an house to keepe such
things safe as be therein, then such false gods: or a pillar of
wood in a palace, then such false gods.</ab>
<ab n="60">For
Sunne, Moone, and starres, being bright and sent to doe their
offices, are obedient.</ab>
<ab n="61">In
like maner the lightning when it breaketh forth is easie to bee
seene, and after the same maner the wind bloweth in euery
country.<note> Or, the same wind.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">And
when God commandeth the clouds to goe ouer the whole world: they
doe as they are bidden:</ab>
<ab n="63">And
the fire sent from aboue to consume hilles and woods, doth as it is
commanded: but these are like vnto them neither in shew, nor
power.</ab>
<ab n="64">Wherefore
it is neither to be supposed nor said, that they are gods, seeing
they are able, neither to iudge causes, nor to doe good vnto
men.</ab>
<ab n="65">Knowing
therefore that they are no gods, feare them not.</ab>
<ab n="66">For
they can neither curse nor blesse kings.</ab>
<ab n="67">Neither
can they signes in the heauens among the heathen: nor shine as the
Sunne, nor giue light as the Moone.</ab>
<ab n="68">The
beasts are better then they: for they can get vnder a couert, and
helpe themselues.</ab>
<ab n="69">It is
then by no meanes manifest vnto vs that they are gods: therefore
feare them not.</ab>
<ab n="70">For as
a scarcrow in a garden of Cucumbers keepeth nothing: so are their
gods of wood, and laid ouer with siluer and gold.</ab>
<ab n="71">And
likewise their gods of wood, and laid ouer with siluer and gold,
are like to a white thorne in an orchard that euery bird sitteth
vpon: as also to a dead body, that is cast into the darke.</ab>
<ab n="72">And
you shall know them to be no gods, by the bright purple that
rotteth vpon them: and they themselues afterward shall be eaten,
and shall be a reproach in the country.<note> Or purple and brightnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="73">Better
therefore is the iust man that hath none idoles: for he shall be
farre from reproach.</ab>



</div>