<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah complaining of the
wickeds prosperitie, by faith seeth their ruine. 5 God admonisheth
him of his brethrens treacherie against him, 7 and lamenteth his
heritage. 14 Hee promiseth to the penitent, returne from
captiuitie.</head>

<ab n="1">Righteous art
thou, O Lord, when I pleade with thee: yet let mee talke with thee
of thy iudgements: Wherefore doeth the way of the wicked prosper?
Wherefore are all they happie that deale very
treacherously?<note> Or, let me reason the case with thee. , Iob 21.7. psal. 37.1. and 73.3. hab. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thou hast
planted them, yea they haue taken root: they grow, yea they bring
foorth fruit, thou art neere in their mouth, and farre from their
reines.<note> Heb. they goe on.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But thou, O
Lord, knowest me; thou hast seene me, and tried mine heart towards
thee: pull them out like sheep for the slaughter, and prepare them
for the day of slaughter.<note> Psal. 17.3. , Heb. with thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">How long shall
the land mourne, and the herbes of euery field wither, for the
wickednesse of them that dwell therein? the beasts are consumed,
and the birds, because they said; He shall not see our last
end.<note> Psal. 107.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ If thou
hast runne with the footmen, and they haue wearied thee, then how
canst thou contend with horses? And if in the land of peace,
wherein thou trustedst, they wearied thee, then how wilt thou doe
in the swelling of Iordan?</ab>
<ab n="6">For euen thy
brethren and the house of thy father, euen they haue dealt
treacherously with thee, yea they haue called a multitude after
thee; beleeue them not, though they speake faire words vnto
thee.<note> Chap.9.4. , Or, they cryed after thee fully. , Heb. good things.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ I haue
forsaken mine house: I haue left mine heritage: I haue giuen the
dearely beloued of my soule into the hand of her
enemies.<note> Heb. the loue.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Mine heritage is
vnto me as a lyon in the forrest: it cryeth out against me,
therefore haue I hated it.<note> Or, yelleth. Heb. giueth out his voice.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Mine heritage is
vnto mee as a speckled bird, the birdes round about are against
her; come yee, assemble all the beasts of the field, come to
deuoure.<note> Or, tallented. , Or, cause them to come.</note></ab>

<fw>The linnen girdle, and wine
bottles.</fw>
<ab n="10">Many pastors
haue destroyed my vineyard; they haue troden my portion vnder
foote: they haue made my pleasant portion a desolate
wildernesse.<note> Heb. portion of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They haue made
it desolate, and being desolate it mourneth vnto me; the whole land
is made desolate, because no man layeth it to heart.</ab>
<ab n="12">The spoilers
are come vpon all high places through the wildernesse: for the
sword of the Lord shall deuoure from the one end of the land euen
to the other end of the land: no flesh shall haue peace.</ab>
<ab n="13">They haue sowen
wheate, but shall reape thornes: they haue put themselues to paine,
but shall not profit: and they shall be ashamed of your reuenues,
because of the fierce anger of the Lord.<note> Leuit. 26. 16. deut.26 38. mic.6. 15. agg.1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Thus
saith the Lord against all mine euill neighbours, that touch the
inheritance, which I haue caused my people Israel to inherit;
Behold, I will plucke them out of their land, and plucke out the
house of Iudah from among them.<note> Deut. 30. 3. chap. 32. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And it shall
come to passe after that I haue plucked them out, I will returne,
and haue compassion on them, and will bring againe euery man to his
heritage, and euery man to his land.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it shall
come to passe, if they will diligently learne the wayes of my
people to sweare by my name (The Lord liueth, as they taught my
people to sweare by Baal:) then shall they be built in the middest
of my people.</ab>
<ab n="17">But if they
will not obey, I will vtterly plucke vp, and destroy that nation,
saith the Lord.<note> Isai.60. 12.</note></ab>



</div>