<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Isaiah-Chapter-66-66-Jeremiah.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The time, 3 and the calling of
Ieremiah: 11 His propheticall visions of an Almond rod, and a
seething pot: 15 His heauy message against Iudah. 17 God
incourageth him with his promise of assistance.</head>

<ab n="1">The wordes of
Ieremiah the sonne of Hilkiah, of the Priests that were in Anathoth
in the land of Beniamin:</ab>
<ab n="2">To whom the word
of the Lord came in the dayes of Iosiah the sonne of Amon king of
Iudah, in the thirteenth yeere of his reigne.</ab>
<ab n="3">It came also in
the dayes of Iehoiakim the sonne of Iosiah king of Iudah, vnto the
ende of the eleuenth yeere of Zedekiah the sonne of Iosiah king of
Iudah, vnto the carrying away of Ierusalem captiue in the fift
moneth.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then the word of
the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Before I formed
thee in the bellie, I knew thee; and before thou camest forth out
of the wombe, I sanctified thee, and I ordeined thee a Prophet vnto
the nations.<note> Isa.49. 1,5. , Gal. 5.1, 15. , Hebr. gaue.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then said I, Ah
Lord God, behold, I cannot speake, for I am a childe.<note> Exo.3.4.</note></ab>

<fw>A seething pot.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ But the
Lord sayd vnto me, Say not, I am a childe: for thou shalt goe to
all that I shall send thee, and whatsoeuer I command thee, thou
shalt speake.</ab>
<ab n="8">Be not afraid of
their faces: for I am with thee to deliuer thee, sayth the
Lord.<note> Eze.3.9. , Exo.3.12. deu.31.6,8. iosh.1.5. heb.13.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then the Lord put
foorth his hand, and touched my mouth, and the Lord said vnto me,
Behold, I haue put my words in thy mouth.<note> Isai.6.7. , Cha.5.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">See, I haue this
day set thee ouer the nations, and ouer the kingdomes, to roote
out, and to pull downe, and to destroy, and to throw down, to build
and to plant.<note> Cha.18.7. 2.cor.10.4,5.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Moreouer,
the word of the Lord came vnto me, saying; Ieremiah, what seest
thou? And I said, I see a rodde of an almond tree.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then said the
Lord vnto me, Thou hast well seene: for I will hasten my word to
performe it.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the worde of
the Lord came vnto mee the second time, saying; What seest thou?
And I said; I see a seething pot, and the face thereof was towards
the North.<note> Heb. from the face of the North.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Then the Lord
said vnto me; Out of the North an euill shal breake foorth vpon all
the inhabitants of the land.<note> Chap. 4.6. , Heb. shall be opened.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For loe, I will
call all the families of the kingdoms of the North, saith the Lord,
and they shall come, and they shall set euery one his throne at the
entring of the gates of Ierusalem, and against all the walles
thereof round about, &amp; against all the cities of
Iudah.<note> Cha.5.15. and 6.22. and 10.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And I will vtter
my iudgements against them touching all their wickednesse, who haue
forsaken me, and haue burnt incense vnto other gods, and worshipped
the workes of their owne hands.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Thou
therefore gird vp thy loynes, and arise and speake vnto them all
that I commaund thee: be not dismayed at their faces, lest I
confound thee before them.<note> Or, breake to pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For behold, I
haue made thee this day a defenced citie, and an yron pillar, and
brasen walles against the whole land, against the kings of Iudah,
against the princes thereof, against the Priests thereof, and
against the people of the land.<note> Cha.6.27. and 15.20. isai. 50.7.</note></ab>

<fw>Mans vnkindnesse.</fw>
<ab n="19">And they shall
fight against thee, but they shall not preuaile against thee: for I
am with thee, sayth the Lord, to deliuer thee.</ab>



</div>