<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-38-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah being set free by
Nebuzaradan, goeth to Gedaliah. 7 The dispersed Iewes repaire vnto
him. 13 Iohanan reuealing Ishmaels conspiracie, is not
beleeued.</head>


<fw>Ieremiah set free.</fw>
<ab n="1">The word which
came to Ieremiah frō the Lord after that Nebuzaradan the
captaine of the guard had let him goe from Ramath, when hee had
taken him being bound in chaines among all that were caried away
captiue of Ierusalem and Iudah, which were caried away captiue vnto
Babylon.<note> Or, manicles.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the captaine
of the gard took Ieremiah, and sayd vnto him, The Lord thy God hath
pronounced this euill vpon this place.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now the Lord
hath brought it, and done according as he hath sayd: because yee
haue sinned against the Lord, and haue not obeyed his voyce,
therefore this thing is come vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="4">And now behold,
I loose thee this day from the chaines which were vpon thine hand:
if it seeme good vnto thee to come with me into Babylon, come, and
I will looke well vnto thee: but if it seeme ill vnto thee to come
with me into Babylon, forbeare: behold, all the land is before
thee: whither it seemeth good and conuenient for thee to goe,
thither goe.<note> Heb. I will set mine eye vpon thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Now while he was
not yet gone backe, he sayd, Goe backe also to Gedaliah the sonne
of Ahikam the sonne of Shaphan, whom the king of Babylon hath made
gouernour ouer all the cities of Iudah, and dwell with him among
the people: or goe wheresoeuer it seemeth conuenient vnto thee to
goe. So the captaine of the gard gaue him vitailes and a reward,
and let him goe.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then went
Ieremiah vnto Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam to Mizpah, and dwelt
with him among the people, that were left in the land.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Now when
all the captaines of the forces which were in the fields, euen they
and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah the
sonne of Ahikam gouernour in the land, and had committed vnto him
men, and women and children, and of the poore of the land, of them
that were not caried away captiue to Babylon;</ab>
<ab n="8">Then they came
to Gedaliah to Mizpah, euen Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah, and
Iohanan, and Ionathan the sonnes of Kareah, and Seraiah the sonne
of Tanhumeth, and the sonnes of Ephai the Netophathite, and
Iezaniah the sonne of a Maachathite, they and their men.</ab>

<fw>A conspiracie.</fw>
<ab n="9">And Gedaliah the
sonne of Ahikam the sonne of Shaphan, sware vnto them and to their
men, saying, Feare not to serue the Caldeans: dwell in the land and
serue the king of Babylon, and it shalbe well with you.<note> Heb. to stand before. And so verse.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">As for me,
behold, I will dwell at Mizpah to serue the Caldeans, which will
come vnto vs: but yee, gather yee wine, and summer fruits, and
oyle, and put them in your vessels, and dwell in your cities, that
yee haue taken.</ab>
<ab n="11">Likewise when
all the Iewes that were in Moab, and among the Ammonites, and in
Edom, and that were in all the countries, heard that the king of
Babylon had left a remnant of Iudah, and that he had set ouer them
Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam the sonne of Shaphan;</ab>
<ab n="12">Euen all the
Iewes returned out of all places whither they were driuen, and came
to the land of Iudah, to Gedaliah vnto Mizpah, and gathered wine
and summer fruits, very much.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Moreouer
Iohanan the sonne of Kareah, and all the captaines of the forces
that were in the fields, came to Gedaliah to Mizpah,</ab>
<ab n="14">And sayd vnto
him, Doest thou certainly know, that Baalis the king of the
Ammonites hath sent Ishmael the sonne of Nethaniah to slay thee?
But Gedaliah the sonne of Ahikam beleeued them not.<note> Heb. to strike thee in soule?</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then Iohanan
the sonne of Kareah, spake to Gedaliah in Mizpah secretly, saying,
Let me goe, I pray thee, and I will slay Ishmael the sonne of
Nethaniah, and no man shall know it. Wherefore should he slay thee,
that all the Iewes which are gathered vnto thee should be
scattered, and the remnant in Iudah perish?</ab>
<ab n="16">But Gedaliah
the sonne of Ahikam sayd vnto Iohanan the sonne of Kareah; Thou
shalt not do this thing, for thou speakest falsely of
Ishmael.</ab>



</div>