<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The vnequall comparison of God and
idoles. 17 The Prophet exhorteth to flie from the calamitie to
come. 19 Hee lamenteth the spoyle of the Tabernacle by foolish
pastours. 23 He maketh an humble supplication.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare ye the
word which the Lord speaketh vnto you, O house of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus sayeth the
Lord, Learne not the way of the heathen, and be not dismayed at the
signes of heauen, for the heathen are dismayed at them.</ab>
<ab n="3">For the customes
of the people are vaine: for one cutteth a tree out of the forrest
(the worke of the handes of the workeman) with the axe.<note> Heb. statutes or ordinances are vanity.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">They decke it
with siluer and with golde, they fasten it with nayles, and with
hammers that it mooue not.</ab>
<ab n="5">They are vpright
as the palme tree, but speake not: they must needes bee borne,
because they cannot goe: be not afraid of them, for they cannot doe
euil, neither also is it in them to doe good.<note> Psa.115. 5. , Isa.46.1, 7. , Isa.41.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Forasmuch as
there is none like vnto thee, O Lord, thou art great, and thy Name
is great in might.<note> Psal.86. 8, 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Who would not
feare thee, O King of nations? for to thee doeth it appertaine:
forasmuch as among all the wise men of the nations, and in all
their kingdomes, there is none like vnto thee.<note> Reue. 15. 4. , Or, it liketh thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But they are
altogether brutish and foolish: the stocke is a doctrine of
vanities.<note> Heb. in one, or at once. , Isa.41.29 abac. 2.18. zec.10.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Siluer spread
into plates is brought from Tarshish, and gold from Uphaz, the
worke of the workeman, and of the hands of the founder: blue and
purple is their clothing: they are all the worke of cunning
men.</ab>
<ab n="10">But the Lord is
the true God, he is the liuing God, and an euerlasting King: at his
wrath the earth shal tremble, and the nations shall not be able to
abide his indignation.<note> Heb. God of trueth. , Heb. King of eternity.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Thus shal ye
say vnto them, The Gods that haue not made the heauens, &amp; the
earth, euen they shall perish from the earth, &amp; from vnder
these heauens.</ab>
<ab n="12">Hee hath made
the earth by his power, he hath established the world by his
wisedome, and hath stretched out the heauens by his
discretion.<note> Gen.1.6. chap.51.15</note></ab>

<fw>Brutish pastours.</fw>
<ab n="13">When he
vttereth his voice, there is a multitude of waters in the heauens,
and hee causeth the vapours to ascend from the ends of the earth:
hee maketh lightnings with raine, and bringeth forth the wind out
of his treasures.<note> Or, noise. , Or, for raine.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Euery man is
brutish in his knowledge, euery founder is confounded by the grauen
image: for his moulten image is falsehood, and there is no breath
in them.<note> Or, is more brutish, then to know. , Chap.51. 17, 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">They are
vanity, and the worke of errours: in the time of their visitation
they shall perish.</ab>
<ab n="16">The portion of
Iacob is not like them: for he is the fourmer of all things, and
Israel is the rod of his inheritance: the Lord of hostes is his
Name.<note> Chap. 51. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Gather
vp thy wares out of the land, O inhabitant of the
fortresse.<note> Heb. inhabitresse.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For thus saith
the Lord, Behold, I will sling out the inhabitants of the land at
this once, and will distresse them, that they may find it
so.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Woe is
mee for my hurt, my wound is grieuous: but I sayd, Truely this is a
griefe, and I must beare it.</ab>
<ab n="20">My Tabernacle
is spoyled, and all my cordes are broken: my children are gone
foorth of me, and they are not: there is none to stretch foorth my
tent any more, and to set vp my curtaines.</ab>
<ab n="21">For the
Pastours are become brutish, and haue not sought the Lord:
therefore they shall not prosper, and all their flockes shall be
scattered.</ab>
<ab n="22">Behold, the
noise of the bruit is come, and a great commotion out of the North
countrey, to make the cities of Iudah desolate, and a denne of
dragons.<note> Chap.1. 15. and 5. 15. and 6. 22. , Chap.9. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ O Lord,
I know that the way of man is not in himselfe: it is not in man
that walketh, to direct his steps.<note> Pro.16.1. and 20.44.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">O Lord, correct
mee, but with iudgement, not in thine anger, lest thou bring me to
nothing.<note> Psal.6.1. and 38.1. cha. 30.11. , Hebr. diminish me.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Powre out thy
fury vpon the heathen that know thee not, and vpon the families
that call not on thy Name: for they haue eaten vp Iacob, and
deuoured him, and consumed him, and haue made his habitation
desolate.<note> Psal. 79.6.</note></ab>



</div>