<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the type of a potter is
shewed Gods absolute power in disposing of Nations. 11 Iudgements
threatned to Iudah for her strange reuolt. 18 Ieremiah prayeth
against his conspiratours.</head>

<ab n="1">The word which
came to Ieremiah from þe Lord saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Arise and go
downe to the potters house, &amp; there I will cause thee to heare
my words.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then I went
downe to the potters house, and behold, hee wrought a worke on the
wheeles.<note> Or, frames or seates.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the vessell
that he made of clay, was marred in the hand of the potter; so he
made it againe another vessell as seemed good to the potter to make
it.<note> Or, that he made, was marred as clay in the hand of the potter. , Hebr. returned and made.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then the word of
the Lord came to me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="6">O house of
Israel, cannot I doe with you as this potter, saith the Lord ?
Behold, as the clay is in the potters hand, so are ye in mine hand,
O house of Israel.<note> Isa.45. 9. rom.9. 10. wisd.15.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">At what instant
I shall speake concerning a nation, and concerning a kingdome, to
plucke vp and to pull downe, and to destroy it.<note> Chap.1. 10.</note></ab>

<fw>Euill for good.</fw>
<ab n="8">If that nation
against whom I haue pronounced, turne from their euill, I will
repent of the euill that I thought to doe vnto them.<note> Iona.3.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And at what
instant I shall speake concerning a nation, and concerning a
kingdome to build and to plant it;</ab>
<ab n="10">If it doe euill
in my sight, that it obey not my voice, then I will repent of the
good; wherewith I saide I would benefite them.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Now
therefore goe to, speake to the men of Iudah, and to the
inhabitants of Ierusalem, saying, Thus saith the Lord; Behold, I
frame euill against you, and deuise a deuice against you: returne
ye now euery one from his euill way, and make your waies and your
doings good.<note> 2. Kin. 17.13. chap. 7. 3. and 25.5. and 35.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they said,
There is no hope, but wee will walke after our owne deuices, and
wee will euery one doe the imagination of his euil
heart.<note> Chap. 2. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore thus
saith the Lord, Aske ye now among the heathen, who hath heard such
things? the Uirgin of Israel hath done a very horrible
thing.<note> Chap. 2. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Will a man
leaue the snow of Lebanon which commeth from the rocke of the
fielde? or shall the colde flowing waters that come from another
place, be forsaken?<note> Or, my fields for a rocke, or for the snow of Lebanon? Shall the running waters be forsaken for the strange cold waters? , Cha.2.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Because my
people hath forgotten mee, they haue burnt incense to vanitie, and
they haue caused them to stumble in their waies from the ancient
paths, to walke in paths, in a way not cast vp,<note> Chap.17. 13. , Chap.6. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">To make their
land desolate and a perpetuall hissing: euery one that passeth
thereby shall bee astonished, and wagge his head.<note> Chap.19. 8. and 49. 13. and 50. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">I will scatter
them as with an East winde before the enemie: I will shew them the
backe, and not the face, in the day of their calamitie.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then
said they, Come, and let vs deuise deuices against Ieremiah: for
the Law shall not perish from the Priest, nor counsell from the
wise, nor the word from the prophet: Come and let vs smite him with
the tongue, and let vs not giue heede to any of his
wordes.<note> Mal. 2.7. , Or, for the tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Giue heed to
me, O Lord, and hearken to the voice of them that contend with
me.</ab>

<fw>The potters vessell.</fw>
<ab n="20">Shall euill bee
recompensed for good? for they haue digged a pit for my soule:
remember that I stood before thee to speake good for them, and to
turne away thy wrath from them.</ab>
<ab n="21">Therefore
deliuer vp their children to the famine, and powre out their blood
by the force of the sword, and let their wiues be bereaued of their
children and be widowes, and let their men be put to death, let
their yong men be slaine by the sword in battell.<note> Heb. powre them out. , Psal.109. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Let a crie bee
heard from their houses, when thou shalt bring a troupe suddenly
vpon them, for they haue digged a pit to take me, and hid snares
for my feet.</ab>
<ab n="23">Yet Lord thou
knowest all their counsell against me to slay mee: forgiue not
their iniquitie, neither blot out their sinne from thy sight, but
let them bee ouerthrowen before thee, deale thus with them in the
time of thine anger.<note> Hebr. for death.</note></ab>



</div>