<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The enemies, sent against Iudah, 4
encourage themselues. 6 God setteth them on worke, because of their
sinnes. 9 The prophet lamenteth the iudgements of God because of
their sinnes. 18 He proclaimeth Gods wrath. 26 He calleth the
people to mourne for the iudgement on their sinnes.</head>

<ab n="1">O yee children of
Beniamin, gather your selues to flee out of the middest of
Ierusalem, and blow the trumpet in Tekoa: and set vp a signe of
fire in Beth-haccerem: for euill appeareth out of the North, and
great destruction.</ab>
<ab n="2">I haue likened
the daughter of Zion to a comely and delicate woman.<note> Or, dwelling at home.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The shepheards
with their flocks shall come vnto her: they shall pitch their tents
against her round about: they shall feede, euery one in his
place.</ab>
<ab n="4">Prepare yee warre
against her: arise, and let vs goe vp at noone: woe vnto vs, for
the day goeth away, for the shadowes of the euening are stretched
out.</ab>
<ab n="5">Arise, and let vs
goe by night, and let vs destroy her palaces.</ab>

<fw>The old way.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶ For thus
hath the Lord of hostes said; Hew yee downe trees and cast a mount
against Ierusalem: this is the citie to be visited, she is wholly
oppression in the midst of her.<note> Or, powre out the engine of shot.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">As a fountaine
casteth out her waters, so she casteth out her wickednesse:
violence and spoile is heard in her, before me continually is
griefe and wounds.<note> Isa. 57.20</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Be thou
instructed, O Ierusalem, lest my soule depart from thee: lest I
make thee desolate, a lande not inhabited.<note> Heb. bee loosed or disiointed.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Thus saith
the Lord of hosts, They shall throughly gleane the remnant of
Israel as a vine: turne backe thine hand as a grape gatherer into
the baskets.</ab>
<ab n="10">To whome shall I
speake and giue warning, that they may heare? Behold, their eare is
vncircumcised, and they cannot hearken: beholde, the word of the
Lord is vnto them a reproch: they haue no delight in
it.<note> Chap.7.26</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore I am
full of the furie of the Lord: I am weary with holding in: I will
powre it out vpon the children abroad, and vpon the assembly of
yong men together: for euen the husband with the wife shall be
taken, the aged with him that is full of dayes.</ab>
<ab n="12">And their houses
shall be turned vnto others, with their fields and wiues together:
for I wil stretch out my hand vpon the inhabitants of the land,
saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">For from the
least of them euen vnto the greatest of them, euery one is giuen to
couetousnesse, and from the prophet euen vnto the priest, euery one
dealeth falsly.<note> Isa.56.11 chap.8.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">They haue healed
also the hurt of the daughter of my people sleightly, saying,
Peace, peace, when there is no peace.<note> Chap. 8. 11. ezek. 13.10. , Heb. bruise or breach.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Were they
ashamed when they had committed abomination? nay they were not at
all ashamed, neither could they blush: therefore they shall fall
among them that fall: at the time that I visit them, they shall bee
cast downe, saith the Lord.<note> Chap.3.3. and 8.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Thus saith the
Lord, Stand ye in the wayes and see, and aske for the old paths,
where is the good way, and walke therein, and ye shall finde rest
for your soules: but they said, We will not walke
therein.<note> Isa. 8.20. mal.4.4. luk.16.29. , Mat.11. 29.</note></ab>

<fw>Rebellious Iewes.</fw>
<ab n="17">Also I set
watchmen ouer you, saying, Hearken to the sound of the trumpet: but
they said, We wil not hearken.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Therefore
heare ye nations, and know, O Congregation what is among
them.</ab>
<ab n="19">Heare, O earth,
behold, I will bring euill vpon this people, euen the fruit of
their thoughts, because they haue not hearkened vnto my wordes, nor
to my law, but reiected it.</ab>
<ab n="20">To what purpose
cōmeth there to me incense from Sheba? and the sweet cane from
a farre countrey? your burnt offerings are not acceptable, nor your
sacrifices sweet vnto me.<note> Isa.1.11. and 66.3. amos 5.21. mic. 6.6, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Therefore thus
saith the Lord, Behold, I will lay stumbling blockes before this
people, and the fathers and the sons together shall fall vpon them:
the neighbor and his friend shall perish.</ab>
<ab n="22">Thus saith the
Lord, Behold, a people commeth from the North countrey, and a great
nation shall bee raised from the sides of the earth.<note> Chap.1.15 and 5.15. and 10. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">They shall lay
hold on bowe and speare: they are cruell, and haue no mercie: their
voice roareth like the Sea, and they ride vpon horses, set in aray
as men for warre against thee, O daughter of Zion.</ab>
<ab n="24">We haue heard
the fame thereof, our hands waxe feeble, anguish hath taken hold of
vs, and paine as of a woman in trauaile.</ab>
<ab n="25">Goe not forth
into the field, nor walke by the way: for the sword of the enemie
and feare is on euery side.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ O
daughter of my people, gird thee with sackcloth, and wallowe thy
selfe in ashes: make thee mourning, as for an onely sonne, most
bitter lamentation: for the spoiler shall suddenly come vpon
vs.<note> Chap.4.8. and 25.36.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">I haue set thee
for a towre, and a fortresse among my people: that thou mayest know
and trie their way.<note> Chap.1. 18. and 15. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">They are all
grieuous reuolters, walking with slanders: they are brasse and
yron, they are all corrupters.<note> Ezek. 22. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The bellowes are
burnt, the lead is consumed of the fire: the founder melteth in
vaine: for the wicked are not plucked away.</ab>
<ab n="30">Reprobate siluer
shall men call them, because the Lord hath reiected
them.<note> Isa. 1.22. , Or, refuse siluer.</note></ab>



</div>