<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_44" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-44-44.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-44-46.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIV.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah expresseth the desolation
of Iudah for their idolatry. 11 Hee prophesieth their destruction,
who commit idolatry in Egypt. 15 The obstinacie of the Iewes. 20
Ieremiah threatneth them for the same, 29 And for a signe,
prophecieth the destruction of Egypt.</head>

<ab n="1">The word that
came to Ieremiah concerning all the Iewes which dwel in the land of
Egypt, which dwell at Migdol, and at Tahpanhes, and at Noph, and in
the countrey of Pathros, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, the God of Israel; Ye haue seene all the euill that
I haue brought vpon Ierusalem, and vpon all the cities of Iudah:
and behold, this day they are a desolation, and no man dwelleth
therein,</ab>
<ab n="3">Because of their
wickednes which they haue committed, to prouoke me to anger, in
that they went to burne incense, and to serue other gods, whom they
knew not, neither they, you, nor your fathers.</ab>
<ab n="4">Howbeit I sent
vnto you all my seruants the Prophets, rising early and sending
them, saying, Oh doe not this abominable thing that I hate.</ab>
<ab n="5">But they
hearkened not, nor enclined their eare to turne from their
wickednes, to burne no incense vnto other gods.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore my
furie and mine anger was powred forth, and was kindled in the
cities of Iudah, and in the streets of Ierusalem, and they are
wasted and desolate, as at this day.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore now
thus saith the Lord the God of hostes, the God of Israel, Wherefore
commit ye this great euill against your soules, to cut off from you
man and woman, childe and suckling out of Iudah, to leaue you none
to remaine.<note> Hebr. out of the midst of Iudah.</note></ab>

<fw>The obstinacie of Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="8">In that yee
prouoke mee vnto wrath with the workes of your hands, burning
incense vnto other gods in the land of Egypt whither ye bee gone to
dwell, that yee might cut your selues off, and that ye might be a
curse, and a reproch among all the nations of the earth?</ab>
<ab n="9">Haue ye
forgotten the wickednes of your fathers, and the wickednesse of the
kings of Iudah, and the wickednes of their wiues, and your owne
wickednesse, and the wickednesse of your wiues, which they haue
committed in the land of Iudah, and in the streets of
Ierusalem?<note> Heb. wickednesses, or, punishments &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They are not
humbled euen vnto this day, neither haue they feared, nor walked in
my Law, nor in my Statutes that I set before you, and before your
fathers.<note> Hebr. contrite.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶
Therefore thus sayeth the Lord of hostes, the God of Israel,
Behold, I will set my face against you for euill, and to cut off
all Iudah.<note> Amos 9.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And I will take
the remnant of Iudah, that haue set their faces to goe into the
land of Egypt to soiourne there, and they shall all be consumed and
fall in the land of Egypt: they shall euen bee consumed by the
sword, and by the famine: they shall die, from the least euen vnto
the greatest, by the sword and by the famine: and they shalbe an
execration and an astonishment, and a curse, and a reproch.</ab>
<ab n="13">For I will
punish them that dwell in the land of Egypt, as I haue punished
Ierusalem, by the sword, by the famine, and by the
pestilence;</ab>
<ab n="14">So that none of
the remnant of Iudah which are gone into the land of Egypt to
soiourne there, shall escape or remaine, that they should returne
into the land of Iudah to the which they haue a desire to returne
to dwell there: for none shall returne but such as shall
escape.<note> Heb. lift vp their soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then all
the men which knew that their wiues had burnt incense vnto other
Gods, and all the women that stood by, a great multitude, euen all
the people that dwelt in the land of Egypt in Pathros, answered
Ieremiah, saying,</ab>
<ab n="16">As for the word
that thou hast spoken vnto vs in the name of the Lord, we will not
hearken vnto thee.</ab>

<fw>The obstinacie of Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="17">But we will
certainly doe whatsoeuer thing goeth forth out of our owne mouth,
to burne incense vnto the queene of heauen, and to powre out drinke
offrings vnto her, as we haue done, we and our fathers, our kings
and our princes in the cities of Iudah, and in the streetes of
Ierusalem: for then had we plentie of vitailes, and were well, and
saw no euill.<note> Or, frame of heauen. , Chap. 7. 18. , Heb. bread.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">But since we
left off to burne incense to the queene of heauen, and to powre out
drinke offrings vnto her, we haue wanted all things, and haue beene
consumed by the sword, and by the famine.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when we
burnt incense to the queene of heauen, and powred out drinke
offrings vnto her, did we make her cakes to worship her, and powre
out drinke offrings vnto her without our men?<note> Chap.7. 18. , Or, husbands.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Then
Ieremiah sayd vnto all the people, to the men and to the women, and
to all the people which had giuen him that answere, saying;</ab>
<ab n="21">The incense
that yee burnt in the cities of Iudah, and in the streetes of
Ierusalem, yee and your fathers, your kings and your princes, and
the people of the land, did not the Lord remember them, and came it
not into his minde?</ab>
<ab n="22">So that the
Lord could no longer beare, because of the euill of your doings,
and because of the abominations, which yee haue committed:
therefore is your land a desolation, and an astonishment, and a
curse without an inhabitant, as at this day.</ab>
<ab n="23">Because you
haue burnt incense, and because yee haue sinned against the Lord,
and haue not obeyed the voyce of the Lord, nor walked in his law,
nor in his statutes, nor in his testimonies: therefore this euill
is happened vnto you, as at this day.</ab>
<ab n="24">Moreouer
Ieremiah sayd vnto all the people, and to all the women; Heare the
word of the Lord, all Iudah, that are in the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="25">Thus saith the
Lord of hostes the God of Israel, saying: Yee and your wiues haue
both spoken with your mouths, and fulfilled with your hand, saying;
We will surely performe our vowes that we haue vowed, to burne
incense to the queene of heauen, and to powre out drinke offrings
vnto her: yee will surely accomplish your vowes, and surely
performe your vowes.</ab>

<fw>Baruch faint.</fw>
<ab n="26">Therefore heare
yee the word of the Lord, all Iudah that dwell in the land of
Egypt, Behold, I haue sworne by my great Name, saith the Lord, that
my Name shal no more be named in the mouth of any man of Iudah, in
all the land of Egypt, saying, The Lord God liueth.</ab>
<ab n="27">Behold, I will
watch ouer them for euill, and not for good, and all the men of
Iudah that are in the land of Egypt shalbe consumed by the sword,
&amp; by the famin, vntil there be an end of them.</ab>
<ab n="28">Yet a small
number that escape the sword, shall returne out of the land of
Egypt into the land of Iudah: and all the remnant of Iudah that are
gone into the land of Egypt to soiourne there, shall know whose
wordes shall stand, mine or theirs.<note> Heb. from me or from them.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And this
shalbe a signe vnto you, saith the Lord, that I will punish you in
this place, that ye may knowe that my words shal surely stand
against you for euill.</ab>
<ab n="30">Thus saith the
Lord, Behold, I will giue Pharaoh-Hophra king of Egypt into the
hand of his enemies, and into the hande of them that seeke his
life, as I gaue Zedekiah king of Iudah into the hand of
Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon his enemy, and that sought his
life.</ab>



</div>