<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the type of breaking a
potters vessell, is foreshewed the desolation of the Iewes for
their sinnes.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus saith the
Lord, Goe and get a potters earthen bottell, and take of the
ancients of the people, and of the ancients of the
Priestes.</ab>
<ab n="2">And goe forth
vnto the valley of the sonne of Hinnom, which is by the entrie of
the Eastgate, and proclaime there the words that I shall tell
thee:<note> Hebr. the Sungate.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And say, Heare
ye the word of the Lord, O kings of Iudah, and inhabitants of
Ierusalem; Thus saith the Lord of hostes, the God of Israel;
Behold, I will bring euill vpon this place, the which whosoeuer
heareth, his eares shall tingle.<note> 1.Sam.3. 11. 2.king. 21.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Because they
haue forsaken mee, and haue estranged this place, and haue burnt
incense in it vnto other gods, whom neither they, nor their fathers
haue knowen, nor the kings of Iudah, and haue filled this place
with the blood of innocents.</ab>
<ab n="5">They haue built
also the high places of Baal, to burne their sonnes with fire for
burnt offerings vnto Baal, which I commanded not, nor spake it,
neither came it into my minde.<note> Chap.7. 31, 32.</note></ab>

<fw>Iudah threatned.</fw>
<ab n="6">Therefore
behold, the daies come, saith the Lord, that this place shall no
more bee called Tophet, nor the valley of the sonne of Hinnom, but
the valley of slaughter.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I will make
void the counsell of Iudah and Ierusalem in this place, and I will
cause them to fall by the sword before their enemies, and by the
hands of them that seek their liues: and their carkeises will I
giue to be meat for the foules of the heauen, and for the beasts of
the earth.<note> Cha.16.4. and 7.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I will make
this citie desolate and an hissing: euery one that passeth thereby
shalbe astonished and hisse, because of all the plagues
thereof.<note> Chap.18.16. and 49.13. and 50.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And I will cause
them to eate the flesh of their sonnes and the flesh of their
daughters, and they shal eate euery one the flesh of his friend in
the siege and straitnesse, wherewith their enemies, and they that
seeke their liues, shall straiten them.<note> Leuit. 26. 29. deu. 28. 53. lam.4. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then shalt thou
breake þe bottle in the sight of the men that goe
with thee,</ab>
<ab n="11">And shalt say
vnto them; Thus saith the Lord of hostes, Euen so will I breake
this people and this citie as one breaketh a potters vessell that
cannot bee made whole againe, and they shall bury them in Tophet,
till there be no place else to bury.<note> Heb. be healed. , Cha. 7.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thus will I doe
vnto this place, sayth the Lord, and to the inhabitants thereof,
and euen make their citie as Tophet.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the houses
of Ierusalem, and the houses of the kings of Iudah shall bee
defiled as the place of Tophet, because of all the houses vpon
whose roofes they haue burnt incense vnto all the hoste of heauen,
&amp; haue powred out drinke offrings vnto other gods.<note> Chap.32. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Then came
Ieremiah from Tophet, whither the Lord had sent him to prophecie,
and hee stood in the court of the Lords house, and said to all the
people,</ab>
<ab n="15">Thus saith the
Lord of hostes the God of Israel, Behold, I wil bring vpon this
city, and vpon all her townes all the euill that I haue pronounced
against it, because they haue hardened their neckes, that they
might not heare my wordes.</ab>



</div>