<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-23-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Vnder the Type of good and bad
figs, 4 he foresheweth the restauration of them that were in
captiuitie, 8 and the desolation of Zedekiah and the
rest.</head>

<ab n="1">The Lord shewed
mee, and behold, two baskets of figges were set before the temple
of the Lord, after that Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon had caried
away captiue Ieconiah the sonne of Iehoiakim king of Iudah, and the
princes of Iudah, with the carpenters and smiths from Ierusalem,
and had brought them to Babylon.<note> 2. Kings. 24. 2.chron. 36.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">One basket had
very good figges, euen like the figges that are first ripe: and the
other basket had very naughty figges, which could not be eaten,
they were so bad.<note> Heb. for badnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then said the
Lord vnto me; What seest thou Ieremiah? and I said: Figges: the
good figges, very good and the euill, very euill, that cannot be
eaten, they are so euill.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Againe,
the word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="5">Thus saith the
Lord, the God of Israel, Like these good figges, so will I
acknowledge them that are caried away captiue of Iudah, whom I haue
sent out of this place into the land of the Caldeans for their
good.<note> Heb. captiuitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For I will set
mine eyes vpon them for good, and I will bring them againe to this
land, and I will build them, and not pull them downe, and I will
plant them, and not plucke them vp.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I will giue
them an heart to know me, that I am the Lord, and they shall be my
people, and I will be their God: for they shall returne vnto me
with their whole heart.<note> Deut. 30. 60. chap. 32 39. ezech. 11. 19. and 36.26.27. , Chap. 30. 22. and 31. 33. and 32. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And as
the euill figges which cannot be eaten, they are so euill; (Surely
thus saith the Lord) so will I giue Zedekiah the king of Iudah, and
his princes, and the residue of Ierusalem, that remaine in this
land, and them that dwell in the land of Egypt.<note> Chap. 29. 17.</note></ab>

<fw>A diligent prophet.</fw>
<ab n="9">And I will
deliuer them to be remoued into all the kingdomes of the earth for
their hurt, to be a reproch and a prouerbe, a taunt and a curse in
all places whither I shall driue them.<note> Heb. for remouing or vexation. , Deut.28. 37. chap. 15 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And I will send
the sword, the famine, and the pestilence among them, till they be
consumed from off the land, that I gaue vnto them, and to their
fathers.</ab>



</div>