<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah sendeth a letter to the
captiues in Babylon, to be quiet there, 8 and not to beleeue the
dreames of their prophets, 10 and that they shall returne with
grace, after seuentie yeeres. 15 He foretelleth the destruction of
the rest for their disobedience. 20 He sheweth the fearefull end of
Ahab and Zedekiah, two lying prophets. 24 Shemaiah writeth a letter
against Ieremiah. 30 Ieremiah readeth his doome.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are
the words of the letter, that Ieremiah the prophet sent from
Ierusalem vnto the residue of the elders which were caried away
captiues, and to the priests, and to the prophets, and to all the
people whom Nebuchad-nezzar had caried away captiue from Ierusalem
to Babylon,</ab>

<fw>False prophets.</fw>
<ab n="2">(After that
Ieconiah the king, and the queene, and the eunuches, the princes of
Iudah and Ierusalem, and the carpenters and the smithes were
departed from Ierusalem)<note> 2.King. 24.12, &amp;c. , Or, chamberleines.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">By the hand of
Elasah the sonne of Shaphan, and Gemariah the sonne of Hilkiah,
whome Zedekiah king of Iudah sent vnto Babylon to Nebuchad-nezzar
king of Babylon, saying,</ab>
<ab n="4">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts the God of Israel vnto all that are caried away
captiues, whom I haue caused to be caried away from Ierusalem vnto
Babylon:</ab>
<ab n="5">Build ye houses
and dwell in them, and plant gardens, and eate the fruit of
them.</ab>
<ab n="6">Take ye wiues,
and beget sonnes and daughters, and take wiues for your sonnes, and
giue your daughters to husbands, that they may beare sonnes and
daughters, that ye may bee increased there, and not
diminished.</ab>
<ab n="7">And seeke the
peace of the citie, whither I haue caused you to be caried away
captiues, &amp; pray vnto the Lord for it: for in the peace thereof
shall yee haue peace.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ For thus
saith the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, Let not your prophets
and your diuiners, that bee in the midst of you, deceiue you,
neither hearken to your dreames which yee cause to be
dreamed.<note> Chap.14. 14. and 23. 21. and 27. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For they
prophecie falsly vnto you in my name: I haue not sent them, saith
the Lord.<note> Hebr. in a lie.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ For thus
saith the Lord, That after seuentie yeeres be accomplished at
Babylon, I will visite you, and performe my good word towards you,
in causing you to returne to this place.<note> 2.Chron. 36.22, ezra 1.1. chap. 25. 12. and 27.22. dan. 9.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For I knowe the
thoughts that I thinke towards you, saith the Lord, thoughts of
peace, and not of euill, to giue you an expected end.<note> Hebr ende and expectation.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then shall ye
call vpon me, and ye shall goe and pray vnto mee, and I will
hearken vnto you.<note> Dan.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And ye shall
seeke me, and finde me, when ye shall search for me with all your
heart.</ab>

<fw>After captiuitie, deliuerence.</fw>
<ab n="14">And I will be
found of you, saith the Lord, and I will turne away your
captiuitie, and I will gather you from all the nations, and from
all the places whither I haue driuen you, saith the Lord, and I
will bring you againe into the place whence I caused you to be
caried away captiue.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Because
yee haue said, The Lord hath raised vs vp prophets in
Babylon:</ab>
<ab n="16">Know that thus
saith the Lord, of the king that sitteth vpon the throne of Dauid,
and of all the people that dwelleth in this citie, and of your
brethren that are not gone foorth with you into captiuitie.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, Beholde, I will send vpon them the sword, the
famine, and the pestilence, and will make them like vile figges,
that cannot be eaten, they are so euill.<note> Chap.24. 8,10. , Chap.24. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And I will
persecute them with the sword, with the famine, and with the
pestilence, and will deliuer them to be remooued to all the
kingdomes of the earth, to be a curse and an astonishment, and an
hissing, and a reproch among all the nations, whither I haue driuen
them.<note> Hebr. for a curse.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Because they
haue not hearkened to my words, saith the Lord, which I sent vnto
them by my seruants the Prophets, rising vp early, and sending
them, but ye would not heare, saith the Lord.<note> Chap. 25. 4. and 32. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Heare
yee therefore the word of the Lord, all ye of the captiuitie, whom
I haue sent from Ierusalem to Babylon.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts the God of Israel, of Ahab the sonne of Kolaiah, and
of Zedekiah the sonne of Maaseiah, which prophecie a lye vnto you
in my Name, Behold, I will deliuer them into the hand of
Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, and hee shall slay them before your
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="22">And of them
shall bee taken vp a eurse by all the captiuitie of Iudah which are
in Babylon, saying, The Lord make thee like Zedekiah, and like
Ahab, whom the king of Babylon rosted in the fire.</ab>
<ab n="23">Because they
haue committed villanie in Israel, and haue committed adulterie
with their neighbors wiues, and haue spoken lying wordes in my
Name, which I haue not commanded them, euen I know, and am a
witnesse, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Thus
shalt thou also speake to Shemaiah the Nehelamite,
saying:<note> Or, dreamer.</note></ab>

<fw>After captiuitie, deliuerence.</fw>
<ab n="25">Thus speaketh
the Lord of hostes the God of Israel, saying, Because thou hast
sent letters in thy name vnto all the people that are at Ierusalem,
and to Zephaniah the sonne of Maaseiah the Priest, and to all the
priests, saying;</ab>
<ab n="26">The Lord hath
made thee Priest in the stead of Iehoiada the Priest, that ye
should be Officers in the house of the Lord, for euery man that is
madde, and maketh himselfe a Prophet, that thou shouldest put him
in prison, and in the stockes:<note> 2.King.9. 11. acts.26. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Now therefore
why hast thou not reproued Ieremiah of Anathoth, which maketh
himselfe a Prophet to you?</ab>
<ab n="28">For therefore
he sent vnto vs in Babylon, saying, This captiuitie is long, build
ye houses and dwell in them, and plant gardens, and eate the fruit
of them.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Zephaniah
the Priest read this letter in the eares of Ieremiah the
Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Then
came the word of the Lord vnto Ieremiah, saying;</ab>
<ab n="31">Send to all
them of the captiuitie, saying, Thus saith the Lord, concerning
Shemaiah the Nehelamite, Because that Shemaiah hath prophecied vnto
you, and I sent him not, and he caused you to trust in a
lye.</ab>
<ab n="32">Therefore thus
saith the Lord, Behold, I will punish Shemaiah the Nehelamite and
his seed: he shall not haue a man to dwell among this people,
neither shall hee behold the good that I will doe for my people,
saith the Lord, because he hath taught rebellion against the
Lord.<note> Chap.28. 16. , Hebr. reuolt.</note></ab>



</div>