<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah lamenteth the Iewes for
their manifold sinnes, 9 and for their iudgement. 12 Disobedience
is the cause of their bitter calamitie. 17 He exhorteth to mourne
for their destruction, 23 and to trust, not in themselues, but in
God. 25 He threatneth both Iewes and Gentiles.</head>

<ab n="1">Oh that my head
were waters, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might
weepe day and night for the slaine of the daughter of my
people.<note> Heb. who will giue my head &amp;c. , Isa.22.4. chap.4.19.</note></ab>

<fw>The Prophets sorow for the
people.</fw>
<ab n="2">Oh that I had in
the wildernesse a lodging place of wayfaring men, that I might
leaue my people, and goe from them: for they be all adulterers, an
assembly of treacherous men.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they bend
their tongue like their bow for lies: but they are not valiant for
the trueth vpon the earth: for they proceed from euil to euill, and
they know not me, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">Take yee heede
euery one of his neighbour, and trust yee not in any brother: for
euery brother will vtterly supplant, and euery neighbour will walke
with slanders.<note> Chap. 12. 6. mich. 7. 5,6. , Or, friend.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And they will
deceiue euery one his neighbour, and will not speake the trueth,
they haue taught their tongue to speake lies, and weary themselues
to commit iniquity.<note> Or, mocke.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thine habitation
is in the middest of deceit, through deceit they refuse to know me,
sayth the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therfore thus
saith the Lord of hostes; Behold, I will melt them, and trie them:
for how shall I doe for the daughter of my people?</ab>
<ab n="8">Their tongue is
as an arrowe shot out, it speaketh deceit: one speaketh peaceably
to his neighbour with his mouth, but in heart he layeth his
waite.<note> Psal.120.4 , Psal. 12.2. and 28.3. , Psa. 12.3. and 28.3. , Heb. in the middest of him. , Or, waite for him.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Shall I
not visit them for these things, saith the Lord ? shall not my
soule be auenged on such a nation as this?<note> Chap.5.9, 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For the
mountaines will I take vp a weeping and wayling, and for the
habitations of the wildernesse a lamentation, because they are
burnt vp, so that none can passe through them, neither can men
heare the voyce of the cattell, both the foule of the heauens, and
the beast are fled, they are gone.<note> Or, pastures , Or, desolate , Heb. from the foule euen to &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I will make
Ierusalem heapes, and a denne of dragons, and I wil make the cities
of Iudah desolate, without an inhabitant.<note> Chap. 11. 10,22. , Heb. desolation.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Who is
the wise man that may vnderstand this, and who is he to whom the
mouth of the Lord hath spoken, that hee may declare it; for what
the land perisheth, and is burnt vp like a wildernesse that none
passeth through?</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord
saith; Because they haue forsaken my law, which I set before them,
and haue not obeyed my voyce, neither walked therein;</ab>
<ab n="14">But haue walked
after the imagination of their owne heart, &amp; after Baalim,
which their fathers taught them:<note> Or, stubburnesse.</note></ab>

<fw>True glory.</fw>
<ab n="15">Therefore thus
saith the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, Behold, I will feed
them, euen this people with wormewood, and giue them water of gall
to drinke.<note> Cha. 8.12. and 23.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I will scatter
them also among the heathen, whome neither they nor their fathers
haue knowen: and I wil send a sword after them, til I haue consumed
them.<note> Leuit. 26. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Thus
saith the Lord of hosts, Consider yee, and call for the mourning
women, that they may come, and send for cunning women, that they
may come.</ab>
<ab n="18">And let them
make haste, and take vp a wailing for vs, that our eyes may run
down with teares, and our eyelids gush out with waters.</ab>
<ab n="19">For a voyce of
wayling is heard out of Zion, How are we spoiled? wee are greatly
confounded, because wee haue forsaken the land, because our
dwellings haue cast vs out.</ab>
<ab n="20">Yet heare the
word of the Lord, O ye women, &amp; let your eare receiue the word
of his mouth, and teach your daughters wailing, and euery one her
neighbour lamentation.</ab>
<ab n="21">For death is
come vp into our windowes, and is entred into our palaces, to cut
off the children from without and the yong men from the
streetes.</ab>
<ab n="22">Speake, Thus
saith the Lord, Euen the carkeises of men shall fall as dung vpon
the open field, and as the handfull after the haruest man, and none
shall gather them.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Thus
saith the Lord, Let not the wise man glory in his wisdom, neither
let the mighty man glory in his might, let not the rich man glory
in his riches.<note> 1.Cor.1. 31. 2.cor. 10.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But let him that
glorieth, glory in this, that hee vnderstandeth and knoweth me,
that I am the Lord which exercise louing kindnesse, iudgement and
righteousnesse in the earth: for in these things I delight, saith
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Behold,
the dayes come, saith the Lord, that I will punish all them which
are circumcised, with the vncircumcised,<note> Heb. visit vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Egypt, and
Iudah, and Edom, and the children of Ammon, and Moab, and all that
are in the vtmost corners, that dwell in the wildernesse: for all
these nations are vncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are
vncircumcised in the heart.<note> Hebr. cut off into corners, or hauing the corners of their haire polled. , Chap. 25. 23. , Rom.2. 28,29.</note></ab>



</div>