<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-23-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-25-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Ieremiah reprouing the Iewes
disobedience to the Prophets, 8 foretelleth the seuenty yeeres
captiuitie, 12 and after that, the destruction of Babylon. 15 Vnder
the Type of a cup of wine he foresheweth the destruction of all
nations. 34 The howling of the Shepheards.</head>

<ab n="1">The word that
came to Ieremiah concerning all the people of Iudah, in the fourth
yeere of Iehoiakim the sonne of Iosiah king of Iudah, that was the
first yeere of Nebuchad-rezzar king of Babylon:</ab>
<ab n="2">The which
Ieremiah the prophet spake vnto all the people of Iudah, and to all
the inhabitants of Ierusalem, saying;</ab>
<ab n="3">From the
thirteenth yere of Iosiah the sonne of Amon king of Iudah, euen
vnto this day (that is the three and twentith yeere) the word of
the Lord hath come vnto me, and I haue spoken vnto you, rising
early and speaking, but yee haue not hearkened.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
hath sent vnto you all his seruants the prophets, rising early and
sending them, but yee haue not hearkened, nor inclined your eare to
heare.<note> Chap.29. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">They sayd, Turne
yee againe now euery one from his euill way, and from the euil of
your doings, and dwell in the land that the Lord hath giuen vnto
you, and to your fathers for euer and euer.<note> 2.Kings. 17.13. cha. 18. 11. and 35. 15. ionas 3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And goe not
after other Gods to serue them, and to worship them, and prouoke
mee not to anger with the workes of your hands, and I will doe you
no hurt.</ab>
<ab n="7">Yet yee haue not
hearkened vnto me, saith the Lord, that yee might prouoke me to
anger with the workes of your hands, to your owne hurt.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Therefore
thus saith the Lord of hostes; Because yee haue not heard my
words:</ab>

<fw>A cup of furie for all nations.</fw>
<ab n="9">Behold, I will
send and take all the families of the North, saith the Lord, and
Nebuchad-rezzar the king of Babylon my seruant, and will bring them
against this land, and against the inhabitants thereof, and against
all these nations round about, and will vtterly destroy them, and
make them an astonishment, and an hissing, and perpetuall
desolations.</ab>
<ab n="10">Moreouer, I
will take from them the voyce of myrth, and the voice of gladnes,
the voice of the bridegrome, and the voice of the bride, the sound
of the milstones, &amp; the light of the candle.<note> Heb. I will cause to perish from them. , Cha.7.34. and 16.9. and 25.10. ezek. 26.13 ose 2.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And this whole
land shall be a desolation, and an astonishment, and these nations
shal serue the king of Babylon seuentie yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And it
shall come to passe when seuentie yeeres are accomplished, that I
will punish the king of Babylon and that nation, saith the Lord,
for their iniquitie, and the land of the Caldeans, and will make it
perpetuall desolations.<note> 2. Chron. 36.22. eszr. 1.1. chap. 29.10. dan. 9.2. , Heb. visite vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I will
bring vpon that land all my words which I haue pronounced against
it, euen all that is written in this booke, which Ieremiah hath
prophecied against all the nations.</ab>
<ab n="14">For many
nations and great kings shall serue themselues of them also: and I
will recompense them according to their deeds, and according to the
workes of their owne hands.<note> Cha.27.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ For thus
saith the Lord God of Israel vnto me, Take the wine cup of this
furie at my hand, and cause all the nations, to whom I send thee,
to drinke it.<note> Isa.51.17 psal.75.8. iob.21.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And they shall
drinke, and be moued, and be mad, because of the sworde that I will
send among them.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then tooke I
the cuppe at the Lords hand, and made all the nations to drinke,
vnto whom the Lord had sent me:</ab>
<ab n="18">To wit
Ierusalem, and the cities of Iudah, and the kings thereof, and the
princes thereof, to make them a desolation, an astonishment, an
hissing, and a curse (as it is this day:)</ab>
<ab n="19">Pharaoh king of
Egypt, and his seruants, and his princes, and all his
people:</ab>
<ab n="20">And all the
mingled people, &amp; all the kings of the land of Uz: and all the
kings of the land of the Philistines, and Ashkelon, and Azzah, and
Ekron, and the remnant of Ashdod:</ab>

<fw>A cup of furie for all nations.</fw>
<ab n="21">Edom, and Moab,
and the children of Ammon:<note> Chap.49. 7, &amp;c. , Chap.48. , Chap.49.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And all the
kings of Tyrus, and all the kings of Zidon, and the kings of the
yles which are beyond the sea:<note> Chap. 47. , Or, region by the Sea side. , Chap. 49. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Dedan, and
Tema, and Buz, and all that are in the vtmost corners:<note> Chap. 49. 28. , Heb. cut off into corners, or hauing the corners of the haire polled, chap. 9.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And all the
kings of Arabia, and all the kings of the mingled people that dwell
in the desert:<note> Chap.49. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And all the
kings of Zimri, and all the kings of Elam, and all the kings of the
Medes:<note> Chap.49. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And all the
kings of the North, farre and neere, one with another, and all the
kingdomes of the world, which are vpon the face of the earth, and
the king of Sheshach shall drinke after them.</ab>
<ab n="27">Therefore thou
shalt say vnto them, Thus saith the Lord of hosts, the God of
Israel, Drinke ye and bee drunken, and spue and fall, and rise no
more, because of the sword which I wil send among you.</ab>
<ab n="28">And it shall
bee, if they refuse to take the cup at thine hand to drinke, then
shalt thou say vnto them, Thus saith the Lord of hosts, Yee shall
certainely drinke.</ab>
<ab n="29">For loe, I
begin to bring euill on the citie, which is called by my name, and
should yee be vtterly vnpunished? ye shall not be vnpunished: for I
will cal for a sword vpon all the inhabitants of the earth, saith
the Lord of hosts.<note> 1.Pet.4. 17. , Heb. vpon which my Name is called.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Therefore
prophecie thou against them all these wordes, and say vnto them,
The Lord shall roare from an high, and vtter his voice from his
holy habitation, he shall mightily roare vpon his habitation, hee
shall giue a shout, as they that treade the grapes, against all the
inhabitants of the earth.<note> Ioel 3. 16 amos 1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">A noise shall
come euen to the ends of the earth; for the Lord hath a
controuersie with the nations: hee will pleade with all flesh, he
will giue them that are wicked to the sword, saith the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="32">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, Behold, euill shall goe forth from nation to nation,
and a great whirlewinde shall be raised vp from the coasts of the
earth.</ab>

<fw>Shepherds howling.</fw>
<ab n="33">And the slaine
of the Lord shall be at that day from one end of the earth euen
vnto the other ende of the earth: they shall not be lamented,
neither gathered nor buried, they shall be doung vpon the
ground.<note> Cha.16.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Howle
yee shepheards and cry, and wallow your selues in the ashes ye
principall of the flocke: for the dayes of your slaughter, and of
your dispersions are accomplished, and yee shall fall like a
pleasant vessell.<note> Chap.4.8 and 6.26. , Hebr. your dayes for slaughter. , Hebr. a vessell of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And the
shepheards shall haue no way to flee, nor the principall of the
flocke to escape.<note> Heb. flight shall perish from the shepheards, and escaping from &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">A voyce of the
cry of the shepheards, and an howling of the principall of the
flocke shall be heard: for the Lord hath spoiled their
pasture.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the
peaceable habitations are cut downe because of the fierce anger of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="38">He hath
forsaken his couert, as the Lyon: for their land is desolate,
because of the fiercenesse of the oppressour, and because of his
fierce anger.<note> Hebr. a desolation.</note></ab>



</div>