<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-23-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-23-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Hee prophecieth a restauration of
the scattered flocke. 5 Christ shall rule and saue them. 9 Against
false prophets, 33 and mockers of the true prophets.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe bee vnto the
pastors that destroy and scatter the sheepe of my pasture, saith
the Lord.<note> Ezech.34. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Therefore thus
saith the Lord God of Israel against the pastors that feed my
people; Yee haue scattered my flocke and driuen them away, and haue
not visited them; behold I will visite vpon you the euill of your
doings, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I wil gather
the remnant of my flocke, out of all countreis whither I haue
driuen them, and will bring them againe to their foldes, and they
shalbe fruitfull and increase.</ab>

<fw>False pastours are threatned.</fw>
<ab n="4">And I will set
vp shepheards ouer them which shall feed them, and they shal feare
no more nor be dismaied, neither shall they bee lacking, saith the
Lord.<note> Chap. 3. 15. ezech. 34.11, 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Behold,
the daies come, saith the Lord, that I wil raise vnto Dauid a
righteous branch, and a King shall reigne and prosper, and shall
execute iudgement and iustice in the earth.<note> Chap.33.14,15. isa. 4.2. and 40. 11. dan.9. 24. iohn 1. 45.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In his dayes
Iudah shalbe saued, and Israel shall dwell safely, and this is his
Name whereby hee shall be called, The Lord Our
Righteousnes.<note> Deut. 33. 28. , Hebr. Iehouah-tsidkenu.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore
behold, the dayes come, saith the Lord, that they shall no more
say; The Lord liueth, which brought vp the children of Israel out
of the land of Egypt:<note> Iere. 16. 14, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But, The Lord
liueth, which brought vp, and which led the seed of the house of
Israel out of the North countrey, and from all countreis whither I
had driuen them, and they shall dwell in their owne land.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Mine
heart within me is broken because of the prophets, all my bones
shake: I am like a drunken man (and like a man whom wine hath
ouercome) because of the Lord, and because of the words of his
Holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="10">For the land is
full of adulterers, for because of swearing the land mourneth: the
pleasant places of the wildernes are dried vp, and their course is
euil, and their force is not right.<note> Or, cursing. , Or, violence.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For both
prophet and priest are prophane, yea in my house haue I found their
wickednesse, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore their
way shalbe vnto them as slippery wayes in the darkenes: they shalbe
driuen on and fall therein: for I will bring euill vpon them, euen
the yeere of their visitation, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And I haue
seene folly in the prophets of Samaria; they prophecied in Baal,
and caused my people Israel to erre.<note> Or, an absurd thing. Hebr. vnsauoury.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I haue seene
also in the prophets of Ierusalem an horrible thing: they commit
adultery, and walke in lies: they strengthen also the hands of
euill doers, that none doeth returne from his wickednesse: they are
all of them vnto me as Sodom, and the inhabitants thereof as
Gomorrah.<note> Or, filthinesse. , Isa. 1.9.</note></ab>

<fw>False prophets.</fw>
<ab n="15">Therefore thus
saith the Lord of hosts concerning the Prophets; Behold, I will
feede them with wormewood, and make them drinke the water of gall:
for from the Prophets of Ierusalem is profanenesse gone forth into
all the land.<note> Cha.8. 14 and 9. 15. , Or, hypocrisie.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, Hearken not vnto the wordes of the prophets that
prophecie vnto you; they make you vaine: they speake a vision of
their owne heart, and not out of the mouth of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">They say still
vnto them that despise me; The Lord hath sayde, Yee shall haue
peace; and they say vnto euery one that walketh after the
imagination of his owne heart, No euill shall come vpon
you.<note> Cha.6.14. and 8.11. eze.13.10. zech.10.2. , Or, stubbornesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For who hath
stood in the counsell of the Lord, and hath perceiued, and heard
his word? who hath marked his word, and heard it?<note> Or, secret.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Behold, a
whirlewinde of the Lord is gone foorth in furie, euen a grieuous
whirlewinde, it shall fall grieuously vpon the head of the
wicked.<note> Chap.30.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The anger of
the Lord shall not returne, vntill hee haue executed, and til he
haue performed the thoughts of his heart: in the latter dayes ye
shall consider it perfectly.<note> Chap.30. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">I haue not sent
these prophets, yet they ranne: I haue not spoken to them, yet they
prophecied.<note> Chap. 14. 14. and 27. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But if they had
stood in my counsell, and had caused my people to heare my wordes,
then they should haue turned them from their euil way, and from the
euill of their doings.</ab>
<ab n="23">Am I a God at
hand, sayth the Lord, and not a God afarre off?</ab>
<ab n="24">Can any hide
himselfe in secret places that I shall not see him, saith the Lord
? doe not I fill heauen and earth, sayth the Lord ?<note> Psal. 139. 7. &amp;c. amos 9.2, 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">I haue heard
what the prophets said, that prophecie lyes in my Name, saying; I
haue dreamed, I haue dreamed.</ab>
<ab n="26">How long shall
this bee in the heart of the prophets that prophecie lies? yea they
are prophets of the deceit of their owne heart;</ab>
<ab n="27">Which thinke to
cause my people to forget my Name by their dreames which they tell
euery man to his neighbour, as their fathers haue forgotten my
Name, for Baal.<note> Iudg. 3. 7. and 8.33.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods word, fire.</fw>
<ab n="28">The prophet
that hath a dreame, let him tell a dreame; and hee that hath my
word, let him speake my word faithfully: what is the chaffe to the
wheat, sayth the Lord ?<note> Heb. with whom is.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Is not my word
like as a fire, saith the Lord ? and like a hammer that breaketh
the rocke in pieces?</ab>
<ab n="30">Therefore,
behold, I am against the prophets, sayth the Lord, that steale my
worde euery one from his neighbour.<note> Deut. 18. 20. cha. 14. 14, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Beholde, I am
against the prophets, saith the Lord, that vse their tongues, and
say; He sayth.<note> Or, that smooth their tongues.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Behold, I am
against them that prophecie false dreames, sayeth the Lord, and doe
tell them, and cause my people to erre by their lyes and by their
lightnesse, yet I sent them not, nor commanded them: therefore they
shall not profite this people at all, sayth the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And when
this people, or the prophet, or a priest shall aske thee, saying;
What is the burden of the Lord ? thou shalt then say vnto them;
What burden? I will euen forsake you, saith the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="34">And as for the
prophet, and the priest, and the people that shal say, The burden
of the Lord, I will euen punish that man and his house.<note> Heb. visite vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Thus shall yee
say euery one to his neighbour, and euery one to his brother, What
hath the Lord answered? and what hath the Lord spoken?</ab>
<ab n="36">And the burden
of the Lord shall yee mention no more: for euery mans word shall be
his burden: for yee haue peruerted the words of the liuing God, of
the Lord of hostes our God.</ab>
<ab n="37">Thus shalt thou
say to the prophet, What hath the Lord answered thee? and what hath
the Lord spoken?</ab>
<ab n="38">But sith ye
say, The burden of the Lord; therefore thus sayeth the Lord,
Because you say this word, The burden of the Lord, and I haue sent
vnto you, saying; Ye shall not say, The burden of the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="39">Therefore
beholde, I, euen I will vtterly forget you, and I will forsake you,
and the citie that I gaue you and your fathers, and cast you out of
my presence.</ab>

<fw>Baskets of figs.</fw>
<ab n="40">And I will
bring an euerlasting reproch vpon you, and a perpetuall shame,
which shall not be forgotten.<note> Chap. 20. 11.</note></ab>



</div>