<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-30-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 God sheweth Ieremiah the returne
of the Iewes. 4 After their trouble, they shall haue deliuerance.
10 He comforteth Iacob. 18 Their returne shalbe gracious. 20 Wrath
shall fall on the wicked.</head>

<ab n="1">The word that
came to Ieremiah from the Lord, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus speaketh
the Lord God of Israel, saying; Write thee all the wordes that I
haue spoken vnto thee, in a booke.</ab>

<fw>Deliuerance after trouble,
promised.</fw>
<ab n="3">For loe, the
dayes come, saith the Lord, that I will bring againe the captiuitie
of my people Israel and Iudah, saith the Lord, and I wil cause them
to returne to the land, that I gaue to their fathers, and they
shall possesse it.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And these
are the words that the Lord spake concerning Israel, and concerning
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="5">For thus sayth
the Lord, Wee haue heard a voice of trembling, of feare, and not of
peace.<note> Or, there is feare, and not peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Aske yee now and
see whether a man doeth trauaile with child? wherefore doe I see
euery man with his handes on his loynes, as a woman in trauaile,
and all faces are turned into palenesse?<note> Heb. a male</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Alas, for that
day is great, so that none is like it: it is euen the time of
Iacobs trouble, but he shall be saued out of it.<note> Ioel 2.11. amos 5. 18. zeph.1.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For it shall
come to passe in that day, saith the Lord of hostes, that I will
breake his yoke from off thy necke, and will burst thy bondes, and
strangers shall no more serue themselues of him.</ab>
<ab n="9">But they shall
serue the Lord their God, and Dauid their King whom I will raise vp
vnto them.<note> Ezek.34.23. and 37.24. hose. 3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶
Therefore feare thou not, O my seruant Iacob, saith the Lord,
neither be dismayed, O Israel; for loe, I will saue thee from
afarre, and thy seede from the land of their captiuitie, and Iacob
shall returne, and shall be in rest, and be quiet, and none shall
make him afraid.<note> Isa.41.13. and 43.5. and 44.1. cha. 46.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For I am with
thee, sayeth the Lord, to saue thee: though I make a full end of
all nations whither I haue scattered thee, yet will I not make a
full ende of thee: but I will correct thee in measure, and will not
leaue thee altogether vnpunished.<note> Psal.6.1. chap.10.24. and 46.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For thus saith
the Lord, Thy bruise is incurable, and thy wound is
grieuous.</ab>
<ab n="13">There is none
to pleade thy cause, that thou mayest bee bonnd vp: thou hast no
healing medicines.<note> Heb. for binding vp, or pressing.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">All thy louers
haue forgotten thee: they seeke thee not, for I haue wounded thee
with the wound of an enemy, with the chastisement of a cruell one,
for the multitude of thine iniquitie: because thy sinnes were
increased.</ab>

<fw>Deliuerance after trouble,
promised.</fw>
<ab n="15">Why cryest thou
for thine affliction? thy sorrow is incurable, for the multitude of
thine iniquitie: because thy sinnes were increased, I haue done
these things vnto thee.<note> Chap. 13.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore all
they that deuoure thee shalbe deuoured, and all thine aduersaries
euery one of them shall goe into captiuitie: and they that spoile
thee shall be a spoile, and all that pray vpon thee, will I giue
for a pray.<note> Exod.23. 22. isai. 41.11</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For I will
restore health vnto thee, and I will heale thee of thy wounds,
sayth the Lord, because they called thee an outcast, saying; This
is Zion whom no man seeketh after.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Thus
saith the Lord, Behold, I will bring againe the captiuitie of
Iacobs tents, and haue mercie on his dwelling places: and the citie
shall be builded vpon her owne heape, and the palace shall remaine
after the manner thereof.<note> Or, little hill.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And out of them
shall proceede thankesgiuing, and the voice of them that make
merry; and I will multiply them, and they shall not be few: I will
also glorifie them, and they shall not be small.</ab>
<ab n="20">Their children
also shall be as aforetime, and their congregation shalbe
established before me, and I will punish all that oppresse
them.</ab>
<ab n="21">And their
nobles shall be of themselues, and their gouernour shall proceede
from the middest of them, and I will cause him to draw neere, and
hee shall approch vnto me: for who is this that engaged his heart
to approch vnto me, sayth the Lord ?</ab>
<ab n="22">And yee shall
be my people, and I will be your God.<note> Cha.24.7. and 31.33. and 32. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Behold, the
whirlewinde of the Lord goeth foorth with furie, a continuing
whirlewinde, it shall fall with paine vpon the head of the
wicked.<note> Chap.23. 19,20. , Heb. cutting. , Or, remaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The fierce
anger of the Lord shall not returne, vntill hee haue done it, and
vntill he haue performed the intents of his heart: in the latter
dayes ye shall consider it.</ab>



</div>