<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_44" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-43-44.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-44-45.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIV.</head>
<head>1 Iosephs policie to stay his
brethren. 14 Iudahs humble supplication to Ioseph.</head>

<ab n="1">And hee
commaunded the steward of his house, saying, Fill the mens sackes
with food, as much as they can carie, and put euery mans money in
his sacks mouth.<note> Heb. him that was ouer his house</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And put my cup,
the siluer cup, in the sackes mouth of the youngest, and his corne
money: and he did according to the word that Ioseph had
spoken.</ab>
<ab n="3">Assoone as the
morning was light, the men were sent away, they, and their
asses.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when they
were gone out of the citie, and not yet farre off, Ioseph said vnto
his steward, Up, follow after the men; and when thou doest ouertake
them, say vnto them, Wherefore haue ye rewarded euill for
good?</ab>

<fw>A cup put in Beniamins sacke.</fw>
<ab n="5">Is not this it,
in which my lord drinketh? and whereby indeed he diuineth? ye haue
done euill in so doing.<note> Or, maketh triall.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And he
ouertooke them, and he spake vnto them these same words.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they said
vnto him, Wherefore saith my lord these words? God forbid that thy
seruants should doe according to this thing.</ab>
<ab n="8">Behold, the money
which wee found in our sackes mouthes, wee brought againe vnto
thee, out of the land of Canaan: how then should wee steale out of
thy lords house, siluer or golde?</ab>
<ab n="9">With whom soeuer
of thy seruants it be found, both let him die, and we also will be
my lords bondmen.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said, Now
also let it be according vnto your wordes: hee with whom it is
found, shall be my seruant: and ye shall be blamelesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then they
speedily tooke downe euery man his sacke to the ground, and opened
euery man his sacke.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he searched,
and began at the eldest, and left at the yongest: and the cup was
found in Beniamins sacke.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then they rent
their clothes, and laded euery man his asse, and returned to the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And Iudah
and his brethren came to Iosephs house: (for he was yet there) and
they fell before him on the ground.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Ioseph said
vnto them, What deed is this that ye haue done? wote ye not, that
such a man as I can certainely diuine?<note> Or, make triall?</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Iudah said,
What shall wee say vnto my lord? what shal we speake? or how shall
we cleare our selues? God hath found out the iniquitie of thy
seruants: beholde, wee are my lords seruants, both we, and he also
with whom the cup is found.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said, God
forbid that I should doe so: but the man in whose hand the cup is
found, he shal be my seruant; and as for you, get you vp in peace
vnto your father.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then
Iudah came neere vnto him, and said, Oh my lord, let thy seruant, I
pray thee, speake a word in my lords eares, &amp; let not thine
anger burne against thy seruant: for thou art euen as
Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="19">My lord asked
his seruants, saying; Haue ye a father, or a brother?</ab>

<fw>Iudahs supplication.</fw>
<ab n="20">And we said vnto
my lord, Wee haue a father, an olde man, and a childe of his old
age, a little one: and his brother is dead, and he alone is left of
his mother, and his father loueth him.</ab>
<ab n="21">And thou saidst
vnto thy seruants, Bring him downe vnto mee, that I may set mine
eyes vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="22">And we said vnto
my lord, The lad cannot leaue his father: for if hee should leaue
his father, his father would die.</ab>
<ab n="23">And thou saidst
vnto thy seruants, Except your yongest brother come downe with you,
you shall see my face no more.<note> Chap. 43. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And it came to
passe when wee came vp vnto thy seruant my father, we told him the
words of my lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">And our father
said, Goe againe, and buy vs a little food.</ab>
<ab n="26">And we saide,
Wee cannot goe downe: if our yongest brother be with vs, then will
we goe downe: for wee may not see the mans face, except our yongest
brother be with vs.</ab>
<ab n="27">And thy seruant
my father said vnto vs, Ye know that my wife bare me two
sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the one went
out from me, and I said, Surely he is torne in pieces: and I saw
him not since.<note> Chap. 37. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And if ye take
this also from me, and mischiefe befall him, ye shall bring downe
my gray haires with sorrow to the graue.</ab>
<ab n="30">Now therefore
when I come to thy seruant my father, and the lad bee not with vs;
(seeing that his life is bound vp in the lads life.)</ab>
<ab n="31">It shall come to
passe, when he seeth that the lad is not with vs, that he will die,
and thy seruants shall bring downe the gray haires of thy seruant
our father with sorrow to the graue.</ab>
<ab n="32">For thy seruant
became surety for the lad vnto my father, saying, If I bring him
not vnto thee, then I shall beare the blame to my father, for
euer.<note> Chap. 43. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Now therefore, I
pray thee, let thy seruant abide in stead of the lad, a bondman to
my lord, and let the lad goe vp with his brethren.</ab>
<ab n="34">For how shall I
goe vp to my father, and the lad be not with mee, lest peraduenture
I see the euill that shall come on my father?<note> Hebr. finde my father.</note></ab>



</div>