<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_46" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-45-46.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-46-47.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLVI.</head>
<head>1 Iacob is comforted by God at
Beersheba. 5 Thence hee with his company goeth into Egypt. 8 The
number of his family that went into Egypt. 28 Ioseph meeteth Iacob.
31 Hee instructeth his brethren how to answere to
Pharaoh.</head>

<ab n="1">And Israel tooke
his iourney with all that hee had, and came to Beersheba, and
offered sacrifices vnto the God of his father Isaac.</ab>
<ab n="2">And God spake
vnto Israel in the visions of the night, and said, Iacob, Iacob.
And he said, Here am I.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he said, I am
God, the God of thy father, feare not to goe downe into Egypt: for
I will there make of thee a great nation.</ab>
<ab n="4">I will goe downe
with thee into Egypt; and I will also surely bring thee vp againe:
and Ioseph shall put his hand vpon thine eyes.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Iacob rose vp
from Beersheba: and the sonnes of Israel caried Iacob their father,
and their litle ones, and their wiues, in the wagons which Pharaoh
had sent to cary him.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they tooke
their cattell, and their goods which they had gotten in the land of
Canaan, and came into Egypt, Iacob, and all his seed with
him:<note> Iosh.24. 4. psal. 105. 23. esai.52. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">His sonnes, and
his sonnes sonnes with him, his daughters, and his sonnes
daughters, and all his seed brought he with him into Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And these
are the names of the children of Israel, which came into Egypt,
Iacob and his sonnes: Reuben Iacobs first borne;<note> Exod. 1.1. and 6.14. num. 26.8. and 1.chro. 5.1. , Num. 26. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the sonnes of
Reuben, Hanoch, and Phallu, and Hezron, and Carmi.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
sonnes of Simeon: Iemuel, and Iamin, and Ohad, and Iachin, and
Zohar, and Shaul the sonne of a Canaanitish woman.<note> Exod. 6. 15. 1.chro. 4.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
sonnes of Leui: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<note> 1.Chro.6. 1.</note></ab>

<fw>Iacobs off-spring.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
sonnes of Iudah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Pharez, and Zerah:
But Er &amp; Onan died in the land of Canaan. And the sonnes of
Pharez, were Hezron, and Hamul.<note> 1.Chro.2. 3. and 4.21. chap. 38. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And the
sonnes of Issachar: Tola, and Phuuah, and Iob, and Shimron.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And the
sonnes of Zebulun: Sered, and Elon, and Iahleel.<note> 1.Chron. 7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">These bee the
sonnes of Leah, which she bare vnto Iacob in Padan-Aram, with his
daughter Dinah: all the soules of his sonnes and his daughters,
were thirtie and three.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
sonnes of Gad: Ziphion, and Haggi, Shuni, and Ezbon, Eri, and
Arodi, and Areli.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
sonnes of Asher: Iimnah, and Ishuah, and Isui, and Beriah, and
Serah their sister: And the sonnes of Beriah: Heber, and
Malchiel.<note> 1.Chro. 7. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">These are the
sonnes of Zilpah, whome Laban gaue to Leah his daughter: and these
she bare vnto Iacob, euen sixteene soules.</ab>
<ab n="19">The sonnes of
Rachel Iacobs wife: Ioseph, and Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And vnto
Ioseph in the lande of Egypt, were borne Manasseh and Ephraim,
which Asenath the daughter of Poti-pherah Priest of On bare vnto
him.<note> Chap. 41. 50. , Or, Prince.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And the
sonnes of Beniamin were Belah, and Becher, and Ashbel, Gera, and
Naaman, Ehi and Rosh, Muppim, and Huppim, and Ard.<note> 1.Chron. 7.6. &amp; 8.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">These are the
sonnes of Rachel which were borne to Iacob: all the soules were
fourteene.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
sonnes of Dan: Hushim.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
sonnes of Naphtali: Iahzeel, and Guni, and Iezer, and
Shillem.</ab>
<ab n="25">These are the
sonnes of Bilhah, which Laban gaue vnto Rachel his daughter, and
she bare these vnto Iacob: all the soules were seuen.</ab>
<ab n="26">All the soules
that came with Iacob into Egypt, which came out of his loines,
besides Iacobs sonnes wiues, all the soules were threescore and
sixe.<note> Deut. 10. 22. , Heb. thigh.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And the sonnes
of Ioseph, which were borne him in Egypt, were two soules: all the
soules of the house of Iacob, which came into Egypt, were
threescore and ten.</ab>

<fw>Ioseph meeteth him.</fw>
<ab n="28">¶ And he
sent Iudah before him vnto Ioseph, to direct his face vnto Goshen,
and they came into the lande of Goshen.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Ioseph made
ready his charet, and went vp to meet Israel his father, to Goshen,
and presented himselfe vnto him: and he fell on his necke, and wept
on his necke a good while.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Israel saide
vnto Ioseph, Now let me die, since I haue seene thy face, because
thou art yet aliue.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Ioseph said
vnto his brethren, and vnto his fathers house, I will goe vp, and
shew Pharaoh, and say vnto him, My brethren, &amp; my fathers
house, which were in the land of Canaan, are come vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the men are
sheapheards, for their trade hath bene to feed cattell: and they
haue brought their flocks, and their heards, and all that they
haue.<note> Hebr. they are men of cattell.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And it shall
come to passe when Pharaoh shall call you, and shall say, What is
your occupation?</ab>
<ab n="34">That ye shall
say, Thy seruants trade hath bene about cattell, from our youth
euen vntill now, both we, and also our fathers: that ye may dwell
in the land of Goshen; for euery shepheard is an abomination vnto
the Egyptians.</ab>



</div>