<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJeremiah_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 The vtter reiection, and manifold
iudgements of the Iewes. 10 Ieremiah complayning of their spight,
receiueth a promise for himselfe, 12 and a threatning for them. 15
He praieth, 19 and receiueth a gracious promise.</head>


<fw>Prayers reiected.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then said the
Lord vnto me, Though Moses and Samuel stood before me, yet my minde
could not be toward this people, cast them out of my sight, and let
them goe foorth.<note> Eze.14. 14. , Exod. 32. 14. , 1. Sam 7. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it shall
come to passe if they say vnto thee, Whither shall wee goe foorth?
then thou shalt tell them; Thus saith the Lord, Such as are for
death to death; and such as are for the sword, to the sword; and
such as are for the famine, to the famine; and such as are for the
captiuitie, to the captiuitie.<note> Chap. 43. 11. zach.11. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And I will
appoint ouer them foure kindes, saith the Lord, the sword to slay,
and the dogs to teare, and the foules of the heauen, and the beasts
of the earth to deuoure and destroy.<note> Leuit.26. 16. , Hebr. families.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I will cause
them to be remoued into all kingdomes of the earth, because of
Manasseh the sonne of Hezekiah king of Iudah, for that which hee
did in Ierusalem.<note> Hebr. I wil giue them for a moouing. , Deut.28. 25. cha.24. 9. , 2.Kin.21. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For who shall
haue pitie vpon thee, O Ierusalem? or who shall bemoane thee? or
who shall goe aside to aske how thou doest?<note> Hebr. to aske of thy thy peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou hast
forsaken me, saith the Lord, thou art gone backward: therefore will
I stretch out my hand against thee, and destroy thee, I am wearie
with repenting.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I will fanne
them with a fanne in the gates of the land: I will bereaue them of
children, I wil destroy my people, sith they returne not from their
waies.<note> Or, whatsoeuer is deare.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Their widowes
are increased to me aboue the sand of the seas: I haue brought vpon
them against the mother of the yongmen, a spoiler at noone day: I
haue caused him to fall vpon it suddenly, and terrors vpon the
citie.<note> Or, against the mother citie, a yong man spoiling, &amp;c. Or, aagainst the mother and the yong men.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">She that hath
borne seuen, languisheth: she hath giuen vp the ghost: her sunne is
gone down while it was yet day: shee hath bene ashamed and
confounded, and the residue of them will I deliuer to the sword
before their enemies, saith the Lord.<note> Amos 8.9.</note></ab>

<fw>God saueth his.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ Woe is
mee, my mother, that that thou hast borne me a man of strife, and a
man of contention to the whole earth: I haue neither lent on
vsurie, nor men haue lent to me on vsurie, yet euery one of them
doeth curse me.<note> Iob 3.1. &amp;c, cha.20.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord said,
Uerely it shall be well with thy remnant, verely I will cause the
enemie to intreat thee well in the time of euill, and in the time
of affliction.<note> Or, I will entreat the enemie for thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Shall yron
breake the Northren yron, and the steele?</ab>
<ab n="13">Thy substance
and thy treasures will I giue to the spoile without price, and that
for all thy sinnes, euen in all thy borders.<note> Cha. 17.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I will make
thee to passe with thine enemies, into a land which thou knowest
not: for a fire is kindled in mine anger, which shall burne vpon
you.<note> Deut. 32. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ O Lord,
thou knowest, remember me, and visit me, and reuenge me of my
persecutors, take mee not away in thy long suffering: know that for
thy sake I haue suffered rebuke.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thy wordes were
found, and I did eate them, and thy word was vnto mee, the ioy and
reioycing of mine heart: for I am called by thy Name, O Lord God of
hostes.<note> Eze.3.3. reuel.10.9. , Heb. thy Name is called vpon me.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">I sate not in
the assembly of the mockers, nor reioyced: I sate alone because of
thy hand: for thou hast filled me with indignation.</ab>
<ab n="18">Why is my paine
perpetuall? and my wound incurable which refuseth to be healed?
wilt thou be altogether vnto me as a lyar, and as waters that
faile?<note> Chap. 30. 15. , Heb. be not sure?</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Therfore
thus saith the Lord; If thou returne, then will I bring thee
againe, and thou shalt stand before me: and if thou take forth the
precious from the vile, thou shalt be as my mouth: let them returne
vnto thee, but returne not thou vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="20">And I will make
thee vnto this people a fenced brasen wall, and they shall fight
against thee, but they shall not preuaile against thee: for I am
with thee to saue thee, and to deliuer thee, sayth the
Lord.<note> Cha.1.18. and 6.27. , Chap.20. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And I will
deliuer thee out of the hand of the wicked, and I will redeeme thee
out of the hand of the terrible.</ab>



</div>