<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-13-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Iob reprooueth his friends of
partialitie. 14 He professeth his confidence in God: 20 and
entreateth to knowe his owne sinnes, and Gods purpose in afflicting
him.</head>

<ab n="1">Loe, mine eye
hath seene all this, mine eare hath heard and vnderstood
it.</ab>
<ab n="2">What yee know,
the same doe I know also, I am not inferiour vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="3">Surely I would
speake to the Almighty, &amp; I desire to reason with God.</ab>
<ab n="4">But ye are
forgers of lies, yee are all Physicians of no value.</ab>
<ab n="5">O that you
would altogether hold your peace, &amp; it should be your
wisdome.</ab>
<ab n="6">Heare now my
reasoning, and hearken to the pleadings of my lips.</ab>
<ab n="7">Wil you speake
wickedly for God? and talke deceitfully for him?</ab>
<ab n="8">Will ye accept
his person? Will yee contend for God?</ab>
<ab n="9">Is it good that
hee should search you out? or as one man mocketh another, doe ye so
mocke him?</ab>
<ab n="10">He will surely
reprooue you, if yee doe secretly accept persons.</ab>
<ab n="11">Shall not his
excellencie make you afraid? and his dread fall vpon you?</ab>
<ab n="12">Your
remembrances are like vnto ashes, your bodies to bodies of
clay.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hold your
peace, let me alone that I may speake, and let come on me what
will.<note> Heb. be silent from me</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Wherefore doe
I take my flesh in my teeth, and put my life in mine hand?</ab>
<ab n="15">Though hee
slay mee, yet will I trust in him: but I will maintaine mine owne
wayes before him.<note> Heb. proue, or argue.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Hee also shall
be my saluation: for an hypocrite shall not come before
him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Heare
diligently my speach, and my declaration with your eares.</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold now, I
haue ordered my cause, I know that I shall be iustified.</ab>

<fw>The breuitie of mans life.</fw>
<ab n="19">Who is hee
that will plead with me? for now if I hold my tongue, I shall giue
vp the ghost.</ab>
<ab n="20">Only doe not
two things vnto me: then will I not hide my selfe from
thee.</ab>
<ab n="21">Withdrawe
thine hand far from me: and let not thy dread make mee
afraid.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then call
thou, and I will answere: or let me speake, and answere thou
mee.</ab>
<ab n="23">How many are
mine iniquities and sinnes? make mee to knowe my transgression, and
my sinne.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore
hidest thou thy face, and holdest me for thine enemie?</ab>
<ab n="25">Wilt thou
breake a leafe driuen to and fro? and wilt thou pursue the drie
stubble?</ab>
<ab n="26">For thou
writest bitter things against mee, and makest me to possesse the
iniquities of my youth.<note> Psal. 25.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Thou puttest
my feete also in the stockes, and lookest narrowly vnto all my
pathes; thou settest a print vpon the heeles of my
feete.<note> Heb. obseruest. , Heb. roots.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And hee, as a
rotten thing consumeth, as a garment that is moth-eaten.</ab>



</div>