<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>Zophar sheweth the state and portion
of the wicked.</head>

<ab n="1">Then answered
Zophar the Naamathite, and saide,</ab>
<ab n="2">Therefore doe
my thoughts cause mee to answere, and for this I make
haste.<note> Hebr. my haste is in me.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I haue heard
the checke of my reproach, and the spirit of my vnderstanding
causeth me to answere.</ab>
<ab n="4">Knowest thou
not this of old, since man was placed vpon earth,</ab>
<ab n="5">That the
triumphing of the wicked is short, and the ioy of the hypocrite but
for a moment?<note> Psal.37. 37. , Hebr. from neere.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Though his
excellencie mount vp to the heauens, and his head reach vnto the
clouds:<note> Heb. cloud.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Yet he shall
perish for euer, like his owne doung: they which haue seene him,
shall say, Where is he?</ab>
<ab n="8">He shall flie
away as a dreame, and shall not be found: yea he shalbe chased away
as a vision of the night.</ab>
<ab n="9">The eye also
which saw him, shall see him no more; neither shall his place any
more behold him.</ab>
<ab n="10">His children
shall seeke to please the poore, and his hands shall restore their
goods.<note> Or, the poore shall oppresse his children.</note></ab>

<fw>The wickeds portion.</fw>
<ab n="11">His bones are
ful of the sinne of his youth, which shall ye downe with him in the
dust.</ab>
<ab n="12">Though
wickednes be sweet in his mouth, though hee hide it vnder his
tongue;</ab>
<ab n="13">Though he
spare it, and forsake it not, but keepe it stil within his
mouth:<note> Hebr. in the midst of his palate.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Yet his meate
in his bowels is turned, it is the gall of Aspes within
him.</ab>
<ab n="15">He hath
swallowed downe riches, and hee shall vomite them vp againe: God
shall cast them out of his belly.</ab>
<ab n="16">He shall sucke
the poison of Aspes: the vipers tongue shall slay him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hee shall not
see the riuers, the floods, the brookes of hony and
butter.<note> Or, streaming brooks.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">That which he
laboured for, shall he restore, &amp; shall not swallow it downe:
according to his substance shall the restitution bee, and hee shall
not reioyce therein.<note> Hebr. according to the substance of his exchange.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Because hee
hath oppressed, and hath forsaken the poore; because he hath
violently taken away an house which he builded not:<note> Hebr. crushed. , Eccles.5. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Surely he
shall not feele quietnesse in his belly, hee shall not saue of that
which he desired.<note> Heb. know.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">There shall
none of his meat be left, therefore shall no man looke for his
goods.<note> Or, there shalbe none left for his meats.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">In the
fulnesse of his sufficiencie, he shalbe in straites: euery hand of
the wicked shall come vpon him.<note> Or, troublesome.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">When he is
about to fill his belly, God shall cast the furie of his wrath vpon
him, and shall raine it vpon him while he is eating.</ab>
<ab n="24">He shall flee
from the iron weapon, and the bow of steele shall strike him
through.</ab>
<ab n="25">It is drawen,
and commeth out of the body; yea the glistering sword commeth out
of his gall; terrours are vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="26">All darknesse
shalbe hid in his secret places: a fire not blowen shall consume
him; it shall goe ill with him that is left in his
tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="27">The heauen
shall reueale his iniquitie: and the earth shall rise vp against
him.</ab>
<ab n="28">The increase
of his house shall depart, and his goods shall flow away in the day
of his wrath.</ab>
<ab n="29">This is the
portion of a wicked man from God, and the heritage appointed vnto
him by God.<note> Hebr. of his decree from God.</note></ab>



</div>