<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-36-38.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 Elihu sheweth how God is iust in
his wayes. 16 How Iobs sinnes hinder Gods blessings. 24 Gods works
are to be magnified.</head>

<ab n="1">Elihu also
proceeded, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Suffer mee a
little, and I will shewe thee, that I haue yet to speake on Gods
behalfe.<note> Heb. that there are yet words for God.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I will fetch my
knowledge from afarre, and will ascribe righteousnesse to my
Maker.</ab>
<ab n="4">For truely my
words shall not be false: he that is perfect in knowledge, is with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="5">Behold, God is
mightie, and despiseth not any: he is mightie in strength and
wisedome.<note> Heb. heart</note></ab>

<fw>The causes of Gods punishments.</fw>
<ab n="6">He preserueth
not the life of the wicked: but giueth right to the
poore.<note> Or, afflicted.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Hee withdraweth
not his eyes from the righteous: but with kings are they on the
throne, yea he doth establish them for euer, and they are
exalted.<note> Psal.34. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And if they bee
bound in fetters, and be holden in cords of affliction:</ab>
<ab n="9">Then hee
sheweth them their worke, and their transgressions, that they haue
exceeded.</ab>
<ab n="10">He openeth
also their eare to discipline, and commandeth that they returne
from iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="11">If they obey
and serue him, they shall spend their dayes in prosperitie, and
their yeeres in pleasures.<note> Iob 21.13</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But if they
obey not, they shall perish by the sword, and they shall die
without knowledge.<note> Heb. they shall passe away by the sword.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But the
hypocrites in heart heape vp wrath: they crie not when he bindeth
them.</ab>
<ab n="14">They die in
youth, and their life is among the vncleane.<note> Hebr. their soule dieth. , Or, Sodomites.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">He deliuereth
the poore in his affliction, and openeth their eares in
oppression.<note> Or, affected.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Euen so would
he haue remooued thee out of the strait into a broad place, where
there is no straitnesse, and that which should be set on thy table,
should be full of fatnesse.<note> Heb. the rest of thy table.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But thou hast
fulfilled the iudgement of the wicked: iudgement and iustice take
hold on thee.<note> Or, iudgement and iustice should uphold thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Because there
is wrath, beware lest he take thee away with his stroke: then a
great ransome cannot deliuer thee.<note> Heb. turn thee aside.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Will he
esteeme thy riches? no not gold, nor all the forces of
strength.</ab>
<ab n="20">Desire not the
night, when people are cut off in their place.</ab>
<ab n="21">Take heed,
regard not iniquitie: for this hast thou chosen rather then
affliction.</ab>
<ab n="22">Beholde, God
exalteth by his power: who teacheth like him?</ab>
<ab n="23">Who hath
inioyned him his way? or who can say, Thou hast wrought
iniquitie?</ab>
<ab n="24">Remember that
thou magnifie his worke, which men behold.</ab>
<ab n="25">Euery man may
see it, man may behold it afarre off.</ab>
<ab n="26">Behold, God is
great, and we know him not, neither can the number of his yeeres be
searched out.</ab>

<fw>The power of God.</fw>
<ab n="27">For hee maketh
small the drops of water: they powre downe raine according to the
vapour thereof:</ab>
<ab n="28">Which the
clouds doe drop, and distill vpon man aboundantly.</ab>
<ab n="29">Also can any
vnderstand the spreadings of the clouds, or the noise of his
tabernacle?</ab>
<ab n="30">Behold, he
spreadeth his light vpon it, and couereth the bottome of the
sea.<note> Heb. the roots.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For by them
iudgeth he the people, he giueth meate in abundance.</ab>
<ab n="32">With clouds he
couereth the light, and commaundeth it not to shine, by the cloud
that commeth betwixt.</ab>
<ab n="33">The noise
thereof sheweth concerning it, the cattel also concerning the
Uapour.<note> Heb. that which goeth vp.</note></ab>



</div>