<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-27-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 There is a knowledge of naturall
things. 12 But wisedome is an excellent gift of God.</head>

<ab n="1">Surely there is
a veine for the siluer, and a place for golde where they fine
it.<note> Or, a mine.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Iron is taken
out of the earth, and brasse is molten out of the
stone.<note> Or, dust.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Hee setteth an
ende to darkenesse, and searcheth out all perfection: the stones of
darkenesse and the shadow of death.</ab>
<ab n="4">The floud
breaketh out from the inhabitant; euen the waters forgotten of the
foote: they are dried vp, they are gone away from men.</ab>
<ab n="5">As for the
earth, out of it commeth bread: and vnder it, is turned vp as it
were fire.</ab>
<ab n="6">The stones of
it are the place of Saphires: and it hath dust of
golde.<note> Or, goldoare.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">There is a path
which no foule knoweth, and which the vulturs eye hath not
seene.</ab>
<ab n="8">The lyons
whelps haue not troden it, nor the fierce lyon passed by
it.</ab>
<ab n="9">Hee putteth
foorth his hand vpon the rocke; hee ouerturneth the mountaines by
the rootes.<note> Or, flint.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee cutteth
out riuers among the rockes, and his eye seeth euery precious
thing.</ab>
<ab n="11">He bindeth the
flouds from ouerflowing, and the thing that is hid, bringeth he
foorth to light.<note> Heb. from weeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But where
shall wisedome bee found? and where is the place of
vnderstanding?</ab>
<ab n="13">Man knoweth
not the price thereof neither is it found in the land of the
liuing.</ab>
<ab n="14">The depth
saith, It is not in me: and the sea saith, It is not with
me.<note> Rom.11. 22,34.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">It cannot be
gotten for golde, neither shall siluer be weighed for the price
thereof.<note> Heb. fine gold shall not be giuen for it. , Pro.3.14. and 8.11, 19. and 16.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">It cannot be
valued with the golde of Ophir, with the precious Onix, or the
Saphire.</ab>

<fw>Iobs forme prosperitie, and present
miserie.</fw>
<ab n="17">The golde and
the chrystall cannot equall it: and the exchange of it shall not be
for iewels of fine golde.<note> Or vessell of fine gold.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">No mention
shalbe made of Corall, or of Pearles: for the price of wisedome is
aboue Rubies.<note> Or, Ramoth.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The Topaze of
Ethiopia shall not equall it, neither shall it be valued with pure
golde.</ab>
<ab n="20">Whence then
commeth wisedome? and where is the place of
vnderstanding?<note> Vers.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Seeing it is
hid from the eyes of all liuing, and kept close from the foules of
the ayre.<note> Or, heauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Destruction
and death say, Wee haue heard the fame thereof with our
eares.</ab>
<ab n="23">God
vnderstandeth the way thereof, and he knoweth the place
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="24">For hee
looketh to the endes of the earth, and seeth vnder the whole
heauen:</ab>
<ab n="25">To make the
weight for the windes, and he weigheth the waters by
measure.</ab>
<ab n="26">When hee made
a decree for the raine, and a way for the lightning of the
thunder:</ab>
<ab n="27">Then did he
see it, and declare it, he prepared it, yea and searched it
out.<note> Or, did number it.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And vnto man
he said, Behold, the feare of the Lord, that is wisedome, and to
depart from euill, is vnderstanding.<note> Psal.111. 10 prou.1. 7&amp;9,10.</note></ab>



</div>