<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>I Ioseph aduanced in Potiphars
house. 7 Hee resisteth his mistresses temptation. 13 He is falsly
accused. 19 Hee is cast in prison. 21 God is with him
there.</head>

<ab n="1">And Ioseph was
brought downe to Egypt, and Potiphar an Officer of Pharaoh,
captaine of þ<note/> guard, an Egyptian, bought him of
the hand of the Ishmeelites, which had brought him downe
thither.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the LORD was
with Ioseph, and hee was a prosperous man, and hee was in the house
of his master the Egyptian.</ab>
<ab n="3">And his master
sawe that the LORD was with him, and that the LORD made all that he
did, to prosper in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Ioseph found
grace in his sight, and he serued him; and hee made him ouerseer
ouer his house, and all that he had he put into his hand.</ab>
<ab n="5">And it came to
passe from the time that hee had made him overseer in his house,
and ouer all that he had, that the LORD blessed the Egyptians house
for Iosephs sake: and the blessing of the LORD was vpon all that he
had in the house, and in the field.</ab>

<fw>Ioseph imprisoned, is
prosperous.</fw>
<ab n="6">And he left all
that he had, in Iosephs hand: and he knew not ought he had, saue
the bread which he did eate: and Ioseph was a goodly person, and
well fauoured.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And it
came to passe after these things, that his masters wife cast her
eyes vpon Ioseph, and shee said, Lie with me.</ab>
<ab n="8">But he refused,
and said vnto his masters wife, Behold, my master wotteth not what
is with mee in the house, and he hath committed all that he hath,
to my hand.</ab>
<ab n="9">There is none
greater in this house then I: neither hath hee kept backe any thing
from me, but thee, because thou art his wife: how then can I doe
this great wickednesse, and sinne against God?</ab>
<ab n="10">And it came to
passe as she spake to Ioseph day by day, that hee hearkened not
vnto her, to lie by her, or to bee with her.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it came to
passe about this time, that Ioseph went in to the house, to doe his
busines, and there was none of the men of the house there
within.</ab>
<ab n="12">And shee caught
him by his garment, saying, Lie with me: and he left his garment in
her hand, and fled, and got him out.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it came to
passe, when she saw that hee had left his garment in her hand, and
was fled forth;</ab>
<ab n="14">That she called
vnto the men of her house, and spake vnto them, saying, See, he
hath brought in an Hebrew vnto vs, to mocke vs: he came in vnto me
to lie with me, and I cried with a loud voice.<note> Heb. great.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe, when hee heard that I lifted vp my voice, and cried, that he
left his garment with mee, and fled, and got him out.</ab>
<ab n="16">And she laid vp
his garment by her, vntill her lord came home.</ab>
<ab n="17">And she spake
vnto him, according to these words, saying, The Hebrew seruant
which thou hast brought vnto vs, came in vnto me to mocke
me.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it came to
passe as I lift vp my voice, and cried, that he left his garment
with me, and fled out.</ab>
<ab n="19">And it came to
passe when his master heard the words of his wife, which she spake
vnto him, saying, After this maner did thy seruant to me, that his
wrath was kindled.</ab>

<fw>Ioseph imprisoned, is
prosperous.</fw>
<ab n="20">And Iosephs
master tooke him, and put him into the prison, a place, where
þ<note/> kings prisoners were bound: and he was there in
the prison.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ But the
LORD was with Ioseph, and shewed him mercie, and gaue him fauour in
the sight of the keeper of the prison.<note> Heb. extended kindnes vnto him.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And the keeper
of the prison committed to Iosephs hand all the prisoners that were
in the prison, and whatsoeuer they did there, he was the doer of
it:</ab>
<ab n="23">The keeper of
the prison looked not to any thing, that was vnder his hand,
because the LORD was with him: &amp; that which he did, the LORD
made it to prosper.</ab>



</div>