<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>1 Of the wild goates and hinds. 5 Of
the wild Asse. 9 The Vnicorne. 13 The Peacock, Storke and Ostrich.
19 The horse. 26 The hauke. 27 The Eagle.</head>

<ab n="1">Knowest thou
the time when the wild goates of the rocke bring forth? or canst
thou marke when the hindes doe calue?<note> Psal. 29.8</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Canst thou
number the moneths that they fulfill? or knowest thou the time when
they bring forth?</ab>
<ab n="3">They bowe
themselues, they bring forth their young ones, they cast out their
sorrowes.</ab>

<fw>Gods power in his creatures.</fw>
<ab n="4">Their yong ones
are in good liking, they grow vp with corne: they go forth, and
returne not vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Who hath sent
out the wild asse free? or who hath looosed the bands of the wild
asse?</ab>
<ab n="6">Whose house I
haue made the wildernesse, and the barren lande his
dwellings.<note> Hebr. salt places.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">He scorneth the
multitude of the citie, neither regardeth he the crying of the
driuer.<note> Hebr. of the exactor.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The range of
the mountaines is his pasture, and hee searcheth after euery greene
thing.</ab>
<ab n="9">Will the
Unicorne be willing to serue thee? or abide by thy cribbe?</ab>
<ab n="10">Canst thou
binde the Unicorne with his band in the furrow? or will he harrow
the valleyes after thee?</ab>
<ab n="11">Wilt thou
trust him because his strength is great? or wilt thou leaue thy
labour to him?</ab>
<ab n="12">Wilt thou
beleeue him that hee will bring home thy seed? and gather it into
thy barne?</ab>
<ab n="13">Gauest thou
the goodly wings vnto the peacocks, or wings and feathers vnto the
Ostrich?<note> Or, the feathers of the storke and Ostrich.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Which leaueth
her egges in the earth, and warmeth them in dust,</ab>
<ab n="15">And forgetteth
that the foot may crush them, or that the wilde beast may breake
them.</ab>
<ab n="16">She is
hardened against her yong ones, as though they were not hers: her
labour is in vaine without feare.</ab>
<ab n="17">Because God
hath depriued her of wisedome, neither hath he imparted to her
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="18">What time she
lifteth vp her selfe on high, she scorneth the horse and his
rider.</ab>
<ab n="19">Hast thou
giuen the horse strength? hast thou clothed his necke with
thunder?</ab>
<ab n="20">Canst thou
make him afraid as a grashopper? the glory of his nostrils is
terrible.<note> Hebr. terrour.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He paweth in
the valley, and reioyceth in his strength: hee goeth on to meet the
armed men.<note> Or, his feet digge. , Hebr. the armour.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">He mocketh at
feare, and is not affrighted: neither turneth he backe from the
sword.</ab>
<ab n="23">The quiuer
ratleth against him, the glittering speare and the shield.</ab>

<fw>Gods power in his creatures.</fw>
<ab n="24">He swalloweth
the ground with fiercenesse and rage: neither beleeueth he that it
is the sound of the trumpet.</ab>
<ab n="25">Hee saith
among the trumpets, Ha, ha: and he smelleth the battaile afarre
off, the thunder of the captaines, and the shouting.</ab>
<ab n="26">Doeth the
hawke flie by thy wisedome, and stretch her wings toward the
South?</ab>
<ab n="27">Doeth the
Eagle mount vp at thy commaund? and make her nest on
high?<note> Hebr. by thy mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">She dwelleth
and abideth on the rocke, vpon the cragge of the rocke, and the
strong place.</ab>
<ab n="29">From thence
she seeketh the pray, and her eyes behold a farre off.</ab>
<ab n="30">Her yong ones
also suck vp blood: and where the slaine are, there is
he.<note> Matt.24. 28. luke 17. 37.</note></ab>



</div>