<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>Iob maketh a solemne protestation of
his integritie in seuerall dueties.</head>

<ab n="1">I made a
couenant with mine eyes; why then should I thinke vpon a
mayd?</ab>
<ab n="2">For what
portion of God is there from aboue? and what inheritance of the
Almighty from on high?</ab>
<ab n="3">Is not
destruction to the wicked? and a strange punishment to the workers
of iniquitie?</ab>
<ab n="4">Doeth not he
see my wayes, and count all my steps?<note> 2. Chron. 16.9. iob 32.21. pro. 5.21. and 15.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">If I haue
walked with vanitie, or if my foot hath hasted to deceit;</ab>
<ab n="6">Let me bee
weighed in an euen ballance, that God may know mine
integritie.<note> Hebr. let him weigh mee in balances of Iustice.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">If my step hath
turned out of the way, and mine heart walked after mine eyes, and
if any blot hath cleaued to my hands:</ab>
<ab n="8">Then let mee
sow, and let another eate, yea let my off-spring be rooted
out.</ab>

<fw>Iob professeth his integritie.</fw>
<ab n="9">If mine heart
haue bene deceiued by a woman, or if I haue layde wait at my
neighbours doore:</ab>
<ab n="10">Then let my
wife grind vnto another, and let others bow downe vpon her.</ab>
<ab n="11">For this is an
heinous crime, yea, it is an iniquitie to bee punished by the
Iudges.</ab>
<ab n="12">For it is a
fire that consumeth to destruction, and would roote out all mine
encrease.</ab>
<ab n="13">If I did
despise the cause of my man-seruant, or of my mayd-seruant, when
they contended with me:</ab>
<ab n="14">What then
shall I do, when God riseth vp? and when hee visiteth, what shall I
answere him?</ab>
<ab n="15">Did not hee
that made mee in the wombe, make him? and did not one fashion vs in
the wombe?<note> Or, did hee not fashion vs in one wombe?</note></ab>
<ab n="16">If I haue
withhelde the poore from their desire, or haue caused the eyes of
the widow to faile:</ab>
<ab n="17">Or haue eaten
my morsell my selfe alone, and the fatherlesse hath not eaten
thereof:</ab>
<ab n="18">(For from my
youth hee was brought vp with me as with a father, and I haue
guided her from my mothers wombe.)<note> That is, the widow,</note></ab>
<ab n="19">If I haue
seene any perish for want of cloathing, or any poore without
couering:</ab>
<ab n="20">If his loynes
haue not blessed me, and if hee were not warmed with the fleece of
my sheepe:</ab>
<ab n="21">If I haue lift
vp my hand against the fatherlesse, when I saw my helpe in the
gate:</ab>
<ab n="22">Then let mine
arme fall from my shoulder-blade, and mine arme be broken from the
bone.<note> Or, the channell bone.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For
destruction from God was a terrour to mee: and by reason of his
highnesse, I could not endure.</ab>
<ab n="24">If I haue made
golde my hope, or haue said to the fine gold, Thou art my
confidence:</ab>
<ab n="25">If I reioyced
because my wealth was great, and because mine hand had gotten
much:<note> Heb. found much.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">If I beheld
the Sunne when it shined, or the Moone walking in
brightnesse:<note> Heb. the light. , Heb. bright.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And my heart
hath bene secretly enticed, or my mouth hath kissed my
hand:<note> Hebr. my hand hath kissed my mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">This also were
an iniquitie to be punished by the Iudge: For I should haue denied
the God that is aboue.</ab>

<fw>Elihu reproueth Iob, and
others.</fw>
<ab n="29">If I reioyced
at the destruction of him that hated me, or lift vp my selfe when
euill found him:</ab>
<ab n="30">(Neither haue
I suffered my mouth to sinne by wishing a curse to his
soule.)<note> Heb. my palate.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">If the men of
my tabernacle said not, Oh that we had of his flesh! wee cannot be
satisfied.</ab>
<ab n="32">The stranger
did not lodge in the street: but I opened my doores to the
trauailer.<note> Or, to the way.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">If I couered
my transgressions, as Adam: by hiding mine iniquitie in my
bosome:<note> Or, after the manner of men.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Did I feare a
great multitude, or did the contempt of families terrifie me: that
I kept silence, and went not out of the doore?</ab>
<ab n="35">O that one
would heare me! beholde, my desire is, that the Almightie would
answere me, and that mine aduersary had written a
booke.<note> Or, behold my signe is that the Almightie will answere mee.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Surely I would
take it vpon my shoulder, and bind it as a crowne to me.</ab>
<ab n="37">I would
declare vnto him the number of my steps, as a prince would I goe
neere vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="38">If my land cry
against me, or that the furrowes likewise thereof
complaine:<note> Heb. weepe</note></ab>
<ab n="39">If I haue
eaten the fruits thereof without money, or haue caused the owners
thereof to loose their life:<note> Heb. the strength thereof. , Heb. caused the soule of the owners therof to expire, or breath out.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Let thistles
grow in stead of wheat, and cockle in stead of barley. The words of
Iob are ended.<note> Or, noy-some weedes</note></ab>



</div>