<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Iob excuseth his desire of death.
12 He complaineth of his owne restlesnesse, 17 and Gods
watchfulnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">Is there not an
appointed time to man vpon earth? are not his dayes also like the
dayes of an hireling?<note> Or, warfare.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">As a seruant
earnestly desireth the shadow, and as an hireling looketh for the
reward of his worke:<note> Hebr. gapeth after.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">So am I made to
possesse moneths of vanitie, and wearisome nights are appointed to
me.</ab>
<ab n="4">When I lie
downe, I say, When shall I arise, and the night be gone? and I am
full of tossings to and fro, vnto the dawning of the
day.<note> Hebr. the euening be measured.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">My flesh is
cloathed with wormes and clods of dust, my skinne is broken, and
become loathsome.</ab>
<ab n="6">My dayes are
swifter then a weauers shuttle, and are spent without
hope.<note> Iob 16.22. psal.90.6 and 102.11 and 103.15. and144.4. isa.40.6. iam.4.14</note></ab>
<ab n="7">O remember that
my life is winde: mine eye shall no more see good.<note> Hebr. shall not returne. , To see, that is, to enioy.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The eye of him
that hath seene me, shall see mee no more: thine eyes are vpon me,
and I am not.<note> That is, I can liue no longer.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">As the cloud is
consumed and vanisheth away: so he that goeth downe to the graue,
shall come vp no more.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee shall
returne no more to his house: neither shall his place know him any
more.</ab>

<fw>Bildads answere.</fw>
<ab n="11">Therefore I
will not refraine my mouth, I wil speake in the anguish of my
spirit, I will complaine in the bitternesse of my soule.</ab>
<ab n="12">Am I a sea, or
a whale, that thou settest a watch ouer me?</ab>
<ab n="13">When I say, My
bed shal comfort me, my couch shall ease my complaint:</ab>
<ab n="14">Then thou
skarest mee with dreames, and terrifiest me through
visions.</ab>
<ab n="15">So that my
soule chooseth strangling: and death rather then my
life.<note> Heb. then my bones.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I loath it, I
would not liue alway: let me alone, for my dayes are
vanitie.</ab>
<ab n="17">What is man,
that thou shouldest magnifie him? and that thou shouldest set thine
heart vpon him?<note> Psal.8.4. and 144.3. heb.2.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And that thou
shouldest visite him euery morning, and trie him euery
moment?</ab>
<ab n="19">How long wilt
thou not depart from me? nor let me alone till I swallow downe my
spittle?</ab>
<ab n="20">I haue sinned,
what shall I doe vnto thee, O thou preseruer of men? why hast thou
set me as a mark against thee, so that I am a burden to my
selfe?</ab>
<ab n="21">And why doest
thou not pardon my transgression, and take away mine iniquitie? for
now shall I sleepe in the dust, and thou shalt seeke me in the
morning, but I shall not be.</ab>



</div>