<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-16-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Iob reproueth his friends of
vnmercifulnesse. 7 He sheweth the pitifulnesse of his case. 17 He
maintaineth his innocencie.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iob
answered, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">I haue heard
many such things: miserable comforters are ye all.<note> Or, troublesome. , Chap. 13. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Shall vaine
words haue an ende? or what emboldeneth thee, that thou
answerest?<note> Heb. words of wind.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I also could
speake as yee doe: if your soule were in my soules stead, I could
heape vp words against you, and shake mine head at you.</ab>

<fw>Iob reckoneth vp his many
afflictions.</fw>
<ab n="5">But I would
strengthen you with my mouth, and the mouing of my lips should
asswage your griefe.</ab>
<ab n="6">Though I
speake, my griefe is not asswaged: and though I forbeare; what am I
eased?<note> Heb. what goeth from me</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But now he hath
made me weary: thou hast made desolate al my companie.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou hast
filled mee with wrinckles, which is a witnesse against me: and my
leannesse rising vp in me, beareth witnesse to my face.</ab>
<ab n="9">He teareth me
in his wrath, who hateth me: he gnasheth vpon me with his teeth;
mine enemy sharpeneth his eyes vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="10">They haue
gaped vpon me with their mouth, they haue smitten me vpon the
cheeke reprochfully, they haue gathered themselues together against
mee.</ab>
<ab n="11">God hath
deliuered me to the vngodly, and turned me ouer into the hands of
the wicked.<note> Hebr. hath shut me up.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I was at ease,
but he hath broken me asunder: he hath also taken me by my necke,
and shaken me to pieces, and set me vp for his marke.</ab>
<ab n="13">His archers
compasse me round about, he cleaueth my reines asunder, and doeth
not spare; he powreth out my gall vpon the ground.</ab>
<ab n="14">He breaketh me
with breach vpon breach, he runneth vpon me like a giant.</ab>
<ab n="15">I haue sowed
sackcloth vpon my skin, and defiled my horne in the dust.</ab>
<ab n="16">My face is
fowle with weeping, and on mine eye-lids is the shadow of
death;</ab>
<ab n="17">Not for any
iniustice in mine hands: also my prayer is pure.</ab>
<ab n="18">O earth couer
not thou my blood, and let my cry haue no place.</ab>
<ab n="19">Also now,
behold my witnesse is in heauen, and my record is on
high.<note> Hebr. in the high places.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">My friends
scorne me: but mine eye powreth out teares vnto God.<note> Heb. are my scorners.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">O that one
might plead for a man with God, as a man pleadeth for his
neighbour.<note> Or, friend.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">When a few
yeeres are come, then I shall goe the way whence I shall not
returne.<note> Heb. yeeres of member.</note></ab>



</div>