<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_41" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-41-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLI.</head>
<head>1 Pharaohs two dreames. 9 Ioseph
interpreteth them. 33 Hee giueth Pharaoh counsell. 38 Ioseph is
aduanced. 50 Hee begetteth Manasseh and Ephraim. 54 The famine
beginneth.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe at the end of two ful yeeres, that Pharaoh dreamed: and
beholde, hee stood by the riuer.</ab>
<ab n="2">And behold, there
came vp out of the riuer seuen well fauoured kine, and fat fleshed,
and they fed in a medow.</ab>
<ab n="3">And behold, seuen
other kine came vp after them out of the riuer, ill fauoured and
leane fleshed, and stood by the other kine, vpon the brinke of the
riuer.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the ill
fauoured and leane fleshed kine, did eate vp the seuen well
fauoured and fat kine: So Pharaoh awoke.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee slept and
dreamed the second time: and beholde, seuen eares of corne came vp
vpon one stalke, ranke and good.<note> Hebr. fat.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And beholde,
seuen thinne eares and blasted with the Eastwind, sprang vp after
them.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the seuen
thinne eares deuoured the seuen ranke and full eares: and Pharaoh
awoke, and behold, it was a dreame.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came to
passe in the morning, that his spirit was troubled, and he sent and
called for all the Magicians of Egypt, and all the wise men
thereof: and Pharaoh tolde them his dreame; but there was none that
could interprete them vnto Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then spake
the chiefe Butler vnto Pharaoh, saying, I doe remember my faults
this day.</ab>
<ab n="10">Pharaoh was
wroth with his seruants, and put mee in warde, in the captaine of
the guards house, both mee, and the chiefe Baker.</ab>
<ab n="11">And we dreamed a
dreame in one night, I and he: we dreamed each man according to the
interpretation of his dreame.</ab>

<fw>Pharaohs dreames are
interpreted.</fw>
<ab n="12">And there was
there with vs a yong man an Hebrew, seruant to the captaine of the
guard: and wee told him, and he interpreted to vs our dreames, to
each man according to his dreame, he did interpret.<note> Chap. 40. 12. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And it came to
passe, as he interpreted to vs, so it was; mee he restored vnto
mine office, and him he hanged.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then
Pharaoh sent and called Ioseph, and they brought him hastily out of
the dungeon: And he shaued himselfe, and changed his raiment, and
came in vnto Pharaoh.<note> Psal. 105. 20. , Hebr. made him runne.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Pharaoh said
vnto Ioseph, I haue dreamed a dreame, and there is none that can
interpret it: and I haue heard say of thee, that thou canst
vnderstand a dreame, to interpret it.<note> Or, When thou hearest a dreame, thou canst interpret it.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Ioseph
answered Pharaoh, saying; It is not in me: God shall giue Pharaoh
an answere of peace.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Pharaoh said
vnto Ioseph; In my dreame, behold, I stood vpon the banke of the
riuer.</ab>
<ab n="18">And behold,
there came vp out of the riuer seuen kine, fat fleshed and well
fauoured, and they fed in a medow.</ab>
<ab n="19">And behold,
seuen other kine came vp after them, poore and very ill fauoured,
and leane fleshed, such as I neuer saw in all the land of Egypt for
badnes.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the leane,
&amp; the ill fauoured kine, did eate vp the first seuen fat
kine.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when they
had eaten them vp, it could not bee knowen that they had eaten
them, but they were still ill fauoured, as at the beginning: So I
awoke.<note> Hebr. come to the inward parts of them.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And I saw in my
dreame, and behold, seuen eares came vp in one stalke, full and
good.</ab>
<ab n="23">And behold,
seuen eares withered, thin &amp; blasted with the East wind, sprung
vp after them.<note> Or, small.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the thin
eares deuoured the seuen good eares: and I told this vnto the
magicians, but there was none that could declare it to me.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And
Ioseph said vnto Pharaoh, the dreame of Pharaoh is one; God hath
shewed Pharaoh what he is about to doe.</ab>
<ab n="26">The seuen good
kine are seuen yeeres: and the seuen good eares are seuen yeeres:
the dreame is one.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the seuen
thin and ill fauoured kine that came vp after them, are seuen
yeeres: and the seuen emptie eares blasted with the East wind,
shall bee seuen yeeres of famine.</ab>

<fw>Pharaohs dreames are
interpreted.</fw>
<ab n="28">This is the
thing which I haue spoken vnto Pharaoh: what God is about to doe,
he sheweth vnto Pharaoh.</ab>
<ab n="29">Behold, there
come seuen yeeres of great plentie, throughout all the land of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="30">And there shall
arise after them, seuen yeeres of famine, and all the plentie shall
be forgotten in the land of Egypt: and the famine shall consume the
land.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the plentie
shal not be knowen in the land, by reason of that famine following:
for it shalbe very grieuous.<note> Heb. heauy</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And for that the
dreame was doubled vnto Pharaoh twice, it is because the thing is
established by God: and God will shortly bring it to
passe.<note> Or, prepared of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Now therfore let
Pharaoh looke out a man discreet and wise, and set him ouer the
land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="34">Let Pharaoh doe
this, and let him appoint officers ouer the land, &amp; take vp the
fift part of the land of Egypt, in the seuen plenteous
yeeres.<note> Or, ouerseers.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And let them
gather all the food of those good yeeres that come, and lay vp
corne vnder the hand of Pharaoh, and let them keepe food in the
cities.</ab>
<ab n="36">And that food
shall be for store to the land, against the seuen yeeres of famine,
which shall bee in the land of Egypt, that the land perish not
through the famine.<note> Heb. be not cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">¶ And the
thing was good in the eyes of Pharaoh, and in the eyes of all his
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="38">And Pharaoh said
vnto his seruants, Can we find such a one, as this is, a man in
whom the spirit of God is?</ab>
<ab n="39">And Pharaoh said
vnto Ioseph, Forasmuch as God hath shewed thee all this, there is
none so discreete and wise, as thou art:</ab>
<ab n="40">Thou shalt be
ouer my house, and according vnto thy word shall all my people be
ruled: only in the throne will I be greater then thou.<note> Psal. 105. 21. 1. mac. 2. 53. act. 7.10. , Heb. armed: or, kisse.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And Pharaoh said
vnto Ioseph, See, I haue set thee ouer all the land of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="42">And Pharaoh
tooke off his ring from his hand, &amp; put it vpon Iosephs hand,
and arayed him in vestures of fine linnen, and put a gold chaine
about his necke.<note> Or, silke.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And he made him
to ride in the second charet which he had: and they cried before
him, Bow the knee: and he made him ruler ouer all the land of
Egypt.<note> Or, Tender father: Heb. Abrech.</note></ab>

<fw>Ioseph exalted.</fw>
<ab n="44">And Pharaoh said
vnto Ioseph, I am Pharaoh, and without thee shall no man lift vp
his hand or foote, in all the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="45">And Pharaoh
called Iosephs name, Zaphnath-Paaneah, and he gaue him to wife
Asenath the daughter of Poti-pherah, priest of On: and Ioseph went
out ouer all the lande of Egypt.<note> Or, Prince</note></ab>
<ab n="46">(¶ And
Ioseph was thirtie yeeres old when he stood before Pharaoh king of
Egypt) and Ioseph went out from the presence of Pharaoh, and went
thorowout all the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="47">And in the seuen
plenteous yeres the earth brought forth by handfuls.</ab>
<ab n="48">And he gathered
vp all the foode of the seuen yeeres, which were in the land of
Egypt, and laid vp the foode in the cities: the foode of the field
which was round about euery citie, laid he vp in the same.</ab>
<ab n="49">And Ioseph
gathered corne as the sand of the sea, very much, vntill he left
numbring: for it was without number.</ab>
<ab n="50">And vnto Ioseph
were borne two sonnes, before the yeeres of famine came: which
Asenath the daughter of Poti-pherah, Priest of On bare vnto
him.<note> Chap.46. 20. &amp; 48.5. , Or, Prince.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And Ioseph
called the name of the first borne Manasseh: for God, said hee,
hath made me forget all my toile, and all my fathers
house.<note> That is, Forgetting.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">And the name of
the second called he Ephraim: for God hath caused mee to be
fruitfull in the land of my affliction.<note> That is, Fruitfull.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">¶ And the
seuen yeeres of plenteousnesse, that was in the land of Egypt, were
ended.</ab>
<ab n="54">And the seuen
yeeres of dearth beganne to come according as Ioseph had saide, and
the dearth was in all lands: but in all the land of Egypt there was
bread.<note> Psal. 105. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And when all the
land of Egypt was famished, the people cried to Pharaoh for bread:
and Pharaoh said vnto all the Egyptians, Goe vnto Ioseph: what he
saith to you, doe.</ab>
<ab n="56">And the famine
was ouer all the face of the earth; and Ioseph opened all the
storehouses, and solde vnto the Egyptians: and the famine waxed
sore in the land of Egypt.<note> Hebr. All wherein was.</note></ab>

<fw>His brethren.</fw>
<ab n="57">And all
countreys came into Egypt to Ioseph, for to buy corne, because that
the famine was so sore in all lands.</ab>



</div>