<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Iob sheweth that euen in the
iudgement of man, he hath reason to be grieued. 7 Sometimes the
wicked doe so prosper, as they despise God. 16 Sometime their
destruction is manifest. 22 The happy and vnhappy are alike in
death. 27 The iudgement of the wicked is in another
world.</head>

<ab n="1">But Iob
answered, and sayd,</ab>
<ab n="2">Heare
diligently my speech, and let this be your consolations.</ab>
<ab n="3">Suffer me that
I may speake, and after that I haue spoken, mocke on.</ab>
<ab n="4">As for mee, is
my complaint to man? and if it were so, why should not my spirit be
troubled?<note> Heb. shortened.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Marke mee, and
be astonished, and lay your hand vpon your mouth.<note> Heb. looke vnto me.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Euen when I
remember, I am afraid, and trembling taketh holde on my
flesh.</ab>
<ab n="7">Wherefore doe
the wicked liue, become old, yea, are mightie in power?<note> Psal.17. 10. and 73 12. iere.12. 1. hab.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Their seede is
established in their sight with them, and their offspring before
their eyes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Their houses
are safe from feare, neither is the rod of God vpon
them.<note> Heb. are peace from feare.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Their bull
gendreth and faileth not, their cow calueth, and casteth not her
calfe.</ab>
<ab n="11">They send
foorth their little ones like a flocke, and their children
dance.</ab>
<ab n="12">They take the
timbrell and harpe, and reioyce at the sound of the organe.</ab>
<ab n="13">They spend
their daies in wealth, and in a moment goe downe to the
graue.<note> Or, in mirth.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Therefore they
say vnto God, Depart from vs: for we desire not the knowledge of
thy wayes.<note> Chap.22. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">What is the
Almightie, that wee should serue him? and what profite should we
haue, if we pray vnto him?</ab>
<ab n="16">Loe, their
good is not in their hand, the counsell of the wicked is farre from
me.</ab>
<ab n="17">How oft is the
candle of the wicked put out? and how oft commeth their destruction
vpon them? God distributeth sorrowes in his anger.<note> Or, lampe.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">They are as
stubble before the winde, and as chaffe that the storme carieth
away.<note> Heb. stealeth away</note></ab>

<fw>All alike in death</fw>
<ab n="19">God layeth vp
his iniquitie for his children: he rewardeth him, and he shall know
it.<note> That is, the punishment of his iniquitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">His eyes shall
see his destruction, and he shall drinke of the wrath of the
Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="21">For what
pleasure hath he in his house after him, when the number of his
moneths is cut off in the middest?</ab>
<ab n="22">Shall any
teach God knowledge? seeing he iudgeth those that are high.</ab>
<ab n="23">One dieth in
his full strength, being wholly at ease and quiet.<note> Heb. in his very perfection, or in the strength of his perfection.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">His breasts
are full of milke, and his bones are moistened with
marrow.<note> Or, milkes pales.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And another
dieth in the bitternesse of his soule, and neuer eateth with
pleasure.</ab>
<ab n="26">They shall lie
downe alike in the dust, and the wormes shall couer them.</ab>
<ab n="27">Behold, I know
your thoughts, and the deuices which yee wrongfully imagine against
me.</ab>
<ab n="28">For ye say,
where is the house of the prince? and where are the dwelling places
of the wicked?<note> Heb the tent of the tabernacles of the wicked.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Haue ye not
asked them that goe by the way? and doe ye not know their
tokens?</ab>
<ab n="30">That the
wicked is reserued to the day of destruction; they shall bee
brought foorth to the day of wrath.<note> Pro.16.4. , Heb. the day of wraths.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Who shall
declare his way to his face? and who shall repay him what he hath
done?</ab>
<ab n="32">Yet shall hee
be brought to the graue, &amp; shall remaine in the
tombe.<note> Heb. graues. , Heb. watch in the heape.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">The cloudes of
the valley shalbe sweete vnto him, and euery man shall draw after
him, as there are innumerable before him.</ab>
<ab n="34">How then
comfort ye me in vaine, seeing in your answeres there remaineth
falshood?<note> Heb. transgression.</note></ab>



</div>