<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_38" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-36-38.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVIII.</head>
<head>1 God chalengeth Iob to answer. 4
God by his mighty workes, conuinceth Iob of Ignorance, 31 and of
imbecillity.</head>

<ab n="1">Then the Lord
answered Iob out of the whirlewind, and sayd,</ab>
<ab n="2">Who is this
that darkneth counsell by words without knowledge?</ab>
<ab n="3">Gird vp nowe
thy loines like a man; for I will demaund of thee, and answere thou
me.<note> Heb. make me know.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Where wast thou
when I layd the foundations of the earth? declare, if thou hast
vnderstanding.<note> Psal. 104. 5. prou. 30.4. , Heb. if thou knowest vnderstanding.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Who hath layd
the measures thereof, if thou knowest? or who hath stretched the
line vpon it?</ab>

<fw>Mans weakenes.</fw>
<ab n="6">Wherepuon are
the foundations thereof fastened? or who layd the corner stone
thereof?<note> Heb. sockets. , Heb. made to sinke.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">When the
morning starres sang together, and all the sonnes of God shouted
for ioy.</ab>
<ab n="8">Or who shut vp
the sea with doores, when it brake foorth as if it had issued out
of the wombe?<note> Psal.104.9</note></ab>
<ab n="9">When I made the
cloud the garment thereof, and thicke darknesse a swadling band for
it,</ab>
<ab n="10">And brake vp
for it my decreed place, and set barres and doores,<note> Or, established my decree vpon it.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And said,
Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further: and heere shall thy proud
waues be stayed.<note> Heb. the pride of thy waues.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Hast thou
commaunded the morning since thy daies? and caused the day-spring
to know his place,</ab>
<ab n="13">That it might
take hold of the endes of the earth, that the wicked might be
shaken out of it?<note> Heb. wings.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">It is turned
as clay to the seale, and they stand as a garment.</ab>
<ab n="15">And from the
wicked their light is withholden, and the high arme shalbe
broken.</ab>
<ab n="16">Hast thou
entred into the springs of the sea? or hast thou walked in the
search of the depth?</ab>
<ab n="17">Haue the gates
of death bene opened vnto thee? or hast thou seene the doores of
the shadow of death?</ab>
<ab n="18">Hast thou
perceiued the breadth of the earth? Declare if thou knowest it
all.</ab>
<ab n="19">Where is the
way where light dwelleth? And as for darknesse, where is the place
thereof?</ab>
<ab n="20">That thou
shouldest take it to the bound thereof, and that thou shouldest
know the pathes to the house thereof.<note> Or, at.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Knowest thou
it, because thou wast then borne? or because the number of thy
daies is great?</ab>
<ab n="22">Hast thou
entred into the treasures of the snowe? or hast thou seene the
treasures of the haile,</ab>
<ab n="23">Which I haue
reserued against the time of trouble, against the day of battaile
and warre?</ab>
<ab n="24">By what way is
the light parted? which scattereth the East wind vpon the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="25">Who hath
diuided a water-course for the ouerflowing of waters? or a way for
the lightning of thunder,</ab>
<ab n="26">To cause it to
raine on the earth, where no man is: on the wildernesse wherein
there is no man?</ab>

<fw>Gods secret workes</fw>
<ab n="27">To satisfie
the desolate and waste ground, and to cause the bud of the tender
herbe to spring forth.</ab>
<ab n="28">Hath the raine
a father? or who hath begotten the drops of dew?</ab>
<ab n="29">Out of whose
wombe came the yce? and the hoary frost of heauen, who hath gendred
it?</ab>
<ab n="30">The waters are
hid as with a stone, and the face of the deepe is
frozen.<note> Heb. is taken.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Canst thou
bind the sweete influences of Pleiades? or loose the bands of
Orion?<note> Or, the seuen-starres. Heb. Cimah. , Heb. Cesil.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Canst thou
bring forth Mazzaroth in his season, or canst thou guide Arcturus
with his sonnes?<note> Or, the twelue signes. , Heb. guide them.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Knowest thou
the ordinances of heauen? canst thou set the dominion thereof in
the earth?</ab>
<ab n="34">Canst thou
lift vp thy voice to the cloudes, that abundance of waters may
couer thee?</ab>
<ab n="35">Canst thou
send lightnings, that they may goe, and say vnto thee, Here we
are?<note> Heb. behold vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Who hath put
wisedome in the inward parts? or who hath giuen vnderstanding to
the heart?<note> Chap.32. 8. Eccle.2. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Who can number
the cloudes in wisedome? or who can stay the bottles of
heauen,<note> Heb. who can cause to lie downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">When the dust
groweeh into hardnesse, and the clods cleaue fast
together?<note> Or, when the dust is turned into myre. , Heb. is powred.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Wilt thou hunt
the pray for the lyon? or fill the appetite of the young
lyons,<note> Psal.104. 21. , Heb. the life.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">When they
couch in their dennes, and abide in the couert to lie in
waite?</ab>
<ab n="41">Who prouideth
for the rauen his foode? when his young ones cry vnto God, they
wander for lacke of meate.<note> Psal.147. 9. Math.6. 26.</note></ab>



</div>