<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 Comparison is not to be made with
God, because our good or euill cannot extend vnto him. 9 Many cry
in their afflictions, but are not heard for want of
faith.</head>

<ab n="1">Elihu spake
moreouer, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Thinkest thou
this to bee right, that thou saydest, My righteousnesse is more
then Gods?</ab>

<fw>The causes of Gods punishments.</fw>
<ab n="3">For thou
saydst, what aduantage will it bee vnto thee, and, what profite
shall I haue, if I bee cleansed from my sinne?<note> Or, by it more then by my sinne.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I will answere
thee, and thy companions with thee.<note> Heb. I wil returne to thee words.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Looke vnto the
heauens and see, and behold the clouds which are higher then
thou.</ab>
<ab n="6">If thou
sinnest, what doest thou against him? or it thy transgressions be
multiplied, what doest thou vnto him?</ab>
<ab n="7">If thou be
righteous, what giuest thou him? or what receiueth hee of thine
hand?<note> Psal.16.2. Rom.11.35 iob.22.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Thy wickednesse
may hurt a man as thou art, and thy righteousnesse may profit the
sonne of man.</ab>
<ab n="9">By reason of
the multitude of oppressions they make the oppressed to crie: they
crie out by reason of the arme of the mightie.</ab>
<ab n="10">But none
saith, where is God my maker, who giueth songs in the
night?</ab>
<ab n="11">Who teacheth
vs more then the beasts of the earth, and maketh vs wiser then the
foules of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="12">There they
crie, (but none giueth answere) because of the pride of euill
men.</ab>
<ab n="13">Surely God wil
not heare vanitie, neither wil the Almightie regard it.<note> Iob.27.9 prou.1.28. isa.1.15. ier. 11.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Although thou
sayest thou shalt not see him, yet iudgement is before him,
therefore trust thou in him.</ab>
<ab n="15">But now
because it is not so, hee hath visited in his anger, yet he knoweth
it not in great extremitie:<note> That is God. , That is, Iob.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore
doeth Iob open his mouth in vaine: he multiplieth words without
knowledge.</ab>



</div>