<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-16-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Iob appealeth from men to God. 6
The vnmercifull dealing of men with the afflicted, may astonish,
but not discourage the righteous. 11 His hope is not in life, but
in death.</head>


<fw>Iob reckoneth vp his many
afflictions.</fw>
<ab n="1">My breath is
corrupt, my dayes are extinct, the graues are ready for
me.<note> Or, my spirit is spent.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Are there not
mockers with mee? and doeth not mine eye continue in their
prouocation?<note> Heb. lodge.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Lay downe now,
put me in a suretie with thee; who is he that will strike hands
with me?</ab>
<ab n="4">For thou hast
hid their heart from vnderstanding: therefore shalt thou not exalt
them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Hee that
speaketh flattery to his friends, euen the eyes of his children
shall faile.</ab>
<ab n="6">He hath made me
also a by-word of the people, and afore time I was as a
tabret.<note> Or, before them.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Mine eye also
is dimme by reason of sorrow, and all my members are as a
shadow.<note> Or, my thoughts.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Upright men
shall be astonied at this, and the innocent shall stirre vp
himselfe against the hypocrite.</ab>
<ab n="9">The righteous
also shall hold on his way, and he that hath cleane hands shalbe
stronger, and stronger.<note> Hebr. shall adde strgth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But as for you
all, doe you returne, and come now, for I cannot find one wise man
among you.</ab>
<ab n="11">My dayes are
past, my purposes are broken off, euen the thoughts of my
heart:<note> Hebr. the possessions.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">They change
the night into day: the light is short, because of
darknes.<note> Heb. neere.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">If I waite,
the graue is mine house: I haue made my bedde in the
darknesse.</ab>
<ab n="14">I haue said to
corruption, Thou art my father: to the worme, Thou art my mother,
and my sister.<note> Heb. cried, or called.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And where is
now my hope? as for my hope, who shall see it?</ab>
<ab n="16">They shall goe
downe to the barres of the pit, when our rest together is in the
dust.</ab>



</div>