<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Iob sheweth that his complaints
are not causelesse. 8 Hee wisheth for death, wherein he is assured
of comfort. 14 He reprooueth his friends of
vnkindnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">But Iob
answered, and sayd,</ab>
<ab n="2">Oh that my
griefe were throughly weighed, and my calamitie layd in the
balances together.<note> Heb. lifted vp.</note></ab>

<fw>Iob complaineth.</fw>
<ab n="3">For now it would
be heauier then the sand of the sea, therefore my words are
swallowed vp.<note> That is, I want words to expresse my griefe.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For the arrowes
of the Almightie are within me, the poyson whereof drinketh vp my
spirit: the terrors of God doe set themselues in aray against
mee.<note> Psal. 38.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Doeth the wilde
asse bray when he hath grasse? or loweth the oxe ouer his
fodder?<note> Hebr. at grasse.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Can that which
is vnsauery, bee eaten without salt? or is there any taste in the
white of an egge?</ab>
<ab n="7">The things that
my soule refused to touch, are as my sorrowfull meat.</ab>
<ab n="8">O that I might
haue my request! and that God would graunt mee the thing that I
long for!<note> Hebr. my expectation.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Euen that it
would please God to destroy mee, that he would let loose his hand,
and cut me off.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then should I
yet haue comfort, yea I would harden my selfe in sorrow; let him
not spare, for I haue not concealed the words of the holy
One.</ab>
<ab n="11">What is my
strength, that I should hope? and what is mine ende, that I should
prolong my life?</ab>
<ab n="12">Is my strength
the strength of stones? or is my flesh of brasse?<note> He.brasen.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Is not my helpe
in me? and is wisedome driuen quite from me?</ab>
<ab n="14">To him that is
afflicted, pitie should be shewed from his friend; But he forsaketh
the feare of the Almighty.<note> Hebr. to him that melteth.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">My brethren
haue delt deceitfully as a brooke, &amp; as the streame of brookes
they passe away,</ab>
<ab n="16">Which are
blackish by reason of the yce, and wherein the snow is hid:</ab>
<ab n="17">What time they
waxe warme, they vanish: when it is hot, they are consumed out of
their place.<note> Hebr. they are cut off. , Hebr. in the heat thereof. , Hebr. extinguished.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The pathes of
their way are turned aside; they goe to nothing, and
perish.</ab>
<ab n="19">The troupes of
Tema looked, the companies of Sheba waited for them.</ab>
<ab n="20">They were
confounded because they had hoped; they came thither, and were
ashamed.</ab>
<ab n="21">For now ye are
nothing; ye see my casting downe, and are afraid.<note> Or, for now ye are like to them. Hebr. to it. , Hebr. Not.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Did I say,
Bring vnto mee? or giue a reward for me of your substance?</ab>
<ab n="23">Or deliuer me
from the enemies hand, or redeeme me from the hand of the
mighty?</ab>

<fw>Mans miserie</fw>
<ab n="24">Teach me, and I
will hold my tongue: and cause mee to vnderstand wherein I haue
erred.</ab>
<ab n="25">How forcible
are right wordes? but what doeth your arguing reproue?</ab>
<ab n="26">Do ye imagine
to reproue words, and the speeches of one that is desperate, which
are as winde?</ab>
<ab n="27">Yea, ye
ouerwhelme the fatherlesse, and you digge a pit for your
friend.<note> Hebr. ye cause to fall vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Now therefore
be content, looke vpon mee, for it is euident vnto you, if I
lie.<note> Heb. before your face.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Returne, I pray
you, let it not be iniquitie; yea returne againe: my righteousnesse
is in it.<note> That is, in this matter.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Is there
iniquitie in my tongue? cannot my taste discerne peruerse
things?<note> Hebr. my palate.</note></ab>



</div>