<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-39-40.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 Iob humbleth himselfe to God. 6
God stirreth him vp to shew his righteousnes, power, and wisedome.
15 Of the Behemoth.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer the
Lord answered Iob, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Shall hee that
contendeth with the Almightie, instruct him? he that reproueth God,
let him answere it.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Then Iob
answered the Lord, and said,</ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, I am
vile, what shall I answere thee? I wil lay my hand vpon my
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="5">Once haue I
spoken, but I will not answere: yea twise, but I will proceed no
further.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then
answered the Lord vnto Iob out of the whirlewinde, and
said:</ab>
<ab n="7">Gird vp thy
loynes now like a man: I will demaund of thee, and declare thou
vnto me.<note> Chap.38. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Wilt thou also
disanul my iudgement? Wilt thou condemne mee, that thou mayest be
righteous?<note> Psal. 50. 21. rom.3. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Hast thou an
arme like God? or canst thou thunder with a voyce like him?</ab>
<ab n="10">Decke thy
selfe now with Maiestie, and excellencie, and aray thy selfe with
glory, and beautie.<note> Psal. 104. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Cast abroad
the rage of thy wrath: and behold euery one that is proud, and
abase him.</ab>
<ab n="12">Looke on euery
one that is proud, and bring him low: and tread downe the wicked in
their place.</ab>

<fw>Behemoth, and Leuiathan</fw>
<ab n="13">Hide them in
the dust together, and binde their faces in secret.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then will I
also confesse vnto thee, that thine owne right hand can saue
thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Beholde
now Behemoth which I made with thee, hee eateth grasse as an
oxe.<note> Or, the Elephant, as some think.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Loe now, his
strength is in his loynes, and his force is in the nauell of his
belly.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hee moueth his
taile like a Cedar: the sinewes of his stones are wrapt
together.<note> Or, he setteth vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">His bones are
as strong pieces of brasse: his bones are like barres of
iron.</ab>
<ab n="19">Hee is the
chiefe of the wayes of God: he that made him, can make his sword to
approach vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="20">Surely the
mountaines bring him foorth foode: where all the beasts of the
field play.</ab>
<ab n="21">He lieth vnder
the shady trees in the couert of the reede, and fennes.</ab>
<ab n="22">The shady
trees couer him with their shaddow: the willowes of the brooke
compasse him about.</ab>
<ab n="23">Behold, he
drinketh vp a riuer, and hasteth not: he trusteth that he can draw
vp Iordan into his mouth.<note> Heb. he oppresseth.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">He taketh it
with his eyes: his nose pearceth through snares.<note> Or, will any take him in his sight? or bore his nose with a ginne?</note></ab>



</div>