<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The harme of inconsideration. 3
The ende of the wicked is misery. 6 God is to be regarded in
affliction. 17 The happy ende of Gods correction.</head>

<ab n="1">Call now, if
there be any that wil answere thee, and to which of the Saints wilt
thou turne?<note> Or, looke.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For wrath
killeth the foolish man, and enuy slayeth the silly
one.<note> Or, indignation.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I haue seene the
foolish taking roote: but suddenly I cursed his habitation.</ab>
<ab n="4">His children are
farre from safetie, and they are crushed in the gate, neither is
there any to deliuer them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Whose haruest
the hungry eateth vp, and taketh it euen out of the thorns, and the
robber swalloweth vp their substance.</ab>
<ab n="6">Although
affliction commeth not forth of the dust, neither doeth trouble
spring out of the ground:<note> Or, iniquity.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Yet man is borne
vnto trouble, as the sparkes flie vpward.<note> Or, labour. , Heb. the sonnes of the burning coale, lift vp to flie.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">I would seeke
vnto God, and vnto God would I commit my cause:</ab>
<ab n="9">Which doth great
things &amp; vnsearchable: marueilous things without
number.<note> Cha.9.10. psal.72.18. rom.11.33. , Heb. and there is no search. , Heb. till there be no number.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Who giueth
raine vpon the earth, and sendeth waters vpon the
fields:<note> Heb. outplaces.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">To set vp on
high those that be low; that those which mourne, may be exalted to
safetie.<note> Psa.113.6. 1.sam.2.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Hee
disappointeth the deuices of the craftie, so that their hands
cannot performe their enterprise.<note> Neh.4.15. psal. 33.10. isa.8.10. , Or, cannot performe anything.</note></ab>

<fw>The diuers ends of godly and
wicked.</fw>
<ab n="13">He taketh the
wise in their owne craftinesse: and the counsell of the froward is
caried headlong.<note> 1.Cor.3. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">They meete with
darkenesse in the day time, and grope in the noone day as in the
night.<note> Deut.28. 29. , Or, runne into.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But he saueth
the poore from the sword, from their mouth, and from the hand of
the mightie.</ab>
<ab n="16">So the poore
hath hope, and iniquitie stoppeth her mouth.<note> Psal. 107. 42.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Behold, happy
is the man whom God correcteth: therefore despise not thou the
chastening of the Almightie.<note> Pro.3.12. iames 1.12. heb.12.5. apoc.3. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For he maketh
sore, and bindeth vp: he woundeth, and his hands make
whole.<note> Deut.32. 39. 1.sam. 2.6. isa.30. 26. hos.6.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Hee shall
deliuer thee in sixe troubles, yea in seuen there shall no euill
touch thee.<note> Psal.91.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">In famine he
shall redeeme thee from death: and in warre from the power of the
sword.<note> Heb. from the hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Thou shalt be
hidde from the scourge of the tongue: neither shalt thou be afraid
of destruction, when it commeth.<note> Or, when the tongue scourgeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">At destruction
and famine thou shalt laugh: neither shalt thou be afraid of the
beasts of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="23">For thou shalt
be in league with the stones of the field: and the beasts of the
field shall be at peace with thee.<note> Hos.2.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And thou shalt
know that thy tabernacle shall bee in peace; and thou shalt visite
thy habitation, and shalt not sinne.<note> Or, that peace is thy tabernacle. , Or, erre.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Thou shalt know
also that thy seede shalbe great, and thine offspring as the grasse
of the earth.<note> Or, much.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Thou shalt come
to thy graue in a full age, like as a shocke of corne commeth in,
in his season.<note> Heb. ascendeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Loe this, wee
haue searched it, so it is; heare it, and know thou it for thy
good.<note> Heb. for thyselfe.</note></ab>



</div>