<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_42" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLII.</head>
<head>1 Iob submitteth himselfe vnto God.
7 God preferring Iobs cause, maketh his friends submit themselues,
&amp; accepteth him. 10 He magnifieth &amp; blesseth Iob. 16 Iobs
age &amp; death.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iob
answered the Lord, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">I know that
thou canst doe euery thing, and that no thought can bee withholden
from thee.<note> Or, no thought of thine can be hindred.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Who is he that
hideth counsel without knowledge? therefore haue I vttered that I
vnderstood not, things too wonderfull for me, which I knew
not.<note> Chap. 38. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Heare, I
beseech thee, and I will speake: I will demand of thee, and declare
thou vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="5">I haue heard of
thee by the hearing of the eare: but now mine eye seeth
thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore I
abhorre my selfe, and repent in dust and ashes.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And it
was so, that after the Lord had spoken these words vnto Iob, the
Lord said to Eliphaz the Temanite, My wrath is kindled against
thee, &amp; against thy two friends: for ye haue not spoken of mee
the thing that is right, as my seruant Iob hath.</ab>

<fw>Iobs repentance, and felicitie.</fw>
<ab n="8">Therefore take
vnto you now seuen bullocks, and seuen rammes, and goe to my
seruant Iob, and offer vp for your selues a burnt offring, and my
seruant Iob shal pray for you, for him wil I accept: lest I deale
with you after your folly, in that ye haue not spoken of mee the
thing which is right, like my seruant Iob.<note> Heb. his face or person.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So Eliphaz the
Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite went,
and did according as the Lord commanded them: the Lord also
accepted Iob.<note> Heb. the face of Iob.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the Lord
turned the captiuitie of Iob, when he prayed for his friends: also
the Lord gaue Iob twice as much as he had before.<note> Heb. added to Iob vnto the double.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then came
there vnto him all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all they
that had bin of his acquaintance before, and did eat bread with him
in his house: and they bemoned him, and comforted him ouer all the
euill that the Lord had brought vpon him: euery man also gaue him a
piece of money, and euery one an eare-ring of gold.</ab>
<ab n="12">So the Lord
blessed the latter end of Iob, more then his beginning: for he had
fourteene thousand sheepe, and sixe thousand camels, and a thousand
yoke of oxen, and a thousand shee asses.</ab>
<ab n="13">He had also
seuen sonnes, and three daughters.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he called
the name of the first, Iemima, and the name of the second, Kezia,
and the name of the third, Keren-happuch.</ab>
<ab n="15">And in all the
land were no women found so faire as the daughters of Iob: and
their father gaue them inheritance among their brethren.</ab>
<ab n="16">After this
liued Iob an hundred and fourtie yeeres, and saw his sonnes, and
his sonnes sonnes, euen foure generations.</ab>
<ab n="17">So Iob died
being old, and full of dayes.</ab>



</div>