<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 Elihu offereth himselfe in stead
of God, with sinceritie and meekenesse to reason with Iob. 8 He
excuseth God from giuing man an account of his wayes, by his
greatnesse. 14 God calleth man to repentance by visions, 19 by
afflictions, 23 and by his ministery. 31 Hee inciteth Iob to
attention.</head>


<fw>Gods chastisements: His mercie.</fw>
<ab n="1">Wherefore, Iob,
I pray thee, heare my speeches, and hearken to all my
wordes.</ab>
<ab n="2">Behold, now I
haue opened my mouth, my tongue hath spoken in my
mouth.<note> Heb. in my palate.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">My words shalbe
of the vprightnesse of my heart: and my lippes shall vtter
knowledge clearely.</ab>
<ab n="4">The Spirit of
God hath made me, and the breath of the Almightie hath giuen me
life.</ab>
<ab n="5">If thou canst,
answere me, set thy wordes in order before me, stand vp.</ab>
<ab n="6">Behold, I am
according to thy wish in Gods stead: I also am formed out of the
clay.<note> Cha.9.35. and 23. 20. , Heb. according to thy mouth. , Heb. cut out of the clay.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Behold, my
terrour shall not make thee afraid, neither shall my hand be heauie
vpon thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Surely thou
hast spoken in mine hearing, and I haue heard the voice of thy
words, saying,<note> Heb. in mine eares.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">I am cleane
without transgression, I am innocent; neither is there iniquitie in
me.</ab>
<ab n="10">Behold, hee
findeth occasions against mee, hee counteth mee for his
enemie.</ab>
<ab n="11">He putteth my
feete in the stockes, he marketh all my pathes.</ab>
<ab n="12">Behold, in
this thou art not iust: I will answere thee, That God is greater
then man.</ab>
<ab n="13">Why doest thou
striue against him? for he giueth not account of any of his
matters.<note> Heb. hee answereth not.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For God
speaketh once, yea twice, yet man perceiueth it not.</ab>
<ab n="15">In a dreame,
in a vision of the night, when deepe sleepe falleth vpon men, in
slumbrings vpon the bed:</ab>
<ab n="16">Then hee
openeth the eares of men, and sealeth their
instruction,<note> Heb. hee reuealeth, or vncouereth.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">That hee may
withdraw man from his purpose, and hide pride from man.<note> Heb. worke.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Hee keepeth
backe his soule from the pit, and his life from perishing by the
sword.<note> Heb. from passing by the sword.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Hee is
chastened also with paine vpon his bed, and the multitude of his
bones with strong paine.</ab>

<fw>Gods chastisements: His mercie.</fw>
<ab n="20">So that his
life abhorreth bread, and his soule daintie meate.<note> Psal.107. 17. , Heb. meate of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">His flesh is
consumed away that it cannot be seene; and his bones that were not
seene, sticke out.</ab>
<ab n="22">His soule
draweth neere vnto the graue, and his life to the
destroyers.</ab>
<ab n="23">If there be a
messenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thousand, to shew
vnto man his vprightnesse:</ab>
<ab n="24">Then hee is
gracious vnto him, and sayth, Deliuer him from going downe to the
pit; I haue found a ransome.<note> Or, an atonement.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">His flesh
shall be fresher then a childes: he shall returne to the dayes of
his youth.<note> Hebr. then childhood.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He shall pray
vnto God, and hee will be fauourable vnto him, and hee shall see
his face with ioy: for hee will render vnto man his
righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="27">He looketh
vpon men, and if any say, I haue sinned, and peruerted that which
was right, and it profited mee not:<note> Or, he shall looke vpon men, and say, I haue sinned, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Hee will
deliuer his soule from going into the pit, and his life shall see
the light.<note> Or, he hath deliuered my soule &amp;c. and my life.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Loe, all these
things worketh God oftentimes with man,<note> Heb. twice and thrice.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">To bring backe
his soule from the pit, to be enlightened with the light of the
liuing.</ab>
<ab n="31">Marke well, O
Iob, hearken vnto me, hold thy peace, and I wil speake.</ab>
<ab n="32">If thou hast
any thing to say, answere me: speake, for I desire to iustifie
thee.</ab>
<ab n="33">If not,
hearken vnto me: holde thy peace, and I shall teach thee
wisedome.</ab>



</div>