<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Eliphaz sheweth that mans
goodnesse profiteth not God. 5 Hee accuseth Iob of diuers sinnes.
21 He exhorteth him to repentance, with promises of
mercy.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Eliphaz
the Temanite answered, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Can a man be
profitable vnto God? as hee that is wise may be profitable vnto
himselfe.<note> Or, if hee may be profitable, doth his good successe depend thereon?</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Is it any
pleasure to the Almighty, that thou art righteous? or is it gaine
to him, that thou makest thy waies perfite?</ab>

<fw>Eliphaz exhorteth Iob to
repentance.</fw>
<ab n="4">Will hee
reproue thee for feare of thee? will he enter with thee into
iudgment?</ab>
<ab n="5">Is not thy
wickednesse great? and thine iniquities infinite?</ab>
<ab n="6">For thou hast
taken a pledge from thy brother for nought, and stripped the naked
of their clothing.<note> Heb. stripped the clothes of the naked.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thou hast not
giuen water to the wearie to drinke, and thou hast withholden bread
from the hungry.</ab>
<ab n="8">But as for the
mightie man, hee had the earth, and the honourable man dwelt in
it.<note> Heb. the man of arme , Heb. eminent or accepted for countenance.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thou hast sent
widowes away emptie, and the armes of the fatherlesse haue bene
broken.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore
snares are round about thee, and sudden feare troubleth
thee,</ab>
<ab n="11">Or darkenes
that thou canst not see, and abundance of waters couer
thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Is not God in
the height of heauen? and behold the height of the starres how high
they are.<note> Heb. the head of the starres.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And thou
sayest, How doth God know? can he iudge through the darke
cloude?<note> Or, what.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thicke cloudes
are a couering to him that he seeth not, and hee walketh in the
circuit of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="15">Hast thou
marked the olde way which wicked men haue troden?</ab>
<ab n="16">Which were cut
downe out of time, whose foundation was ouerflowen with a
flood.<note> Heb. a flood was powred vpon their foundation.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Which said
vnto God, Depart from vs, and what can the Almightie doe for
them?<note> Chap. 21. 14. , Or, to them</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Yet he filled
their houses with good things: but the counsell of the wicked is
farre from me.<note> Chap. 21. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The righteous
see it, and are glad, and the innocent laugh them to
scorne.<note> Psal.107. 42.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Whereas our
substance is not cut downe, but the remnant of them the fire
consumeth.<note> Or, estate. , Or, their excellencie.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Acquaint now
thy selfe with him, and be at peace: thereby good shal come vnto
thee.<note> That is, with God.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Receiue, I
pray thee, the Lawe from his mouth, and lay vp his words in thine
heart.</ab>
<ab n="23">If thou
returne to the Almightie, thou shalt be built vp, thou shalt put
away iniquitie farre from thy tabernacles.<note> Chap.8. 5.</note></ab>

<fw>Eliphaz exhorteth Iob to
repentance.</fw>
<ab n="24">Then shalt
thou lay vp golde as dust, and the gold of Ophir as the stones of
the brookes.<note> Or on the dust.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Yea the
Almightie shall bee thy defence, and thou shalt haue plenty of
siluer.<note> Or, gold. , Heb. siluer of strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For then shalt
thou haue thy delight in the Almightie, and shalt lift vp thy face
vnto God.</ab>
<ab n="27">Thou shalt
make thy prayer vnto him, and he shall heare thee, and thou shalt
pay thy vowes.</ab>
<ab n="28">Thou shalt
also decree a thing, and it shal be established vnto thee: and the
light shall shine vpon thy wayes.</ab>
<ab n="29">When men are
cast downe, then thou shalt say, There is lifting vp: and he shall
saue the humble person.<note> Heb. him that hath lowe eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">He shall
deliuer the Iland of the innocent: and it is deliuered by the
purenesse of thine hands.<note> Or, the innocent shall deliuer the Iland.</note></ab>



</div>