<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Eliphaz reprooueth Iob for want of
religion. 7 He teacheth Gods iudgements to bee not for the
righteous, but for the wicked. 12 His fearefull vision, to humble
the excellencie of Creatures before God.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Eliphaz the
Temanite answered, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">If we assay to
commune with thee, wilt thou be grieued? But who can withhold
himselfe from speaking?<note> Hebr. a word. , Heb. who can refraine from words?</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Beholde, Thou
hast instructed many, and thou hast strengthened the weake
hands.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thy words haue
vpholden him that was falling, and thou hast strengthened the
feeble knees.<note> Hebr. the bowing knees.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But now it is
come vpon thee, and thou faintest, it toucheth thee, and thou art
troubled.</ab>
<ab n="6">Is not this thy
feare, thy confidence; the vprightnesse of thy wayes and thy
hope?</ab>
<ab n="7">Remember, I pray
thee, who euer perished, being innocent? or where were the
righteous cut off?</ab>
<ab n="8">Euen as I haue
seene, they that plow iniquity, and sow wickednsse, reape the
same.<note> Prou.22.8 ose 10.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">By the blast of
God they perish, and by the breath of his nostrils are they
consumed.<note> That is, by his anger, as Esa.30. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The roaring of
the Lyon, and the voice of the fierce Lyon, and the teeth of the
yong Lyons are broken.</ab>
<ab n="11">The old Lyon
perisheth for lacke of pray, and the stout Lyons whelpes are
scattered abroad.</ab>
<ab n="12">Nowe a thing
was secretly brought to me, and mine eare receiued a litle
thereof.<note> Heb. by stealth.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">In thoughts
from the visions of the night, when deepe sleepe falleth on
men:</ab>
<ab n="14">Feare came vpon
me, and trembling, which made all my bones to shake.<note> Heb. met mee. , Heb. the multitude of my bones.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then a spirit
passed before my face: the haire of my flesh stood vp.</ab>
<ab n="16">It stood still,
but I could not discerne the forme thereof: an image was before
mine eyes, there was silence, and I heard a voyce,
saying,<note> Or, I heard a still voyce.</note></ab>

<fw>The diuers ends of godly and
wicked.</fw>
<ab n="17">Shall mortall
man be more iust then God? shall a man bee more pure then his
maker?</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold, hee put
no trust in his seruants; and his Angels hee charged with
folly:<note> Chap. 15. 15. 2.pet. 2.4. , Or, nor in his Angels, in whom he put light.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Howe much lesse
on them that dwell in houses of clay, whose foundation is in the
dust, which are crushed before the moth.<note> 2.Cor.5.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">They are
destroyed from morning to euening: they perish for euer, without
any regarding it.<note> Heb. beaten in pieces.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Doeth not their
excellencie which is in them, goe away? they die, euen without
wisedome.</ab>



</div>