<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 Iobs honour is turned into extreme
contempt. 15 His prosperitie into calamitie.</head>

<ab n="1">But nowe they
that are yonger then I, haue mee in derision, whose fathers I would
haue disdained to haue set with the dogs of my flocke.<note> Heb. of fewer dayes then I.</note></ab>

<fw>Iobs former prosperitie, and present
miserie.</fw>
<ab n="2">Yea whereto
might the strength of their hands profit me, in whom olde age was
perished?</ab>
<ab n="3">For want and
famine they were solitarie: flying into the wildernesse in former
time desolate and waste:<note> Or, darke as the night. , Heb. yesternight.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Who cut vp
mallowes by the bushes, and Iuniper rootes for their meate.</ab>
<ab n="5">They were
driuen foorth from among men, (they cried after them, as after a
thiefe.)</ab>
<ab n="6">To dwell in the
clifts of the valleys, in caues of the earth, and in the
rockes.<note> Heb. holes.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Among the
bushes they brayed: vnder the nettles they were gathered
together.</ab>
<ab n="8">They were
children of fooles, yea children of base men: they were viler then
the earth.<note> Heb. men of no name.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And now am I
their song, yea I am their by-word.<note> Psal.35. 15. and 69. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They abhorre
me, they flee farre from me, and spare not to spit in my
face.<note> Heb. and withhold not spittle from my face.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Because hee
hath loosed my cord and afflicted me, they haue also let loose the
bridle before me.</ab>
<ab n="12">Upon my right
hand rise the youth, they push away my feete, and they raise vp
against mee the wayes of their destruction.</ab>
<ab n="13">They marre my
path, they set forward my calamitie, they haue no helper.</ab>
<ab n="14">They came vpon
me as a wide breaking in of waters: in the desolation they rolled
themselues vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="15">Terrours are
turned vpon mee: they pursue my soule as the wind: and my welfare
passeth away as a cloude.<note> Heb. my principall one</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And now my
soule is powred out vpon me: the dayes of affliction haue taken
hold vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="17">My bones are
pierced in mee in the night season: and my sinewes take no
rest.</ab>
<ab n="18">By the great
force of my disease, is my garment changed: it bindeth mee about as
the collar of my coat.</ab>
<ab n="19">He hath cast
mee into the myre, and I am become like dust and ashes.</ab>
<ab n="20">I crie vnto
thee, and thou doest not heare me: I stand vp, and thou regardest
me not.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thou art
become cruell to me: with thy strong hand thou opposest thy selfe
against me.<note> Heb. turned to be cruell. , Hebr. the strength of thy hand.</note></ab>

<fw>Iob professeth his integritie.</fw>
<ab n="22">Thou liftest
me vp to the wind: thou causest me to ride vpon it, and dissoluest
my substance.<note> Or, wisedome.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For I know
that thou wilt bring me to death, and to the house appointed for
all liuing.</ab>
<ab n="24">Howbeit he
will not stretch out his hand to the graue, though they cry in his
destruction.<note> Heb. heape.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Did not I
weepe for him that was in trouble? was not my soule grieued for the
poore?<note> Rom.12. 15. psal.35. 13. , Heb. for him that was hard of day.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">When I looked
for good, then euill came vnto mee: and when I waited for light,
there came darkenes.</ab>
<ab n="27">My bowels
boyled and rested not: the dayes of affliction preuented
mee.</ab>
<ab n="28">I went
mourning without the Sunne: I stood vp, and I cried in the
Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="29">I am a brother
to dragons, and a companion to owles.<note> Psal.102. 6. , Or, ostriches.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">My skinne is
blacke vpon mee, and my bones are burnt with heat.</ab>
<ab n="31">My harpe also
is turned to mourning, and my organe into the voyce of them that
weepe.</ab>



</div>