<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-27-29.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>Iob bemoaneth himselfe, of his
former prosperitie and honour.</head>

<ab n="1">Moreouer Iob
continued his parable, and said,<note> Heb. added to take vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">O that I were
as in moneths past, as in the dayes when God preserued me.</ab>
<ab n="3">When his candle
shined vpon my head, and when by his light I walked through
darkenesse:<note> Or.lampe</note></ab>
<ab n="4">As I was in the
dayes of my youth, when the secret of God was vpon my
tabernacle:</ab>
<ab n="5">When the
Almightie was yet with me, when my children were about me:</ab>
<ab n="6">When I washed
my steps with butter, and the rocke powred me out riuers of
oyle:<note> Heb. with me.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">When I went out
to the gate, through the citie, when I prepared my seate in the
street.</ab>

<fw>Iobs former prosperitie, and present
miserie.</fw>
<ab n="8">The yong men
saw me, and hid themselues: and the aged arose, and stood
vp.</ab>
<ab n="9">The princes
refrained talking, and laid their hand on their mouth.</ab>
<ab n="10">The Nobles
held their peace, and their tongue cleaued to the roofe of their
mouth.<note> Heb. the voice of the nobles was hid.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">When the eare
heard mee, then it blessed me, and when the eye saw me, it gaue
witnesse to me:</ab>
<ab n="12">Because I
deliuered the poore that cried, and the fatherlesse, and him that
had none to helpe him.</ab>
<ab n="13">The blessing
of him that was readie to perish, came vpon me: and I caused the
widowes heart to sing for ioy.</ab>
<ab n="14">I put on
righteousnesse, and it clothed me: my iudgement was as a robe and a
diademe.</ab>
<ab n="15">I was eyes to
the blind, and feet was I to the lame.</ab>
<ab n="16">I was a father
to the poore: and the cause which I knewe not, I searched
out.</ab>
<ab n="17">And I brake
the iawes of the wicked, and pluckt the spoile out of his
teeth.<note> Heb. the iaw teeth or the grinders , Heb. I cast</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Then I said, I
shall die in my nest, and I shall multiplie my dayes as the
sand.</ab>
<ab n="19">My roote was
spread out by the waters, and the dew lay all night vpon my
branch.<note> Heb. opened.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">My glory was
fresh in mee, and my bow was renewed in my hand.<note> Heb. new. , Heb. changed.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Unto me men
gaue eare, and waited, and kept silence at my counsell.</ab>
<ab n="22">After my words
they spake not againe, &amp; my speach dropped vpon them,</ab>
<ab n="23">And they
waited for me as for the raine, and they opened their mouth wide as
for the latter raine.</ab>
<ab n="24">If I laughed
on them, they beleeued it not, and the light of my countenance they
cast not downe.</ab>
<ab n="25">I chose out
their way, and sate chiefe, and dwelt as a king in the army, as one
that comforteth the mourners.</ab>



</div>