<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Iob mainteineth himselfe against
his friends that reproue him. 7 He acknowledgeth the generall
doctrine of Gods omnipotencie.</head>


<fw>Gods perfection.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Iob
answered, and sayd,</ab>
<ab n="2">No doubt but ye
are the people, and wisedome shall die with you.</ab>
<ab n="3">But I haue
vnderstanding as well as you, I am not inferiour to you: yea, who
knoweth not such things as these?<note> Heb. an heart. , Heb. I fall not lower then you. , Heb. with whom are not such as these?</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I am as one
mocked of his neighbour, who calleth vpon God, and he answereth
him: the iust vpright man is laughed to scorne.</ab>
<ab n="5">He that is
ready to slippe with his feet, is as a lamp despised in the thought
of him that is at ease.</ab>
<ab n="6">The tabernacles
of robbers prosper, and they that prouoke God are secure, into
whose hand God bringeth abundantly.</ab>
<ab n="7">But aske now
the beasts, and they shall teach thee; and the foules of the aire,
and they shall tell thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Or speake to
the earth, and it shall teach thee; and the fishes of the sea shall
declare vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">Who knoweth not
in all these, that the hand of the Lord hath wrought this?</ab>
<ab n="10">In whose hand
is the soule of euery liuing thing, and the breath of all
mankinde.<note> Or, life. , Heb. all flesh of man.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Doeth not the
eare trie wordes? and the mouth taste his meate?<note> Cha.34.3. , Heb. palate.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">With the
ancient is wisedome, and in length of dayes, vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="13">With him is
wisedome &amp; strength, he hath counsell and
vnderstanding.<note> That is, with God.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, he
breaketh downe, and it cannot be built againe: hee shutteth vp a
man, and there can be no opening.<note> Isa.22.22. , Apoc 3.7. , Heb. vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Behold, hee
withholdeth the waters, and they drie vp: also hee sendeth them
out, and they ouerturne the earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">With him is
strength &amp; wisedome: the deceiued, and the deceiuer, are
his.</ab>
<ab n="17">He leadeth
counsellers away spoiled, and maketh the Iudges fooles.</ab>
<ab n="18">He looseth the
bond of kings, and girdeth their loines with a girdle.</ab>
<ab n="19">He leadeth
Princes away spoiled, and ouerthroweth the mightie.</ab>
<ab n="20">He remooueth
away the speech of the trustie, and taketh away the vnderstanding
of the aged.<note> Cha.32.9. , Heb. the lip of the faithfull.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He powreth
contempt vpon princes, and weakeneth the strength of the
mightie.<note> Or, looseth the girdle of the strong.</note></ab>

<fw>Iobs confidence.</fw>
<ab n="22">Hee
discouereth deepe things out of darkenesse, and bringeth out to
light the shadow of death.</ab>
<ab n="23">He increaseth
the nations, and destroyeth them: hee inlargeth the nations, and
straiteneth them againe.<note> Heb. leadeth in.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">He taketh away
the heart of the chiefe of the people of the earth, and causeth
them to wander in a wildernes where there is no way.</ab>
<ab n="25">They grope in
the darke without light, and hee maketh them to stagger like a
drunken man.<note> Heb. wander.</note></ab>



</div>