<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Bildad sheweth Gods iustice, in
dealing with men according to their workes. 8 He alledgeth
antiquitie to proue the certaine destruction of the Hypocrite. 20
Hee applieth Gods iust dealing to Iob.</head>

<ab n="1">Then answered
Bildad the Shuhite, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">How long wilt
thou speake these things? and how long shall the wordes of thy
mouth be like a strong wind?</ab>
<ab n="3">Doth God peruert
iudgement? or doth the Almightie peruert iustice?<note> Deu.32.4 2.chro.19.7 dan.9.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">If thy children
haue sinned against him, and he haue cast them away for their
transgression:<note> Heb. in the hand of their transgression</note></ab>
<ab n="5">If thou wouldest
seeke vnto God betimes, and make thy supplication to the
Almightie:<note> Chap.22. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">If thou wert
pure and vpright, surely now he would awake for thee, and make the
habitation of thy righteousnes prosperous.</ab>

<fw>God righteous.</fw>
<ab n="7">Though thy
beginning was small, yet thy latter end should greatly
increase.</ab>
<ab n="8">For enquire, I
pray thee, of the former age, and prepare thy selfe to the search
of their fathers.<note> Deut.4. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">(For we are but
of yesterday, and know nothing, because our dayes vpon earth are a
shadow.)<note> See chap. 7.6. gen.47 9. 1.chron. 29.15. psal. 144.4. psal. 39.14. , Heb. not.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Shall not they
teach thee, and tell thee, &amp; vtter words out of their
heart?</ab>
<ab n="11">Can the rush
growe vp without myre? can the flag growe without water?</ab>
<ab n="12">Whilest it is
yet in his greennesse, and not cut downe, it withereth before any
other herbe.<note> Psal. 129. 6. ier.17.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">So are the
paths of all that forget God, and the hypocrites hope shall
perish:<note> Iob.11.20 and 18,14. psal.112.10 prou.10.28</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Whose hope
shall be cut off, and whose trust shall be a spiders
web.<note> Heb. a spiders house.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">He shall leane
vpon his house, but it shall not stand: he shal hold it fast, but
it shall not endure.</ab>
<ab n="16">He is greene
before the sunne, and his branch shooteth forth in his
garden.</ab>
<ab n="17">His roots are
wrapped about the heape, and seeth the place of stones.</ab>
<ab n="18">If he destroy
him from his place, then it shal denie him, saying, I haue not
seene thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">Beholde, this
is the ioy of his way, and out of the earth shall others
grow.</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, God
will not cast away a perfect man, neither will hee helpe the euill
doers:<note> Heb. take the vngodly by the hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Till he fill
thy mouth with laughing, and thy lips with reioycing.<note> Heb. shouting for ioy.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">They that hate
thee shall be cloathed with shame, and the dwelling place of the
wicked shall come to nought.<note> Heb. shall not be.</note></ab>



</div>