<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Iob, taking libertie of complaint,
expostulateth with God about his afflictions. 18 Hee complaineth of
life, and craueth a little ease before death.</head>

<ab n="1">My soule is
weary of my life, I will leaue my complaint vpon my selfe; I will
speake in the bitternesse of my soule.<note> Or, eue of while I liue.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I will say vnto
God, Doe not condemne mee; shewe me wherefore thou contendest with
me.</ab>
<ab n="3">Is it good vnto
thee, that thou shouldest oppresse? that thou shouldest despise the
worke of thine hands? and shine vpon the counsell of the
wicked?<note> Heb. the labour of thine hands.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Hast thou eyes
of flesh? or seest thou as man seeth?</ab>
<ab n="5">Are thy dayes
as the dayes of man? are thy yeeres as mans dayes,</ab>
<ab n="6">That thou
enquirest after mine iniquitie, and searchest after my
sinne?</ab>
<ab n="7">Thou knowest
that I am not wicked, and there is none that can deliuer out of
thine hand.<note> Heb. It is vpon thy knowledge.</note></ab>

<fw>Mans righteousnesse.</fw>
<ab n="8">Thine hands
haue made me and fashioned me together round about yet thou doest
destroy me.<note> Heb. tooke praises about me.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Remember, I
beseech thee, that thou hast made me as the clay, and wilt thou
bring me into dust againe?</ab>
<ab n="10">Hast thou not
powred me out as milke, and cruddled me like cheese?<note> Psal.139. 4 and 14, 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Thou hast
cloathed me with skin and flesh, and hast fenced me with bones and
sinewes.<note> Heb. hedged.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thou hast
granted me life and fauour, and thy visitation hath preserued my
spirit.</ab>
<ab n="13">And these
things hast thou hid in thine heart; I know that this is with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">If I sinne,
then thou markest me, and thou wilt not acquite me from mine
iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="15">If I be
wicked, woe vnto me; and if I be righteous, yet will I not lift vp
my head: I am full of confusion, therefore see thou mine
affliction:</ab>
<ab n="16">For it
increaseth: thou huntest me as a fierce Lion: and againe thou
shewest thy selfe marueilous vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thou renuest
thy witnesses against me, and increasest thine indignation vpon me;
Changes and warre are against me.<note> That is, thy plagues.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Wherfore then
hast thou brought me forth out of the wombe? Oh that I had giuen vp
the ghost, and no eye had seene me!<note> Chap.3. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">I should haue
bene as though I had not bene, I should haue bene caried from the
wombe to the graue.</ab>
<ab n="20">Are not my
dayes few? cease then, and let me alone that I may take comfort a
litle,<note> See Chap. 8.9. and 7. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Before I goe
whence I shall not returne, euen to the land of darknes and the
shadow of death,</ab>
<ab n="22">A land of
darknes, as darknes it selfe, and of the shadow of death, without
any order, and where the light is as darkenes.</ab>



</div>