<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-25-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-27-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Iob protesteth his sincerity. 8
The Hypocrite is without hope. 11 The blessings, which the wicked
haue, are turned into curses:</head>


<fw>Hypocrites hope.</fw>
<ab n="1">Moreouer Iob
continued his parable, and sayd,<note> Heb. added to take vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">As God liueth,
who hath taken away my iudgment, and the Almighty, who hath vexed
my soule;<note> Heb. made my soule bitter.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">All the while
my breath is in mee, and the spirit of God is in my
nostrils;<note> That is, the breath which God gaue him.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">My lips shall
not speake wickednesse, nor my tongue vtter deceit.</ab>
<ab n="5">God forbid that
I should iustifie you: till I die, I will not remoue my integritie
from me.</ab>
<ab n="6">My
righteousnesse I hold fast, and will not let it goe: my heart shall
not reproach me so long as I liue.<note> Heb. from my daies.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Let mine enemie
be as the wicked, and he that riseth vp against me, as the
vnrighteous.</ab>
<ab n="8">For what is the
hope of the hypocrite, though he hath gained, when God taketh away
his soule?<note> Mat.16. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Will God heare
his cry, when trouble commeth vpon him?<note> Prou.1. 28. Ezech. 8.18. Iohn. 9.31. Iam. 4.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Will he
delight himselfe in the Almightie? will hee alwayes call vpon
God?</ab>
<ab n="11">I will teach
you by the hand of God: that which is with the Almightie, will I
not conceale.<note> Or, bring in the hand &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Behold, all ye
your selues haue seene it, why then are yee thus altogether
vaine?</ab>
<ab n="13">This is the
portion of a wicked man with God, and the heritage of oppressours
which they shall receiue of the Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="14">If his
children be multiplied, it is for the sword: and his offpring shall
not be satisfied with bread.</ab>
<ab n="15">Those that
remaine of him shall bee buried in death: and his widowes shall not
weepe.<note> Psal.78. 65.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Though he
heape vp siluer as the dust, and prepare rayment as the
clay:</ab>
<ab n="17">He may prepare
it, but the iust shall put it on, and the innocent shall diuide the
siluer.</ab>
<ab n="18">He buildeth
his house as a moth, and as a booth that the keeper maketh.</ab>
<ab n="19">The rich man
shall lie downe, but he shall not be gathered: he openeth his eyes,
and he is not:</ab>
<ab n="20">Terrours take
hold on him as waters, a tempest stealeth him away in the
night.<note> Chap. 18.11.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wisedome.</fw>
<ab n="21">The East winde
carieth him away, and he departeth: and as a storme hurleth him out
of his place.</ab>
<ab n="22">For God shall
cast vpon him, and not spare: hee would faine flee out of his
hand.<note> Heb. in fleeing he would flee.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Men shall clap
their handes at him, and shall hisse him out of his place.</ab>



</div>