<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 Elihu accuseth Iob for charging
God with iniustice. 10 God omnipotent cannot be vniust. 31 Man must
humble himselfe vnto God. 34 Elihu reprooueth Iob.</head>

<ab n="1">Furthermore
Elihu answered, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Heare my
wordes, O yee wise men, and giue eare vnto me, ye that haue
knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="3">For the eare
trieth words, as the mouth tasteth meate.<note> Chap. 12. 11. , Heb. palate.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Let vs chuse to
vs iudgement: let vs know among our selues what is good.</ab>

<fw>Gods power, and iustice.</fw>
<ab n="5">For Iob hath
said, I am righteous: and God hath taken away my iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="6">Should I lye
against my right? my wound is incurable without
transgression.<note> Hebr. mine arrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">What man is
like Iob, who drinketh vp scorning like water?</ab>
<ab n="8">Which goeth in
company with the workers of iniquitie, and walketh with wicked
men.</ab>
<ab n="9">For hee hath
said, It profiteth a man nothing, that he should delight himselfe
with God.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore
hearken vnto me, ye men of vnderstanding: farre bee it from God,
that he should doe wickednes, and from the Almighty, that hee
should commit iniquitie.<note> Hebr. men of heart. , Exod. 32. 4. iob 8.3. and 36.23. psal. 92.15. rom 9.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For the worke
of a man shall he render vnto him, and cause euery man to finde
according to his wayes.<note> Psal.62. 12. pro. 24. 12. iere.2. 32,19. cze. 33. 20. mat. 16.27. rom. 26.2. cor. 3.10. 1.pet. 1.17. apoc. 22.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Yea surely God
will not doe wickedly, neither will the Almighty peruert
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="13">Who hath giuen
him a charge ouer the earth? or who hath disposed the whole
world?<note> Hebr. all of it.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">If he set his
heart vpon man, if he gather vnto himselfe his spirit and his
breath;<note> Psal. 104. 19. , Hebr. vpon him.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">All flesh
shall perish together, and man shall turne againe vnto
dust.<note> Eccles.12. 6. gene.3. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">If now thou
hast vnderstanding, heare this: hearken to the voyce of my
words.</ab>
<ab n="17">Shall euen he
that hateth right, gouerne? and wilt thou condemne him that is most
iust?<note> Heb. binde.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Is it fit to
say to a King, Thou art wicked? and to Princes, Ye are
vngodly?</ab>
<ab n="19">How much lesse
to him that accepteth not the persons of Princes, nor regardeth the
rich more then the poore? for they all are the woorke of his
hands.<note> Deut. 10. 17.2. chro. 9.7. act. 10.34. rom. 2.11. gal. 2.6. ephe. 6 9. colos.3.25. I. pet. 1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">In a moment
shall they die, and the people shalbe troubled at midnight, and
passe away: and the mighty shall be taken away without
hand.<note> Heb. they shall take away the mighty.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For his eyes
are vpon the wayes of man, and he seeth all his goings.<note> Pro.5.21. and 15.3. iob 31.4. 1. chro. 16. 9 iere.16. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">There is no
darkenes, nor shadow of death, where the workers of iniquitie may
hide themselues.</ab>
<ab n="23">For hee will
not lay vpon man more then right; that he should enter into
iudgement with God.<note> Hebr. goe.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods power, and iustice.</fw>
<ab n="24">He shall
breake in pieces mighty men without number, and set others in their
stead.<note> Heb. without searching out.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore hee
knoweth their workes, and he ouerturneth them in the night, so that
they are destroyed.<note> Hebr. crushed.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He striketh
them as wicked men, in the open sight of others:<note> Hebr. in the place of beholders.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Because they
turned backe from him, and would not consider any of his
wayes.<note> Hebr. from after him.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">So that they
cause the cry of the poore to come vnto him, and he heareth the cry
of the afflicted.</ab>
<ab n="29">When he giueth
quietnesse, who then can make trouble? and when hee hideth his
face, who then can beholde him? whether it be done against a
nation, or against a man onely:</ab>
<ab n="30">That the
hypocrite raigne not, lest the people be ensnared.</ab>
<ab n="31">Surely it is
meete to be said vnto God, I haue borne chastisement, I will not
offend any more.</ab>
<ab n="32">That which I
see not, teach thou me; If I haue done iniquitie, I will doe no
more.</ab>
<ab n="33">Should it bee
according to thy minde? he will recompense it, whether thou refuse,
or whether thou chuse, and not I: therefore speake what thou
knowest.<note> Hebr. Should it be from with thee?</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Let men of
vnderstanding tell mee, and let a wise man hearken vnto
mee.<note> Hebr. of heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Iob hath
spoken without knowledge, and his words were without
wisdome.</ab>
<ab n="36">My desire is
that Iob may bee tried vnto the ende, because of his answeres for
wicked men.<note> Or, My father, let Iob be tried.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">For he addeth
rebellion vnto his sinne, hee clappeth his handes amongst vs, and
multiplieth his words against God.</ab>



</div>