<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Zophar reproueth Iob, for
iustifying himselfe. 5 Gods wisdome is vnsearchable. 13 The assured
blessing of repentance.</head>

<ab n="1">Then answered
Zophar the Naamathite, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Should not the
multitude of words be answered? and should man ful of talke be
iustified?<note> Hebr. a man of lips.</note></ab>

<fw>Iob reproued.</fw>
<ab n="3">Should thy lies
make men hold their peace? and when thou mockest, shall no man make
thee ashamed?<note> Or, deuises.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For thou hast
said, My doctrine is pure, and I am cleane in thine eyes.</ab>
<ab n="5">But, O that God
would speake, and open his lippes against thee,</ab>
<ab n="6">And that he
would shew thee the secrets of wisedome, that they are double to
that which is: know therefore that God exacteth of thee lesse then
thine iniquitie deserueth.</ab>
<ab n="7">Canst thou by
searching finde out God? canst thou finde out the Almightie vnto
perfection?</ab>
<ab n="8">It is as high
as heauen, what canst thou doe? deeper then hell, what canst thou
know?<note> Hebr. the heights of heauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The measure
therof is longer then the earth, and broader then the sea.</ab>
<ab n="10">If he cut off,
and shut vp, or gather together, then who can hinder
him?<note> Or, make a change. , Hebr. who can turne him away?</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For, he
knoweth vaine men: hee seeth wickednesse also, will he not then
consider it?</ab>
<ab n="12">For vaine man
would be wise; though man be borne like a wilde asses
coult.<note> Hebr. emptie.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">If thou
prepare thine heart, and stretch out thine hands toward
him:</ab>
<ab n="14">If iniquitie
be in thine hand, put it farre away, and let not wickednes dwell in
thy tabernacles.</ab>
<ab n="15">For then shalt
thou lift vp thy face without spot, yea thou shalt be stedfast, and
shalt not feare:</ab>
<ab n="16">Because thou
shalt forget thy misery, and remember it as waters that passe
away:</ab>
<ab n="17">And thine age
shalbe clearer then the noone day; thou shalt shine foorth, thou
shalt be as the morning.<note> Hebr. shall arise aboue the nooneday.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And thou shalt
be secure because there is hope, yea thou shalt digge about thee,
and thou shalt take thy rest in safety.</ab>
<ab n="19">Also thou
shalt lye downe, and none shall make thee afraid; yea many shall
make suite vnto thee.<note> Leuit. 26. 5. , Hebr. entreat thy face.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But the eyes
of the wicked shall faile, and they shall not escape, and their
hope shall be as the giuing vp of the ghost.<note> Heb. flight shall perish from them. , Chap.8. 14. and 18. 14. , Or, a puffe of breath.</note></ab>



</div>