<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-23-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Iob longeth to appeare before God,
6 in confidence of his mercie. 8 God who is inuisible, obserueth
our wayes. 11 Iobs innocencie. 13 Gods decree is
immutable.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iob
answered, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Euen to day is
my complaint bitter: my stroke is heauier then my
groning.<note> Hebr. my hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">O that I knewe
where I might find him! that I might come euen to his
seate!</ab>
<ab n="4">I would order
my cause before him, and fill my mouth with arguments.</ab>
<ab n="5">I would know
the words which he would answere me, and vnderstand what he would
say vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="6">Will he plead
against me with his great power? No, but hee would put strength in
me.</ab>
<ab n="7">There the
righteous might dispute with him; so should I be deliuered for euer
from my Iudge.</ab>
<ab n="8">Behold, I goe
forward, but he is not there, and backward, but I cannot perceiue
him:</ab>
<ab n="9">On the left
hand where hee doeth worke, but I cannot behold him: he hideth
himselfe on the right hand, that I cannot see him.</ab>
<ab n="10">But he knoweth
the way that I take: when he hath tried me, I shall come forth as
gold.<note> Heb. the way that is with me.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">My foot hath
held his steps, his way haue I kept, and not declined.</ab>

<fw>The oppression of the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="12">Neither haue I
gone backe from the commaundement of his lippes, I haue esteemed
the words of his mouth more then my necessary food.<note> Hebr. I haue hid, or layd vp. , Or, my appointed portion.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But hee is in
one minde, and who can turne him? and what his soule desireth, euen
that he doeth.<note> Psal.115. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For he
performeth the thing that is appointed for mee: and many such
things are with him.</ab>
<ab n="15">Therefore am I
troubled at his presence: when I consider, I am afraid of
him.</ab>
<ab n="16">For God maketh
my heart soft, and the Almighty troubleth me:</ab>
<ab n="17">Because I was
not cut off before the darknes, neither hath he couered the darknes
from my face.</ab>



</div>