<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Iob curseth the day, and seruices
of his birth. 13 The ease of death. 20 He complaineth of life,
because of his anguish.</head>

<ab n="1">After this,
opened Iob his mouth, and cursed his day.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Iob spake,
and said,<note> Hebr. answered.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Let the day
perish, wherein I was borne, and the night in which it was said,
There is a man-childe conceiued.<note> Chap.10. 18, 19. iere. 20.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Let that day bee
darkenesse, let not God regard it from aboue, neither let the light
shine vpon it.</ab>

<fw>Iobs impatiencie is
reprehended.</fw>
<ab n="5">Let darkenes and
the shadowe of death staine it, let a cloud dwell vpon it, let the
blacknes of the day terrifie it.<note> Or, challenge it. , Or, let them terrifie it, as those who haue a bitter day.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">As for that
night, let darkenesse seaze vpon it, let it not be ioyned vnto the
dayes of the yeere, let it not come into the number of the
moneths.<note> Or, let it not reioyce among the dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Loe, let that
night be solitarie, let no ioyfull voice come therein.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let them curse
it that curse the day, who are ready to raise vp their
mourning.<note> Or, Leuiathan.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Let the starres
of the twilight thereof be darke, let it looke for light, but haue
none, neither let it see the dawning of the day:<note> Heb. the eye lids of the morning.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Because it shut
not vp the doores of my mothers wombe, nor hid sorrowe from mine
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="11">Why died I not
from the wombe? why did I not giue vp the ghost when I came out of
the bellie?</ab>
<ab n="12">Why did the
knees preuent mee? or why the breasts, that I should sucke?</ab>
<ab n="13">For now should
I haue lien still and beene quiet, I should haue slept; then had I
bene at rest,</ab>
<ab n="14">With Kings and
counsellers of the earth, which built desolate places for
themselues,</ab>
<ab n="15">Or with Princes
that had golde, who filled their houses with siluer:</ab>
<ab n="16">Or as an hidden
vntimely birth, I had not bene; as infants which neuer saw
light.</ab>
<ab n="17">There the
wicked cease from troubling: and there the wearie be at
rest.<note> Heb. wearied in strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">There the
prisoners rest together, they heare not the voice of the
oppressour.</ab>
<ab n="19">The small and
great are there, and the seruant is free from his master.</ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore is
light giuen to him that is in misery, and life vnto the bitter in
soule?</ab>
<ab n="21">Which long for
death, but it commeth not, and dig for it more then for hid
treasures:<note> Heb. wait.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Which reioice
exceedingly, and are glad when they can finde the graue?</ab>
<ab n="23">Why is light
giuen to a man, whose way is hid, and whom God hath hedged
in?<note> Chap.19.8</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For my sighing
commeth before I eate, and my roarings are powred out like the
waters.<note> Heb. before my meat.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For the thing
which I greatly feared is come vpon me, and that which I was afraid
of, is come vnto me.<note> Heb. I feared a feare, and it came vpon me.</note></ab>

<fw>Iobs impatiencie is
reprehended.</fw>
<ab n="26">I was not in
safetie, neither had I rest, neither was I quiet: yet trouble
came.</ab>



</div>