<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-13-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Eliphaz reproueth Iob of impiety
in iustifying himselfe. 17 He proueth by Tradition the vnquietnes
of wicked men.</head>

<ab n="1">Then answered
Eliphaz the Temanite, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Should a wise
man vtter vaine knowledge, and fill his belly with the East
winde?<note> Heb. knowledge of wind</note></ab>

<fw>Causes why Iob is reprehended.</fw>
<ab n="3">Should hee
reason with vnprofitable talke? or with speeches wherewith he can
doe no good?</ab>
<ab n="4">Yea thou
castest off feare, and restrainest prayer before God.<note> Heb. thou makest void. , Or, speech.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For thy mouth
vttereth thine iniquitie, and thou choosest the tongue of the
craftie.<note> Heb. teacheth.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thine owne
mouth condemneth thee, and not I: yea thine owne lippes testifie
against thee.</ab>
<ab n="7">Art thou the
first man that was borne? or wast thou made before the
hilles?</ab>
<ab n="8">Hast thou heard
the secret of God? and doest thou restraine wisedome to thy
selfe?<note> Rom.11. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">What knowest
thou that we know not? what vnderstandest thou, which is not in
vs?</ab>
<ab n="10">With vs are
both the gray headed, and very aged men, much elder then thy
father.</ab>
<ab n="11">Are the
consolations of God small with thee? is there any secret thing with
thee?</ab>
<ab n="12">Why doeth
thine heart carie thee away? and what doe thine eyes winke
at,</ab>
<ab n="13">That thou
turnest thy spirit against God, and lettest such words goe out of
thy mouth?</ab>
<ab n="14">What is man,
that he should be cleane? and he which is borne of a woman, that he
should be righteous?<note> Chap.14. 4. 1.king. 8. 46. 2.chron. 6.36. psal. 14.3. prou. 20.9. 1.iohn 1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Beholde, he
putteth no trust in his Saints, yea, the heauens are not cleane in
his sight.<note> Iob.4.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">How much more
abominable and filthie is man, which drinketh iniquitie like
water?</ab>
<ab n="17">I will shew
thee, heare me, and that which I haue seene, I wil declare,</ab>
<ab n="18">Which wise men
haue tolde from their fathers, and haue not hid it:</ab>
<ab n="19">Unto whom
alone the earth was giuen, and no stranger passed among
them.</ab>
<ab n="20">The wicked man
trauaileth with paine all his dayes, and the number of yeeres is
hidden to the oppressour.</ab>
<ab n="21">A dreadfull
sound is in his eares; in prosperitie the destroyer shall come vpon
him.<note> Hebr. a sound of feares.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">He beleeueth
not that he shall returne out of darkenesse, and he is waited for,
of the sword.</ab>

<fw>Causes why Iob is reprehended.</fw>
<ab n="23">He wandereth
abroad for bread, saying, Where is it? he knoweth that the day of
darkenes is ready at his hand.</ab>
<ab n="24">Trouble and
anguish shall make him afraid; they shall preuaile against him, as
a king ready to the battell.</ab>
<ab n="25">For he
stretcheth out his hand against God, and strengtheneth himselfe
against the Almightie.</ab>
<ab n="26">He runneth
vpon him, euen on his necke, vpon the thicke bosses of his
bucklers:</ab>
<ab n="27">Because he
couereth his face with his fatnesse, and maketh collops of fat on
his flankes.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he
dwelleth in desolate cities, and in houses which no man inhabiteth,
which are ready to become heapes.</ab>
<ab n="29">He shall not
be rich, neither shall his substance continue, neither shall he
prolong the perfection thereof vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="30">He shall not
depart out of darkenesse, the flame shall drie vp his branches, and
by the breath of his mouth shall he goe away.</ab>
<ab n="31">Let not him
that is deceiued, trust in vanitie: for vanitie shalbe his
recompence.</ab>
<ab n="32">It shall be
accomplished before his time, and his branch shall not bee
greene.<note> Or, cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">He shal shake
off his vnripe grape as the Uine, and shall cast off his flowre as
the Oliue.</ab>
<ab n="34">For the
congregation of hypocrites shall be desolate, and fire shall
consume the tabernacles of briberie.</ab>
<ab n="35">They conceiue
mischiefe, and bring forth vanitie, and their belly prepareth
deceit.<note> Esay 59.4 psal.7.15 , Or, iniquitie.</note></ab>



</div>