<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The holinesse, riches, and
religious care of Iob for his children. 6 Satan appearing before
God, by calumniation obtaineth leaue to tempt Iob. 13.
Vnderstanding of the losse of his goods and children, in his
mourning hee blesseth God.</head>

<ab n="1">There was a man
in the land of Uz, whose name was Iob, and that man was perfect and
vpright, and one that feared God, and eschewed euill.<note> Chap.2.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And there were
borne vnto him seuen sonnes, and three daughters.</ab>
<ab n="3">His substance
also was seuen thousand sheepe, and three thousand camels, and fiue
hundred yoke of oxen, and fiue hundred shee asses, and a very great
houshold; so that this man was the greatest of all the men of the
East.<note> Or, cattell. , Or, husbandrie. , Heb. sonnes of the East.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And his sonnes
went and feasted in their houses, euery one his day, and sent and
called for their three sisters, to eate and to drinke with
them.</ab>
<ab n="5">And it was so,
when the dayes of their feasting were gone about, that Iob sent and
sanctified them, and rose vp early in the morning, and offered
burnt offerings according to the number of them all: For Iob said,
It may be that my sonnes haue sinned, and cursed God in their
hearts: Thus did Iob continually.<note> 1.King. 21.10, 13. , Heb. all the dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Now there
was a day, when the sons of God came to present themselues before
the Lord, and Satan came also among them.<note> Heb. the aduersarie. , Heb. in the midst of them.</note></ab>

<fw>Satans malice.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the Lord
said vnto Satan, Whence commest thou? Then Satan answered the Lord,
and sayde, From going to and fro in the earth, and from walking vp
and downe in it.<note> 1.Pet.5.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the Lord
sayd vnto Satan, Hast thou considered my seruant Iob, that there is
none like him in the earth? a perfect and an vpright man, one that
feareth God, and escheweth euill?<note> Heb. hast thou set thy heart on?</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then Satan
answered þe Lord, and sayd, Doeth Iob feare God for
nought?</ab>
<ab n="10">Hast not thou
made an hedge about him, and about his house, and about all that he
hath on euery side? thou hast blessed the worke of his hands, and
his substance is increased in the land.<note> Or, cattell.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But put foorth
thine hand now, and touch all that he hath, and he will curse thee
to thy face.<note> Hebr. if he curse thee not to thy face.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Lord
said vnto Satan, Behold, all that hee hath is in thy power, onely
vpon himselfe put not foorth thine hand. So Satan went forth from
the presence of the Lord.<note> Heb. hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
there was a day, when his sonnes and his daughters were eating and
drinking wine in their eldest brothers house:</ab>
<ab n="14">And there came
a messenger vnto Iob, and said, The oxen were plowing, and the
asses feeding beside them,</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Sabeans
fell vpon them, and tooke them away: yea they haue slaine the
seruants with the edge of the sword, and I onely am escaped alone,
to tell thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">While he was
yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The fire of God is
fallen from heauen, and hath burnt vp the sheepe, and the seruants,
and consumed them, and I onely am escaped alone, to tell
thee.<note> Or, a great fire.</note></ab>

<fw>Iobs patience. His wife tempteth
him.</fw>
<ab n="17">While he was
yet speaking, there came also another, and said, The Caldeans made
out three bands, and fell vpon the camels, and haue caried them
away, yea, and slaine the seruants with the edge of the sword, and
I onely am escaped alone, to tell thee.<note> Hebr. rushed.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">While he was
yet speaking, there came also another, &amp; said, Thy sonnes, and
thy daughters, were eating and drinking wine in their eldest
brothers house.</ab>
<ab n="19">And beholde,
there came a great winde from the wildernes, and smote the foure
corners of the house, and it fell vpon the yong men, and they are
dead, and I onely am escaped alone to tell thee.<note> Heb from a side, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then Iob arose,
and rent his mantle, and shaued his head, and fell downe vpon the
ground and worshipped,<note> Or, robe.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And said, Naked
came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked shall I returne thither:
the Lord gaue, and the Lord hath taken away, blessed be the Name of
the Lord.<note> Eccles.5. 14. 1.tim. 6.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">In all this Iob
sinned not, nor charged God foolishly.<note> Or, attributed folly to God.</note></ab>



</div>