<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Isaac blesseth Iacob, and sendeth
him to Padan Aram. 6 Esau marrieth Mahalal the daughter of Ishmael.
10 The Vision of Iacobs ladder. 18 The stone of Bethel. 20 Iacobs
vow.</head>

<ab n="1">And Isaac called
Iacob, and blessed him, and charged him, and saide vnto him, Thou
shalt not take a wife, of the daughters of Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="2">Arise, goe to
Padan Aram, to the house of Bethuel thy mothers father, and take
thee a wife from thence, of the daughters of Laban thy mothers
brother.<note> Ose. 12. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And God Almighty
blesse thee, and make thee fruitfull, and multiply thee, that thou
mayest be a multitude of people:<note> Hebr. an assembly of people.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And giue thee the
blessing of Abraham, to thee and to thy seede with thee, that thou
mayest inherit the lande wherein thou art a stranger, which God
gaue vnto Abraham.<note> Hebr. of thy soiournings.</note></ab>

<fw>Iacobs dreame:</fw>
<ab n="5">And Isaac sent
away Iacob, and hee went to Padan-Aram vnto Laban, sonne of Bethuel
the Syrian, the brother of Rebekah, Iacobs and Esaus
mother.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ When Esau
sawe that Isaac had blessed Iacob, and sent him away to Padan-Aram,
to take him a wife from thence; and that as he blessed him, he gaue
him a charge, saying, Thou shalt not take a wife of the daughters
of Canaan;</ab>
<ab n="7">And that Iacob
obeyed his father, and his mother, and was gone to
Padan-Aram;</ab>
<ab n="8">And Esau seeing
that the daughters of Canaan pleased not Isaac his
father.<note> Heb. were euill in the eyes, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then went Esau
vnto Ishmael, and tooke vnto the wiues which hee had, Mahalath the
daughter of Ishmael Abrahams sonne, the sister of Nebaioth, to be
his wife.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And Iacob
went out from Beer-sheba, and went toward Haran.<note> Called Acts 7.2. Charran.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And hee lighted
vpon a certaine place, and taried there all night, because the
sunne was set: and hee tooke of the stones of that place, and put
them for his pillowes, and lay downe in that place to
sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he dreamed,
and beholde, a ladder set vp on the earth, and the top of it
reached to heauen: and beholde the Angels of God ascending and
descending on it.</ab>
<ab n="13">And behold, the
LORD stood aboue it, and said, I am the LORD God of Abraham thy
father, and the God of Isaac: the land whereon thou liest, to thee
will I giue it, and to thy seede.<note> Chap. 35. 1, &amp; 48.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And thy seed
shall be as the dust of the earth, and thou shalt spread abroad to
the West, and to the East, and to the North, and to the South: and
in thee, and in thy seed, shall all the families of the earth be
blessed.<note> Heb. break forth. , Deut. 12. 3. , Cha.12.3 and 18.18. and 22.18. and 26.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And behold, I am
with thee, and will keepe thee in all places whither thou goest,
and will bring thee againe into this land: for I will not leaue
thee, vntill I haue done that which I haue spoken to thee
of.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And Iacob
awaked out of his sleepe, and he said, Surely the LORD is in this
place, and I knew it not.</ab>

<fw>He meeteth with Rachel, and marieth
her.</fw>
<ab n="17">And he was
afraid, and said, How dreadful is this place? this is none other,
but the house of God, and this is the gate of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Iacob rose
vp earely in the morning, and tooke the stone that hee had put for
his pillowes, and set it vp for a pillar, and powred oile vpon the
top of it.</ab>
<ab n="19">And hee called
the name of that place Beth-el: but the name of that citie was
called Luz, at the first.<note> That is, the house of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Iacob vowed
a vow, saying, If God will be with me, and will keepe me in this
way that I goe, and will giue me bread to eate, and raiment to put
on,</ab>
<ab n="21">So that I come
againe to my fathers house in peace: then shall the LORD be my
God.</ab>
<ab n="22">And this stone
which I haue set for a pillar, shall be Gods house: and of all that
thou shalt giue me, I will surely giue the tenth vnto thee.</ab>



</div>