<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 Dinah is rauished by Shechem. 4 He
sueth to marry her. 13 The sonnes of Iacob offer the condition of
Circumcision to the Shechemites. 20 Hamor and Shechem perswade them
to accept it. 25 The sonnes of Iacob vpon that aduantage slay them,
27 and spoile their citie. 30 Iacob reprooueth Simeon and
Leui.</head>

<ab n="1">And Dinah the
daughter of Leah, which shee bare vnto Iacob, went out to see the
daughters of the land.</ab>
<ab n="2">And when Shechem
the sonne of Hamor the Hiuite, prince of the countrey saw her, he
tooke her, and lay with her, and defiled her.<note> Hebr. humbled her.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And his soule
claue vnto Dinah the daughter of Iacob, and hee loued the damsell,
and spake kindly vnto the damsell.<note> Hebr. to her heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Shechem spake
vnto his father Hamor, saying, Get mee this damsell to
wife.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Iacob heard
that he had defiled Dinah his daughter (now his sonnes were with
his cattel in the field) and Iacob helde his peace vntill they were
come.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Hamor
the father of Shechem went out vnto Iacob to commune with
him.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the sonnes of
Iacob came out of the field when they heard it, and the men were
grieued: and they were very wroth, because hee had wrought folly in
Israel, in lying with Iacobs daughter; which thing ought not to be
done.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Hamor
communed with them, saying, The soule of my sonne Shechem longeth
for your daughter: I pray you giue her him to wife.</ab>
<ab n="9">And make ye
mariages with vs, and giue your daughters vnto vs, and take our
daughters vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="10">And ye shall
dwell with vs, and the land shall be before you: dwell and trade
you therein, and get you possessions therein.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Shechem said
vnto her father, and vnto her brethren, Let mee finde grace in your
eyes, and what yee shall say vnto me, I will giue.</ab>

<fw>The Shechemites are spoiled.</fw>
<ab n="12">Aske mee neuer
so much dowrie and gift, and I will giue according as yee shall say
vnto mee: but giue me the damsell to wife.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the sonnes
of Iacob answered Shechem, and Hamor his father deceitfully, and
said, because he had defiled Dinah their sister.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they saide
vnto them, wee cannot doe this thing, to giue our sister to one
that is vncircumcised: for that were a reproch vnto vs.</ab>
<ab n="15">But in this will
we consent vnto you: If ye will be as we be, that euery male of you
be circumcised:</ab>
<ab n="16">Then wil we giue
our daughters vnto you, and we wil take your daughters to vs, and
we will dwell with you, and we will become one people.</ab>
<ab n="17">But if ye will
not hearken vnto vs, to be circumcised, then will we take our
daughter, and we will be gone.</ab>
<ab n="18">And their words
pleased Hamor, and Shechem Hamors sonne.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the yong man
deferred not to doe the thing, because he had delight in Iacobs
daughter: and he was more honourable then all the house of his
father.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And Hamor
and Shechem his sonne came vnto the gate of their citie, and
communed with the men of their citie, saying:</ab>
<ab n="21">These men are
peaceable with vs, therefore let them dwel in the land, and trade
therein: for the land, behold, it is large enough for them: let vs
take their daughters to vs for wiues, and let vs giue them our
daughters.</ab>
<ab n="22">Onely herein
will the men consent vnto vs, for to dwell with vs to be one
people, if euery male among vs bee circumcised, as they are
circumcised.</ab>
<ab n="23">Shall not their
cattell, and their substance, and euery beast of theirs bee ours?
onely let vs consent vnto them, and they will dwell with
vs.</ab>
<ab n="24">And vnto Hamor
and vnto Shechem his sonne, hearkened all that went out of the gate
of his citie; and euery male was circumcised, all that went out of
the gate of his citie.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And it
came to passe on the thirde day when they were sore, that two of
the sonnes of Iacob, Simeon and Leui, Dinahs brethren, tooke each
man his sword and came vpon the citie boldly, and slew all the
males.<note> Chap. 49.6.</note></ab>

<fw>The Shechemites are spoiled.</fw>
<ab n="26">And they slew
Hamor and Shechem his sonne, with the edge of the sword, and tooke
Dinah out of Shechems house, and went out.<note> Hebr. mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">The sonnes of
Iacob came vpon the slaine, and spoiled the citie, because they had
defiled their sister.</ab>
<ab n="28">They tooke their
sheepe, and their oxen, and their asses, and that which was in the
citie, and that which was in the field.</ab>
<ab n="29">And all their
wealth, and all their little ones, and their wiues tooke they
captiue, and spoiled euen all that was in the house.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Iacob said
to Simeon and Leui, Ye haue troubled me to make me to stinke among
the inhabitants of the land, amongst the Canaanites, and the
Perizzites: and I being few in number, they shall gather themselues
together against me, and slay me, and I shal be destroyed, I and my
house.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they said,
Should hee deale with our sister, as with an harlot?</ab>



</div>