<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_37" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-36-38.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVII.</head>
<head>1 God is to be feared because of his
great works. 15 His wisdome is vnsearchable in them.</head>

<ab n="1">At this also my
heart trembleth, and is moued out of his place.</ab>
<ab n="2">Heare
attentiuely the noise of his voice, and the sound that goeth out of
his mouth.<note> Heb. heare in hearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Hee directeth
it vnder the whole heauen, and his lightning vnto the ends of the
earth.<note> Heb. light. , Heb. wings of the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">After it a
voyce roareth: he thundreth with the voice of his excellencie, and
hee will not stay them when his voice is heard.</ab>
<ab n="5">God thundereth
maruellously with his voice: great things doth hee, which we cannot
comprehend.</ab>
<ab n="6">For he saith to
the snow, Be thou on the earth: likewise to the small raine, and to
the great raine of his strength.<note> Psal. 147. 16. &amp; 17. , Heb and to the shower of raine, and to the showers of raine of his strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">He sealeth vp
the hand of euery man; that all men may knowe his worke.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then the
beastes goe into dennes: and remaine in their places.</ab>
<ab n="9">Out of the
South commeth the whirlewinde: and cold out of the
North.<note> Heb. out of the chamber. , Heb. scattering winds.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">By the breath
of God, frost is giuen: and the breadth of the waters is
straitned.</ab>
<ab n="11">Also by
watring he wearieth the thicke cloud: hee scattereth his bright
cloud.<note> Heb. the of his light.</note></ab>

<fw>The power of God.</fw>
<ab n="12">And it is
turned round about by his counsels: that they may doe whatsoeuer
hee commaundeth them vpon the face of the world in the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="13">He causeth it
to come, whether for correction, or for his land, or for
mercy.<note> Heb. a rod.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Hearken vnto
this, O Iob: stand still, and consider the wondrous workes of
God.</ab>
<ab n="15">Doest thou
knowe when God disposed them, and caused the light of his cloud to
shine?</ab>
<ab n="16">Doest thou
know the ballancings of the clouds, the wondrous workes of him
which is perfect in knowledge?</ab>
<ab n="17">How thy
garments are warme, when hee quieteth the earth by the South
wind?</ab>
<ab n="18">Hast thou with
him spread out the skie, which is strong, and as a molten looking
glasse?</ab>
<ab n="19">Teach vs what
we shall say vnto him; for we cannot order our speach by reason of
darknes.</ab>
<ab n="20">Shall it bee
told him that I speake? if a man speake, surely he shalbe swallowed
vp.</ab>
<ab n="21">And nowe men
see not the bright light which is in the clouds: but the wind
passeth and cleanseth them.</ab>
<ab n="22">Faire weather
commeth out of the North: with God is terrible
maiestie.<note> Heb. gold</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Touching the
Almighty, we cannot find him out: he is excellent in power, and in
iudgement, and in plenty of iustice: he will not afflict.</ab>
<ab n="24">Men doe
therefore feare him: he respecteth not any that are wise of
heart.</ab>



</div>