<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJob_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Job-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 Elihu is angry with Iob and his
three friends. 6 Because wisedome cometh not from age, he excuseth
the boldnesse of his youth. 11 He reprooueth them for not
satisfying of Iob. 16 His zeale to speake.</head>

<ab n="1">So these three
men ceased to answere Iob, because he was righteous in his owne
eyes.<note> Heb. from answering.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then was
kindled the wrath of Elihu, the sonne of Barachel the Buzite, of
the kinred of Ram: against Iob was his wrath kindled, because he
iustified himselfe rather then God.<note> Heb. his soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Also against
his three friends was his wrath kindled: because they had found no
answere, and yet had condemned Iob.</ab>

<fw>Elihu reproueth Iob, and
others.</fw>
<ab n="4">Now Elihu had
waited till Iob had spoken: because they were elder then
he.<note> Heb. expected Iob in words. , Heb. elder for dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">When Elihu saw
that there was no answere in the mouth of these three men, then his
wrath was kindled.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Elihu the
sonne of Barachel the Buzite answered and sayd: I am yong, and yee
are very old, wherefore I was afraid, and durst not shew you mine
opinion.<note> Heb. few of dayes. , Heb. I feared.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">I said, Dayes
should speake, and multitude of yeeres should teach
wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="8">But there is a
spirit in man: and the inspiration of the Almightie giueth them
vnderstanding.<note> Iob.38.36 prou. 2.6. eccl. 2.26. dan. 1.17. &amp; 2.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Great men are
not alwayes wise: neither doe the aged vnderstand
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therfore I
sayd, Hearken to me: I also will shew mine opinion.</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, I
waited for your words: I gaue eare to your reasons, whilest you
searched out what to say.<note> Heb. vnderstandings , Heb. words</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Yea, I
attended vnto you: and beholde, there was none of you that
conuinced Iob, or that answered his words:</ab>
<ab n="13">Lest ye should
say, We haue found out wisdom: God thrusteth him down, not
man.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now he hath
not directed his words against me: neither will I answere him with
your speeches.<note> Or, ordered his words.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">They were
amased, they answered no more, they left off speaking.<note> Heb. they remoued speeches from themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">When I had
waited, (for they spake not, but stood still and answered no
more.)</ab>
<ab n="17">I sayd, I will
answere also my part, I also will shew mine opinion.</ab>
<ab n="18">For I am full
of matter, the spirit within me constraineth me.<note> Heb. words , Heb. the spirit of my belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Behold, my
belly is as wine, which hath no vent, it is ready to burst like new
bottles.<note> Heb. is not opened.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">I will speake,
that I may be refreshed: I will open my lippes, and
answere.<note> Heb. that I may breath.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Let me not, I
pray you, accept any mans person: neither let me giue flattering
titles vnto man.</ab>
<ab n="22">For I know not
to giue flattering titles: in so doing my maker would soone take me
away.</ab>



</div>