<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoel_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Hosea-Chapter-14-14-Joel.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joel-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Ioel, declaring sundry iudgements
of God, exhorteth to obserue them, 8 and to mourne. 14 He
prescribeth a fast, for complaint.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of the
Lord that came to Ioel the sonne of Pethuel.</ab>
<ab n="2">Heare this, yee
olde men, and giue eare, all yee inhabitants of the lande: Hath
this been in your dayes, or euen in the dayes of your
fathers?</ab>
<ab n="3">Tell ye your
children of it, and let your children tell their children, and
their children another generation.</ab>
<ab n="4">That which the
palmer worme hath left, hath the locust eaten; and that which the
locust hath left, hath the canker-worme eaten; and that which the
canker-worme hath left, hath the caterpillar eaten.<note> Heb. the residue of the palmer-worme.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Awake ye
drunkards, and weepe, and howle all yee drinkers of wine, because
of the new wine, for it is cut off from your mouth.</ab>
<ab n="6">For a nation is
come vp vpon my lande, strong, and without number, whose teeth are
the teeth of a lyon, and he hath the cheeke-teeth of a great
lyon.</ab>
<ab n="7">He hath laide
my vine waste: and barked my figge-tree: hee hath made it cleane
bare, and cast it away, the branches thereof are made
white.<note> Heb. laid my figgetree for a barking.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Lament
like a virgine girded with sackecloth for the husband of her
youth.</ab>
<ab n="9">The meate
offring and the drinke offering is cut off from the house of the
Lord, the Priestes the Lords ministers mourne.</ab>
<ab n="10">The field is
wasted, the lande mourneth; for the corne is wasted: the new wine
is dried vp, the oyle languisheth.<note> Or, ashamed.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Be yee
ashamed, O yee husbandmen: howle, O yee vine-dressers, for the
wheate and for the barley; because the haruest of the field is
perished.</ab>
<ab n="12">The vine is
dried vp, and the figgetree languisheth, the pomegranate tree, the
palme tree also and the apple tree, euen all the trees of the field
are withered: because ioy is withered away from the sonnes of
men.</ab>
<ab n="13">Gird your
selues, and lament, yee Priests: howle, ye ministers of the Altar:
come, lie all night in sackecloth, ye ministers of my God: for the
meat offering and the drinke offering is withholden from the house
of your God.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶
Sanctifie yee a fast: call a solemne assembly: gather the Elders,
and all the inhabitants of the land into the house of the Lord your
God, and cry vnto the Lord:<note> Cha.2.15. , Or, day of restraint.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Alas for the
day: for the day of the Lord is at hand, and as a destruction from
the Almightie shall it come.<note> Isai. 13.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Is not the
meate cut off before your eyes, yea ioy and gladnesse from the
house of our God?</ab>
<ab n="17">The seede is
rotten vnder their clods: the garners are laide desolate: the
barnes are broken downe, for the corne is withered.<note> Heb. grains</note></ab>
<ab n="18">How doe the
beastes grone? the heards of cattell are perplexed, because they
haue no pasture, yea the flockes of sheepe are made
desolate.</ab>

<fw>Deuouring fire.</fw>
<ab n="19">O Lord, to
thee will I crie: for the fire hath deuoured the pastures of the
wildernesse, and the flame hath burnt all the trees of the
field.<note> Or, habitations.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The beasts of
the field crie also vnto thee: for the riuers of waters are dried
vp, and the fire hath deuoured the pastures of the
wildernesse.</ab>



</div>