<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Iesus excuseth Mary anointing his
feet. 9 The people flocke to see Lazarus. 10 The high Priests
consult to kill him. 12 Christ rideth into Ierusalem. 20 Greekes
desire to see Iesus. 23 He foretelleth his death. 37 The Iewes are
generally blinded: 42 yet many chiefe rulers beleeue, but do not
confesse him: 44 therfore Iesus calleth earnestly for confession of
faith.</head>


<fw>Iudas, a thiefe.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then Iesus,
sixe dayes before the Passouer, came to Bethanie, where Lazarus
was, which had bene dead, whom hee raised from the dead.</ab>
<ab n="2">There they
made him a supper, and Martha serued: but Lazarus was one of them
þt sate at the table with him.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then tooke
Mary a pound of ointment, of Spikenard, very costly, and anointed
the feet of Iesus, &amp; wiped his feet with her haire: and the
house was filled with the odour of the ointment.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then saith one
of his disciples, Iudas Iscariot, Simons sonne, which should betray
him,</ab>
<ab n="5">Why was not
this ointment sold for three hundred pence, and giuen to the
poore?</ab>
<ab n="6">This he said,
not that he cared for the poore: but because hee was a thiefe, and
had the bag, and bare what was put therein.<note> Cha.13.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then said
Iesus, Let her alone, against the day of my burying hath she kept
this.</ab>
<ab n="8">For the poore
alwayes yee haue with you: but me ye haue not alwayes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Much people of
the Iewes therefore knew that he was there: and they came, not for
Iesus sake onely, but that they might see Lazarus also, whom he had
raised from the dead.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ But the
chiefe Priests consulted, þt they might put Lazarus
also to death,</ab>
<ab n="11">Because that by
reason of him many of the Iewes went away and beleeued on
Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ On the next
day, much people that were come to the feast, when they heard that
Iesus was comming to Hierusalem,<note> Cha.21.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Tooke branches of
Palme trees, and went foorth to meet him, and cried, Hosanna,
blessed is the king of Israel that cōmeth in the Name of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Iesus, when he
had found a yong asse, sate thereon, as it is written,</ab>
<ab n="15">Feare not, daughter
of Sion, behold, thy King commeth, sitting on an asses
colt.<note> Zach.9.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">These things
vnderstood not his disciples at the first: but when Iesus was
glorified, then remēbred they that these things were written
of him, and that they had done these things vnto him.</ab>

<fw>The wheat corne.</fw>
<ab n="17">The people
therefore that was with him, when he called Lazarus out of his
graue, and raised him from the dead, bare record.</ab>
<ab n="18">For this cause the
people also met him, for that they heard that hee had done this
miracle.</ab>
<ab n="19">The Pharisees
therefore saide among themselues, Perceiue ye how yee preuaile
nothing? Behold, the world is gone after him.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And there
were certaine Greeks among them, that came vp to worship at the
feast:</ab>
<ab n="21">The same came
therefore to Philip which was of Bethsaida of Galilee, and desired
him, saying, Sir, we would see Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="22">Philip commeth and
telleth Andrew: and againe Andrew and Philip told Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And Iesus
answered them, saying, The houre is come, that the Sonne of man
should be glorified.</ab>
<ab n="24">Uerely, verely, I
say vnto you, Except a corne of wheat fall into the ground, and
die, it abideth alone: but if it die, it bringeth forth much
fruit.</ab>
<ab n="25">He that loueth his
life, shall lose it: and hee that hateth his life in this world,
shall keepe it vnto life eternall.<note> Matth.10. 39.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">If any man serue
me, let him follow me, and where I am, there shall also my seruant
be: If any man serue me, him will my father honour.</ab>
<ab n="27">Now is my soule
troubled, and what shall I say? Father, saue me from this houre,
but for this cause came I vnto this houre.</ab>
<ab n="28">Father, glorifie
thy Name. Then came there a voice from heauen, saying, I haue both
glorified it, and wil glorifie it againe.</ab>
<ab n="29">The people
therefore that stood by, and heard it, said, that it thundered:
others said, An Angel spake to him.</ab>
<ab n="30">Iesus answered, and
said, This voice came not because of mee, but for your
sakes.</ab>
<ab n="31">Now is the
iudgement of this world: now shall the prince of this world be cast
out.</ab>
<ab n="32">And I, if I be
lifted vp from the earth, will draw all men vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="33">(This hee said,
signifying what death he should die)</ab>
<ab n="34">The people answered
him, We haue heard out of the Law, that Christ abideth for euer:
and how sayest thou, The Sonne of man must bee lift vp? Who is this
Sonne of man?<note> Psal.110.4.</note></ab>

<fw>Christ a light.</fw>
<ab n="35">Then Iesus said
vnto them, Yet a little while is the light with you: walke while ye
haue the light, lest darkdesse come vpon you: For he that walketh
in darkenesse, knoweth not whither he goeth.</ab>
<ab n="36">While ye haue
light, beleeue in the light, that ye may bee the children of light.
These things spake Iesus, and departed, and did hide himselfe from
them.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ But though
he had done so many miracles before them, yet they beleeued not on
him:</ab>
<ab n="38">That the saying of
Esaias the Prophet might be fulfilled, which hee spake, Lord, who
hath beleeued our report? and to whom hath the arme of the Lord
beene reuealed?<note> Esai.53.1. rom.10.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Therefore they
could not beleeue, because that Esaias said againe,</ab>
<ab n="40">He hath blinded
their eyes, and hardned their heart, that they should not see with
their eyes, nor vnderstand with their heart, and be conuerted, and
I should heale them.<note> Mat.13. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">These things said
Esaias, when he saw his glory, and spake of him.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶
Neuerthelesse, among the chiefe rulers also, many beleeued on him;
but because of the Pharisees they did not confesse him, lest they
should be put out of the Synagogue.</ab>
<ab n="43">For they loued the
praise of men, more then the praise of God.<note> Chap.5. 44.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ Iesus cried,
and said, He that beleeueth on me, beleeueth not on me, but on him
that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="45">And he that seeth
me, seeth him that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="46">I am come a light
into the world, that whosoeuer beleeueth on me, should not abide in
darkenesse.<note> Chap.3. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And if any man
heare my words, and beleeue not, I iudge him not; For I came not to
iudge the world, but to saue the world.<note> Chap.3. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">He that reiecteth
me, and receiueth not my words, hath one that iudgeth him:
þe word that I haue spoken, the same shall iudge
him in the last day.<note> Marke 16 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">For I haue not
spoken of my selfe; but the Father which sent me, he gaue me a
commaundement what I should say, and what I should speake.</ab>
<ab n="50">And I know that his
commandement is life euerlasting: whatsoeuer I speake therefore,
euen as the Father said vnto me, so I speake.</ab>



</div>