<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Iesus washeth the disciples feete:
exhorteth them to humilitie and charitie. 18 He foretelleth, and
discouereth to Iohn by a token that Iudas should betray him: 31
Commandeth them to loue one another, 36 And forewarneth Peter of
his deniall.</head>

<ab n="1">Now before the
feast of the Passeouer, when Iesus knew that his houre was come,
that he should depart out of this world vnto the Father, hauing
loued his owne which were in the world, he loued them vnto the
end.<note> Mat.26. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And supper
being ended (the deuill hauing now put into the heart of Iudas
Iscariot Simons sonne to betray him.)</ab>
<ab n="3">Iesus knowing
that the Father had giuen all things into his hands, and that he
was come from God, and went to God:</ab>
<ab n="4">He riseth from
supper, and layed aside his garments, and tooke a towell, and
girded himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="5">After that, he
powreth water into a bason, and beganne to wash the disciples
feete, and to wipe them with the towell wherewith he was
girded.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then commeth
he to Simon Peter: and Peter saith vnto him, Lord, doest thou wash
my feete?</ab>
<ab n="7">Iesus
answered, and said vnto him, What I doe, thou knowest not now: but
thou shalt know heereafter.</ab>
<ab n="8">Peter saith
vnto him, Thou shalt neuer wash my feete. Iesus answered him, If I
wash thee not, thou hast no part with me.</ab>
<ab n="9">Simon Peter
saith vnto him, Lord, not my feete only, but also my hands, and my
head.</ab>
<ab n="10">Iesus saith to him,
He that is washed, needeth not, saue to wash his feet, but is
cleane euery whit: and ye are cleane, but not all.</ab>
<ab n="11">For he knew who
should betray him, therefore said he, Ye are not all
cleane.</ab>
<ab n="12">So after he had
washed their feet, and had taken his garments, and was set downe
againe, he said vnto them, Know ye what I haue done to you?</ab>
<ab n="13">Ye call me Master
and Lord, and ye say well: for so I am.</ab>

<fw>Iudas, the traitour.</fw>
<ab n="14">If I then your Lord
and Master haue washed your feete, yee also ought to wash one
anothers feete.</ab>
<ab n="15">For I haue giuen
you an example, that yee should doe, as I haue done to you.</ab>
<ab n="16">Uerily, verily I
say vnto you, the seruant is not greater then his lord, neither he
that is sent, greater then hee that sent him.<note> Matth.10. 24. chap. 15.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">If yee know these
things, happy are ye if ye doe them.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ I speake not
of you all, I know whom I haue chosen: but that the Scripture may
be fulfilled, He that eateth bread with mee, hath lift vp his heele
against me.<note> Psal.41. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Now I tell you
before it come, that when it is come to passe, yee may beleeue that
I am he.<note> Or, from henceforth.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Uerily, verily I
say vnto you, he that receiueth whomsoeuer I send, receiueth me:
and he that receiueth me, receiueth him that sent me.<note> Matth.10. 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">When Iesus had thus
sayd, hee was troubled in spirit, and testified, and said, Uerily,
verily I say vnto you, that one of you shall betray me.<note> Matth.26. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then the disciples
looked one on another, doubting of whom hee spake.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now there was
leaning on Iesus bosome one of his disciples, whom Iesus
loued.</ab>
<ab n="24">Simon Peter
therefore beckened to him, that he should aske who it should be of
whom he spake.</ab>
<ab n="25">Hee then lying on
Iesus breast, saith vnto him, Lord, who is it?</ab>
<ab n="26">Iesus answered, Hee
it is to whom I shall giue a soppe, when I haue dipped it. And when
he had dipped the sop, he gaue it to Iudas Iscariot the sonne of
Simon.<note> Or, morsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And after the
soppe, Satan entred into him, Then said Iesus vnto him, That thou
doest, doe quickly.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now no man at the
table knew, for what intent he spake this vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="29">For some of them
thought, because Iudas had the bagge, that Iesus had sayd vnto him,
Buy those things that wee haue need of against the feast: or that
he should giue some thing to the poore.</ab>
<ab n="30">He then hauing
receiued the sop, went immediatly out: and it was night.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Therefore
when hee was gone out, Iesus sayd, Now is the Sonne of man
glorified: and God is glorified in him.</ab>

<fw>Mutuall loue.</fw>
<ab n="32">If God be glorified
in him, God shall also glorifie him in himselfe, and shall
straightway glorifie him.</ab>
<ab n="33">Litle children, yet
a litle while I am with you. Ye shall seeke mee, and as I said vnto
the Iewes, whither I go, ye cannot come: so now I say to
you.<note> Chap.7. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">A new commandement
I giue vnto you, That yee loue one another, as I haue loued you,
that yee also loue one another.<note> Chap.15. 17. leui.19. 18. 1.iohn 4.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">By this shall all
men know that ye are my disciples, if yee haue loue one to
another.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ Simon Peter
sayd vnto him, Lord, whither goest thou? Iesus answered him,
Whither I goe, thou canst not follow me now: but thou shalt follow
me afterwards.</ab>
<ab n="37">Peter said vnto
him, Lord, why can not I follow thee now? I will lay downe my life
for thy sake.<note> Matt.26. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Iesus answered him,
Wilt thou lay downe thy life for my sake? Uerily, verily I say vnto
thee, the Cocke shall not crow, til thou hast denied me
thrise.</ab>



</div>