<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-5-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Iesus on the Sabbath day cureth
him that was diseased eight &amp; thirtie yeeres. 10 The Iewes
therefore cauill, and persecute him for it. 17 He answereth for
himselfe, and reprooueth them, shewing by the testimonie of his
Father, 32 of Iohn, 36 of his workes, 39 and of the Scriptures, who
he is.</head>

<ab n="1">After this
there was a feast of the Iewes, and Iesus went vp to
Hierusalem.<note> Leuit. 23. 2. deut. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Now there is at
Hierusalem by the sheepe market, a poole, which is called in the
Hebrew tongue Bethesda, hauing fiue porches.<note> Or, gate.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">In these lay a
great multitude of impotent folke, of blind, halt, withered,
waiting for the mouing of the water.</ab>
<ab n="4">For an Angel
went downe at a certaine season into the poole, and troubled the
water: whosoeuer then first after the troubling of the water
stepped in, was made whole of whatsoeuer disease he had.</ab>
<ab n="5">And a certaine
man was there, which had an infirmitie thirtie and eight
yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="6">When Iesus saw
him lie, &amp; knew that hee had beene now a long time in that
case, he sayth vnto him, Wilt thou be made whole?</ab>
<ab n="7">The impotent
man answered him, Sir, I haue no man when the water is troubled, to
put mee into the poole: but while I am comming, another steppeth
downe before me.</ab>
<ab n="8">Iesus sayth
vnto him, Rise, take vp thy bed, and walke.</ab>
<ab n="9">And immediatly
the man was made whole, and tooke vp his bed, and walked: And on
the same day was the Sabbath.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ The
Iewes therefore said vnto him that was cured, It is the Sabbath
day, it is not lawfull for thee to cary thy bed.<note> Ier.17.22</note></ab>
<ab n="11">He answered
them, He that made me whole, the same said vnto me, Take vp thy
bed, and walke.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then asked
they him, What man is that which said vnto thee, Take vp thy bed,
and walke?</ab>

<fw>Of the resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="13">And he that
was healed, wist not who it was: for Iesus had conueyed himselfe
away, a multitude being in that place.<note> Or, from the multitude that was.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Afterward
Iesus findeth him in the Temple, &amp; said vnto him, Behold, thou
art made whole: sinne no more, lest a worse thing come vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">The man
departed, and tolde the Iewes that it was Iesus which had made him
whole.</ab>
<ab n="16">And therefore
did the Iewes persecute Iesus, and sought to slay him, because he
had done these things on the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ But
Iesus answered them, My Father worketh hitherto, &amp; I
worke.</ab>
<ab n="18">Therefore the
Iewes sought the more to kill him, not onely because hee had broken
the Sabbath, but said also, that God was his father, making
himselfe equall with God.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then answered
Iesus, and saide vnto them, Uerily, verily I say vnto you, The
sonne can doe nothing of himselfe, but what he seeth the Father
doe: for what things soeuer he doeth, these also doth the sonne
likewise.</ab>
<ab n="20">For the father
loueth the sonne, and sheweth him all things that himselfe doth:
&amp; he will shew him greater works then these, that ye may
marueile.</ab>
<ab n="21">For as the
Father raiseth vp the dead, and quickeneth them: euen so the Sonne
quickeneth whom he will.</ab>
<ab n="22">For the Father
iudgeth no man: but hath committed all iudgement vnto the
Sonne:</ab>
<ab n="23">That all men
should honour the Son, euen as they honour the Father. He that
honoureth not þe Sonne, honoreth not
þe Father which hath sent him.</ab>
<ab n="24">Uerily, verily
I say vnto you, Hee that heareth my word, &amp; beleeueth on him
that sent mee, hath euerlasting life, and shall not come into
condemnation: but is passed from death vnto life.</ab>
<ab n="25">Uerily, verily
I say vnto you, The houre is comming, &amp; now is, when the dead
shall heare the voice of the Sonne of God: and they that heare,
shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="26">For as the
Father hath life in himselfe: so hath he giuen to the Sonne to haue
life in himselfe:</ab>
<ab n="27">And hath giuen
him authority to execute iudgement also, because he is the Sonne of
man.</ab>
<ab n="28">Marueile not
at this: for the houre is comming, in the which all that are in the
graues shall heare his voice,</ab>

<fw>Search the Scriptures.</fw>
<ab n="29">And shall come
foorth, they that haue done good, vnto the resurrection of life,
and they that haue done euill, vnto the resurrection of
damnation.<note> Matth.25. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">I can of mine
owne selfe doe nothing: as I heare, I iudge: and my iudgement is
iust, because I seeke not mine owne will, but the will of the
Father, which hath sent me.</ab>
<ab n="31">If I beare
witnesse of my selfe, my witnesse is not true.<note> Chap.8. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ There
is another that beareth witnesse of me, &amp; I know that the
witnesse which he witnesseth of me, is true.<note> Matth.3. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Ye sent vnto
Iohn, and he bare witnesse vnto the trueth.<note> Chap.1.7</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But I receiue
not testimonie from man: but these things I say, that ye might be
saued.</ab>
<ab n="35">He was a
burning and a shining light: and ye were willing for a season to
reioyce in his light.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ But I
haue greater witnesse then that of Iohn: for the workes which the
Father hath giuen me to finish, the same workes that I doe, beare
witnesse of mee, that the Father hath sent me.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the Father
himselfe which hath sent me, hath borne witnesse of me. Ye haue
neither heard his voyce at any time, nor seene his
shape.<note> Matth.3. 17. and 17. 5. , Deut.4. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And ye haue
not his word abiding in you: for whom he hath sent, him ye beleeue
not.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ Search
the Scriptures, for in them ye thinke ye haue eternall life, and
they are they which testifie of me.</ab>
<ab n="40">And ye will
not come to me, that ye might haue life.</ab>
<ab n="41">I receiue not
honour from men.</ab>
<ab n="42">But I know
you, that ye haue not the loue of God in you.</ab>
<ab n="43">I am come in
my Fathers name, and ye receiue me not: if another shall come in
his owne Name, him ye will receiue.</ab>
<ab n="44">How can ye
beleeue, which receiue honour one of another, &amp; seeke not the
honour that commeth from God onely?<note> Chap.12. 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Doe not thinke
that I will accuse you to the Father: there is one that accuseth
you, euen Moses, in whom ye trust?</ab>
<ab n="46">For had ye
beleeued Moses, ye would haue beleeued me: for he wrote of
me.<note> Gen.3.15. deut.18.15</note></ab>
<ab n="47">But if ye
beleeue not his writings, how shall ye beleeue my words?</ab>



</div>