<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 Mary commeth to the Sepulchre. 3
So doe Peter and Iohn ignorant of the Resurrection. 11 Iesus
appeareth to Mary Magdalene, 19 And to his Disciples. 24 The
incredulitie, and confession of Thomas. 30 The Scripture is
sufficient to saluation.</head>

<ab n="1">The first day
of the weeke, commeth Mary Magdalene earely when it was yet darke,
vnto the Sepulchre, and seeth the stone taken away from the
Sepulchre.<note> Mat.28. 1. mark. 16. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Then she
runneth and commeth to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple whom
Iesus loued, and saith vnto them, They haue taken away the Lord out
of the Sepulchre, and we know not where they haue laid
him.<note> Chap.13. 23.and 21. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Peter
therefore went forth, and that other disciple, and came to the
Sepulchre.</ab>
<ab n="4">So they ranne
both together, and the other disciple did outrun Peter, and came
first to the Sepulchre.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he
stouping downe and looking in, saw the linnen clothes lying, yet
went he not in.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then commeth
Simon Peter following him, and went into the Sepulchre, and seeth
the linnen clothes lie,</ab>
<ab n="7">And the napkin
that was about his head, not lying with the linnen clothes, but
wrapped together in a place by it selfe.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then went in
also that other disciple which came first to the Sepulchre, and he
saw, and beleeued.</ab>
<ab n="9">For as yet
they knew not the Scripture, that hee must rise againe from the
dead.</ab>

<fw>Christ and Mary.</fw>
<ab n="10">Then the disciples
went away againe vnto their owne home.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ But Mary
stood without at the sepulchre, weeping: &amp; as shee wept, she
stouped downe, and looked into the Sepulchre,</ab>
<ab n="12">And seeth two
Angels in white, sitting, the one at the head, and the other at the
feete, where the body of Iesus had layen:</ab>
<ab n="13">And they say vnto
her, Woman, why weepest thou? Shee saith vnto them, Because they
haue taken away my Lord, and I know not where they haue laied
him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when she had
thus said, she turned herselfe backe, and saw Iesus standing, and
knew not that it was Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="15">Iesus saith vnto
her, Woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She supposing him
to be the gardiner, saith vnto him, Sir, if thou haue borne him
hence, tell me where thou hast laied him, and I will take him
away.</ab>
<ab n="16">Iesus saith vnto
her, Mary. She turned herselfe, and saith vnto him, Rabboni, which
is to say, Master.</ab>
<ab n="17">Iesus saith vnto
her, Touch me not: for I am not yet ascended to my Father: but goe
to my brethren, and say vnto them, I ascend vnto my Father, and
your Father, and to my God, and your God.</ab>
<ab n="18">Mary Magdalene came
and told the disciples that shee had seene the Lord, and that hee
had spoken these things vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then the
same day at euening, being the first day of the weeke, when the
doores were shut, where the disciples were assembled for feare of
the Iewes, came Iesus, and stood in the midst, and saith vnto them,
Peace bee vnto you.<note> Marke 16. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And when hee had so
saide, hee shewed vnto them his hands and his side. Then were the
disciples glad, when they saw the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then said Iesus to
them againe, Peace be vnto you: As my Father hath sent me, euen so
send I you.</ab>
<ab n="22">And when he had
said this, hee breathed on them, and saith vnto them, Receiue ye
the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="23">Whose soeuer sinnes
yee remit, they are remitted vnto them, and whose soeuer sinnes yee
retaine, they are retained.<note> Matth.18. 18.</note></ab>

<fw>Thomas beleeueth.</fw>
<ab n="24">¶ But Thomas
one of the twelue, called Didymus, was not with them when Iesus
came.</ab>
<ab n="25">The other disciples
therefore said vnto him, We haue seene the Lord. But he said vnto
them, Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nailes, and
put my finger into the print of the nailes, and thrust my hand into
his side, I will not beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And after
eight dayes, againe his disciples were within, and Thomas with
them: Then came Iesus, the doores being shut, and stood in the
midst, and said, Peace be vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then saith he to
Thomas Reach hither thy finger, and beholde my hands, and reach
hither thy hand, and thrust it into my side, and bee not
faithlesse, but beleeuing.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Thomas
answered, and said vnto him, My Lord, and my God.</ab>
<ab n="29">Iesus saith vnto
him, Thomas, because thou hast seene mee, thou hast beleeued:
blessed are they that haue not seene, and yet haue
beleeued.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And many
other signes truely did Iesus in the presence of his disciples,
which are not written in this booke:<note> Chap.21. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">But these are
written, that yee might beleeue that Iesus is the Christ the Sonne
of God, and that beleeuing ye might haue life through his
Name.</ab>



</div>