<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Christ turneth water into wine, 12
Departeth into Capernaum, and to Ierusalem, 14 Where hee purgeth
the temple of buyers and sellers. 19 He foretelleth his death and
resurrection. 23 Many beleeued because of his miracles, but he
would not trust himselfe with them.</head>


<fw>Water made wine.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the third
day there was a mariage in Cana of Galilee, and the mother of Iesus
was there.</ab>
<ab n="2">And both Iesus
was called, and his disciples, to the mariage.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when they
wanted wine, the mother of Iesus saith vnto him, They haue no
wine.</ab>
<ab n="4">Iesus saith
vnto her, Woman, what haue I to doe with thee? mine houre is not
yet come.</ab>
<ab n="5">His mother
saith vnto þe seruants, Whatsoeuer he saith vnto
you, doe it.</ab>
<ab n="6">And there were
set there sixe water pots of stone, after the maner of the
purifying of the Iewes, conteining two or three firkins
apeece.</ab>
<ab n="7">Iesus saith
vnto them, Fill the water pots with water. And they filled them vp
to the brimme.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee saith
vnto them, Drawe out now, and beare vnto the gouernor of the feast.
And they bare it.</ab>
<ab n="9">When the ruler
of the feast had tasted the water that was made wine, and knew not
whence it was, (but the seruants which drew the water knew) the
gouernor of the feast called the bridegrome,</ab>
<ab n="10">And saith vnto
him, Euery man at the beginning doth set foorth good wine, and when
men haue well drunke, then that which is worse: but thou hast kept
the good wine vntill now.</ab>
<ab n="11">This beginning
of miracles did Iesus in Cana of Galilee, and manifested forth his
glory, and his disciples beleeued on him.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ After
this hee went downe to Capernaum, hee and his mother, and his
brethren, and his disciples, and they continued there not many
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And the
Iewes Passeouer was at hand, &amp; Iesus went vp to
Hierusalem</ab>
<ab n="14">And found in
the Temple those that sold oxen, and sheepe, and doues, and the
changers of money, sitting.</ab>
<ab n="15">And when he
had made a scourge of small cordes, he droue them all out of the
Temple, and the sheepe &amp; the oxen, and powred out the changers
money, and ouerthrew the tables,</ab>
<ab n="16">And said vnto
them that sold doues Take these things hence, make not my fathers
house an house of merchandize.</ab>
<ab n="17">And his
disciples remembred that it was written, The zeale of thine house
hath eaten me vp.<note> Psal.69.9.</note></ab>

<fw>Of regeneration.</fw>
<ab n="18">¶ Then
answered the Iewes, and said vnto him, What signe shewest thou vnto
vs, seeing that thou doest these things?</ab>
<ab n="19">Iesus
answered, and said vnto them, Destroy this temple, and in three
dayes I will raise it vp.<note> Mat.26. 61.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then said the
Iewes, Fourty and six yeres was this Temple in building, and wilt
thou reare it vp in three dayes?</ab>
<ab n="21">But he spake
of the temple of his body.</ab>
<ab n="22">When therefore
hee was risen from the dead, his disciples remembred that hee had
said this vnto them: and they beleeued the Scripture, and the word
which Iesus had said.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Now
when hee was in Hierusalem at the Passeouer, in the feast day, many
beleeued in his Name, when they saw the miracles which he
did.</ab>
<ab n="24">But Iesus did
not commit himselfe vnto them, because he knew al men,</ab>
<ab n="25">And needed not
that any should testifie of man: for hee knew what was in
man.</ab>



</div>