<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-18-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Iudas betrayeth Iesus. 6 The
Officers fall to the ground. 10 Peter smiteth off Malchus eare. 12
Iesus is taken, and led vnto Annas and Caiaphas. 15 Peters deniall.
19 Iesus examined before Caiaphas. 28 His arraignment before
Pilate. 36 His Kingdome. 40 The Iewes aske Barabbas to be let
loose.</head>

<ab n="1">When Iesus had
spoken these wordes, hee went foorth with his disciples ouer the
Brooke Cedron, where was a garden, into the which hee entred and
his disciples.<note> Matth.26. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Iudas also
which betrayed him, knew the place: for Iesus oft times resorted
thither with his disciples.</ab>
<ab n="3">Iudas then
hauing receiued a band of men, and officers from the chiefe Priests
and Pharisees, commeth thither with lanternes and torches, and
weapons.<note> Matth.26. 47.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Iesus
therefore knowing all things that should come vpon him, went
foorth, and sayde vnto them, Whom seeke ye?</ab>
<ab n="5">They answered
him, Iesus of Nazareth. Iesus saith vnto them, I am hee. And Iudas
also which betraied him, stood with them.</ab>
<ab n="6">Assoone then
as he had said vnto them, I am he, they went backeward, and fell to
the ground.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then asked hee
them againe, Whom seeke ye? And they said, Iesus of
Nazareth.</ab>
<ab n="8">Iesus
answered, I haue tolde you that I am he: If therefore ye seeke me,
let these goe their way:</ab>

<fw>Peters deniall.</fw>
<ab n="9">That the
saying might be fulfilled which he spake, Of them which thou gauest
me, haue I lost none.<note> Chap.17. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then Simon Peter
hauing a sword, drewe it, and smote the high Priests seruant, &amp;
cut off his right eare: The seruants name was Malchus.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then said Iesus
vnto Peter, Put vp thy sword into the sheath: the cup which my
father hath giuen me, shall I not drinke it?</ab>
<ab n="12">Then the band and
the captaine, and officers of the Iewes, tooke Iesus, and bound
him,</ab>
<ab n="13">And led him away to
Annas first, (for he was father in law to Caiaphas) which was the
high Priest that same yeere.<note> And Annas sent Christ bound vnto Caiaphas the high Priest, ver. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Now Caiaphas was he
which gaue counsell to the Iewes, that it was expedient that one
man should die for the people.<note> Chap. 11. 50.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And Simon
Peter followed Iesus, and so did another disciple: that disciple
was knowen vnto the high Priest, and went in with Iesus into the
palace of the high Priest.<note> Mat.26. 58.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But Peter stood at
the doore without. Then went out that other disciple, which was
knowen vnto the high Priest, and spake vnto her that kept the
doore, and brought in Peter.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then saith the
damosell that kept the doore vnto Peter, Art not thou also one of
this mans disciples? He sayth, I am not.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the seruants
and officers stood there, who had made a fire of coales, (for it
was colde) and they warmed themselues: and Peter stood with them,
and warmed himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ The high
Priest then asked Iesus of his disciples, and of his
doctrine.</ab>
<ab n="20">Iesus answered him,
I spake openly to the world, I euer taught in the Synagogue, and in
the Temple, whither the Iewes alwayes resort, and in secret haue I
said nothing:</ab>
<ab n="21">Why askest thou me?
Aske them which heard me, what I haue said vnto them: behold, they
know what I said.</ab>
<ab n="22">And when hee had
thus spoken, one of the officers which stood by, stroke Iesus with
the palme of his hand, saying, Answerest thou the hie priest
so?<note> Or, with a rod.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Iesus answered him,
If I haue spoken euill, beare witnesse of the euill: but if well,
why smitest thou me?</ab>

<fw>Christs kingdome.</fw>
<ab n="24">Now Annas had sent
him bound vnto Caiaphas the high Priest.<note> Mat.26. 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Simon Peter
stood and warmed himselfe: They said therefore vnto him, Art not
thou also one of his disciples? Hee denied it, and said, I am
not.<note> Mat.26. 69.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">One of the seruants
of the high Priests (being his kinsman whose eare Peter cut off)
saith, Did not I see thee in the garden with him?</ab>
<ab n="27">Peter then denied
againe, and immediatly the cocke crew.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Then led
they Iesus from Caiaphas vnto the hall of Iudgement: And it was
earely, and they themselues went not into the Iudgement hall, lest
they should be defiled: but that they might eat the
Passeouer.<note> Mat.27.2. , Or, Pilats house. , Acts 10. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Pilate then went
out vnto them, and said, What accusation bring you against this
man?</ab>
<ab n="30">They answered,
&amp; said vnto him, If he were not a malefactor, we would not haue
deliuered him vp vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then saide Pilate
vnto them, Take ye him, and iudge him according to your law. The
Iewes therefore said vnto him, It is not lawfull for vs to put any
man to death:</ab>
<ab n="32">That the saying of
Iesus might be fulfilled, which hee spake, signifying what death he
should die.<note> Mat.20. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Then Pilate entred
into the Iudgement hall againe, and called Iesus, and saide vnto
him, Art thou the King of the Iewes?<note> Mat.27. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Iesus answered him,
Sayest thou this thing of thy selfe? or did others tell it thee of
me?</ab>
<ab n="35">Pilate answered, Am
I a Iew? Thine owne nation, and the chiefe Priests haue deliuered
thee vnto mee: What hast thou done?</ab>
<ab n="36">Iesus answered, My
kingdome is not of this world: if my kingdome were of this world,
then would my seruants fight, that I should not be deliuered to the
Iewes: but now is my kingdome not from hence.</ab>
<ab n="37">Pilate therefore
saide vnto him, Art thou a King then? Iesus answered, Thou saiest
that I am a King. To this end was I borne, and for this cause came
I into the world, that I should beare witnesse vnto the trueth:
euery one that is of the trueth heareth my voice.</ab>

<fw>Barabbas preferred.</fw>
<ab n="38">Pilate saith vnto
him, What is trueth? And when hee had said this, he went out againe
vnto the Iewes, and saith vnto them, I find in him no fault at
all.</ab>
<ab n="39">But yee haue a
custome that I should release vnto you one at the Passeouer: will
ye therefore that I release vnto you the king of the
Iewes?<note> Matth. 27 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Then cried they all
againe, saying, Not this man, but Barabbas. Now Barabbas was a
robber.<note> Act.3.14.</note></ab>



</div>