<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-24-24b-John.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The Diuinitie, Humanitie, and
Office of Iesus Christ. 15 The testimonie of Iohn. 39 The calling
of Andrew, Peter, &amp;c.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
beginning was the Word, &amp; the Word was with God, and the Word
was God.</ab>
<ab n="2">The same was in
the beginning with God.<note> Gen.1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">All things were
made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was
made.<note> Col.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">In him was
life, and the life was the light of men.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the light
shineth in darknesse, and the darknesse comprehended it
not.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ There
was a man sent from God, whose name was Iohn.<note> Mat.3.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The same came
for a witnesse, to beare witnesse of the light, that all men
through him might beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="8">Hee was not
that light, but was sent to beare witnesse of that light.</ab>
<ab n="9">That was the
true light, which lighteth euery man that commeth into the
world.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee was in the
world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him
not.<note> Heb.11.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Hee came vnto
his owne, and his owne receiued him not.</ab>
<ab n="12">But as many as
receiued him, to them gaue hee power to become the sonnes of God,
euen to them that beleeue on his Name:<note> Or, the right or priuiledge.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Which were
borne, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will
of man, but of God.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the Word
was made flesh, and dwelt among vs (&amp; we beheld his glory, the
glory as of the onely begotten of the Father) full of grace and
trueth.<note> Mat.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Iohn
bare witnesse of him, and cried, saying, This was he of whom I
spake, He that commeth after me, is preferred before me, for he was
before me.</ab>
<ab n="16">And of his
fulnesse haue all wee receiued, and grace for grace.<note> Col.1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For the Law
was giuen by Moses, but grace and trueth came by Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="18">No man hath
seene God at any time: the onely begotten Sonne, which is in the
bosome of the Father, he hath declared him.<note> 1.Iohn 4. 12. 1.tim. 6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And
this is the record of Iohn, when the Iewes sent Priests and Leuites
from Hierusalem, to aske him, Who art thou?</ab>
<ab n="20">And he
confessed, and denied not: but confessed, I am not the
Christ.</ab>

<fw>The Lambe of God.</fw>
<ab n="21">And they asked
him, What then? Art thou Elias? And he saith, I am not. Art thou
that Prophet? And hee answered, No.<note> Or, a Prophet.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then said they
vnto him, Who art thou, that we may giue an answere to them that
sent vs? What sayest thou of thy selfe?</ab>
<ab n="23">He said, I am
the voice of one crying in the wildernesse: Make straight the way
of the Lord, as said the Prophet Esaias.<note> Mat.3.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And they which
were sent, were of the Pharises.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they asked
him, and said vnto him, Why baptizest thou then, if thou be not
that Christ, nor Elias, neither that Prophet?</ab>
<ab n="26">Iohn answered
them, saying, I baptize with water, but there standeth one among
you, whom ye know not,</ab>
<ab n="27">He it is, who
comming after me, is preferred before me, whose shoes latchet I am
not worthy to vnloose.<note> Mat.3.11. acts 19.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">These things
were done in Bethabara beyond Iordane, where Iohn was
baptizing.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ The
next day, Iohn seeth Iesus comming vnto him, and saith, Behold the
Lambe of God, which taketh away the sinne of the world.<note> Or, beareth.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">This is he of
whom I said, After me commeth a man, which is preferred before me:
for he was before me.</ab>
<ab n="31">And I knew him
not: but that he should be made manifest to Israel, therfore am I
come baptizing with water.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Iohn bare
record saying, I saw the Spirit descending from heauen, like a
Doue, and it abode vpon him.<note> Mat.3.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And I knew him
not: but he that sent me to baptize with water, the same said vnto
me, Upon whom thou shalt see the Spirit descending, &amp; remaining
on him, the same is he which baptizeth with the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="34">And I saw, and
bare record, that this is the sonne of God.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ Againe
the next day after, Iohn stood, and two of his disciples.</ab>
<ab n="36">And looking
vpon Iesus as he walked, he saith, Behold the Lambe of God.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the two
disciples heard him speake, and they followed Iesus.</ab>

<fw>A true Israelite.</fw>
<ab n="38">Then Iesus
turned, and saw them following, and saith vnto them, What seeke ye?
They said vnto him, Rabbi, (which is to say being interpreted,
Master) where dwellest thou?<note> Or, abidest.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">He saith vnto
them, Come and see. They came and saw where he dwelt, and abode
with him that day: for it was about the tenth houre.<note> That was two houres before night.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">One of the two
which heard Iohn speake, and followed him, was Andrew, Simon Peters
brother.</ab>
<ab n="41">He first
findeth his owne brother Simon, and saith vnto him, We haue found
the Messias, which is, being interpreted, the Christ.<note> Or, the anointed.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And he brought
him to Iesus. And when Iesus beheld him, he said, Thou art Simon
the sonne of Iona, thou shalt be called Cephas, which is by
interpretation, a stone.<note> Or, Peter.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">¶ The day
following, Iesus would goe foorth into Galilee, &amp; findeth
Philip, &amp; saith vnto him, Follow me.</ab>
<ab n="44">Now Philip was
of Bethsaida, the citie of Andrew and Peter.</ab>
<ab n="45">Philip findeth
Nathaneel, and saith vnto him, We haue found him of whom Moses in
the Law, and the Prophets did write, Iesus of Nazareth the sonne of
Ioseph.<note> Gen.49.10. leuit.18. 18. , Esai.4.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And Nathaneel
said vnto him, Can there any good thing come out of Nazareth?
Philip saith vnto him, Come and see.</ab>
<ab n="47">Iesus saw
Nathaneel comming to him, and saith of him, Behold an Israelite
indeed in whom is no guile.</ab>
<ab n="48">Nathaneel
sayeth vnto him, Whence knowest thou me? Iesus answered, and said
vnto him, Before that Philip called thee, when thou wast vnder the
figge tree, I saw thee.</ab>
<ab n="49">Nathaneel
answered, and saith vnto him, Rabbi, thou art the Sonne of God,
thou art the king of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="50">Iesus
answered, and said vnto him, Because I said vnto thee, I saw thee
vnder the figge tree, beleeuest thou? thou shalt see greater things
then these.</ab>
<ab n="51">And hee saith
vnto him, Uerily, verily I say vnto you, heereafter yee shall see
heauen open, and the Angels of God ascending, and descending vpon
the sonne of man.</ab>



</div>