<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>Iesus reprooueth the ambition and
boldnesse of his kinsemen: 10 goeth vp from Galilee to the feast of
Tabernacles, 14 teacheth in the Temple. 40 Diuers opinions of him
among the people. 45 The Pharisees are angry that their officers
tooke him not, &amp; chide with Nicodemus for taking his
part.</head>

<ab n="1">After these
things, Iesus walked in Galilee: for hee would not walk in Iurie,
because the Iewes sought to kill him.</ab>
<ab n="2">Now the Iewes
feast of Tabernacles was at hand.<note> Leuit. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">His brethren
therefore saide vnto him, Depart hence, and go into Iudea, that thy
Disciples also may see the works that thou doest.</ab>
<ab n="4">For there is no
man that doth any thing in secret, and hee himselfe seeketh to be
knowen openly: If thou doe these things, shew thy selfe to
þe world.</ab>
<ab n="5">For neither did
his brethren beleeue in him.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Iesus said
vnto them, My time is not yet come: but your time is alway
ready.</ab>

<fw>Christs doctrine.</fw>
<ab n="7">The world
cannot hate you, but me it hateth, because I testifie of it, that
the workes thereof are euill.</ab>
<ab n="8">Goe ye vp vnto
this feast: I goe not vp yet vnto this feast, for my time is not
yet full come.<note> Cha. 8.20</note></ab>
<ab n="9">When he had
said these words vnto them, he abode still in Galilee.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ But
when his brethren were gone vp, then went he also vp vnto the
feast, not openly, but as it were in secret.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then the Iewes
sought him at the feast, and said, Where is he?</ab>
<ab n="12">And there was
much murmuring among the people, concerning him: For some said, Hee
is a good man: Others said, Nay, but he deceiueth the
people.</ab>
<ab n="13">Howbeit, no
man spake openly of him, for feare of the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Now
about the middest of the feast, Iesus went vp into the Temple, and
taught.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Iewes
marueiled, saying, How knoweth this man letters, hauing neuer
learned?<note> Or, learning.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Iesus answered
them, My doctrine is not mine, but his that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="17">If any man
will doe his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of
God, or whether I speake of my selfe.</ab>
<ab n="18">He that
speaketh of himselfe, seeketh his owne glory: but he that seeketh
his glory that sent him, the same is true, and no vnrighteousnesse
is in him.</ab>
<ab n="19">Did not Moses
giue you the Law, and yet none of you keepeth the Law? Why goe ye
about to kill me?<note> Exo.24.3. , Cha.5.18</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The people
answered, and sayd, Thou hast a deuill: Who goeth about to kill
thee?</ab>
<ab n="21">Iesus
answered, and saide vnto them, I haue done one worke, and yee all
marueile.</ab>
<ab n="22">Moses
therefore gaue vnto you Circumcision (not because it is of Moses,
but of the fathers) and yee on the Sabbath day circumcise a
man.<note> Leui.12.3 , Gen.17.10</note></ab>
<ab n="23">If a man on
the Sabbath day receiue circumcision, that the Lawe of Moses should
not be broken; are ye angry at me, because I haue made a man euery
whit whole on the Sabbath day?<note> Or, without breaking the Law of Moses.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Iudge not
according to the appearance, but iudge righteous
iudgement.<note> Deu.1.16</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then said some
of them of Hierusalem, Is not this hee, whome they seeke to
kill?</ab>

<fw>Liuing water.</fw>
<ab n="26">But loe, he
speaketh boldly, and they say nothing vnto him: Doe the rulers know
indeede that this is the very Christ?</ab>
<ab n="27">Howbeit wee
know this man whence he is: but when Christ commeth, no man knoweth
whence he is.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then cried
Iesus in the Temple as he taught, saying, Ye both know me, and ye
know whence I am, and I am not come of my selfe, but he that sent
me, is true, whom ye know not.</ab>
<ab n="29">But I know
him, for I am from him, and he hath sent me.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then they
sought to take him: but no man laid hands on him, because his houre
was not yet come.</ab>
<ab n="31">And many of
the people beleeued on him, &amp; said, When Christ commeth, will
hee doe moe miracles then these which this man hath done?</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ The
Pharisees heard that the people murmured such things concerning
him: And the Pharisees and the chiefe Priests sent officers to take
him.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then said
Iesus vnto them, Yet a litle while am I with you, and then I goe
vnto him that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="34">Ye shall seeke
me, and shall not find me: and where I am, thither yee cannot
come.<note> Chap.13. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Then saide the
Iewes among themselues, Whither will hee goe, that we shall not
find him? will he goe vnto the dispersed among the Gentiles, and
teach the Gentiles?<note> Or, Greeks.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">What maner of
saying is this that he said, Ye shall seeke me, and shall not find
me? and where I am, thither ye cannot come?</ab>
<ab n="37">In the last
day, that great day of the feast, Iesus stood, and cried, saying,
If any man thirst, let him come vnto me, and drinke.<note> Leuit.23. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">He that
beleeueth on me, as the Scripture hath saide, out of his belly
shall flow riuers of liuing water.<note> Deut.18. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">(But this
spake he of the Spirit which they that beleeue on him, should
receiue. For the holy Ghost was not yet giuen, because that Iesus
was not yet glorified.)<note> Ioel.2.28. esai.44.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">¶ Many of
the people therefore, when they heard this saying, saide, Of a
trueth this is the Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="41">Others said,
This is the Christ. But some said, Shall Christ come out of
Galilee?</ab>

<fw>Nicodemus counsell.</fw>
<ab n="42">Hath not the
Scripture saide, that Christ commeth of the seede of Dauid, and out
of the towne of Bethlehem, where Dauid was?<note> Mat.2.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">So there was
diuision among the people because of him.</ab>
<ab n="44">And some of
them would haue taken him, but no man layed hands on him.</ab>
<ab n="45">¶ Then
came the officers to the chiefe Priests and Pharises, and they said
vnto them, Why haue ye not brought him?</ab>
<ab n="46">The officers
answered, Neuer man spake like this man.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then answered
them the Pharisees, Are ye also deceiued?</ab>
<ab n="48">Haue any of
the rulers, or of the Pharises beleeued on him?</ab>
<ab n="49">But this
people who knoweth not the Law, are cursed.</ab>
<ab n="50">Nicodemus
saith vnto them, (He that came to Iesus by night, being one of
them,)<note> Chap.3.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">Doth our Law
iudge any man before it heare him, &amp; know what he
doth?<note> Deut.17. 10. and 19. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">They answered,
and said vnto him, Art thou also of Galilee? Search, and looke: for
out of Galilee ariseth no Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="53">And euery man
went vnto his owne house.</ab>



</div>