<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Christ raiseth Lazarus, foure
dayes buried. 45 Many Iewes beleeue. 47 The high Priests and
Pharisees gather a counsel against Christ. 49 Caiaphas prophecieth.
54 Iesus hid himselfe. 55 At the Passeouer they enquire after him,
and lay wait for him.</head>

<ab n="1">Now a certaine
man was sicke, named Lazarus of Bethanie, the towne of Mary, and
her sister Martha.</ab>
<ab n="2">(It was that
Mary which anoynted the Lord with oyntment, and wiped his feete
with her haire, whose brother Lazarus was sicke.)<note> Matt,26. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore his
sister sent vnto him, saying, Lord, behold, hee whom thou louest,
is sicke.</ab>
<ab n="4">When Iesus
heard that, hee said, This sicknesse is not vnto death, but for the
glory of God, that the Sonne of God might be glorified
thereby.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now Iesus
loued Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus.</ab>
<ab n="6">When he had
heard therefore that he was sicke, he abode two dayes still in the
same place where he was.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then after
that, saith hee to his disciples, Let vs go into Iudea
againe.</ab>
<ab n="8">His disciples
say vnto him, Master, the Iewes of late sought to stone thee, and
goest thou thither againe?</ab>
<ab n="9">Iesus
answered, Are there not twelue houres in the day? If any man walke
in the day, he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this
world.</ab>

<fw>Lazarus dieth, and is raised to
life.</fw>
<ab n="10">But if a man walke
in the night, hee stumbleth, because there is no light in
him.</ab>
<ab n="11">These things said
hee, and after that, hee saith vnto them, Our friend Lazarus
sleepeth, but I goe, that I may awake him out of sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then said his
disciples, Lord, if he sleepe, he shall doe well.</ab>
<ab n="13">Howbeit Iesus spake
of his death: but they thought that hee had spoken of taking of
rest in sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then saide Iesus
vnto them plainly, Lazarus is dead:</ab>
<ab n="15">And I am glad for
your sakes, that I was not there (to the intent yee may beleeue:)
Neuerthelesse, let vs goe vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then said Thomas,
which is called Didymus, vnto his fellow disciples, Let vs also
goe, that we may die with him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then when Iesus
came, hee found that hee had lien in the graue foure dayes
already.</ab>
<ab n="18">(Now Bethanie was
nigh vnto Hierusalem, about fifteene furlongs off:)<note> That is, about two mile.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And many of the
Iewes came to Martha, and Mary, to comfort them concerning their
brother.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then Martha, as
soone as shee heard that Iesus was comming, went and met him: but
Mary sate still in the house.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then saide Martha
vnto Iesus, Lord, if thou hadst bene here, my brother had not
died.</ab>
<ab n="22">But I know, that
euen now, whatsoeuer thou wilt aske of God, God will giue it
thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">Iesus saith vnto
her, Thy brother shall rise againe.</ab>
<ab n="24">Martha sayeth vnto
him, I know that he shall rise againe in the resurrection at the
last day.<note> Luke 14.14. chap.5. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Iesus said vnto
her, I am the resurrection, and the life: hee that beleeueth in me,
though he were dead, yet shall he liue.<note> Chap.6. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And whosoeuer
liueth, and beleeueth in mee, shall neuer die. Beleeuest thou
this?</ab>
<ab n="27">She saith vnto him,
Yea Lord, I beleeue that thou art the Christ the Sonne of God,
which should come into the world.</ab>

<fw>Iesus weepeth.</fw>
<ab n="28">And when shee had
so said, shee went her way, and called Mary her sister secretly,
saying, The Master is come, and calleth for thee.</ab>
<ab n="29">Assoone as she
heard that, she arose quickely, and came vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="30">Now Iesus was not
yet come into the towne, but was in that place where Martha met
him.</ab>
<ab n="31">The Iewes then
which were with her in the house, and comforted her, when they saw
Mary that she rose vp hastily, and went out, followed her, saying,
Shee goeth vnto the graue, to weepe there.</ab>
<ab n="32">Then when Mary was
come where Iesus was, and saw him, shee fell downe at his feete,
saying vnto him, Lord, if thou hadst beene here, my brother had not
dyed.</ab>
<ab n="33">When Iesus
therefore sawe her weeping, and the Iewes also weeping which came
with her, hee groned in the Spirit, and was troubled,<note> Gr. Hee troubled himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And said, Where
haue ye laid him? They say vnto him, Lord, come, &amp; see.</ab>
<ab n="35">Iesus wept.</ab>
<ab n="36">Then said the
Iewes, Behold, how he loued him.</ab>
<ab n="37">And some of them
said, Could not this man, which opened the eyes of the blinde, haue
caused that euen this man should not haue died?<note> Chap.9.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Iesus therefore
againe groning in himselfe, commeth to the graue. It was a caue,
and a stone lay vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="39">Iesus said, Take
yee away the stone. Martha, the sister of him that was dead, sayth
vnto him, Lord, by this time he stinketh: for he hath beene dead
foure dayes.</ab>
<ab n="40">Iesus saith vnto
her, Said I not vnto thee, that if thou wouldst beleeue, thou
shouldest see the glory of God?</ab>
<ab n="41">Then they tooke
away the stone from the place where the dead was laid. And Iesus
lift vp his eyes, and said, Father, I thanke thee, that thou hast
heard me.</ab>
<ab n="42">And I knewe that
thou hearest me alwayes: but because of the people which stand by,
I said it, that they may beleeue that thou hast sent me.</ab>
<ab n="43">And when hee thus
had spoken, he cryed with a loude voice, Lazarus, come
foorth.</ab>
<ab n="44">And he that was
dead, came forth, bound hand &amp; foot with graue-clothes: and his
face was bound about with a napkin. Iesus saith vnto them, Loose
him, and let him goe.</ab>

<fw>Caiaphas prophecie.</fw>
<ab n="45">Then many of the
Iewes which came to Mary, and had seene the things which Iesus did,
beleeued on him.</ab>
<ab n="46">But some of them
went their wayes to the Pharises, and tolde them what things Iesus
had done.</ab>
<ab n="47">¶ Then
gathered þe chiefe Priests and the Pharises a
councell, and said, What doe wee? for this man doeth many
miracles.</ab>
<ab n="48">If we let him thus
alone, all men will beleeue on him, and the Romanes shall come, and
take away both our place and nation.</ab>
<ab n="49">And one of them
named Caiaphas, being the high Priest that same yeere, said vnto
them, Ye know nothing at all,</ab>
<ab n="50">Nor consider that
it is expedient for vs, that one man should die for the people, and
that the whole nation perish not.<note> Chap.18. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And this spake he
not of himselfe: but being high Priest that yeere, he prophecied
that Iesus should die for that nation:</ab>
<ab n="52">And not for that
nation only, but that also hee should gather together in one, the
children of God that were scattered abroad.</ab>
<ab n="53">Then from that day
foorth, they tooke counsell together for to put him to
death.</ab>
<ab n="54">Iesus therefore
walked no more openly among the Iewes: but went thence vnto a
countrey neere to the wildernesse, into a city called Ephraim, and
there continued with his disciples.</ab>
<ab n="55">¶ And the
Iewes Passeouer was nigh at hand, and many went out of the countrey
vp to Hierusalem before the Passeouer to purifie
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="56">Then sought they
for Iesus, and spake among themselues, as they stood in the Temple,
What thinke ye, that he will not come to the feast?</ab>
<ab n="57">Now both the chiefe
Priests and the Pharises had giuen a commandement, that if any man
knew where hee were, he should shew it, that they might take
him.</ab>



</div>