<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Christ teacheth Nicodemus the
necessitie of regeneration. 14 Of faith in his death. 16 The great
loue of God towards the world. 18 Condemnation for vnbeliefe. 23
The baptisme, witnes &amp; doctrine of Iohn concerning
Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">There was a man
of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of þe
Iewes:</ab>
<ab n="2">The same came
to Iesus by night, and said vnto him, Rabbi, wee know that thou art
a teacher come from God: for no man can doe these miracles that
thou doest, except God be with him.</ab>
<ab n="3">Iesus answered,
and said vnto him, Uerily, verily I say vnto thee, except a man be
borne againe, he cannot see the kingdome of God.<note> Or, from aboue.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Nicodemus saith
vnto him, How can a man be borne when he is old? can he enter the
second time into his mothers wombe, and be borne?</ab>
<ab n="5">Iesus answered,
Uerily, verily I say vnto thee, except a man be borne of water and
of the spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">That which is
borne of the flesh, is flesh, and that which is borne of the
spirit, is spirit.</ab>
<ab n="7">Marueile not
that I saide vnto thee, Ye must be borne againe.<note> Or, from aboue.</note></ab>

<fw>The force of faith.</fw>
<ab n="8">The winde
bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but
canst not tel whence it commeth, and whither it goeth: So is euery
one that is borne of the Spirit.</ab>
<ab n="9">Nicodemus
answered, and said vnto him, How can these things be?</ab>
<ab n="10">Iesus
answered, and saide vnto him, Art thou a master of Israel, and
knowest not these things?</ab>
<ab n="11">Uerely, verely
I say vnto thee, We speake that we doe know, and testifie that wee
haue seene; and yee receiue not our witnesse.</ab>
<ab n="12">If I haue
tolde you earthly things, and ye beleeue not: how shall ye beleeue
if I tell you of heauenly things?</ab>
<ab n="13">And no man
hath ascended vp to heauen, but hee that came downe from heauen,
euen the Sonne of man which is in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And as
Moses lifted vp the serpent in the wildernesse: euen so must the
Sonne of man be lifted vp:<note> Num.21. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">That whosoeuer
beleeueth in him, should not perish, but haue eternall
life.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ For God
so loued þe world, that he gaue his only begotten
Sonne: that whosoeuer beleeueth in him, should not perish, but haue
euerlasting life.<note> 1. Iohn 4. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For God sent
not his Sonne into the world to condemne the world: but that the
world through him might be saued.<note> Chap. 12. 47.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ He that
beleeueth on him, is not condemned: but hee that beleeueth not, is
condemned already, because hee hath not beleeued in the Name of the
onely begotten Sonne of God.</ab>
<ab n="19">And this is
the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men loued
darknesse rather then light, because their deedes were
euill.<note> Cha.1.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For euery one
that doeth euill, hateth the light, neither commeth to the light,
lest his deeds should be reproued.<note> Or, discouered.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But hee that
doeth trueth, commeth to the light, that his deeds may be made
manifest, that they are wrought in God.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ After
these things, came Iesus and his disciples into the land of Iudea,
and there hee taried with them, and baptized.<note> Chap.4. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
Iohn also was baptizing in Aenon, neere to Salim, because there was
much water there: and they came, and were baptized.</ab>

<fw>Iohns testimonie.</fw>
<ab n="24">For Iohn was
not yet cast into prison.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Then
there arose a question between some of Iohns disciples and the
Iewes, about purifying.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they came
vnto Iohn, and said vnto him, Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond
Iordane, to whom thou barest witnesse, behold, the same baptizeth,
and all men come to him.<note> Chap.1. 7,34.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Iohn answered,
and said, A man can receiue nothing, except it be giuen him from
heauen.<note> Heb.5.4. , Or, take vnto himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Ye your selues
beare me witnesse, that I said, I am not the Christ, but that I am
sent before him.<note> Chap.1. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">He that hath
the bride, is the bridegrome: but the friend of the bridegrome,
which standeth and heareth him, reioyceth greatly because of the
bridegromes voice: This my ioy therefore is fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="30">Hee must
increase, but I must decrease.</ab>
<ab n="31">Hee that
commeth from aboue, is aboue all: hee that is of the earth, is
earthly, and speaketh of the earth: hee that cōmeth from
heauen is aboue all:</ab>
<ab n="32">And what hee
hath seene and heard, that he testifieth, and no man receiueth his
testimony:</ab>
<ab n="33">He that hath
receiued his testimonie, hath set to his seale, that God is
true.<note> Rom.3.4</note></ab>
<ab n="34">For he whom
God hath sent, speaketh the words of God: For God giueth not the
Spirit by measure vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="35">The Father
loueth the Sonne, and hath giuen al things into his
hand.<note> Matth.11. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">He that
beleeueth on the Sonne, hath euerlasting life: and he that
beleeueth not the Sonne, shall not see life: but the wrath of God
abideth on him.<note> Habac.2. 4. 1.iohn 5. 10.</note></ab>



</div>