<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The man that was borne blinde
restored to sight. 8 Hee is brought to the Pharises. 13 They are
offended at it, and excommunicate him: 35 But hee is receiued of
Iesus, and confesseth him. 39 Who they are whome Christ
enlighteneth.</head>

<ab n="1">And as Iesus
passed by, he saw a man which was blinde from his birth.</ab>
<ab n="2">And his
disciples asked him, saying, Master, who did sinne, this man, or
his parents, that he was borne blinde?</ab>
<ab n="3">Iesus answered,
Neither hath this man sinned, nor his parents: but that the workes
of God should be made manifest in him.</ab>
<ab n="4">I must worke
the workes of him that sent me, while it is day: the night commeth
when no man can worke.</ab>
<ab n="5">As long as I am
in the world, I am the light of the world.<note> Chap.1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">When he had
thus spoken, he spat on the ground, and made clay of the spettle,
and he anointed the eyes of the blinde man with the
clay,<note> Or, spread the clay vpon the eyes of the blinde man.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And said vnto
him, Goe wash in the poole of Siloam (which is by interpretation,
Sent.) He went his way therfore, and washed, and came
seeing.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ The
neighbours therefore, and they which before had seene him, that he
was blinde, said, Is not this he that sate and begged?</ab>
<ab n="9">Some said, This
is hee: others said, Hee is like him: but hee sayd, I am
hee.</ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore said
they vnto him, How were thine eyes opened?</ab>

<fw>The blind, healed, beleeueth in
Christ.</fw>
<ab n="11">He answered
and said, A man that is called Iesus, made clay, and anointed mine
eyes, and said vnto me, Goe to the poole of Siloam, and wash: and I
went and washed, and I receiued sight.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then said they
vnto him, Where is he? He said, I know not.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ They
brought to the Pharisees him that aforetime was blind.</ab>
<ab n="14">And it was the
Sabbath day when Iesus made the clay, and opened his eyes.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then againe
the Pharisees also asked him how he had receiued his sight. He said
vnto them, Hee put clay vpon mine eyes, and I washed, and doe
see.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore said
some of the Pharisees, This man is not of God, because hee keepeth
not the Sabbath day. Others said, How can a man that is a sinner,
doe such miracles? and there was a diuision among them.</ab>
<ab n="17">They say vnto
the blind man againe, What sayest thou of him, that he hath opened
thine eyes? He said, Hee is a Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="18">But the Iewes
did not beleeue concerning him, that hee had bin blind, and
receiued his sight, vntill they called the parents of him that had
receiued his sight.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they asked
them, saying, Is this your sonne, who ye say was borne blind? how
then doth he now see?</ab>
<ab n="20">His parents
answered them, and said, We know that this is our sonne, and that
he was borne blind:</ab>
<ab n="21">But by what
meanes he now seeth, we know not, or who hath opened his eyes we
know not: hee is of age, aske him, he shall speake for
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="22">These words
spake his parents, because they feared the Iewes: for the Iewes had
agreed already, that if any man did confesse that he was Christ, he
should be put out of the Synagogue.</ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore said
his parents, He is of age, aske him.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then againe
called they the man that was blind, and said vnto him, Giue God the
praise, we know that this man is a sinner.</ab>
<ab n="25">He answered,
and said, Whether he be a sinner or no, I know not: One thing I
know, that whereas I was blind, now I see.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then saide
they to him againe, What did he to thee? How opened hee thine
eyes?</ab>

<fw>The blind, healed, beleeueth in
Christ.</fw>
<ab n="27">He answered
them, I haue told you already, and ye did not heare: wherfore would
you heare it againe? Will ye also be his disciples?</ab>
<ab n="28">Then they
reuiled him, and said, Thou art his disciple, but we are Moses
disciples.</ab>
<ab n="29">Wee know that
God spake vnto Moses: as for this fellow, we knowe not from whence
he is.</ab>
<ab n="30">The man
answered, and said vnto them, Why herein is a marueilous thing,
that ye know not from whence he is, and yet he hath opened mine
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="31">Now we know
that God heareth not sinners: but if any man bee a worshipper of
God, and doth his will, him he heareth.</ab>
<ab n="32">Since the
world began was it not heard that any man opened the eyes of one
that was borne blinde:</ab>
<ab n="33">If this man
were not of God, he could doe nothing.</ab>
<ab n="34">They answered,
and saide vnto him, Thou wast altogether borne in sinnes, and doest
thou teach vs? And they cast him out.<note> Or, excommunicated him.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Iesus heard
that they had cast him out; and when hee had found him, he said
vnto him, Doest thou beleeue on the Sonne of God?</ab>
<ab n="36">He answered
and said, Who is he, Lord, that I might beleeue on him?</ab>
<ab n="37">And Iesus said
vnto him, Thou hast both seene him, and it is he that talketh with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="38">And he said,
Lord, I beleeue: and he worshipped him.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And
Iesus said, For iudgment I am come into this world, that they which
see not, might see, and that they which see, might be made
blind.</ab>
<ab n="40">And some of
the Pharisees which were with him, heard these words, and saide
vnto him, Are wee blinde also?</ab>
<ab n="41">Iesus saide
vnto them, If yee were blind, ye should haue no sinne: but now ye
say, We see, therfore your sinne remaineth.</ab>



</div>