<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Christ is the doore and the good
Shepheard. 19 Diuers opinions of him. 24 He proueth by his workes,
that he is Christ the Sonne of God, 39 Escapeth the Iewes, 40 and
went againe beyond Iordane, where many beleeued on
him.</head>


<fw>The good Shepheard.</fw>
<ab n="1">Uerily, verily
I say vnto you, He that entreth not by þe doore
into the sheepefold, but climeth vp some other way, the same is a
theefe, and a robber.</ab>
<ab n="2">But hee that
entreth in by the doore, is the shepherd of the sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="3">To him the
porter openeth, and the sheepe heare his voyce, and he calleth his
owne sheepe by name, and leadeth them out.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when he
putteth foorth his owne sheepe, he goeth before them, and the
sheepe follow him: for they know his voyce.</ab>
<ab n="5">And a stranger
will they not follow, but will flee from him, for they know not the
voyce of strangers.</ab>
<ab n="6">This parable
spake Iesus vnto them: but they vnderstood not what things they
were which he spake vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then said
Iesus vnto them againe, Uerily, verily I say vnto you, I am the
doore of the sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="8">All that euer
came before me, are theeues and robbers: but the sheepe did not
heare them.</ab>
<ab n="9">I am the doore
by me if any man enter in, he shall be saued, and shall goe in and
out, and find pasture.</ab>
<ab n="10">The theefe commeth
not, but for to steale and to kill, and to destroy: I am come that
they might haue life, and that they might haue it more
abundantly.</ab>
<ab n="11">I am the good
shepheard: the good shepheard giueth his life for the
sheepe.<note> Esai.40.11. ezech. 34.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But hee that is an
hireling and not the shepheard, whose owne the sheepe are not,
seeth the woolfe coming, and leaueth the sheep, and fleeth: and the
woolfe catcheth them, and scattereth the sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="13">The hireling
fleeth, because he is an hireling, &amp; careth not for the
sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="14">I am the good
shepheard, and know my sheepe, and am knowen of mine.</ab>
<ab n="15">As the father
knoweth me, euen so know I the father: &amp; I lay downe my life
for the sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="16">And other sheepe I
haue, which are not of this fold: them also I must bring, and they
shall heare my voyce; and there shall be one fold, and one
shepheard.<note> Esai.37. 22.</note></ab>

<fw>Christs sheepe.</fw>
<ab n="17">Therefore doth my
father loue me, because I lay downe my life that I might take it
againe.<note> Esay.53. 7,8.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">No man taketh it
from me, but I lay it downe of my selfe: I haue power to lay it
downe, and I haue power to take it againe. This commandement haue I
receiued of my father.<note> Acts 2.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ There was a
diuision therefore againe among the Iewes for these
sayings.</ab>
<ab n="20">And many of them
said, He hath a deuill, and is mad, why heare ye him?</ab>
<ab n="21">Others said, These
are not the words of him that hath a deuill. Can a deuill open the
eyes of the blind?</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And it was
at Hierusalem the feast of the dedication, &amp; it was
winter.<note> 1.Macc.4. 59.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Iesus walked in
the temple in Solomons porch.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then came the Iewes
round about him, and said vnto him, How long doest thou make vs to
doubt? If thou be the Christ, tell vs plainely.<note> Or, hold vs in suspence.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Iesus answered
them, I told you, and ye beleeued not: the workes that I doe in my
Fathers name, they beare witnesse of me.</ab>
<ab n="26">But ye beleeue not,
because ye are not of my sheepe, as I said vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="27">My sheepe heare my
voyce, and I know them, and they follow me.</ab>
<ab n="28">And I giue vnto
them eternall life, and they shall neuer perish, neither shall any
man plucke them out of my hand.</ab>
<ab n="29">My father which
gaue them me, is greater then all: and no man is able to plucke
them out of my fathers hand.</ab>
<ab n="30">I and my father are
one.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then the Iewes
tooke vp stones againe to stone him.</ab>
<ab n="32">Iesus answered
them, Many good workes haue I shewed you from my Father; for which
of those workes doe ye stone me?</ab>
<ab n="33">The Iewes answered
him, saying, For a good worke we stone thee not, but for blasphemy,
and because that thou, being a man, makest thy selfe God.</ab>
<ab n="34">Iesus answered
them, Is it not written in your law, I said, ye are
gods?<note> Psal.82.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">If hee called them
gods, vnto whom the word of God came, and the Scripture cannot be
broken:</ab>

<fw>Lazarus dieth, and is raised to
life.</fw>
<ab n="36">Say ye of him, whom
the father hath sanctified and sent into the world, Thou
blasphemest; because I said, I am the Sonne of God?</ab>
<ab n="37">If I doe not the
workes of my Father, beleeue me not.</ab>
<ab n="38">But if I doe,
though yee beleeue not me, beleeue the works: that ye may know and
beleeue that the Father is in me, and I in him.</ab>
<ab n="39">Therefore they
sought againe to take him: but hee escaped out of their
hand,</ab>
<ab n="40">And went away
againe beyond Iordane, into the place where Iohn at first baptized:
and there he abode.</ab>
<ab n="41">And many resorted
vnto him, and said, Iohn did no miracle: but all things that Iohn
spake of this man, were true.</ab>
<ab n="42">And many beleeued
on him there.</ab>



</div>