<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Christ deliuereth the woman taken
in adultery. 12 He preacheth himselfe the light of the world, and
iustifieth his Doctrine: 33 Answereth the Iewes that boasted of
Abraham, 59 And conueigheth himselfe from their
crueltie.</head>

<ab n="1">Iesus went vnto
þe Mount of Oliues:</ab>
<ab n="2">And earely in
the morning hee came againe into the Temple, and all the people
came vnto him, and he sate downe, and taught them.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the Scribes
and Pharisees brought vnto him a woman taken in adultery, and when
they had set her in the mids,</ab>
<ab n="4">They say vnto
him, Master, this woman was taken in adultery, in the very
act.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now Moses in
the Law commanded vs, that such should be stoned: but what sayest
thou?<note> Leuit.20. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">This they said,
tempting him, that they might haue to accuse him. But Iesus stouped
downe, and with his finger wrote on the ground as though he heard
them not.</ab>

<fw>True testimonie.</fw>
<ab n="7">So when they
continued asking him, hee lift vp himselfe, and saide vnto them,
Hee that is without sinne among you, let him first cast a stone at
her.<note> Deut. 17. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And againe, hee
stouped downe, and wrote on the ground.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they which
heard it, being conuicted by their owne conscience, went out one by
one, beginning at the eldest, euen vnto the last: and Iesus was
left alone, and the woman standing in the midst.</ab>
<ab n="10">When Iesus had
lift vp himselfe, and saw none but the woman, hee said vnto her,
Woman, where are those thine accusers? Hath no man condemned
thee?</ab>
<ab n="11">She saide, No
man, Lord. And Iesus saide vnto her, Neither doe I condemne thee:
Goe, and sinne no more.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then
spake Iesus againe vnto them, saying, I am the light of the world:
he that followeth mee, shall not walke in darkenesse, but shall
haue the light of life.<note> Chap.1. 5.and 9.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The Pharisees
therefore said vnto him, Thou bearest record of thy selfe, thy
record is not true.</ab>
<ab n="14">Iesus
answered, and said vnto them, Though I beare record of my selfe,
yet my record is true: for I know whence I came, and whither I goe:
but ye cannot tell whence I come, and whither I goe.<note> Chap.5. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Yee iudge
after the flesh, I iudge no man.</ab>
<ab n="16">And yet if I
iudge, my iudgement is true: for I am not alone, but I and the
Father that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="17">It is also
written in your Law, that the testimonie of two men is
true.<note> Deut. 17. 6. matt.18. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">I am one that
beare witnesse of my selfe, and the Father that sent mee, beareth
witnesse of me.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then said they
vnto him, Where is thy Father? Iesus answered, Ye neither know me,
nor my Father: if ye had knowen mee, yee should haue knowen my
Father also.</ab>
<ab n="20">These words
spake Iesus in the treasury, as hee taught in the Temple: and no
man layd hands on him, for his houre was not yet come.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then saide
Iesus againe vnto them, I goe my way, and ye shall seeke me, &amp;
shall die in your sinnes: Whither I goe, ye cannot come.</ab>

<fw>True freedome.</fw>
<ab n="22">Then said the
Iewes, Will hee kill himselfe? because he saith, Whither I goe, ye
cannot come.</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee said
vnto them, Yee are from beneath, I am from aboue: Yee are of this
world, I am not of this world.</ab>
<ab n="24">I said
therefore vnto you, that ye shall die in your sinnes. For if yee
beleeue not that I am hee, yee shall die in your sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then said they
vnto him, Who art thou? And Iesus saith vnto them, Euen the same
that I saide vnto you from the beginning.</ab>
<ab n="26">I haue many
things to say, and to iudge of you: But hee that sent mee is true,
and I speake to the world, those things which I haue heard of
him.</ab>
<ab n="27">They
vnderstood not that hee spake to them of the Father.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then saide
Iesus vnto them, When yee haue lift vp the Sonne of man, then shall
ye know that I am he, and that I doe nothing of my selfe: but as my
Father hath taught mee, I speake these things.</ab>
<ab n="29">And he that
sent me, is with me: the Father hath not left mee alone: for I doe
alwayes those things that please him.</ab>
<ab n="30">As hee spake
those words, many beleeued on him.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then said
Iesus to those Iewes which beleeued on him, If ye continue in my
word, then are yee my disciples indeed.</ab>
<ab n="32">And ye shall
know the Trueth, and the Trueth shall make you free.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ They
answered him, We be Abraham seed, and were neuer in bondage to any
man: how sayest thou, Yee shall be made free?</ab>
<ab n="34">Iesus answered
them, Uerily, verily I say vnto you, Whosoeuer committeth sinne, is
the seruant of sinne.<note> Rom.6. 20. 2.pet. 2.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And the
seruant abideth not in the house for euer: but the Sonne abideth
euer.</ab>
<ab n="36">If the Sonne
therfore shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed.</ab>
<ab n="37">I know that
yee are Abrahams seed, but ye seeke to kill mee, because my word
hath no place in you.</ab>
<ab n="38">I speake that
which I haue seene with my Father: and ye do that which ye haue
seene with your father.</ab>

<fw>The true children of Abraham.</fw>
<ab n="39">They answered,
and said vnto him, Abraham is our father. Iesus sayth vnto them, If
yee were Abrahams children, ye would doe the works of
Abraham.</ab>
<ab n="40">But now yee
seeke to kill me, a man that hath tolde you the trueth, which I
haue heard of God: this did not Abraham.</ab>
<ab n="41">Ye doe the
deeds of your father. Then said they to him, We be not borne of
fornication, wee haue one Father, euen God.</ab>
<ab n="42">Iesus said
vnto them, If God were your Father, yee would loue me, for I
proceeded foorth, and came from God: neither came I of my selfe,
but he sent me.</ab>
<ab n="43">Why doe yee
not vnderstand my speech? euen because yee cannot heare my
word.</ab>
<ab n="44">Ye are of your
father the deuill, and the lusts of your father ye will doe: hee
was a murtherer from the beginning, and abode not in the trueth,
because there is no truth in him. When he speaketh a lie, he
speaketh of his owne: for he is a liar, and the father of
it.<note> 1.Ioh.3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And because I
tell you the truth, ye beleeue me not.</ab>
<ab n="46">Which of you
conuinceth mee of sinne? And if I say the trueth, why doe ye not
beleeue me?</ab>
<ab n="47">He that is of
God, heareth Gods words: ye therefore heare them not, because ye
are not of God.<note> 1.Ioh.4.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Then answered
the Iewes, and said vnto him, Say wee not well that thou art a
Samaritane, &amp; hast a deuill?</ab>
<ab n="49">Iesus
answered, I haue not a deuill: but I honour my Father, and ye doe
dishonour me.</ab>
<ab n="50">And I seeke
not mine owne glory, there is one that seeketh &amp;
iudgeth.</ab>
<ab n="51">Uerely, verely
I say vnto you, If a man keepe my saying, hee shall neuer see
death.</ab>
<ab n="52">Then said the
Iewes vnto him, Now we know that thou hast a deuill. Abraham is
dead, and the Prophets: and thou sayest, If a man keepe my saying,
he shall neuer taste of death.</ab>
<ab n="53">Art thou
greater then our father Abraham, which is dead? and the Prophets
are dead: whom makest thou thy selfe?</ab>

<fw>The true children of Abraham.</fw>
<ab n="54">Iesus
answered, If I honour myselfe, my honour is nothing: it is my
Father that honoureth me, of whom ye say, that he is your
God:</ab>
<ab n="55">Yet ye haue
not knowen him, but I know him: and if I should say, I know him
not, I shalbe a lyar like vnto you: but I know him, and keepe his
saying.</ab>
<ab n="56">Your father
Abraham reioyced to see my day: and he saw it, &amp; was
glad.</ab>
<ab n="57">Then said the
Iewes vnto him, Thou art not yet fiftie yeeres olde, and hast thou
seene Abraham?</ab>
<ab n="58">Iesus said
vnto them, Uerely, verely I say vnto you, Before Abraham was, I
am.</ab>
<ab n="59">Then tooke
they vp stones to cast at him: but Iesus hidde himselfe, and went
out of the Temple, going thorow the midst of them, and so passed
by.</ab>



</div>