<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Christ talketh with a woman of
Samaria, and reueileth himselfe vnto her. 27 His disciples
marueile. 31 He declareth to them his zeale to Gods glory. 39 Many
Samaritanes beleeue on him. 43 He departeth into Galile, and
healeth the Rulers sonne that lay sicke at Capernaum.</head>

<ab n="1">When therefore
the Lord knew how the Pharisees had heard that Iesus made and
baptized moe disciples then Iohn,</ab>
<ab n="2">(Though Iesus
himselfe baptized not, but his disciples:)</ab>

<fw>Iacobs well.</fw>
<ab n="3">He left Iudea,
and departed againe into Galile.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee must
needs goe thorow Samaria.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then commeth he
to a city of Samaria, which is called Sychar, neere to the parcell
of ground that Iacob gaue to his sonne Ioseph.<note> Gen.33. 12.and 48. 12. iohn. 24.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Now Iacobs Well
was there. Iesus therefore being wearied with his iourney, sate
thus on the Well: and it was about the sixth houre.</ab>
<ab n="7">There commeth a
woman of Samaria to draw water: Iesus sayth vnto her, Giue me to
drinke.</ab>
<ab n="8">For his
disciples were gone away vnto the city to buy meate.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then saith the
woman of Samaria vnto him, How is it that thou, being a Iewe,
askest drinke of me, which am a woman of Samaria? For the Iewes
haue no dealings with the Samaritanes.</ab>
<ab n="10">Iesus
answered, and said vnto her, If thou knewest the gift of God, and
who it is that sayth to thee, Giue me to drinke; thou wouldest haue
asked of him, and hee would haue giuen thee liuing water.</ab>
<ab n="11">The woman
saith vnto him, Sir, thou hast nothing to drawe with, and the Well
is deepe: from whence then hast thou that liuing water?</ab>
<ab n="12">Art thou
greater then our father Iacob, which gaue vs the Well, and dranke
thereof himselfe, and his children, and his cattell?</ab>
<ab n="13">Iesus
answered, and said vnto her, Whosoeuer drinketh of this water,
shall thirst againe:</ab>
<ab n="14">But whosoeuer
drinketh of the water that I shal giue him, shall neuer thirst: but
the water that I shall giue him, shalbe in him a well of water
springing vp into euerlasting life.</ab>
<ab n="15">The woman
saith vnto him, Sir, giue me this water, that I thirst not, neither
come hither to draw.</ab>
<ab n="16">Iesus saith
vnto her, Goe, call thy husband, and come hither.</ab>
<ab n="17">The woman
answered, and said, I haue no husband. Iesus said vnto her, Thou
hast well said, I haue no husband:</ab>
<ab n="18">For thou hast
had fiue husbands, and he whom thou now hast, is not thy husband:
In that saidest thou truely.</ab>
<ab n="19">The woman
saith vnto him, Sir, I perceiue that thou art a Prophet.</ab>

<fw>True worshippers.</fw>
<ab n="20">Our fathers
worshipped in this mountaine, and ye say, that in Hierusalem is the
place where men ought to worship.<note> Deu.12.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Iesus saith
vnto her, Woman, beleeue me, the houre commeth when ye shall
neither in this mountaine, nor yet at Hierusalem, worship the
Father.</ab>
<ab n="22">Ye worship ye
know not what: we know what we worship: for saluation is of the
Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="23">But the houre
commeth, and now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the
Father in spirit, and in trueth: for the Father seeketh such to
worship him.</ab>
<ab n="24">God is a
Spirit, and they that worship him, must worship him in spirit, and
in trueth.<note> 2.Cor.3. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The woman
saith vnto him, I know that Messias commeth, which is called
Christ: when he is come, hee will tell vs all things.</ab>
<ab n="26">Iesus sayth
vnto her, I that speake vnto thee, am hee.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And
vpon this came his disciples, and marueiled that he talked with the
woman: yet no man said, What seekest thou, or, Why talkest thou
with her?</ab>
<ab n="28">The woman then
left her waterpot, and went her way into the city, and sayth to the
men,</ab>
<ab n="29">Come, see a
man, which tolde me all things that euer I did: Is not this the
Christ?</ab>
<ab n="30">Then they went
out of the citie, and came vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ In the
meane while his disciples prayed him, saying, Master, eate.</ab>
<ab n="32">But hee said
vnto them, I haue meate to eate that ye know not of.</ab>
<ab n="33">Therefore said
the disciples one to another, Hath any man brought him ought to
eate?</ab>
<ab n="34">Iesus saith
vnto them, My meat is, to doe the will of him that sent mee, and to
finish his worke.</ab>
<ab n="35">Say not ye,
There are yet foure moneths, and then commeth haruest? Behold, I
say vnto you, Lift vp your eyes, and looke on the fields: for they
are white already to haruest.<note> Mat.9.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And hee that
reapeth receiueth wages, and gathereth fruite vnto life eternall:
that both he that soweth, and he that reapeth, may reioyce
together.</ab>
<ab n="37">And herein is
that saying true: One soweth, and another reapeth.</ab>

<fw>The dead raised.</fw>
<ab n="38">I sent you to
reape that, whereon ye bestowed no labour: other men laboured, and
yee are entred into their labours.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And
many of the Samaritanes of that citie beleeued on him, for the
saying of the woman, which testified, Hee told me all that euer I
did.</ab>
<ab n="40">So when the
Samaritanes were come vnto him, they besought him that he would
tarie with them, and he abode there two dayes.</ab>
<ab n="41">And many moe
beleeued, because of his owne word:</ab>
<ab n="42">And said vnto
the woman, Now we beleeue, not because of thy saying, for we haue
heard him our selues, and know that this is indeed the Christ, the
Sauiour of the world.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ Now
after two dayes he departed thence, and went into
Galilee:<note> Matth. 13 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">For Iesus
himselfe testified, that a Prophet hath no honour in his owne
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then when hee
was come into Galilee, the Galileans receiued him, hauing seene all
the things that hee did at Hierusalem at the Feast: for they also
went vnto the Feast.</ab>
<ab n="46">So Iesus came
againe into Cana of Galilee, where hee made the water wine. And
there was a certaine noble man, whose sonne was sicke at
Capernaum.<note> Chap.2.1. , Or, Courtier, or ruler.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">When he heard
that Iesus was come out of Iudea into Galilee, hee went vnto him,
and besought him that he would come downe, and heale his sonne: for
he was at the point of death.</ab>
<ab n="48">Then said
Iesus vnto him, Except ye see signes and wonders, yee will not
beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="49">The noble man
saith vnto him, Syr, come downe ere my child die.</ab>
<ab n="50">Iesus saith
vnto him, Go thy way, thy sonne liueth. And the man beleeued the
word that Iesus had spoken vnto him, and he went his way.</ab>
<ab n="51">And as he was
now going down, his seruants met him, and told him, saying, Thy
sonne liueth.</ab>
<ab n="52">Then inquired
hee of them the houre when he began to amend: and they said vnto
him, Yesterday at the seuenth houre the feuer left him.</ab>
<ab n="53">So the father
knewe that it was at the same houre, in the which Iesus said vnto
him, Thy sonne liueth, and himselfe beleeued, and his whole
house.</ab>

<fw>The sicke healed.</fw>
<ab n="54">This is againe
the second miracle that Iesus did, when hee was come out of Iudea
into Galilee.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>