<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 The Consolation and mutuall loue
betweene Christ and his members, vnder the parable of the vine. 18
A comfort in the hatred and persecution of the world. 26 The office
of the holy Ghost, and of the Apostles.</head>

<ab n="1">I am the true
vine, and my Father is þe husbandman.</ab>
<ab n="2">Euery branch
in me that beareth not fruit, hee taketh away: and euery branch
that beareth fruit, he purgeth it, that it may bring foorth more
fruit.<note> Mat.15. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now ye are
cleane through the word which I haue spoken vnto you.<note> Iohn.13. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Abide in me,
and in you: As the branch cannot beare fruit of itselfe, except it
abide in the vine: no more can ye, except ye abide in me.</ab>
<ab n="5">I am the vine,
ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same
bringeth forth much fruit: for without me ye can doe
nothing.<note> Or, seuered from me.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">If a man abide
not in me, he is cast forth as a branch, and is withered, and men
gather them, and cast them into the fire, and they are
burned.</ab>
<ab n="7">If ye abide in
me, and my words abide in you, ye shall aske what ye will, and it
shall be done vnto you.</ab>

<fw>Of mutuall loue.</fw>
<ab n="8">Herein is my
Father glorified, that ye beare much fruit, so shall ye bee my
Disciples.</ab>
<ab n="9">As the Father
hath loued me, so haue I loued you: continue ye in my loue.</ab>
<ab n="10">If ye keepe my
Commandements, ye shal abide in my loue, euen as I haue kept my
Fathers Commandements, and abide in his loue.</ab>
<ab n="11">These things haue I
spoken vnto you, that my ioy might remaine in you, and that your
ioy might be full.</ab>
<ab n="12">This is my
Commaundement, that ye loue one another, as I haue loued
you.<note> Chap.13. 34. 1.thes. 4.9. 1.iohn 3.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Greater loue hath
no man then this, that a man lay downe his life for his
friends.</ab>
<ab n="14">Ye are my friends,
if ye do whatsoeuer I command you.</ab>
<ab n="15">Henceforth I call
you not seruants, for the seruant knoweth not what his lord doth,
but I haue called you friends: for all things that I haue heard of
my Father, I haue made knowen vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="16">Ye haue not chosen
me, but I haue chosen you, and ordeined you, that you should goe
and bring foorth fruit, and that your fruite should remaine: that
whatsoeuer ye shall aske of the Father in my Name, he may giue it
you.<note> Mat.28.19</note></ab>
<ab n="17">These things I
commaund you, that ye loue one another.</ab>
<ab n="18">If the world hate
you, yee know that it hated me before it hated you.</ab>
<ab n="19">If ye were of the
world, the world would loue his owne: But because yee are not of
the world, but I haue chosen you out of the world, therfore the
world hateth you.</ab>
<ab n="20">Remember the word
that I said vnto you, The seruant is not greater then the Lord: if
they haue persecuted me, they will also persecute you: if they haue
kept my saying, they will keepe yours also.<note> Chap.13. 16. mat.10. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But all these
things will they doe vnto you for my Names sake, because they know
not him that sent me.</ab>
<ab n="22">If I had not come,
and spoken vnto them, they had not had sinne: but now they haue no
cloke for their sinne.<note> Or, excuse.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">He that hateth me,
hateth my Father also.</ab>

<fw>The Comforter.</fw>
<ab n="24">If I had not done
among thē the works which none other man did, they had not had
sinne: but now haue they both seene, &amp; hated both me &amp; my
father.</ab>
<ab n="25">But this commeth to
passe, that the word might be fulfilled that is written in their
law, They hated me without a cause.<note> Psa.35.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But when the
Comforter is come, whom I wil send vnto you from the Father, euen
the Spirit of trueth, which proceedeth from the Father, hee shall
testifie of me.<note> Chap.14. 26. luke 24 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And ye also shall
beare witnesse, because ye haue bene with me from the
beginning.</ab>



</div>