<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJohn_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/John-Chapter-21-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Christ appearing againe to his
disciples was knowen of them by the great draught of fishes. 12 Hee
dineth with them: 15 earnestly commandeth Peter to feed his Lambes
and sheepe: 18 Foretelleth him of his death: 22 Rebuketh his
curiositie touching Iohn. 25 The conclusion.</head>

<ab n="1">After these
things Iesus shewed himselfe againe to the disciples at the sea of
Tiberias, and on this wise shewed he himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="2">There were
together Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathaneel of
Cana in Galilee, and the sonnes of Zebedee, and two other of his
disciples.</ab>
<ab n="3">Simon Peter
saith vnto them, I goe a fishing. They say vnto him, Wee also goe
with thee. They went foorth and entred into a ship immediatly, and
that night they caught nothing.</ab>

<fw>Draught of fishes.</fw>
<ab n="4">But when the
morning was now come, Iesus stood on the shore: but the disciples
knewe not that it was Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then Iesus
saith vnto them, Children, haue ye any meat? They answered him,
No.<note> Or, Sirs.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he said
vnto them, Cast the net on the right side of the ship, and yee
shall finde. They cast therfore, and now they were not able to draw
it, for the multitude of fishes.</ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore that
Disciple whome Iesus loued, saith vnto Peter, It is the Lord. Now
when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girt his fishers
coate vnto him, (for hee was naked) &amp; did cast himselfe into
the sea.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the other
disciples came in a litle ship (for they were not farre from land,
but as it were two hundred cubites) dragging the net with
fishes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Assoone then
as they were come to land, they saw a fire of coales there, and
fish laid thereon, and bread.</ab>
<ab n="10">Iesus saith vnto
them, Bring of the fish, which ye haue now caught.</ab>
<ab n="11">Simon Peter went
vp, &amp; drewe the net to land full of great fishes, an hundred
and fiftie and three: and for all there were so many, yet was not
the net broken.</ab>
<ab n="12">Iesus saith vnto
them, Come, and dine. And none of the disciples durst aske him, Who
art thou? knowing that it was the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">Iesus then commeth,
and taketh bread, and giueth them, and fish likewise.</ab>
<ab n="14">This is nowe the
third time that Iesus shewed himselfe to his disciples, after that
hee was risen from the dead.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ So when they
had dined, Iesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, sonne of Ionas,
louest thou mee more then these? He saith vnto him, Yea, Lord, thou
knowest that I loue thee. He saith vnto him, Feed my
lambes.</ab>

<fw>Feed my sheepe.</fw>
<ab n="16">He saith to him
againe the second time, Simon sonne of Ionas, louest thou me? He
saith vnto him, Yea Lord, thou knowest that I loue thee. He saith
vnto him, Feed my sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="17">He said vnto him
the third time, Simon sonne of Ionas, louest thou mee? Peter was
grieued, because hee saide vnto him the third time, Louest thou me?
And he said vnto him, Lord, thou knowest all things, thou knowest
that I loue thee. Iesus sayth vnto him, Feed my sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="18">Uerily, verily I
say vnto thee, whē thou wast yong, thou girdedst thy selfe,
and walkedst whither thou wouldest: but when thou shalt be old,
thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee,
and carie thee whither thou wouldest not.</ab>
<ab n="19">This spake hee,
signifying by what death he should glorifie God. And when he had
spoken this, he sayth vnto him, Follow me.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then Peter turning
about, seeth the Disciple whom Iesus loued, following, which also
leaned on his breast at supper, and said, Lord, which is hee that
betraieth thee?<note> Iohn. 13. 23 &amp; 20.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Peter seeing him,
saith to Iesus, Lord, and what shall this man doe?</ab>
<ab n="22">Iesus saith vnto
him, If I will that he tary till I come, what is that to thee?
Follow thou me.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then went this
saying abroad among the brethren, that that Disciple should not
die: yet Iesus sayd not vnto him, He shall not die: but, If I will
that he tary till I come, what is that to thee?</ab>
<ab n="24">This is the
Disciple which testifieth of these things, and wrote these things,
and we know that his testimonie is true.</ab>
<ab n="25">And there are also
many other things which Iesus did, the which if they should be
written euery one, I suppose that euen the world it selfe could not
conteine the bookes that should be written, Amen.<note> Chap. 20. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>