<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJonah_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jonah-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jonah-Chapter-4-4-Micah.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Ionah repining at Gods mercy, 4 is
reprooued by the type of a Gourd.</head>

<ab n="1">But it
displeased Ionah exceedingly, and he was very angry.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he prayed
vnto the Lord, and sayd, I pray thee, O Lord, was not this my
saying, when I was yet in my countrey? Therefore I fledde before
vnto Tarshish: for I knew that thou art a gracious God, and
mercifull, slow to anger, and of great kindnesse, and repentest
thee of the euill.<note> Chap. 1.8. , Exo.34.6. psal.86.5. ioel 2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore now,
O Lord, Take, I beseech thee, my life from me; for it is better for
me to die then to liue.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then
said the Lord, Doest thou well to be angry?<note> Or, art thou greatly angry?</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So Ionah went
out of the citie, and sate on the East side of the city, and there
made him a boothe, and sate vnder it in the shadow, till hee might
see what would become of the citie.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Lord
God prepared a gourd, and made it to come vp ouer Ionah, that it
might be a shadow ouer his head, to deliuer him from his griefe. So
Ionah was exceeding glad of the gourd.<note> Or, palmecrist. Heb. Kikaion. , Heb. reioyced with great ioy.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But God
prepared a worme when the morning rose the next day, and it smote
the gourd that it withered.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came to
passe when the Sunne did arise, that God prepared a vehement East
wind; and the Sunne beat vpon the head of Ionah, that hee fainted,
and wished in himselfe to die, and said, It is better for me to
die, then to liue.<note> Or, silent.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wrath against Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="9">And God said
to Ionah, Doest thou well to be angry for the gourd? and he said, I
doe well to be angry, euen vnto death.<note> Or, art thou greatly angry? , Or, I am greatly angry.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wrath against Idolaters.</fw>
<ab n="10">Then said the Lord,
Thou hast had pitie on the gourde, for the which thou hast not
laboured, neither madest it grow, which came vp in a night, and
perished in a night:<note> Or, spared. , Heb. was the sonne of the night.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And should not I
spare Nineueh that great citie, wherein are more then sixscore
thousand persons, that cannot discerne betweene their right hand
and their left hand, and also much cattell?</ab>



</div>