<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJonah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jonah-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Ionah sent to Nineueh, fleeth to
Tarshish. 4 He is bewrayed by a tempest, 11 throwen into the sea,
17 and swallowed by a fish.</head>

<ab n="1">Now the word
of the Lord came vnto Ionah the sonne of Amittai,
saying,<note> Called, Matth. 12. 39. Ionas.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Arise, goe to
Nineueh that great citie, and cry against it: for their wickednes
is come vp before me.<note> Gene. 10. 11. 12. cha. 3.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But Ionah rose
vp to flee vnto Tarshish, from the presence of the Lord, and went
downe to Ioppa, and he found a ship going to Tarshish: so he payed
the fare thereof, and went downe into it, to goe with them vnto
Tarshish from the presence of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ But the
Lord sent out a great winde into the sea, and there was a mightie
tempest in the sea, so that the ship was like to be
broken.<note> Heb. cast foorth. , Hebr. thought to be broken.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then the
Mariners were afraid, and cried euery man vnto his god, and cast
foorth the wares that were in the ship, into the sea, to lighten it
of them: but Ionah was gone downe into the sides of the ship, and
hee lay, and was fast asleepe.</ab>
<ab n="6">So the
shipmaster came to him, and said vnto him; What meanest thou, O
sleeper? Arise, call vpon thy God, if so be that God wil thinke
vpon vs, that we perish not.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they said
euery one to his fellow; Come, and let vs cast lots, that we may
know for whose cause this euil is vpon vs. So they cast lots, and
the lot fell vpon Ionah.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then said they
vnto him, Tel vs, we pray thee, for whose cause this euill is vpon
vs: What is thine occupation? and whence commest thou? What is thy
countrey? and of what people art thou?</ab>

<fw>By lot, Ionah is cast into the
sea.</fw>
<ab n="9">And hee said
vnto them, I am an Hebrew, and I feare the Lord the God of heauen,
which hath made the sea, and the dry land.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then were the men
exceedingly afraid, and saide vnto him; Why hast thou done this?
(for the men knew that he fled from the presence of the Lord,
because he had told them.)<note> Hebr. with great feare.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Then said
they vnto him, What shall we doe vnto thee, that the sea may be
calme vnto vs? (for the sea wrought and was
tempestuous.)<note> Hebr. may be silent from vs. , Or grew more and more tempestuous. Heb. went.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And he said vnto
them, Take me vp, and cast mee foorth into the sea; so shall the
sea be calme vnto you: for I know that for my sake this great
tempest is vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="13">Neuerthelesse the
men rowed hard to bring it to the land, but they could not: for the
sea wrought, and was tempestuous against them.<note> Hebr. digged.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Wherefore they
cried vnto the Lord, and said, We beseech thee, O Lord, We beseech
thee, let vs not perish for this mans life, and lay not vpon vs,
innocent blood: for thou, O Lord, hast done as it pleased
thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">So they tooke vp
Ionah, and cast him foorth into the sea, and the sea ceased from
her raging.<note> Hebr. flood.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Then the men feared
the Lord exceedingly, and offered a sacrifice vnto the Lord, and
made vowes.<note> Hebr. sacrificed a sacrifice, and vowed vowes.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Now the Lord
had prepared a great fish to swallow vp Ionah, and Ionah was in the
belly of the fish three dayes, and three nights.<note> Matt.12. 40. and 16. 4. luke 11. 30. , Hebr. bowels.</note></ab>



</div>