<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The Canaanites are afraid. 2
Ioshua renueth Circumcision. 10 The Passeouer is kept at Gilgal. 12
Manna ceaseth. 13 An Angel appeareth to Ioshua.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came
to passe when all the Kings of the Amorites which were on the side
of Iordan Westward, and all the Kings of the Canaanites, which were
by the Sea, heard that the Lord had dried vp the waters of Iordan
from before the children of Israel, vntill we were passed ouer,
that their heart melted; neither was there spirit in them any more,
because of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">¶ At
that time the Lord said vnto Ioshua, Make thee sharpe kniues, and
circumcise againe the children of Israel the second
time.<note> Exod.4. 25. , Or, kniues of flints.</note></ab>

<fw>Manna ceaseth.</fw>
<ab n="3">And Ioshua
made him sharpe kniues, and circumcised the children of Israel at
the hill of the foreskinnes.<note> Or, Gibeah-haaraloth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And this is
the cause why Ioshua did circumcise: all the people that came out
of Egypt, that were males, euen all the men of warre, died in the
wildernes by the way after they came out of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now all the
people that came out, were circumcised, but all the people that
were borne in the wildernesse by the way, as they came foorth out
of Egypt, them they had not circumcised.</ab>
<ab n="6">For the
children of Israel walked fourtie yeeres in the wildernesse, till
all the people that were men of warre which came out of Egypt were
consumed, because they obeyed not the voyce of the Lord, vnto whome
the Lord sware that hee would not shew them the land which the Lord
sware vnto their fathers, that he would giue vs, a land that
floweth with milke &amp; honie.<note> Num.14 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And their
children, whom hee raised vp in their stead, them Ioshua
circumcised, for they were vncircumcised: because they had not
circumcised them by the way.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came
to passe when they had done circumcising all the people, that they
abode in their places in the campe, till they were
whole.<note> Heb. when the people had made an end to be circumcised.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the Lord
saide vnto Ioshua, This day haue I rolled away the reproch of Egypt
from off you: Wherefore the name of the place is called Gilgal vnto
this day.<note> i. rolling.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
children of Israel incamped in Gilgal, and kept the Passeouer, on
the fourteenth day of the moneth at euen, in the plaines of
Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they did eate
of the olde corne of the land, on the morrow after the Passeouer,
vnleauened cakes, and parched corne in the selfe same day.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
Manna ceased on the morrow after they had eaten of the old corne of
the land, neither had the children of Israel Manna any more, but
they did eate of the fruit of the land of Canaan that
yeere.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And it came
to passe when Ioshua was by Iericho, that he lift vp his eyes, and
looked, and beholde, there stood a man ouer against him, with his
sword dawen in his hand: and Ioshua went vnto him, and said vnto
him, Art thou for vs, or for our aduersaries?<note> Exod. 23. 23.</note></ab>

<fw>How Iericho is besieged.</fw>
<ab n="14">And he said, Nay,
but as captaine of the hoste of the Lord am I now come. And Ioshua
fell on his face to the earth, and did worship, and said vnto him,
What saith my Lord vnto his seruant?<note> Or, Prince.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the captaine
of the Lords hoste said vnto Ioshua, Loose thy shooe from off thy
foote, for the place whereon thou standest, is holy: And Ioshua did
so.<note> Exod.3.9. acts.7.33.</note></ab>



</div>