<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The first Sabbath. 4 The maner of
the creation. 8 The planting of the garden of Eden, 10 and the
riuer thereof. 17 The tree of knowledge onely forbidden. 19. 20 The
naming of the creatures. 21 The making of woman, and institution of
Mariage.</head>

<ab n="1">Thus the heauens
and the earth were finished, and all the hoste of them.</ab>
<ab n="2">And on the seuenth
day God ended his worke, which hee had made: And he rested on the
seuenth day from all his worke, which he had made.<note> Exod. 20. 11. and 31. 17. deut. 5. 14. Hebr.4. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And God blessed
the seuenth day, and sanctified it: because that in it he had
rested from all his worke, which God created and made.<note> Heb. created to make.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ These are
the generations of the heauens, &amp; of the earth, when they were
created; in the day that the LORD God made the earth, and the
heauens,</ab>
<ab n="5">And euery plant of
the field, before it was in the earth, and euery herbe of the
field, before it grew: for the LORD God had not caused it to raine
vpon the earth, and there was not a man to till the ground.</ab>
<ab n="6">But there went vp
a mist from the earth, and watered the whole face of the
ground.<note> Or, a mist which went vp from &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the LORD God
formed man of the dust of the ground, &amp; breathed into his
nostrils the breath of life; and man became a liuing
soule.<note> Heb. dust of the ground. , 1.Cor.15 47. , 1.Corin. 15.45.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the
LORD God planted a garden Eastward in Eden; and there he put the
man whom he had formed.</ab>
<ab n="9">And out of the
ground made the LORD God to grow euery tree that is pleasant to the
sight, and good for food: the tree of life also in the midst of the
garden, and the tree of knowledge of good and euill.</ab>
<ab n="10">And a riuer went
out of Eden to water the garden, and from thence it was parted, and
became into foure heads.</ab>
<ab n="11">The name of the
first is Pison: that is it which compasseth the whole land of
Hauilah, where there is gold.<note> Ecclus. 24. 29.</note></ab>

<fw>Mariage instituted.</fw>
<ab n="12">And the gold of
that land is good: There is Bdellium and the Onix stone.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the name of
the second riuer is Gihon: the same is it that compasseth the whole
land of Ethiopia.<note> Heb. Cush.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the name of
the third riuer is Hiddekel: that is it which goeth toward the East
of Assyria: and the fourth riuer is Euphrates.<note> Or, Eastward to Assyria.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the LORD God
tooke the man, and put him into the garden of Eden, to dresse it,
and to keepe it.<note> Or, Adam.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the LORD God
commanded the man, saying, Of euery tree of the garden thou mayest
freely eate.<note> Hebr. eating thou shalt eate.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But of the tree
of the knowledge of good and euill, thou shalt not eate of it: for
in the day that thou eatest thereof, thou shalt surely
die.<note> Hebr. dying thou shalt die.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And the
LORD God said, It is not good that the man should be alone: I will
make him an helpe meet for him.<note> Ecclus. 17.5. , Hebr. as before him.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And out of
þ<note/> ground the LORD God formed euery beast of the
field, and euery foule of the aire, and brought them vnto Adam, to
see what he would call them: and whatsoeuer Adam called euery
liuing creature, that was the name thereof.<note> Or, the man.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Adam gaue
names to all cattell, and to the foule of the aire, and to euery
beast of the fielde: but for Adam there was not found an helpe
meete for him.<note> Hebr. called.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the LORD God
caused a deepe sleepe to fall vpon Adam, and hee slept; and he
tooke one of his ribs, and closed vp the flesh in stead
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the rib which
the LORD God had taken from man, made hee a woman, &amp; brought
her vnto the man.<note> Hebr. builded.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Adam said,
This is now bone of my bones, and flesh of my flesh: she shalbe
called woman, because shee was taken out of man.<note> 1.Corin. 11.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Therefore shall a
man leaue his father and his mother, and shall cleaue vnto his
wife: and they shalbe one flesh.<note> Matt. 19 5. mar.10. 7. 1.corin. 6.16. ephe. 5.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And they were
both naked, the man &amp; his wife, and were not ashamed.</ab>



</div>