<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 God incourageth Ioshua. 3 The
stratageme whereby Ai was taken. 29 The king thereof is hanged. 30
Ioshua buildeth an Altar, 32 writeth the Lawe on stones, 33
propoundeth blessings and cursings.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
said vnto Ioshua, Feare not, neither be thou dismaid: take all the
people of warre with thee, and arise, goe vp to Ai: See, I haue
giuen into thy hand the king of Ai, and his people, and his citie,
and his land.<note> Deut.1. 21. &amp; 7.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And thou
shalt doe to Ai and her king, as thou diddest vnto Iericho and her
king: Onely the spoile thereof and the cattell thereof shall ye
take for a pray vnto your selues: lay thee an ambush for the citie,
behind it.<note> Chap.6.21 , Deut.20 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ So
Ioshua arose, and all the people of warre, to goe vp against Ai:
and Ioshua chose out thirtie thousand mighty men of valour, and
sent them away by night:</ab>
<ab n="4">And he
commanded them, saying, Behold, ye shall lie in wait against the
citie, euen behind the citie: goe not very farre from the citie,
but be ye all ready:</ab>
<ab n="5">And I, and
all the people that are with mee, will approch vnto the citie: and
it shall come to passe when they come out against vs, as at the
first, that we will flee before them,</ab>

<fw>Ai is besieged, and set on
fire.</fw>
<ab n="6">(For they
will come out after vs) till we haue drawen them from the citie;
for they will say, They flee before vs, as at the first: therefore
we will flee before them.<note> Hebr. pulled.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then yee
shall rise vp from the ambush, and seise vpon the citie: for the
Lord your God will deliuer it into your hand.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it shall
be when yee haue taken the citie, that ye shall set the citie on
fire: according to the commandement of the Lord shall ye do. See, I
haue commanded you.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Ioshua
therefore sent them foorth, and they went to lie in ambush, and
abode betweene Bethel and Ai, on the West side of Ai: but Ioshua
lodged that night among the people.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Ioshua rose vp
early in the morning, and numbred the people, and went vp; he, and
the Elders of Israel, before the people to Ai.</ab>
<ab n="11">And all the
people, euen the people of warre that were with him, went vp, and
drew nigh, and came before the city, and pitched on the North side
of Ai: now there was a valley betweene them and Ai.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he tooke about
fiue thousand men, and set them to lye in ambush betweene Bethel
and Ai, on the West side of the citie.<note> Or, of Ai.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And when they had
set the people, euen all the hoste that was on the North of the
city, and their liers in wait on the West of the citie: Ioshua went
that night into the midst of the valley.<note> Hebr. their lying in wait.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And it came
to passe when the King of Ai saw it, that they hasted, and rose vp
early, and the men of the citie went out against Israel to battell,
hee, and all his people, at a time appointed, before the plaine,
but hee wist not that there were liers in ambush against him behind
the city.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Ioshua and all
Israel made as if they were beaten before them, and fled by the way
of the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="16">And all the people
that were in Ai, were called together to pursue after them: and
they pursued after Ioshua, and were drawen away from the
city.</ab>
<ab n="17">And there was not
a man left in Ai or Bethel, that went not out after Israel: and
they left the citie open, and pursued after Israel.</ab>

<fw>Ai is besieged, and set on
fire.</fw>
<ab n="18">And the Lord said
vnto Ioshua, Stretch out the speare that is in thy hand, toward Ai;
for I will giue it into thine hand. And Ioshua stretched out the
speare that hee had in his hand, toward the city.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the ambush
arose quickly out of their place, and they ranne as soone as he had
stretched out his hand: and they entred into the city, and tooke
it, and hasted, and set the citie on fire.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when the men
of Ai looked behind them, they saw, and behold, the smoke of the
city ascended vp to heauen, and they had no power to flee this way
or that way: and the people that fled to the wildernesse, turned
backe vpon the pursuers.<note> Heb. hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And when Ioshua
and all Israel saw that the ambush had taken the city, and that the
smoke of the city ascended, then they turned againe and slew the
men of Ai.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the other
issued out of the citie against them, so they were in the midst of
Israel; some on this side, and some on that side, and they smote
them; so that they let none of them remaine or escape.<note> Deut.7 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the King of Ai
they tooke aliue, and brought him to Ioshua.</ab>
<ab n="24">And it came to
passe when Israel had made an end of slaying all the inhabitants of
Ai, in the field, in the wildernesse wherein they chased them, and
when they were all fallen on the edge of the sword, vntill they
were consumed, that all the Israelites returned vnto Ai, and smote
it with the edge of the sword.</ab>
<ab n="25">And so it was that
all that fell that day, both of men and women, were twelue
thousand, euen all the men of Ai.</ab>
<ab n="26">For Ioshua drew
not his hand backe wherewith hee stretched out the speare, vntill
he had vtterly destroyed all the inhabitants of Ai.</ab>
<ab n="27">Onely the cattell,
and the spoile of that city Israel tooke for a pray vnto
themselues, according vnto the word of the Lord, which he
commaunded Ioshua.<note> Num.31. 22, 26. , Verse 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And Ioshua burnt
Ai, and made it an heape for euer, euen a desolation vnto this
day.</ab>

<fw>The law read.</fw>
<ab n="29">And the king of Ai
he hanged on a tree vntil euentide: and assoone as the sunne was
downe, Ioshua commaunded that they should take his carkeise downe
from the tree, and cast it at the entring of the gate of the citie,
and raise thereon a great heape of stones that remaineth vnto this
day.<note> Chap.7. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Then Ioshua
built an Altar vnto the Lord God of Israel in mount Ebal,</ab>
<ab n="31">As Moses the
seruant of the Lord commaunded the children of Israel, as it is
written in the booke of the Law of Moses, an Altar of whole stones,
ouer which no man hath lift vp any yron: and they offred theron
burnt offerings vnto the Lord, and sacrificed peace
offerings.<note> Exod. 20. 25. deut. 27.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And he
wrote there vpon the stones a copie of the Lawe of Moses, which hee
wrote in the presence of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="33">And all Israel,
and their Elders, and Officers, and their Iudges, stood on this
side the Arke, and on that side, before the Priests the Leuites,
which bare the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord, aswell the
stranger, as he that was borne among them: halfe of them ouer
against mount Gerizim, and halfe of them ouer against mount Ebal,
as Moses the seruant of the Lord had commanded before, that they
should blesse the people of Israel.<note> Deut. 11. 29. &amp; 27.12</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And afterward hee
read all the words of the Law, the blessings and cursings,
according to all that is written in the booke of the Law.</ab>
<ab n="35">There was not a
word of all that Moses commanded, which Ioshua read not before all
the Congregation of Israel, with the women and the litle ones, and
the strangers that were conuersant among them.<note> Deut. 31. 12. , Hebr. walked.</note></ab>



</div>