<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Ioshua commeth to Iordan. 2 The
Officers instruct the people for the passage. 7 TheLord incourageth
Ioshua. 9 Ioshua incourageth the people. 14 The waters of Iordan
are diuided.</head>


<fw>The Arke borne.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Ioshua
rose early in the morning, and they remooued from Shittim, and came
to Iordan, hee and all the children of Israel, and lodged there
before they passed ouer.</ab>
<ab n="2">And it came
to passe after three dayes, that the Officers went thorow the
hoste;</ab>
<ab n="3">And they
commanded the people, saying, When ye see the Arke of the Couenant
of the Lord your God, and the Priests the Leuites bearing it, then
yee shall remooue from your place, and goe after it.</ab>
<ab n="4">Yet there
shalbe a space betweene you and it, about two thousand cubites by
measure: come not neere vnto it, that ye may know the way by which
ye must goe: for yee haue not passed this way
heretofore.<note> Hebr. since yesterday &amp; the third day.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Ioshua
said vnto the people, Sanctifie your selues: for to morrow the Lord
wil do wōders among you.<note> Leuit. 20.7. num.11. 18. chap. 7. 13. 1.sam. 16.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Ioshua
spake vnto the Priests, saying, Take vp the Arke of the Couenant,
and passe ouer before the people. And they tooke vp the Arke of the
Couenant, and went before the people.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
the Lord saide vnto Ioshua, This day wil I begin to magnifie thee
in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that as I was with
Moses, so I will be with thee.<note> Chap.1. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And thou
shalt commaund the Priests that beare the Arke of the Couenant,
saying; When ye are come to the brinke of the water of Iordan, yee
shall stand still in Iordan.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Ioshua said vnto the children of Israel, Come hither, and heare the
words of the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Ioshua said,
Hereby ye shall know that the liuing God is among you, and that he
will without faile driue out from before you the Canaanites, and
the Hittites, and the Hiuites, and the Perizzites, and Girgashites,
and the Amorites, and the Iebusites.</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, the Arke
of the Couenant, euen the Lord of all the earth, passeth ouer
before you, into Iordan.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now therefore take
yee twelue men out of the Tribes of Israel, out of euery Tribe a
man.</ab>

<fw>Iordan is dried vp.</fw>
<ab n="13">And it shall come
to passe, assoone as the soles of the feete of the Priestes that
beare the Arke of the Lord, the Lord of all the earth, shall rest
in the waters of Iordan, that the waters of Iordan shall be cut
off, from the waters that come downe from aboue: and they shall
stand vpon an heape.<note> Psal. 114. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And it came
to passe when the people remooued from their tents, to passe ouer
Iordan, and the Priests bearing the Arke of the Couenant before the
people;<note> Acts 7.45.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And as they that
bare the Arke were come vnto Iordan, and the feet of the Priestes
that bare the Arke, were dipped in the brimme of the water, (for
Iordan ouerfloweth all his banks at the time of
haruest)<note> 1. Chron. 12.15. ecclus. 24.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">That the waters
which came downe from aboue, stood and rose vp vpon an heape very
farre, from the city Adam, that is beside Zaretan: and those that
came downe toward the sea of the plaine, euen the salt sea, failed,
and were cut off: and the people passed ouer right against
Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Priestes
that bare the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord, stood firme on drie
ground, in the midst of Iordan, and all the Israelites passed ouer
on drie ground, vntill all the people were passed cleane ouer
Iordan.</ab>



</div>