<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-22-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 The two Tribes and halfe with a
blessing are sent home. 9 They build the Altar of Testimony, in
their iourney. 11 The Israelites are offended thereat. 21 They giue
them good satisfaction.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Ioshua called
the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the halfe tribe of
Manasseh,</ab>
<ab n="2">And said vnto
them, Yee haue kept all that Moses the seruant of the Lord
commanded you, and haue obeyed my voyce in all that I commanded
you.</ab>

<fw>Reubens &amp;c. altar.</fw>
<ab n="3">Yee haue not left
your brethren these many dayes vnto this day, but haue kept the
charge of the commandement of the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="4">And now the Lord
your God hath giuen rest vnto your brethren, as hee promised them:
therefore now returne yee, and get yee vnto your tents, and vnto
the land of your possession, which Moses the seruant of the Lord
gaue you on the other side Iordane.<note> Num.32. 33. chap.13.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But take diligent
heed, to doe the Commandement and the Law, which Moses the seruant
of the Lord charged you, to loue the Lord your God, and to walke in
all his wayes, and to keepe his Commaundements, and to cleaue vnto
him, and to serue him with all your heart, and with all your
soule.<note> Deut.10. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">So Ioshua blessed
them, and sent them away: and they went vnto their tents.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Now to the
one halfe of the tribe of Manasseh Moses had giuen possession in
Bashan: but vnto the other halfe therof gaue Ioshua among their
brethren on this side Iordane Westward. And when Ioshua sent them
away also vnto their tents, then hee blessed them,</ab>
<ab n="8">And he spake vnto
them, saying; Returne with much riches vnto your tents, and with
very much cattell, with siluer and with gold, and with brasse, and
with iron, and with very much raiment: Diuide the spoile of your
enemies with your brethren.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and the halfe tribe of
Manasseh returned, and departed from the children of Israel out of
Shiloh which is in the land of Canaan, to goe vnto the countrey of
Gilead, to the land of their possession, whereof they were
possessed, according to the word of the Lord by the hand of
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And when
they came vnto the borders of Iordan, that are in the land of
Canaan, the children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and the
halfe tribe of Manasseh built there an altar by Iordan, a great
altar to see to.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
children of Israel heard say, Behold, the children of Reuben, and
the children of Gad, and the halfe tribe of Manasseh, haue built an
altar ouer against the land of Canaan, in the borders of Iordan, at
the passage of the children of Israel.</ab>

<fw>Being reproued, they make
answere.</fw>
<ab n="12">And when the
children of Israel heard of it, the whole Congregation of the
children of Israel gathered themselues together at Shiloh, to goe
vp to warre against them.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the children
of Israel sent vnto the children of Reuben, and to the children of
Gad, and to the halfe tribe of Manasseh into the lande of Gilead,
Phinehas son of Eleazar the Priest,</ab>
<ab n="14">And with him ten
princes, of ech chiefe house a prince, throughout all the tribes of
Israel, and each one was an head of the house of their fathers,
among the thousands of Israel.<note> Heb. house of the father.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And they
came vnto the children of Reuben, and to the children of Gad, and
to the halfe tribe of Manasseh vnto the land of Gilead, and they
spake with them, saying,</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus saith the
whole Congregation of the Lord, What trespasse is this that ye haue
committed against the God of Israel, to turne away this day from
following the Lord, in that ye haue builded you an altar, that yee
might rebell this day against the Lord ?</ab>
<ab n="17">Is the iniquitie
of Peor too litle for vs, from which we are not cleansed vntil this
day, (although there was a plague in the Congregation of the Lord
)<note> Num. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">But that ye must
turne away this day from following the Lord ? And it will be,
seeing yee rebell to day against the Lord, that to morrow he will
be wroth with the whole Congregation of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="19">Notwithstanding,
if the lande of your possession be vncleane, then passe yee ouer
vnto the land of the possession of the Lord, wherein the Lords
Tabernacle dwelleth, and take possession among vs: but rebell not
against the Lord, nor rebell against vs, in building you an altar,
beside the Altar of the Lord our God.</ab>
<ab n="20">Did not Achan the
sonne of Zerah commit a trespasse in the accursed thing, and wrath
fell on all the Congregation of Israel? and that man perished not
alone in his iniquitie.<note> Chap. 7. 1,5.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then the
children of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and the halfe tribe of
Manasseh, answered and saide vnto the heads of the thousands of
Israel,</ab>

<fw>Being reproued, they make
answere.</fw>
<ab n="22">The Lord God of
gods, the Lord God of gods, hee knoweth, and Israel he shall know;
if it bee in rebellion, or if in transgression against the Lord,
(saue vs not this day,)</ab>
<ab n="23">That wee haue
built vs an altar to turne from following the Lord, or if to offer
thereon burnt offering, or meat offering, or if to offer peace
offerings thereon, let the Lord himselfe require it;</ab>
<ab n="24">And if we haue
not rather done it for feare of this thing, saying, In time to come
your children might speake vnto our children, saying, What haue you
to doe with the Lord God of Israel?<note> Hebr. to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For the Lord hath
made Iordan a border betweene vs and you, yee children of Reuben,
and children of Gad, yee haue no part in the Lord: so shal your
children make our children cease from fearing the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore we
said, Let vs now prepare to build vs an altar, not for burnt
offering, nor for sacrifice,</ab>
<ab n="27">But that it may
bee a witnesse betweene vs and you, and our generations after vs,
that we might do the seruice of the Lord before him with our burnt
offrings, and with our sacrifices, and with our peace offerings,
that your children may not say to our children in time to come, Ye
haue no part in the Lord.<note> Gen. 31. 48. chap. 24 27. ver. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore said
we, that it shalbe, when they should so say to vs, or to our
generations in time to come, that wee may say againe, Beholde the
paterne of the altar of the Lord, which our fathers made, not for
burnt offrings, nor for sacrifices, but it is a witnes betweene vs
and you.</ab>
<ab n="29">God forbid that
we should rebell against the Lord, and turne this day from
following the Lord, to build an altar for burnt offerings, for
meate offerings, or for sacrifices, besides the Altar of the Lord
our God that is before his Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And when
Phinehas the Priest and the Princes of the Congregation, and Heads
of the thousands of Israel which were with him, heard the words
that the children of Reuben and the children of Gad, and the
children of Manasseh spake, it pleased them.<note> Hebr. it was good in their eyes.</note></ab>

<fw>Exhortations to the loue of
God.</fw>
<ab n="31">And Phinehas the
sonne of Eleazar the Priest said vnto the children of Reuben, and
to the children of Gad, and to the children of Manasseh, This day
we perceiue that the Lord is among vs, because ye haue not
committed this trespasse against the Lord: now ye haue deliuered
the children of Israel out of the hand of the Lord.<note> Hebr. Then.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And
Phinehas the sonne of Eleazar the Priest, and the Princes, returned
from the children of Reuben, and from the children of Gad, out of
the land of Gilead, vnto the land of Canaan, to the children of
Israel, &amp; brought them word againe.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the thing
pleased the children of Israel, and the children of Israel blessed
God, and did not intend to goe vp against them in battel, to
destroy the land wherein the children of Reuben and Gad
dwelt.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the children
of Reuben, and the children of Gad called the altar Ed: for it
shall bee a witnesse betweene vs, that the Lord is God.<note> That is, a witnesse.</note></ab>



</div>