<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-15-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 The lot of Manasseh. 8 His coast.
12 The Canaanites not driuen out. 14 The children of Ioseph obtaine
another lot.</head>

<ab n="1">There was also a
lot for the tribe of Manasseh; ( for hee was the first borne of
Ioseph) to wit, for Machir the first borne of Manasseh the father
of Gilead: because he was a man of warre, therefore hee had Gilead
and Bashan.<note> Gene.41 51. and 46 20. and 50. 23. num. 32.39.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">There was also a
lot for the rest of the children of Manasseh by their families; for
the children of Abiezer, and for the children of Helek, and for the
children of Asriel, and for the children of Shechem, and for the
children of Hepher, and for the children of Shemida: these were the
male children of Manasseh, the sonne of Ioseph by their
families.<note> Num.26. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ But
Zelophehad the sonne of Hepher, the sonne of Gilead, the sonne of
Machir, the sonne of Manasseh, had no sonnes but daughters: And
these are the names of his daughters, Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah,
Milcah, and Tirzah.<note> Num.26. 33. and 27 1. and 36.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And they came
neere before Eleazar the Priest, and before Ioshua the sonne of
Nun, and before the Princes, saying, The Lord commanded Moses to
giue vs an inheritance among our brethren: therefore according to
the commaundement of the Lord, hee gaue them an inheritance among
the brethren of their father.</ab>
<ab n="5">And there fel ten
portions to Manasseh, beside the land of Gilead and Bashan, which
were on the other side Iordan;</ab>
<ab n="6">Because the
daughters of Manasseh had an inheritance among his sonnes: and the
rest of Manassehs sonnes had the land of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And the
coast of Manasseh was from Asher to Michmethah, that lieth before
Shechem, and the border went along on the right hand, vnto the
inhabitants of Entappuah.</ab>

<fw>Their cities.</fw>
<ab n="8">Now Manasseh had
the land of Tappuah: but Tappuah on the border of Manasseh belonged
to the children of Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the coast
descended vnto the riuer Kanah, Southward of the riuer: these
cities of Ephraim are among the cities of Manasseh: the coast of
Manasseh also was on the North side of the riuer, and the outgoings
of it were at the Sea.<note> Or, brooke of reeds.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Southward it was
Ephraims, and Northward it was Manassehs, and the sea is his
border, and they met together in Asher on the North, and in
Issachar on the East.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Manasseh had
in Issachar and in Asher, Bethshean &amp; her townes, and Ibleam
and her townes, and the inhabitants of Dor and her townes, and the
inhabitants of Endor and her townes, and the inhabitants of Taanach
and her townes, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and her townes, euen
three countreyes.</ab>
<ab n="12">Yet the children
of Manasseh could not driue out the inhabitants of those cities,
but the Canaanites would dwell in that land.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yet it came to
passe when the children of Israel were waxen strong, that they put
the Canaanites to tribute: but did not vtterly driue them
out.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the children
of Ioseph spake vnto Ioshua, saying, Why hast thou giuen me but one
lot and one portion to inherit, seeing I am a great people,
forasmuch as the Lord hath blessed me hitherto?</ab>
<ab n="15">And Ioshua
answered them, If thou be a great people, then get thee vp to the
wood countrey, and cut downe for thy selfe there in the land of the
Perizzites, and of the giants, if mount Ephraim be too narrow for
thee.<note> Or Rephaims.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the children
of Ioseph saide, The hill is not enough for vs: and all the
Canaanites that dwell in the lande of the valley, haue charets of
yron, both they who are of Bethshean and her townes, and they who
are of the valley of Iezreel.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Ioshua spake
vnto the house of Ioseph, euen to Ephraim, and to Manasseh, saying,
Thou art a great people, and hast great power: Thou shalt not haue
one lot onely.</ab>

<fw>The Tabernacle.</fw>
<ab n="18">But the mountaine
shalbe thine, for it is a wood, and thou shalt cut it downe: and
the outgoings of it shalbe thine: for thou shalt driue out the
Canaanites, though they haue yron charets, and though they be
strong.</ab>



</div>