<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 The lot of Simeon, 10 Of Zebulun,
17 Of Issachar, 24 Of Asher, 32 Of Naphtali, 40 Of Dan. 46 The
children of Israel giue an inheritance to Ioshua.</head>

<ab n="1">And the second lot
came foorth to Simeon, euen for the tribe of the children of Simeon
according to their families: and their inheritance was within the
inheritance of the children of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="2">And they had in
their inheritance Beer-sheba, or Sheba, and Moladah,</ab>
<ab n="3">And Hazarshual,
and Balah, and Azem,</ab>
<ab n="4">And Eltolad, and
Bethul, and Hormah,</ab>
<ab n="5">And Ziklag, and
Beth-marcaboth, and Hazar-susah,</ab>
<ab n="6">And Beth-lebaoth,
and Sharuhen: thirteene cities and their villages.</ab>
<ab n="7">Ain, Remmon, and
Ether, and Ashan: foure cities and their villages,</ab>
<ab n="8">And all the
villages that were round about these cities, to Baalath-Beer,
Ramath of the South: This is the inheritance of the tribe of the
children of Simeon according to their families.</ab>

<fw>Zebuluns, Ashers, Naphtalis
portion.</fw>
<ab n="9">Out of the portion
of the children of Iudah was the inheritance of the children of
Simeon: for the part of the children of Iudah was too much for
them: therefore the children of Simeon had their inheritance within
the inheritance of them.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
third lot came vp for the children of Zebulun, according to their
families: and the border of their inheritance was vnto
Sarid.</ab>
<ab n="11">And their border
went vp toward the Sea, and Maralah, and reached to Dabbasheth, and
reached to the riuer that is before Iokneam,</ab>
<ab n="12">And turned from
Sarid Eastward, toward the Sunne rising, vnto the border of
Chisloth Tabor, and then goeth out to Daberath, and goeth vp to
Iaphia,</ab>
<ab n="13">And from thence
passeth on along on the East to Gittah-Hepher, to Ittah-Kazin, and
goeth out to Remmon Methoar to Neah.<note> Or, which is drawen.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the border
compasseth it on the North side to Hannathon: and the outgoings
thereof are in the valley of Iiphthah-el.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Kattath, and
Nahallal, and Shimron, and Idalah, and Bethlehem: twelue cities
with their villages.</ab>
<ab n="16">This is the
inheritance of the children of Zebulun according to their families,
these cities with their villages.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
fourth lot came out to Issachar for the children of Issachar
according to their families.</ab>
<ab n="18">And their border
was toward Izreel, and Chesulloth, and Shunem,</ab>
<ab n="19">And Hapharaim,
and Shion, and Anaharath,</ab>
<ab n="20">And Rabbith, and
Kishion, and Abez,</ab>
<ab n="21">And Remeth, and
Engannim, and Enhaddah, and Bethpazzez.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the coast
reacheth to Tabor, and Shahazimath, and Bethshemesh, and the
outgoings of their border were at Iordan, sixteene cities with
their villages.</ab>
<ab n="23">This is the
inheritance of the tribe of the children of Issachar according to
their families, the cities, and their villages.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
fift lot came out for the tribe of the children of Asher according
to their families.</ab>
<ab n="25">And their border
was Helkath, and Hali, and Beten, and Achshaph,</ab>

<fw>Zebuluns, Ashers, Naphtalis
portion.</fw>
<ab n="26">And Alammelech,
and Amad, and Misheal, and reacheth to Carmel westward, and to
Shihor-Libnath,</ab>
<ab n="27">And turneth
toward the Sunne rising to Beth-dagon, and reacheth to Zebulun, and
to the valley of of Iiphthahel toward the Northside of Bethemek,
and Neiel, and goeth out to Cabul on the left hand,</ab>
<ab n="28">And Hebron, and
Rehob, and Hammon, and Kanah, euen vnto great Zidon:</ab>
<ab n="29">And then the
coast turneth to Ramah, and to the strong citie Tyre, and the coast
turneth to Hosah: and the outgoings thereof are at the Sea from the
coast to Achzib.<note> Heb. Tzor.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Ummah also, and
Aphek, and Rehob: twentie and two cities with their
villages.</ab>
<ab n="31">This is the
inheritance of the tribe of the children of Asher according to
their families, these cities with their villages.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ The sixt
lot came out to the children of Naphtali: euen for the children of
Naphtali according to their families.</ab>
<ab n="33">And their coast
was from Heleph, from Allon to Zaanannim, and Adami, Nekeb, and
Iabneel vnto Lakum: and the outgoings thereof were at
Iordan.</ab>
<ab n="34">And then the
coast turneth westward to Aznoth-Tabor, and goeth out from thence
to Hukkok, and reacheth to Zebulun on the Southside, and reacheth
to Asher on the Westside, and to Iudah vpon Iordan toward the Sun
rising.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the fenced
cities are Ziddim, Zer, and Hammath, Rakkath, and
Cinnereth,</ab>
<ab n="36">And Adamah, and
Ramah, and Hazor,</ab>
<ab n="37">And Kedesh, and
Edrei, and Enhazor,</ab>
<ab n="38">And Iron, and
Migdal-el, Horem, and Bethanah, and Bethshemesh, nineteene cities
with their villages.</ab>
<ab n="39">This is the
inheritance of the tribe of the children of Naphtali according to
their families, the cities and their villages.</ab>
<ab n="40">¶ And the
seuenth lot came out for the tribe of the children of Dan according
to their families:</ab>
<ab n="41">And the coast of
their inheritance was Zorah, and Eshtaol, and Irshemesh,</ab>

<fw>Dans portion.</fw>
<ab n="42">And Shaalabbin,
and Aiialon, and Iethlah,</ab>
<ab n="43">And Elon, and
Thimnathah, and Ekron,</ab>
<ab n="44">And Eltekeh, and
Gibbethon, and Baalah,</ab>
<ab n="45">And Iehud, and
Bene-berak, and Gath-rimmon,</ab>
<ab n="46">And Meiarkon, and
Rakkon, with the border before Iapho.<note> Or, ouer against. , Or, Ioppa, Acts.9.36.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And the coast of
the children of Dan went out too little for them: therefore the
children of Dan went vp to fight against Leshem, and tooke it, and
smote it with the edge of the sword, and possessed it, and dwelt
therein, and called Leshem, Dan, after the name of Dan their
father.<note> Iudg.18. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">This is the
inheritance of the tribe of the children of Dan according to their
families, these cities with their villages.</ab>
<ab n="49">¶ When they
had made an end of diuiding the land for inheritance by their
coasts, the children of Israel gaue an inheritance to Ioshua the
sonne of Nun among them:</ab>
<ab n="50">According to the
word of the Lord, they gaue him the citie which he asked, euen
Timnath-Serah in mount Ephraim: and he built the citie, and dwelt
therein.<note> Chap.24. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">These are the
inheritances which Eleazar the Priest, and Ioshua the sonne of Nun,
and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of
Israel, diuided for an inheritance by lot, in Shiloh before the
Lord, at the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation: so they
made an end of diuiding the countrey.<note> Num.34. 17.</note></ab>



</div>