<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Diuers Kings ouercome at the
waters of Merom. 10 Hazor is taken and burnt. 16 All the countrey
taken by Ioshua. 21 The Anakims cut off.</head>


<fw>Ioshua conquereth diuers kings.</fw>
<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when Iabin king of Hazor had heard those things, that hee
sent to Iobab king of Madon, and to the king of Shimron, &amp; to
the king of Achshaph,</ab>
<ab n="2">And to the kings
that were on the North of the mountaines, and of the plaines South
of Cinneroth, and in the valley, and in the borders of Dor, on the
West;</ab>
<ab n="3">And to the
Canaanite on the East and on the West, and to the Amorite, and the
Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Iebusite in the mountaines, and
to the Hiuite vnder Hermon in the land of Mizpeh.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they went out,
they and all their hostes with them, much people, euen as the sand
that is vpon the Seashore in multitude, with horses and charets
very many.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when all these
Kings were met together, they came and pitched together at the
waters of Merom, to fight against Israel.<note> Hebr. assembled by appointment.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Ioshua, Be not afraid because of them: for to
morrow about this time will I deliuer them vp al slaine before
Israel: thou shalt hough their horses, and burne their charets with
fire.</ab>
<ab n="7">So Ioshua came,
and all the people of warre with him, against them by the waters of
Merom suddenly, and they fell vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the Lord
deliuered them into the hand of Israel, who smote them, and chased
them vnto great Zidon, and vnto Misrephothmaim, and vnto the valley
of Mizpeh Eastward, and they smote them, vntill they left them none
remayning.<note> Or, Zidon-Rabbah. , Or, salt pits: Hebr. burning of waters.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Ioshua did
vnto them as the Lord bade him: hee houghed their horses, and burnt
their charets with fire.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And Ioshua
at that time turned backe, and tooke Hazor, and smote the king
thereof with the sword: for Hazor beforetime was the head of all
those kingdomes.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they smote
all the soules that were therein with the edge of the sword,
vtterly destroying them: there was not any left to breathe; and he
burnt Hazor with fire.<note> Hebr. any breath.</note></ab>

<fw>Diuers conquests made by
Ioshua.</fw>
<ab n="12">And all the
cities of those kings, and all the kings of them, did Ioshua take,
and smote them with the edge of the sword, and he vtterly destroied
them, as Moses the seruant of the Lord commanded.<note> Num.33. 52. deut. 7. 2. and 20, 16,17.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But as for the
cities that stood still in their strength, Israel burned none of
them, saue Hazor onely; that did Ioshua burne.<note> Hebr. on their heape.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And all the
spoile of these cities, and the cattell, the children of Israel
tooke for a pray vnto themselues: but euery man they smote with the
edge of the sword, vntill they had destroyed them, neither left
they any to breathe.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ As the
Lord commanded Moses his seruant, so did Moses command Ioshua, and
so did Ioshua: hee left nothing vndone of all that the Lord
commanded Moses.<note> Exod.34. 11. , Deut. 7.2 , Heb. he remoued nothing.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">So Ioshua tooke
all that land, the hilles, and all the South countrey, and all the
land of Goshen, and the valley, and the plaine, and the mountaine
of Israel, and the valley of the same:</ab>
<ab n="17">Euen from the
mount Halak, that goeth vp to Seir, vnto Baal-Gad, in the valley of
Lebanon, vnder mount Hermon: and all their kings he tooke, and
smote them, and slew them.<note> Or, the smoothe mountaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Ioshua made warre
a long time, with all those kings.</ab>
<ab n="19">There was not a
citie that made peace with the children of Israel, saue the Hiuites
the inhabitants of Gibeon; all other they tooke in
battell.<note> Chap.9.3</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For it was of the
Lord to harden their hearts, that they should come against Israel
in battell, that he might destroy them vtterly, &amp; that they
might haue no fauour: but that hee might destroy them, as the Lord
commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And at
that time came Ioshua and cut off the Anakims from the mountaines,
from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, and from all the mountaines of
Iudah, and from all the mountaines of Israel: Ioshua destroyed them
vtterly with their cities.</ab>
<ab n="22">There was none of
the Anakims left in the land of the children of Israel: onely in
Gaza, in Gath, and in Ashdod, there remained.</ab>

<fw>Diuers conquests made by
Ioshua.</fw>
<ab n="23">So Ioshua tooke
the whole land according to all that the Lord saide vnto Moses, and
Ioshua gaue it for an inheritance vnto Israel, according to their
diuisions by their tribes: and the land rested from
warre.<note> Numb.26 53.</note></ab>



</div>