<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-15-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The generall borders of the sonnes
of Ioseph. 5 The border of the inheritance of Ephraim. 10 The
Canaanites not conquered.</head>

<ab n="1">And the lot of the
children of Ioseph fell from Iordan by Iericho, vnto the water of
Iericho on the East, to the wildernesse that goeth vp from Iericho
throughout mount Bethel;<note> Hebr. went foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And goeth out from
Bethel to Luz, and passeth along vnto the borders of Archi, to
Ataroth,<note> Iudg.1. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And goeth downe
Westward, to the coast of Iaphleti, vnto the coast of Bethoron the
nether, and to Gezer: and the goings out thereof are at the
Sea.</ab>
<ab n="4">So the children of
Ioseph, Manasseh, and Ephraim, tooke their inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
border of the children of Ephraim according to their families, was
thus: euen the border of their inheritance on the East side was
Ataroth-Addar, vnto Bethoron the vpper.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the border
went out toward the Sea, to Michmethah on the Northside, and the
border went about Eastward vnto Taanath Shiloh, and passed by it on
the East to Ianohah:</ab>
<ab n="7">And it went downe
from Ianohah to Ataroth and to Naarath, and came to Iericho, and
went out at Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="8">The border went
out from Tappuah Westward vnto the riuer Kanah: and the goings out
thereof were at the Sea. This is the inheritance of the tribe of
the children of Ephraim by their families.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the separate
cities for the children of Ephraim were among the inheritance of
the children of Manasseh, all the cities with their
villages.</ab>

<fw>Manassehs lot.</fw>
<ab n="10">And they draue
not out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gezer: but the Canaanites
dwell among the Ephramites vnto this day, and serue vnder
tribute.</ab>



</div>