<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Twelue men are appointed to take
twelue stones for a memoriall out of Iordan. 9 Twelue other stones
are set vp in the middest of Iordan. 10. 19 The people passe ouer.
14 God magnifieth Ioshua. 20 The twelue stones are pitched in
Gilgal.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came
to passe when all the people were cleane passed ouer Iordan, that
the Lord spake vnto Ioshua, saying,<note> Deut. 27. 2. , Chap.3. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Take you
twelue men out of the people, out of euery tribe a man,</ab>
<ab n="3">And command
you them, saying, Take you hence out of the mids of Iordan, out of
the place where the Priests feet stood firme, twelue stones, and
yee shal cary them ouer with you, and leaue them in the lodging
place where you shall lodge this night.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then Ioshua
called the twelue men, whom he had prepared of the children of
Israel, out of euery tribe a man:</ab>

<fw>Twelue stones.</fw>
<ab n="5">And Ioshua
said vnto them, Passe ouer before the Arke of the Lord your God
into the mids of Iordan, and take ye vp euery man of you a stone
vpon his shoulder, according vnto the number of the tribes of the
children of Israel:</ab>
<ab n="6">That this may
be a signe among you, that when your children aske their fathers in
time to come, saying, What meane you by these stones?<note> Heb. to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then yee
shall answere them, That the waters of Iordan were cut off before
the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord, when it passed ouer Iordan,
the waters of Iordan were cut off: and these stones shall bee for a
memoriall vnto the children of Israel for euer.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the
children of Israel did so as Ioshua commanded, and tooke vp twelue
stones out of the midst of Iordan, as the Lord spake vnto Ioshua,
according to the number of the tribes of the children of Israel,
and caried them ouer with them, vnto the place where they lodged,
and laid them downe there.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Ioshua
set vp twelue stones in the midst of Iordan, in the place where the
feet of the Priests which bare the Arke of the Couenant, stood: and
they are there vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ For the
Priests which bare the Arke, stood in the midst of Iordan, vntill
euery thing was finished that the Lord commanded Ioshua to speake
vnto the people, according to all that Moses commanded Ioshua: and
the people hasted and passed ouer.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it came to
passe when all the people were cleane passed ouer, that the Arke of
the Lord passed ouer, and the Priests in the presence of the
people.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the children
of Reuben, and the children of Gad, and halfe the tribe of
Manasseh, passed ouer armed before the children of Israel, as Moses
spake vnto them:<note> Num. 32. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">About fourty
thousand prepared for war, passed ouer before the Lord vnto
battell, to the plaines of Iericho.<note> Or. ready armed.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ On that day
the Lord magnified Ioshua in the sight of all Israel, and they
feared him, as they feared Moses all the dayes of his life.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Lord spake
vnto Ioshua, saying,</ab>

<fw>Stones in Gilgal.</fw>
<ab n="16">Command the
Priests that beare the Arke of the Testimony, that they come vp out
of Iordan.</ab>
<ab n="17">Ioshua therefore
commaunded the Priests, saying, Come yee vp out of Iordan.</ab>
<ab n="18">And it came to
passe when the Priests that bare the Arke of the Couenant of the
Lord, were come vp out of the mids of Iordan, and the soles of the
Priests feete were lift vp vnto the dry land, that the waters of
Iordan returned vnto their place, and flowed ouer all his banks, as
they did before.<note> Hebr. plucked vp. , Hebr. went.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And the
people came vp out of Iordan on the tenth day of the first moneth,
and encamped in Gilgal, in the East border of Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="20">And those twelue
stones which they tooke out of Iordan, did Ioshua pitch in
Gilgal.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he spake vnto
the children of Israel, saying, When your children shal aske their
fathers in time to come, saying, What meane these
stones?<note> Hebr. to morrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Then yee shall let
your children know, saying, Israel came ouer this Iordan on dry
land.</ab>
<ab n="23">For the Lord your
God dried vp the waters of Iordan from before you, vntill yee were
passed ouer, as the Lord your God did to the Red sea, which hee
dried vp from before vs, vntill we were gone ouer:<note> Exod. 14. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">That all the
people of the earth might know the hand of the Lord, that it is
mighty, that ye might feare the Lord your God for euer.<note> Hebr. all dayes.</note></ab>



</div>