<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Iericho is shut vp. 2 God
instructeth Ioshua how to besiege it. 12 The citie is compassed. 17
It must be accursed. 20 The walles fall downe. 22 Rahab is saued.
26 The builder of Iericho is cursed.</head>

<ab n="1">Now Iericho
was straitly shut vp, because of the children of Israel: none went
out, &amp; none came in.<note> Hebr. did shut vp, and was shut vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
said vnto Ioshua, See, I haue giuen into thine hand Iericho, and
the King thereof, and the mighty men of valour.</ab>
<ab n="3">And ye shall
compasse the city, all yee men of warre, and goe round about the
city once: thus shalt thou doe sixe dayes.</ab>
<ab n="4">And seuen
Priests shall beare before the Arke seuen trumpets of rams hornes:
and the seuenth day yee shall compasse the city seuen times, and
the Priests shall blow with the trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="5">And it shall
come to passe that when they make a long blast with the
rammes-horne, and when ye heare the sound of the trumpet, all the
people shall shout with a great shout: and the wall of the citie
shall fall downe flat, and the people shall ascend vp euery man
straight before him.<note> Hebr. vnder it.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
Ioshua the sonne of Nun called the Priests, and said vnto them,
Take vp the Arke of the Couenant, and let seuen Priests beare seuen
trumpets of rammes-hornes, before the Arke of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he said
vnto the people, Passe on, and compasse the city, and let him that
is armed passe on before the Arke of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>How Iericho is besieged.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ And it
came to passe when Ioshua had spoken vnto the people, that the
seuen Priestes bearing the seuen trumpets of rammes hornes, passed
on before the Lord, and blew with the trumpets: and the Arke of the
Couenant of the Lord followed them.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
the armed men went before the Priests that blew with the trumpets:
and the rereward came after the Arke, the Priests going on, and
blowing with the trumpets.<note> Heb. gathering host</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Ioshua had
commanded the people, saying, Ye shall not shout, nor make any
noise with your voice, neither shall any word proceed out of your
mouth, vntill the day I bid you shoute, then shall ye
shoute.<note> Heb. make your voyce to be heard.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">So the Arke of the
Lord compassed the citie, going about it once: and they came into
the campe, and lodged in the campe.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Ioshua
rose earely in the morning, and the Priests tooke vp the Arke of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And seuen Priests
bearing seuen trumpets of rammes hornes before the Arke of the
Lord, went on continually, and blew with the trumpets: and the
armed men went before them, but the rereward came after the Arke of
the Lord, the Priests going on and blowing with the
trumpets.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the second day
they compassed the citie once, and returned into the campe: so they
did sixe dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe on the seuenth day, that they rose early about the dawning of
the day, and compassed the citie after the same maner, seuen times:
only on that day they compassed the citie seuen times.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it came to
passe at the seuenth time, when the Priests blewe with the
trumpets, Ioshua said vnto the people, Shout, for the Lord hath
giuen you the citie.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
citie shalbe accursed, euen it, and all that are therein, to the
Lord: onely Rahab the harlot shal liue, she, and all that are with
her in the house, because she hid the messengers that we
sent.<note> Or, deuoted. , Chap.2.4</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And you, in any
wise keepe your selues from the accursed thing, lest yee make your
selues accursed, when yee take of the accursed thing, and make the
campe of Israel a curse, and trouble it.</ab>
<ab n="19">But all the
siluer, and gold, and vessels of brasse and yron, are consecrated
vnto the Lord: they shall come into the treasurie of the
Lord.<note> Hebr. holinesse.</note></ab>

<fw>Iericho is taken.</fw>
<ab n="20">So the people
shouted when the Priests blew with the trumpets: and it came to
passe when the people heard the sound of the trumpet, and the
people shouted with a great shout, that the wall fell downe flat,
so that the people went vp into the citie, euery man straight
before him, and they tooke the citie.<note> Heb.11. 30. , Hebr. vnder it.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And they vtterly
destroyed all that was in the city, both man and woman, yong and
old, and oxe, and sheepe, and asse, with the edge of the
sword.</ab>
<ab n="22">But Ioshua had
said vnto the two men that had spied out the countrey; Goe into the
harlots house, and bring out thence the woman and all that she
hath, as ye sware vnto her.<note> Chap.2. 14. Heb.11. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the yong men
that were spies, went in, and brought out Rahab, and her father,
and her mother, and her brethren, and all that she had: and they
brought out all her kinred, and left them without the campe of
Israel.<note> Hebr. families.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And they burnt the
city with fire, and all that was therein: onely the siluer &amp;
the gold, and the vessels of brasse and of yron, they put into the
Treasury of the house of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Ioshua saued
Rahab the harlot aliue, and her fathers houshold, and all that she
had: and she dwelleth in Israel euen vnto this day, because she hid
the messengers which Ioshua sent to spy out Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And Ioshua
adiured them at that time, saying, Cursed be the man before the
Lord, that riseth vp and buildeth this city Iericho: he shall lay
the foundation therof in his first borne, and in his yongest sonne
shall hee set vp the gates of it.<note> 1.King. 16.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">So the Lord was
with Ioshua, and his fame was noised throughout all the
countrey.</ab>



</div>