<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Deuteronomy-Chapter-34-34-Joshua.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The Lord appointeth Ioshua to
succeede Moses. 3 The borders of the promised land. 5. 9 God
promiseth to assist Ioshua. 8 He giueth him instructions. 10 He
prepareth the people to passe ouer Iordan. 12 Ioshua putteth the
two tribes and halfe in minde of their promise to Moses. 16 They
promise him fealty.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe after
the death of Moses the seruant of the Lord, it came to passe, that
the Lord spake vnto Ioshua the sonne of Nun, Moses minister,
saying,<note> Deut. 1. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Moses my
seruant is dead: now therefore arise, goe ouer this Iordan, thou,
and all this people, vnto the land which I doe giue to them, euen
to the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">Euery place
that the sole of your foote shall tread vpon, that haue I giuen
vnto you, as I said vnto Moses.<note> Deut.11. 24. chap. 14.9.</note></ab>

<fw>Moses age, death, and
successour.</fw>
<ab n="4">From the
wildernesse and this Lebanon, euen vnto the great Riuer, the riuer
Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites, and vnto the great sea,
toward the going downe of the Sunne, shalbe your coast.</ab>
<ab n="5">There shall
not any man be able to stand before thee all the dayes of thy life:
as I was with Moses, so I will be with thee: I will not faile thee,
nor forsake thee.<note> Heb. 13. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Bee strong,
and of a good courage: for vnto this people shalt thou diuide for
an inheritance the land which I sware vnto their fathers to giue
them.<note> Deut. 31. 23. , Or, thou shalt cause this people inherite the land, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Onely bee
thou strong, and very courageous, that thou mayest obserue to doe
according to all the Law, which Moses my seruant commaunded thee:
turne not from it to the right hand, or to the left, that thou
mayest prosper whither soeuer thou goest.<note> Deu. 5.32 and 28. 14. , Or, doe wisely.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">This booke of
the Law shal not depart out of thy mouth, but thou shalt meditate
therein day and night, that thou mayest obserue to doe according to
all that is written therein: for then thou shalt make thy way
prosperous, and then thou shalt haue good successe.<note> Or, doe wisely.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Haue not I
commanded thee? be strong, and of a good courage, bee not afraid,
neither be thou dismayed: for the Lord thy God is with thee,
whither soeuer thou goest.</ab>

<fw>Spies are sent to view Iericho.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ Then Ioshua
commanded the Officers of the people, saying,</ab>
<ab n="11">Passe through the
hoste, and command the people, saying, Prepare you victuals: for
within three dayes ye shal passe ouer this Iordan, to goe in to
possesse the land which the Lord your God giueth you, to possesse
it.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And to the
Reubenites, and to the Gadites, and to halfe the tribe of Manasseh,
spake Ioshua, saying,</ab>
<ab n="13">Remember the word
which Moses the seruant of the Lord commanded you, saying, The Lord
your God hath giuen you rest, and hath giuen you this
land:<note> Num.32 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Your wiues, your
litle ones, and your cattell shall remaine in the lande which Moses
gaue you on this side Iordan; but ye shall passe before your
brethren armed, all the mightie men of valour, and helpe
them:<note> Heb. marshalled by fiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Untill the Lord
haue giuen your brethren rest, as he hath giuen you, and they also
haue possessed the lande which the Lord your God giueth them: then
yee shall returne vnto the land of your possession, and enioy it,
which Moses the Lords seruant gaue you on this side Iordan toward
the Sunne rising.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And they
answered Ioshua, saying, All that thou commandest vs, we will doe,
and whither soeuer thou sendest vs, we will goe.</ab>
<ab n="17">According as we
hearkened vnto Moses in all things, so will we hearken vnto thee:
onely the Lord thy God be with thee, as he was with Moses.</ab>
<ab n="18">Whosoeuer he be
that doth rebell against thy commandement, and will not hearken
vnto thy words, in all that thou commandest him, he shall bee put
to death: onely be strong, and of a good courage.</ab>



</div>