<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-24-24-Judges.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Ioshua assembleth the tribes at
Shechem. 2 A briefe historie of Gods benefits from Terah. 14 He
reneweth a couenant betweene them and God. 26 A stone the witnesse
of the couenant. 29 Ioshuas age, death and buriall. 32 Iosephs
bones are buried. 33 Eleazar dieth.</head>

<ab n="1">And Ioshua
gathered all the Tribes of Israel to Shechem, and called for the
Elders of Israel, and for their Heads, and for their Iudges, and
for their Officers, and they presented themselues before
God.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Ioshua said
vnto all the people, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Your
fathers dwelt on the other side of the flood in old time, euen
Terah the father of Abraham, and the father of Nachor: and they
serued other gods.<note> Gen. 11. 31. iudit. 5. 6,7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And I tooke your
father Abraham frō the other side of the flood, and led him
throughout all the land of Canaan, and multiplied his seed, and
gaue him Isaac.<note> Gen. 21. 2</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I gaue vnto
Isaac, Iacob and Esau: &amp; I gaue vnto Esau mount Seir, to
possesse it: but Iacob and his children went downe into
Egypt.<note> Gen. 25. 26. , Gen. 36.8 , Gen. 46.6</note></ab>
<ab n="5">I sent Moses also
and Aaron, and I plagued Egypt, according to that which I did
amongst them: and afterward, I brought you out.<note> Exo. 3. 10</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I brought your
fathers out of Egypt: and you came vnto the sea, and the Egyptians
pursued after your fathers with charets and horsemen vnto the red
sea.<note> Exod. 12. 37. , Exod.14. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And when they
cried vnto the Lord, hee put darkenesse betweene you and the
Egyptians, and brought the sea vpon them, and couered them, and
your eyes haue seene what I haue done in Egypt, and ye dwelt in the
wildernes a long season.</ab>
<ab n="8">And I brought you
into the land of the Amorites, which dwelt on the other side
Iordan: and they fought with you, and I gaue them into your hand,
that ye might possesse their land, and I destroyed them from before
you.<note> Num.21 33.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods benefites on the
Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="9">Then Balak the
sonne of Zippor king of Moab, arose and warred against Israel, and
sent and called Balaam the sonne of Beor to curse you:<note> Num. 22. 5. deut. 23. 4</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But I would not
hearken vnto Balaam, therefore he blessed you still: so I deliuered
you out of his hand.</ab>
<ab n="11">And ye went ouer
Iordan, and came vnto Iericho: and the men of Iericho fought
against you, the Amorites, and the Perizzites, &amp; the
Canaanites, and the Hittites, and the Girgashites, the Hiuites, and
the Iebusites, and I deliuered them into your hand.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I sent the
hornet before you, which draue them out from before you, euen the
two kings of the Amorites: but not with thy sword, nor with thy
bow.<note> Exod. 23. 28. deut.7. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I haue giuen
you a land for which ye did not labour, &amp; cities which ye built
not, and yee dwell in them: of the vineyards and Oliue-yards which
ye planted not, doe ye eate.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Now
therefore, feare the Lord, and serue him in sinceritie, and in
trueth, and put away the gods which your fathers serued on the
other side of the flood, and in Egypt: and serue yee the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">And if it seeme
euill vnto you to serue the Lord, choose you this day whome you
will serue, whether the gods which your fathers serued that were on
the other side of the flood, or the gods of the Amorites, in whose
lande ye dwell: but as for mee and my house, we will serue the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the people
answered and said, God forbid that wee should forsake the Lord, to
serue other gods.</ab>
<ab n="17">For the Lord our
God, he it is that brought vs vp and our fathers out of the land of
Egypt, from the house of bondage, &amp; which did those great
signes in our sight, and preserued vs in all the way wherein we
went, and among all the people through whom we passed.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Lord
draue out from before vs all the people, euen the Amorites which
dwelt in the land: therefore will we also serue the Lord, for he is
our God.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Ioshua said
vnto the people, Ye cannot serue the Lord: for hee is an holy God:
he is a ielous God, he will not forgiue your transgressions nor
your sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="20">If yee forsake
the Lord, and serue strange gods, then he will turne, and doe you
hurt, and consume you, after that he hath done you
good.<note> Chap. 23. 15.</note></ab>

<fw>Ioshuas exhortation, His age, and
death.</fw>
<ab n="21">And the people
said vnto Ioshua, Nay, but we will serue the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Ioshua said
vnto the people, Yee are witnesses against your selues, that yee
haue chosen you the Lord, to serue him. And they said, We are
witnesses.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now therefore put
away, said he, the strange gods which are among you, and encline
your heart vnto the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the people
saide vnto Ioshua; The Lord our God will we serue, and his voice
will we obey.</ab>
<ab n="25">So Ioshua made a
couenant with the people that day, and set them a Statute, &amp; an
Ordinance in Shechem.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And Ioshua
wrote these words in the booke of the Law of God, and tooke a great
stone, and set it vp there, vnder an oake, that was by the
Sanctuary of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Ioshua saide
vnto all the people, Behold, this stone shalbe a witnesse vnto vs;
for it hath heard all the words of the Lord which hee spake vnto
vs; it shall be there for a witnesse vnto you, lest ye deny your
God.</ab>

<fw>Ioshuas exhortation, His age, and
death.</fw>
<ab n="28">So Ioshua let the
people depart, euery man vnto his inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And it
came to passe after these things, that Ioshua the sonne of Nun the
seruant of the Lord died, being an hundred and ten yeeres
old.</ab>
<ab n="30">And they buried
him in the border of his inheritance in Timnath-Serah, which is in
mount Ephraim, on the North side of the hill of Gaash.<note> Chap. 19. 50. iudg.2. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And Israel serued
the Lord all the dayes of Ioshua, &amp; all the dayes of the Elders
that ouerliued Ioshua, and which had knowen al the works of the
Lord, that he had done for Israel.<note> Hebr. prolonged their dayes after Ioshua.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And the
bones of Ioseph, which the children of Israel brought vp out of
Egypt, buried they in Shechem, in a parcell of ground which Iacob
bought of the sonnes of Hamor the father of Shechem, for an hundred
pieces of siluer; and it became the inheritance of the children of
Ioseph.<note> Gen. 50. 25. exod. 13.19. , Gene. 33. 19. , Or, lambs.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And Eleazar the
sonne of Aaron died, and they buried him in a hill that pertained
to Phinehas his son, which was giuen him in mount Ephraim.</ab>



</div>