<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 The Tabernacle is set vp at
Shiloh. 2 The remainder of the land is described, and diuided into
seuen parts. 10 Ioshua diuideth it by lot. 11 The lot and border of
Beniamin. 21 Their cities.</head>

<ab n="1">And the whole
Congregation of the children of Israel assembled together at
Shiloh, &amp; set vp the Tabernacle of the Congregation there, and
the land was subdued before them.</ab>
<ab n="2">And there remained
among the children of Israel seuen tribes, which had not yet
receiued their inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Ioshua said
vnto the children of Israel, how long are you slacke to goe to
possesse the lande which the Lord God of your fathers hath giuen
you?</ab>
<ab n="4">Giue out from
among you three men, for each tribe: and I will send them, and they
shall rise, &amp; goe through the land, and describe it according
to the inheritance of them, and they shal come againe to
me.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they shall
diuide it into seuen parts: Iudah shall abide in their coast on the
South, and the house of Ioseph shall abide in their coasts on the
North.</ab>
<ab n="6">Ye shall therfore
describe the land into seuen parts, and bring the description
hither to me: that I may cast lots for you here before the Lord our
God.</ab>
<ab n="7">But the Leuites
haue no part among you, for the Priesthood of the Lord is their
inheritance: and Gad and Reuben, and halfe the tribe of Manasseh,
haue receiued their inheritance beyond Iordan on the East, which
Moses the seruant of the Lord gaue them.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the men
arose, and went away: and Ioshua charged them that went to describe
the land, saying, Goe, and walke through the land, &amp; describe
it, and come againe to me, that I may here cast lots for you,
before the Lord in Shiloh.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the men went,
and passed thorow the land, and described it by cities, into seuen
parts in a booke, and came againe to Ioshua to the hoste at
Shiloh.</ab>

<fw>The lot, borders, and cities of
Beniamin.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ And Ioshua
cast lots for them in Shiloh, before the Lord: and there Ioshua
diuided the land vnto the children of Israel according to their
diuisions.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
lot of the tribe of the children of Beniamin came vp according to
their families: and the coast of their lot came foorth betweene the
children of Iudah, and the children of Ioseph.</ab>
<ab n="12">And their border
on the Northside was from Iordan, and the border went vp to the
side of Iericho, on the North side, and went vp through the
mountaines Westward, and the goings out thereof were at the
wildernesse of Beth-auen.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the border
went ouer from thence toward Luz, to the side of Luz, (which is
Bethel) Southward, and the border descended to Ataroth-Adar, neere
the hill that lieth on the South side of the nether
Beth-horon.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the border
was drawen thence, and compassed the corner of the Sea Southward,
from the hill that lieth before Beth-horon Southward: and the
goings out thereof were at Kiriath-baal (which is Kiriath-iearim) a
city of the children of Iudah: This was the West quarter.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the South
quarter was from the end of Kiriath-iearim, &amp; the border went
out on the West, and went out to the well of waters of
Nephtoah.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the border
came downe to the end of the mountaine, that lieth before the
valley of the sonne of Hinnom, and which is in the valley of the
Giants on the North, and descended to the valley of Hinnom to the
side of Iebusi on the South, and descended to En-Rogel,</ab>
<ab n="17">And was drawen
frō the North, and went foorth to Enshemesh, and went foorth
toward Geliloth, which is ouer against the going vp of Adummim, and
descended to the stone of Bohan the sonne of Reuben,<note> Chap.15. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And passed along
toward the side ouer against Arabah Northward, and went downe vnto
Arabah.<note> Or, the plaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the border
passed along to the side of Beth-hoglah Northward: and the
outgoings of the border were at the North bay of the salt Sea at
the South end of Iordane: This was the South coast.<note> Hebr. tongue.</note></ab>

<fw>The lot, borders, and cities of
Beniamin.</fw>
<ab n="20">And Iordane was
the border of it on the East side: this was the inheritance of the
children of Beniamin, by the coasts thereof round about, according
to their families.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now the cities of
the tribe of the children of Beniamin according to their families,
were Iericho, and Bethhoglah, and the valley of Keziz,</ab>
<ab n="22">And Betharabah,
and Zemaraim, and Bethel,</ab>
<ab n="23">And Auim, and
Parah, and Ophrah,</ab>
<ab n="24">And
Chephar-Haammonai, and Ophni, and Gaba, twelue cities with their
villages.</ab>
<ab n="25">Gibeon, and
Ramah, and Beeroth,</ab>
<ab n="26">And Mizpeh, and
Chephirah, and Mozah,</ab>
<ab n="27">And Rekem, and
Irpeel, and Taralah,</ab>
<ab n="28">And Zela, Eleph,
and Iebusi, (which is Ierusalem) Gibeath, and Kiriath, foureteene
cities with their villages. This is the inheritance of the children
of Beniamin according to their families.</ab>



</div>