<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Rahab receiueth and concealeth the
two spies sent from Shittim. 8 The couenant betweene her and them.
23 Their returne and relation.</head>

<ab n="1">And Ioshua
the sonne of Nun sent out of Shittim two men, to spie secretly,
saying, Go, view the land, euen Iericho: and they went, and came
into an harlots house, named Rahab, and lodged there.<note> Heb.11. 31 iam.2. 25. , Heb. lay.</note></ab>

<fw>Spies are sent to view Iericho.</fw>
<ab n="2">And it was
told the king of Iericho, saying, Behold, there came men in hither
to night, of the children of Israel, to search out the
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the king
of Iericho sent vnto Rahab, saying, Bring forth the men that are
come to thee, which are entred into thine house: for they bee come
to search out all the countrey.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the woman
tooke the two men, and hid them, &amp; said thus: There came men
vnto mee, but I wist not whence they were:</ab>
<ab n="5">And it came
to passe about the time of shutting of the gate, when it was darke,
that the men went out: whither the men went, I wote not: pursue
after them quickely, for ye shall ouertake them.</ab>
<ab n="6">But shee had
brought them vp to the roofe of the house, and hid them with the
stalkes of flaxe, which she had laid in order vpon the
roofe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the men
pursued after them the way to Iordan, vnto the foords: and assoone
as they which pursued after them were gone out, they shut the
gate.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
before they were laide downe, shee came vp vnto them vpon the
roofe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And she said
vnto the men, I know that the Lord hath giuen you the land, and
that your terrour is fallen vpon vs, and that all the inhabitants
of the land faint because of you:<note> Heb. melt.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For wee haue heard
how the Lord dried vp the water of the red Sea for you; when you
came out of Egypt, and what you did vnto the two kings of the
Amorites that were on the other side Iordan, Sihon and Og; whom ye
vtterly destroyed.<note> Exod.14 21. chap. 4. 23. , Num.21 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And assoone as we
had heard these things, our hearts did melt, neither did there
remaine any more courage in any man, because of you: for the Lord
your God, he is God in heauen aboue, and in earth
beneath.<note> Heb. rose vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Now therfore, I
pray you, sweare vnto me by the Lord, since I haue shewed you
kindnesse, that ye will also shew kindnesse vnto my fathers house,
and giue me a true token:</ab>
<ab n="13">And that ye will
saue aliue my father, and my mother, and my brethren, and my
sisters, and all that they haue, and deliuer our liues from
death.</ab>

<fw>Rahabs couenant.</fw>
<ab n="14">And the men
answered her, Our life for yours, if yee vtter not this our
businesse. And it shall bee when the Lord hath giuen vs the land,
that wee will deale kindely and truely with thee.<note> Hebr. in stead of you to die.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then shee let them
downe by a coard thorow the window: for her house was vpon the
towne wall, and she dwelt vpon the wall.</ab>
<ab n="16">And she said vnto
them, Get you to the mountaine, lest the pursuers meete you; and
hide your selues there three dayes, vntill the pursuers bee
returned, and afterward may ye goe your way.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the men said
vnto her, Wee will bee blamelesse of this thine oath which thou
hast made vs sweare:</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold, when we
come into the land, thou shalt binde this line of scarlet threed in
the window which thou didst let vs downe by: and thou shalt bring
thy father and thy mother, and thy brethren, and all thy fathers
houshold home vnto thee.<note> Hebr. gather.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And it shall bee,
that whosoeuer shall goe out of the doores of thy house into the
street, his blood shalbe vpon his head, and wee will bee
guiltlesse: and whosoeuer shall bee with thee in the house, his
blood shalbe on our head, if any hand be vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And if thou vtter
this our businesse, then we wilbe quit of thine oath which thou
hast made vs to sweare.</ab>
<ab n="21">And shee saide,
According vnto your words, so be it. And she sent them away, &amp;
they departed: and she bound the scarlet line in the
window.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they went, and
came vnto the mountaine, and abode there three dayes, vntill the
pursuers were returned. And the pursuers sought them thorowout all
the way, but found them not.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ So the two
men returned, and descended from the mountaine, and passed ouer,
and came to Ioshua the sonne of Nun, and told him all things that
befell them.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they saide
vnto Ioshua, Truely the Lord hath deliuered into our hands all the
land; for euen all the inhabitants of the countrey doe faint
because of vs.<note> Hebr. melt.</note></ab>



</div>