<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The two kings whose countreys
Moses tooke and disposed of. 7 The one and thirty kings on the
other side Iordan which Ioshua smote.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are the
kings of the land, which the children of Israel smote, and
possessed their land on the other side Iordan, toward the rising of
the Sunne: from the riuer Arnon, vnto mount Hermon, and all the
plaine on the East.</ab>
<ab n="2">Sihon king of the
Amorites who dwelt in Heshbon, and ruled from Aroer, which is vpon
the banke of the riuer of Arnon, and from the middle of the riuer,
and from halfe Gilead vnto the riuer Iabbok; which is the border of
the children of Ammon:<note> Num. 21 24. deu.3.6</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And from the
plaine, to the Sea of Cinneroth on the East, and vnto the sea of
the plaine, euen the salt sea on the East, the way to
Beth-Ieshimoth: and from the South, vnder
Ashdoth-Pisgah.<note> Or, Teman , Or, the springs of Pisgah, or the hill. , Deut.3. 17. &amp; 4.49.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And the
coast of Og king of Bashan, which was of the remnant of the Giants,
that dwelt at Ashtaroth, and at Edrei,<note> Deut.3. 11. chap. 13.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And reigned in
mount Hermon, and in Salcah, and in all Bashan, vnto the border of
the Geshurites, and the Maachathites, and halfe Gilead, the border
of Sihon king of Heshbon.</ab>
<ab n="6">Them did Moses the
seruant of the Lord, and the children of Israel smite, and Moses
the seruant of the Lord gaue it for a possession vnto the
Reubenites, and Gadites, and the halfe tribe of
Manasseh.<note> Num. 32. 29. deut. 3. 12. chap. 13.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And these
are the kings of the countrey which Ioshua and the children of
Israel smote on this side Iordan on the West, from Baal Gad in the
valley of Lebanon, euen vnto the mount Halak, that goeth vp to
Seir, which Ioshua gaue vnto the tribes of Israel for a possession,
according to their diuisions:<note> Chap. 11. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">In the mountaines
and in the valleys, and in the plaines, and in the springs, and in
the wildernesse, and in the South countrey: the Hittites, the
Amorites, and the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hiuites, and the
Iebusites.</ab>

<fw>Kings conquered.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ The king of
Iericho, one: the king of Ai, which is beside Bethel,
one:<note> Chap. 6.2. , Chap. 8. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The king of
Ierusalem, one: the king of Hebron, one:<note> Chap. 10. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The king of
Iarmuth, one: the king of Lachis, one:</ab>
<ab n="12">The king of
Eglon, one: the king of Gezer, one:<note> Chap.10. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The king of
Debir, one: the king of Geder, one:<note> Chap.10. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The king of
Hormah one: the king of Arad, one:</ab>
<ab n="15">The king of
Libnah, one: the king of Adullam, one:<note> Chap. 10. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The king of
Makkedah, one: the king of Bethel, one:<note> Chap. 10. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The king of
Tappuah, one: the king of Hepher, one:</ab>
<ab n="18">The king of
Aphek, one: the king of Lasharon, one:<note> Or, Saron.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The king of
Madon, one: the king of Hazor, one:<note> Chap. 11. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">The king of
Shimron-Meron, one: the king of Achshaph, one:</ab>
<ab n="21">The king of
Taanach, one: the king of Megiddo, one:</ab>
<ab n="22">The king of
Kedesh, one: the king of Iokneam of Carmel, one:</ab>
<ab n="23">The king of Dor,
in the coast of Dor, one: the king of the nations of Gilgal,
one:<note> Genes.14. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The king of
Tirzah, one: all the kings thirtie and one.</ab>



</div>