<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 God commandeth, 7 and the children
of Israel appoint the sixe cities of Refuge.</head>

<ab n="1">The Lord also
spake vnto Ioshua, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake to the
children of Israel, saying, Appoint out for you cities of refuge,
whereof I spake vnto you by the hand of Moses:<note> Exod.21. 13. num. 35.6,11. 14. deut.19.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">That the slayer
that killeth any person vnawares and vnwittingly, may flee thither:
and they shall be your refuge from the auenger of blood.</ab>

<fw>Cities of refuge.</fw>
<ab n="4">And when he that
doeth flee vnto one of those cities, shall stand at the entring of
the gate of the city, and shall declare his cause in the eares of
the Elders of that citie; they shall take him into the citie vnto
them, and giue him a place, that he may dwell among them.</ab>
<ab n="5">And if the auenger
of blood pursue after him, then they shal not deliuer the slayer vp
into his hand: because hee smote his neighbour vnwittingly, and
hated him not beforetime.</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee shall
dwell in that citie, vntill he stand before the Congregation for
iudgement, and vntill the death of the high Priest that shall bee
in those dayes: then shall the slayer returne, and come vnto his
owne city, and vnto his owne house, vnto the citie from whence he
fled.<note> Num.35. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And they
appointed Kedesh in Galilee, in mount Naphtali, and Shechem in
mount Ephraim, and Kiriath-arba (which is Hebron) in the mountaine
of Iudah.<note> Hebr. sanctified.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And on the other
side Iordan by Iericho Eastward, they assigned Bezer in the
wildernesse vpon the plaine, out of the tribe of Reuben, and Ramoth
in Gilead out of the tribe of Gad, and Golan in Bashan out of the
tribe of Manasseh.<note> Deut.4 43. 1.chro. 6.78.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">These were the
cities appointed for all the children of Israel, and for the
stranger that soiourneth among them, that whosoeuer killeth any
person at vnawares might flee thither, &amp; not die by the hand of
the auenger of blood, vntill he stood before the
Congregation.</ab>



</div>