<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Ioshuas exhortation before his
death, 3 by former benefits, 5 by promises, 11 and by
threatnings.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, a long time after that the Lord had giuen rest vnto Israel
from all their enemies round about, that Ioshua waxed old, and
stricken in age.<note> Heb. come into dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Ioshua called
for all Israel, and for their Elders, &amp; for their Heads, and
for their Iudges, and for their Officers, and said vnto them; I am
old, and stricken in age.</ab>
<ab n="3">And yee haue seene
all that the Lord your God hath done vnto all these nations,
because of you; for the Lord your God is hee that hath fought for
you.<note> Exod. 14. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, I haue
diuided vnto you by lot these nations that remaine, to bee an
inheritance for your tribes, from Iordan, with all the nations that
I haue cut off, euen vnto the great Sea Westward.<note> Hebr. at the Sunne set.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the Lord your
God, hee shall expell them from before you, and driue them from out
of your sight, &amp; ye shall possesse their land, as the Lord your
God hath promised vnto you.</ab>

<fw>Exhortations to the loue of
God.</fw>
<ab n="6">Be ye therefore
very courageous to keepe and to doe all that is written in the
booke of the Law of Moses, that yee turne not aside therefrom, to
the right hand, or to the left,<note> Deut. 5. 32.and 28. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">That yee come not
among these nations, these that remaine amongst you, neither make
mention of the name of their gods, nor cause to sweare by them,
neither serue them, nor bow your selues vnto them.<note> Psal. 16.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But cleaue vnto
the Lord your God, as yee haue done vnto this day.<note> Or, for if you will cleaue, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For the Lord hath
driuen out from before you, great nations, and strong: But as for
you, no man hath beene able to stand before you vnto this
day.<note> Or, then the LORD will driue.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">One man of you
shall chase a thousand: for the Lord your God, he it is that
fighteth for you, as hee hath promised you.<note> Leuit. 26. 8. deut. 32. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Take good heed
therefore vnto your selues, that ye loue the Lord your
God.<note> Heb. soules.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Else, if ye do in
any wise go backe, and cleaue vnto the remnant of these nations,
euen these that remaine among you, and shall make marriages with
them, and goe in vnto them, and they to you:</ab>
<ab n="13">Know for a
certainety, that the Lord your God will no more driue out any of
these nations from before you: but they shalbe snares and traps
vnto you, and scourges in your sides, and thornes in your eyes,
vntill yee perish from off this good land which the Lord your God
hath giuen you.<note> Exod. 23. 33. numb. 33.55. deu 7.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And behold, this
day I am going the way of all the earth, and ye know in all your
hearts, and in all your soules, that not one thing hath failed of
all the good things which the Lord your God spake concerning you;
all are come to passe vnto you, and not one thing hath failed
thereof.<note> Chap. 21. 45.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Therefore it
shall come to passe, that as all good things are come vpon you,
which the Lord your God promised you: so shall the Lord bring vpon
you all euill things, vntill he haue destroyed you from off this
good land which the Lord your God hath giuen you.</ab>

<fw>Gods benefites on the
Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="16">When yee haue
transgressed the Couenant of the Lord your God, which hee
commaunded you, and haue gone and serued other gods, and bowed your
selues to them: then shall the anger of the Lord bee kindled
against you, and yee shall perish quickly from off the good land
which hee hath giuen vnto you.</ab>



</div>