<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-21-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Eight and fortie cities giuen by
lot, out of the other tribes, vnto the Leuites. 43 God gaue the
land, and rest vnto the Israelites, according to his
promise.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came neere
the heads of the fathers of the Leuites vnto Eleazar the Priest,
and vnto Ioshua the sonne of Nun, and vnto the heads of the fathers
of the tribes of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And they spake
vnto them at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, saying, The Lord
commaunded by the hand of Moses, to giue vs Cities to dwell in,
with the suburbs thereof for our cattell.<note> Num.35. 2.</note></ab>

<fw>Cities giuen to the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="3">And the children
of Israel gaue vnto the Leuites out of their inheritance at the
commandement of the Lord, these cities and their suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the lot came
out for the families of the Kohathites: and the children of Aaron
the Priest, which were of the Leuites, had by lot out of the tribe
of Iudah, and out of the tribe of Simeon, and out of the tribe of
Beniamin, thirteene cities.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the rest of
the children of Kohath had by lot, out of the families of the tribe
of Ephraim, and out of the tribe of Dan, and out of the halfe tribe
of Manasseh, ten cities.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the children
of Gershon had by lot out of the families of the tribe of Issachar,
and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali,
and out of the halfe tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteene
cities.</ab>
<ab n="7">The children of
Merari by their families, had out of the tribe of Reuben, and out
of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelue
cities.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the children
of Israel gaue by lot vnto the Leuites these cities with their
suburbs, as the Lord commanded by the hand of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And they
gaue out of the tribe of the children of Iudah, and out of the
tribe of the children of Simeon, these cities which are here
mentioned by name,<note> Hebr. called.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Which the
children of Aaron being of the families of the Kohathites, who were
of the children of Leui, had: (for theirs was the first
lot.)</ab>
<ab n="11">And they gaue
them the citie of Arbah the father of Anak (which citie is Hebron)
in the hill countrey of Iudah, with þe suburbs
thereof round about it.<note> Or, Kiriath-arbah.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But the fields of
the citie, and the villages thereof, gaue they to Caleb the sonne
of Iephunneh, for his possession.<note> Chap.14 14. 1.chro. 6.56.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Thus they
gaue to the children of Aaron the Priest Hebron with her suburbs to
bee a citie of refuge for the slayer, and Libnah with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="14">And Iattir with
her suburbs, and Eshtemoa with her suburbs:</ab>
<ab n="15">And Holon with
her suburbs, and Debir with her suburbs:</ab>
<ab n="16">And Ain with her
suburbs, and Iuttah with her suburbs, and Bethshemesh with her
suburbs, nine cities out of those two tribes.</ab>
<ab n="17">And out of the
tribe of Beniamin, Gibeon with her suburbs, Geba with her
suburbs,</ab>

<fw>Cities giuen to the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="18">Anathoth with her
suburbs, and Almon with her suburbs, foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="19">All the cities of
the children of Aaron the Priests, were thirteene cities with their
suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
families of the children of Kohath the Leuites, which remained of
the children of Kohath, euen they had the cities of their lot out
of the tribe of Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="21">For they gaue
them Shechem with her suburbs in mount Ephraim, to be a citie of
refuge for the slayer: and Gezer with her suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="22">And Kibzaim with
her suburbs, and Beth-horon with her suburbs, foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="23">And out of the
tribe of Dan, Eltekeh with her suburbs, Gibethon with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="24">Aijalon with her
suburbs, Gathrimmon, with her suburbs: foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="25">And out of the
halfe tribe of Manasseh, Tanach with her suburbs, and Gathrimmon
with her suburbs, two cities.</ab>
<ab n="26">All the cities
were ten with their suburbs, for the families of the children of
Kohath that remained.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And vnto
the children of Gershon of the families of the Leuites, out of the
other halfe tribe of Manasseh, they gaue Golan in Bashan, with her
suburbs, to be a citie of refuge for the slayer: and Beeshterah
with her suburbs, two cities.</ab>
<ab n="28">And out of the
tribe of Issachar, Kishon with her suburbs, Dabareh with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="29">Iarmuth with her
suburbs, Engannim with her suburbs, foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="30">And out of the
tribe of Asher Mishal with her suburbs, Abdon with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="31">Helkah with her
suburbs, and Rehob with her suburbs, foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="32">And out of the
tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with her suburbs, to be a
citie of refuge for the slayer, and Hammoth-dor with her suburbs,
and Kartan with her suburbs, three cities.</ab>
<ab n="33">All the cities of
the Gershonites according to their families were thirteen cities
with their suburbs.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites cities.</fw>
<ab n="34">¶ And vnto
the families of the children of Merari the rest of the Leuites, out
of the tribe of Zebulun, Iokneam, with her suburbs, and Kartah with
her suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="35">Dimnah with her
suburbs, Nahalal with her suburbs, foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="36">And out of the
tribe of Reuben, Bezer with her suburbs, and Iahazah with her
suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="37">Kedemoth with her
suburbs, and Mephaath with her suburbs, foure cities.</ab>
<ab n="38">And out of the
tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with her suburbs, to be a city of
refuge for the slayer; and Mahanaim with her suburbs,</ab>
<ab n="39">Heshbon with her
suburbs, Iazer with her suburbs, foure cities in all.</ab>
<ab n="40">So all the cities
for the children of Merari by their families, which were remayning
of the families of the Leuites, were by their lot, twelue
cities.</ab>
<ab n="41">All the cities of
the Leuites within the possession of the children of Israel, were
fourty and eight cities, with their suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="42">These cities were
euery one with their suburbs round about them: thus were all these
cities.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ And the
Lord gaue vnto Israel all the land which hee sware to giue vnto
their fathers: and they possessed it, and dwelt therein.</ab>
<ab n="44">And the Lord gaue
them rest round about, according to all that he sware vnto their
fathers, and there stood not a man of all their enemies before
them: the Lord deliuered all their enemies into their hand.</ab>
<ab n="45">There failed not
ought of any good thing which the Lord had spoken vnto the house of
Israel: all came to passe.<note> Chap.23.14,15.</note></ab>



</div>