<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The kings combine against Israel.
3 The Gibeonites by craft obtaine a League. 16 For which they are
condemned to perpetual bondage.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came
to passe when all the kings which were on this side Iordan in the
hilles, and in the valleys, and in all the coasts of the great sea,
ouer against Lebanon, the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite,
the Perizzite, the Hiuite, and the Iebusite heard thereof:</ab>
<ab n="2">That they
gathered themselues together to fight with Ioshua, and with Israel,
with one accord.<note> Heb. mouth</note></ab>

<fw>The Gibeonites craft.</fw>
<ab n="3">¶ And
when the inhabitants of Gibeon heard what Ioshua had done vnto
Iericho, and to Ai,</ab>
<ab n="4">They did
worke wilily, and went and made as if they had beene embassadours,
and tooke old sackes vpon their asses, and wine-bottels, old, and
rent, and bound vp,</ab>
<ab n="5">And old
shooes and clowted vpon their feet, &amp; olde garments vpon them,
and all the bread of their prouision was drie and mouldie.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they went
to Ioshua vnto the campe at Gilgal, and said vnto him, and to the
men of Israel, Wee be come from a farre countrey: Now therefore
make ye a league with vs.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the men
of Israel said vnto the Hiuites, Peraduenture yee dwell among vs,
and how shall wee make a league with you.?</ab>
<ab n="8">And they said
vnto Ioshua, Wee are thy seruants. And Ioshua said vnto them, Who
are ye? And from whence come ye?</ab>
<ab n="9">And they said
vnto him, From a very farre countrey thy seruants are come, because
of the Name of the Lord thy God: for wee haue heard the fame of
him, and all that hee did in Egypt,</ab>
<ab n="10">And all that hee
did to the two kings of the Amorites, that were beyond Iordan, to
Sihon king of Heshbon, and to Og king of Bashan, which was at
Ashtaroth.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore our
Elders and all the inhabitants of our countrey, spake to vs,
saying, Take victuals with you for the iourney, and goe to meete
them, and say vnto them, Wee are your seruants: therefore now make
ye a league with vs.<note> Hebr. in your hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">This our bread,
wee tooke hote for our prouision out of our houses, on the day we
came forth to goe vnto you: but now behold, it is dry, &amp; it is
mouldy.</ab>
<ab n="13">And these bottels
of wine which we filled, were new, and behold, they be rent: and
these our garments, and our shooes are become old, by reason of the
very long iourney.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the men tooke
of their victuals, and asked not counsell at the mouth of the
Lord.<note> Or, they receiued the men by reason of their victuals.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Ioshua made
peace with them, and made a league with them, to let them liue: and
the princes of the Congregation sware vnto them.</ab>

<fw>Gibeonites slaues.</fw>
<ab n="16">¶ And it came
to passe at the end of three dayes, after they had made a league
with them, that they heard that they were their neighbours, and
that they dwelt among them.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the children
of Israel iourneyed, and came vnto their cities on the third day:
now their cities were Gibeon, and Chephirah, and Beeroth, and
Kiriath iearim.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the children
of Israel smote them not, because the Princes of the Congregation
had sworne vnto them by the Lord God of Israel: And all the
Congregation murmured against the Princes.</ab>
<ab n="19">But all the
Princes said vnto all the Congregation, We haue sworne vnto them by
the Lord God of Israel: now therefore we may not touch
them.</ab>
<ab n="20">This we will doe
to them; wee will euen let them liue, lest wrath be vpon vs,
because of the oath which wee sware vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the Princes
said vnto them, Let them liue, (but let them bee hewers of wood,
and drawers of water, vnto all the Congregation,) as the Princes
had promised them.<note> Verse 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And Ioshua
called for them, and he spake vnto them, saying, Wherefore haue ye
beguiled vs, saying, We are very farre from you? when ye dwell
among vs.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now therefore ye
are cursed, and there shall none of you bee freed from being
bondmen, and hewers of wood, and drawers of water, for the house of
my God.<note> Hebr. not be cut off from you.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And they answered
Ioshua, and said, Because it was certainely told thy seruants, how
that the Lord thy God commanded his seruant Moses to giue you all
the land, and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from
before you, therefore we were sore afraid of our liues because of
you, and haue done this thing.<note> Deut.7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And now behold, we
are in thine hand: as it seemeth good and right vnto thee to doe
vnto vs, doe.</ab>
<ab n="26">And so did he vnto
them, and deliuered them out of the hand of the children of Israel,
that they slew them not.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Ioshua made
them that day, hewers of wood, and drawers of water for the
Congregation, and for the Altar of the Lord, euen vnto this day, in
the place which he should choose.</ab>



</div>