<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 The nine tribes and a halfe are to
haue their inheritance by lot. 6 Caleb by priuiledge obtaineth
Hebron.</head>

<ab n="1">And these are the
countreys which the children of Israel inherited in the lande of
Canaan, which Eleazar the Priest, &amp; Ioshua the sonne of Nun,
and the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the children of
Israel distributed for inheritance to them:<note> Num. 34. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">By lot was their
inheritance, as the Lord commanded by the hande of Moses, for the
nine tribes, and for the halfe tribe.<note> Num. 26 55. &amp; 33. 54.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For Moses had
giuen the inheritance of two tribes and an halfe tribe, on the
other side Iordan: but vnto the Leuites hee gaue none inheritance
among them.</ab>
<ab n="4">For the children
of Ioseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim: therefore they
gaue no part vnto the Leuites in the land, saue cities to dwell in,
with their suburbs for their cattell, and for their
substance.</ab>
<ab n="5">As the Lord
commaunded Moses, so the children of Israel did, and they diuided
the land.<note> Num. 35 2. chap. 21.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then the
children of Iudah came vnto Ioshua in Gilgal: and Caleb the sonne
of Iephunneh the Kenezite, said vnto him, Thou knowest the thing
that the Lord said vnto Moses the man of God concerning me and
thee, in Kadesh Barnea.</ab>
<ab n="7">Fourtie yeeres
olde was I when Moses the seruant of the Lord sent me from Kadesh
Barnea, to espie out the land, and I brought him worde againe, as
it was in mine heart.</ab>

<fw>Calebs inheritance.</fw>
<ab n="8">Neuerthelesse, my
brethren that went vp with me, made the heart of the people melt:
but I wholly followed the Lord my God.<note> Num. 14. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Moses sware on
that day, saying, Surely the land whereon thy feet haue troden,
shall be thine inheritance, and thy childrens for euer, because
thou hast wholly followed the Lord my God.</ab>
<ab n="10">And now beholde,
the Lord hath kept me aliue, as he said, these forty and fiue
yeres, euen since the Lord spake this word vnto Moses, while the
children of Israel wandered in the wildernesse: and now loe, I am
this day fourescore and fiue yeeres old.<note> Hebr. walked.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">As yet I am as
strong this day, as I was in the day that Moses sent mee: as my
strength was then, euen so is my strength now, for warre, both to
goe out and to come in.<note> Ecclus. 46.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Now therefore
giue mee this mountaine, whereof the Lord spake in that day, (for
thou heardest in that day how the Anakims were there, and that the
cities were great and fenced) if so be the Lord will be with me,
then I shall bee able to driue them out, as the Lord said.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Ioshua
blessed him, and gaue vnto Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh, Hebron for
an inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="14">Hebron therefore
became the inheritance of Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh the Kenezite
vnto this day: because that hee wholly followed the Lord God of
Israel.<note> Chap.21.12. 1. macc, 2.56.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the name of
Hebron before, was Kiriath-Arba, which Arba was a great man among
the Anakims: and the land had rest from warre.<note> Chap.15. 13.</note></ab>



</div>