<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJoshua_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 God blesseth Noah. 4 Blood and
murder are forbidden. 9 Gods Couenant 13 signified by the Rainebow.
18 Noah replenisheth the world, 20 planteth a Vineyard, 21 is
drunken, and mocked of his sonne: 25 Curseth Canaan, 26 Blesseth
Shem, 27 prayeth for Iaphet, 28 and dieth.</head>

<ab n="1">And God blessed
Noah, and his sonnes, and said vnto them, Bee fruitfull and
multiply, and replenish the earth.<note> Chap.1. 28. and 8. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the feare of
you, &amp; the dread of you shall be vpon euery beast of the earth,
and vpon euery fowle of the aire, vpon all that mooueth vpon the
earth, and vpon all the fishes of the sea; into your hand are they
deliuered.</ab>
<ab n="3">Euery mouing thing
that liueth, shalbe meat for you; euen as the greene herbe haue I
giuen you all things.<note> Chap.1. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But flesh with the
life thereof, which is the blood thereof, shall you not
eate.<note> Leuit.17. 14.</note></ab>

<fw>The Rainbow.</fw>
<ab n="5">And surely your
blood of your liues will I require: at the hand of euery beast will
I require it, &amp; at the hand of man, at the hand of euery mans
brother will I require the life of man.</ab>
<ab n="6">Who so sheddeth
mans blood, by man shall his blood be shed: for in the image of God
made he man.<note> Matt. 26. 52. reuel. 13.10. , Chap.1. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And you, be ye
fruitfull, and multiply, bring foorth aboundantly in the earth, and
multiply therein.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And God
spake vnto Noah, and to his sonnes with him, saying;</ab>
<ab n="9">And I, behold, I
establish my couenant with you, and with your seede after
you:</ab>
<ab n="10">And with euery
liuing creature that is with you, of the fowle, of the cattell, and
of euery beast of the earth with you, from all that goe out of the
Arke, to euery beast of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I wil
establish my couenant with you, neither shal all flesh be cut off
any more, by the waters of a flood, neither shall there any more be
a flood to destroy the earth.<note> Esa.54.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And God said,
This is the token of the Couenant which I make betweene mee and
you, and euery liuing creature that is with you, for perpetuall
generations.</ab>
<ab n="13">I doe set my bow
in the cloud, and it shall be for a token of a couenant, betweene
me and the earth.</ab>
<ab n="14">And it shall come
to passe, when I bring a cloud ouer the earth, that the bow shall
be seene in the cloud.<note> Ecclus.43. 11,12.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And I will
remember my couenant, which is betweene mee and you, and euery
liuing creature of all flesh: and the waters shall no more become a
flood to destroy all flesh.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the bow
shalbe in the cloud; and I will looke vpon it, that I may remember
the euerlasting couenant betweene God and euery liuing creature, of
all flesh that is vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">And God said vnto
Noah, This is the token of the couenant, which I haue established
betweene mee and all flesh, that is vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And the
sonnes of Noah that went forth of the Arke, were Shem, and Ham, and
Iaphet: and Ham is the father of Canaan.<note> Heb. Chenaan.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">These are the
three sonnes of Noah: and of them was the whole earth
ouerspread.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Noah began to
bee an husbandman, and he planted a vineyard.</ab>

<fw>Noahs generations.</fw>
<ab n="21">And he dranke of
the wine, and was drunken, and hee was vncouered within his
tent.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Ham, the
father of Canaan, saw the nakednesse of his father, and told his
two brethren without.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Shem and
Iaphet tooke a garment, and layed it vpon both their shoulders, and
went backward, and couered the nakednesse of their father, and
their faces were backward, and they saw not their fathers
nakednesse.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Noah awoke
from his wine, and knew what his yonger sonne had done vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he said,
Cursed bee Canaan: a seruant of seruants shall hee be vnto his
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="26">And hee saide,
Blessed bee the LORD God of Shem, and Canaan shalbe his
seruant.<note> Or, seruant to them.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">God shall enlarge
Iaphet, and he shal dwel in the tents of Shem, and Canaan shalbe
his seruant.<note> Or, perswade.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And Noah
liued after the flood, three hundred and fifty yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="29">And all the dayes
of Noah were nine hundred &amp; fifty yeeres, and he died.</ab>



</div>