<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJude_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/3-John-Chapter-1-1-Jude.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jude-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>Hee exhorteth them to bee constant
in the profession of the faith. 14 False teachers are crept in to
seduce them: for whose damnable doctrine and manners horrible
punishment is prepared: 20 Whereas the godly, by the assistance of
the holy Spirit, and prayers to God, may perseuere, and grow in
grace, and keepe themselues, and recouer others out of the snares
of those deceiuers.</head>

<ab n="1">Iude the
seruant of Iesus Christ, and brother of Iames, to them that are
sanctified by God the Father, and preserued in Iesus Christ, &amp;
called:</ab>
<ab n="2">Mercie vnto
you, and peace, and loue be multiplied.</ab>
<ab n="3">Beloued, when I
gaue all diligence to write vnto you of the common saluation: it
was needfull for mee to write vnto you, and exhort you that ye
should earnestly contend for the faith which was once deliuered
vnto the Saints.</ab>

<fw>Euill Angels.</fw>
<ab n="4">For there are
certaine men crept in vnawares, who were before of olde ordained to
this condemnation, vngodly men, turning the grace of our God into
lasciuiousnesse, and denying the onely Lord God, &amp; our Lord
Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="5">I will
therefore put you in remembrance, though ye once knew this, how
that the Lord hauing saued the people out of the land of Egypt
afterward destroied them that beleeued not.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Angels
which kept not their first estate, but left their own habitation,
he hath reserued in euerlasting chaines vnder darkenesse, vnto the
iudgement of the great day.<note> Or, principalitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Euen as Sodom
and Gomorrha, and the cities about them, in like maner giuing
themselues ouer to fornication, and going after strange flesh, are
set forth for an example, suffring the vengeance of eternall
fire.<note> Gr. other.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Likewise also
these filthy dreamers defile the flesh, despise dominion, and
speake euill of dignities.</ab>
<ab n="9">Yet Michael the
Archangel, when contending with the deuill, he disputed about the
body of Moses, durst not bring against him a railing accusation,
but said, The Lord rebuke thee.<note> Zac.3.2.</note></ab>

<fw>Balaams reward.</fw>
<ab n="10">But these
speake euill of those things, which they know not: but what they
knowe naturally, as brute beastes, in those things they corrupt
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wo vnto them,
for they haue gone in the way of Kain, and ranne greedily after the
errour of Balaam, for reward, and perished in the gainsaying of
Core.</ab>
<ab n="12">These are
spottes in your feasts of charitie, when they feast with you,
feeding themselues without feare: cloudes they are without water,
caried about of winds, trees whose fruit withereth, without fruit,
twise dead, plucked vp by the rootes.</ab>
<ab n="13">Raging waues
of the sea, foming out their owne shame, wandring stars, to whom is
reserued the blacknesse of darkenesse for euer.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Enoch
also, the seuenth from Adam, prophesied of these, saying, Behold,
the Lord commeth with ten thousands of his Saints,</ab>
<ab n="15">To execute
iudgement vpon all, and to conuince all that are vngodly among
them, of all their vngodly deeds which they haue vngodly committed,
and of all their heard speaches, which vngodly sinners haue spoken
against him.</ab>

<fw>The last time.</fw>
<ab n="16">These are
murmurers complainers, walking after their owne lustes, and their
mouth speaketh great swelling wordes, hauing mens persons in
admiration because of aduantage.</ab>
<ab n="17">But beloued,
remember yee the words, which were spoken before of the Apostles of
our Lord Iesus Christ:</ab>
<ab n="18">How that they
tolde you there should be mockers in the last time, who should
walke after their own vngodly lustes.</ab>
<ab n="19">These be they
who separate themselues, sensual, hauing not the spirit.</ab>
<ab n="20">But yee
beloued, building vp your selues on your most holy faith, praying
in the holy Ghost,</ab>
<ab n="21">Keepe your
selues in the loue of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Iesus
Christ vnto eternall life.</ab>
<ab n="22">And of some
haue compassion, making a difference:</ab>
<ab n="23">And others
saue with feare, pulling them out of the fire: hating euen the
garment spotted by the flesh.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now vnto him
that is able to keepe you from falling, and to present you
faultlesse before the presence of his glory with exceeding
ioy,</ab>
<ab n="25">To the onely
wise God our Sauiour, be glory and maiestie, dominion and power,
now and euer. Amen.</ab>



</div>