<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-21-21-Ruth.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 The people bewaile the desolation
of Beniamin. 8 By the destruction of Iabesh Gilead they prouide
them foure hundred wiues. 16 They aduise them to surprise the
virgines that daunced at Shiloh.</head>

<ab n="1">Nowe the men of
Israel had sworne in Mizpeh, saying, There shall not any of vs giue
his daughter vnto Beniamin to wife.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the people
came to the house of God, and abode there till euen before God, and
lift vp their voices, and wept sore:</ab>
<ab n="3">And said, O Lord
God of Israel, why is this come to passe in Israel, that there
should bee to day one tribe lacking in Israel?</ab>
<ab n="4">And it came to
passe on the morrow, that the people rose early, and built there an
Altar, and offered burnt offerings, and peace offerings.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the children
of Israel sayd, Who is there among all the tribes of Israel, that
came not vp with the congregation vnto the Lord ? for they had made
a great oath concerning him that came not vp to the Lord to Mizpeh,
saying, He shall surely be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the children
of Israel repented them for Beniamin their brother, and said, There
is one tribe cut off from Israel this day:</ab>

<fw>Care for wiues.</fw>
<ab n="7">How shall wee doe
for wiues for them that remaine, seeing wee haue sworne by the
Lord, that wee will not giue them of our daughters to
wiues?</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And they
said, What one is there of the tribes of Israel, that came not vp
to Mizpeh to the Lord ? And beholde, there came none to the campe
from Iabesh Gilead to the assembly.</ab>
<ab n="9">For the people
were numbred, and behold, there were none of the inhabitants of
Iabesh Gilead there.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
congregation sent thither twelue thousand men of the valiantest,
and commaunded them, saying, Goe, and smite the inhabitants of
Iabesh Gilead with the edge of the sword, with the women and the
children.</ab>
<ab n="11">And this is the
thing that yee shall doe, Yee shall vtterly destroy euery male, and
euery woman that hath lien by man.<note> Num. 31.17. , Heb. knoweth the lying with man.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they found
among the inhabitants of Iabesh Gilead, foure hundred yong virgins
that had knowen no man, by lying with any male: and they brought
them vnto the campe to Shiloh, which is in the land of
Canaan.<note> Hebr. yong women virgins.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the whole
Congregation sent some to speake to the children of Beniamin that
were in the rocke Rimmon, and to call peaceably vnto
them.<note> Hebr. and spake and called. , Or, proclaime peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Beniamin came
againe at that time, and they gaue them wiues which they had saued
aliue of the women of Iabesh Gilead: and yet so they sufficed them
not.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the people
repented them for Beniamin, because that the Lord had made a breach
in the tribes of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then the
Elders of the Congregation said, How shall we doe for wiues for
them that remaine? seeing the women are destroyed out of
Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they said,
There must be an inheritance for them that bee escaped of Beniamin,
that a tribe be not destroyed out of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">Howbeit wee may
not giue them wiues of our daughters. For the children of Israel
haue sworne, saying, Cursed be he that giueth a wife to
Beniamin.</ab>

<fw>VViues for the Beniamites.</fw>
<ab n="19">Then they said,
Behold, there is a feast of the Lord in Shiloh yerely, in a place
which is on the Northside of Bethel on the East side of the hie way
that goeth vp from Bethel to Shechem, and on the South of
Lebanon.<note> Heb. from yeere to yeere. , Or, towards the Sunne rising. , Or, on.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore they
commanded the children of Beniamin, saying, Goe and lie in wait in
the vineyards.</ab>
<ab n="21">And see, and
behold, if the daughters of Shiloh come out to daunce in daunces,
then come yee out of the vineyards, and catch you euery man his
wife of the daughters of Shiloh, and goe to the land of
Beniamin.</ab>

<fw>VViues for the Beniamites.</fw>
<ab n="22">And it shall bee
when their fathers or their brethren come vnto vs to complaine,
that we will say vnto them, Bee fauourable vnto them for our sakes:
because we reserued not to each man his wife in the warre: for yee
did not giue vnto them at this time, that you should be
guiltie.<note> Or, gratifie vs in them.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the children
of Beniamin did so, and tooke them wiues according to their number,
of them that daunced, whome they caught: and they went and returned
vnto their inheritance, and repaired the cities, and dwelt in
them.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the children
of Israel departed thence at that time, euery man to his tribe, and
to his family, and they went out from thence euery man to his
inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="25">In those dayes
there was no King in Israel: euery man did that which was right in
his owne eyes.<note> Chap.17. 6. and 18. 1. and 19.1.</note></ab>



</div>