<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Samson desireth a wife of the
Philistines. 2 In his iourney hee killeth a Lion. 8 In a second
iourney hee findeth hony in the carkeis. 10 Samsons marriage feast.
12 His riddle by his wife is made knowen. 19 He spoileth thirtie
Philistines. 20 His wife is married to another.</head>

<ab n="1">And Samson went
down to Timnath, and sawe a woman in Timnath, of the daughters of
the Philistines.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee came vp,
and told his father and his mother, and said, I haue seene a woman
in Timnath, of the daughters of the Philistines: nowe therefore get
her for me to wife.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then his father
and his mother said vnto him, Is there neuer a woman among the
daughters of thy brethren, or among all my people, that thou goest
to take a wife of the vncircumcised Philistines? And Samson said
vnto his father, Get her for me, for shee pleaseth me
well.<note> Heb. she is right in mine eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But his father and
his mother knew not that it was of the Lord, that hee sought an
occasion against the Philistines: for at that time the Philistines
had dominion ouer Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then went
Samson downe, and his father &amp; his mother, to Timnath, and
came, to the vineyards of Timnath: and behold, a young Lion roared
against him.<note> Hebr. in meeting him.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the Spirit of
the Lord came mightily vpon him, and hee rent him as he would haue
rent a kid, and he had nothing in his hand: but hee told not his
father or his mother what hee had done.</ab>

<fw>His riddle.</fw>
<ab n="7">And hee went downe
and talked with the woman, and she pleased Samson well.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And after a
time hee returned to take her, and he turned aside to see the
carkeis of the Lion: and beholde, there was a swarme of Bees, and
honie in the carkeis of the Lion.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee tooke
thereof in his handes, and went on eating, and came to his father
and mother, and hee gaue them, and they did eate: but he told not
them that he had taken the hony out of the carkeis of the
Lion.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ So his
father went downe vnto the woman, and Samson made there a feast:
for so vsed the young men to doe.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it came to
passe when they saw him, that they brought thirtie companions to be
with him.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Samson
said vnto them, I will now put foorth a riddle vnto you: if you can
certeinly declare it me, within the seuen dayes of the feast, and
finde it out, then I will giue you thirtie sheetes, and thirtie
change of garments:<note> Or, shirts</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But if ye cannot
declare it me, then shall yee giue me thirtie sheetes, and thirtie
change of garments. And they said vnto him, Put foorth thy riddle,
that we may heare it.</ab>
<ab n="14">And hee said vnto
them, Out of the eater came foorth meate, aud out of the strong
came foorth sweetnesse. And they could not in three dayes expound
the riddle.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe on the seuenth day, that they said vnto Samsons wife, Entice
thy husband, that hee may declare vnto vs the riddle, lest we burne
thee and thy fathers house with fire: Haue yee called vs, to take
that wee haue? is it not so?<note> Heb. to possesse vs, or to impouerish vs?</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Samsons wife
wept before him, and said, Thou doest but hate me, and louest me
not: thou hast put foorth a riddle vnto the children of my people,
and hast not tolde it me. And hee said vnto her, Behold, I haue not
tolde it my father nor my mother, and shall I tell it thee?</ab>
<ab n="17">And shee wept
before him the seuen dayes, while the feast lasted: and it came to
passe on the seuenth day, that he tolde her, because shee lay sore
vpon him: and she tolde the riddle to the children of her
people.<note> Or, the rest of the seuen dayes, &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>His foxe-tailes:</fw>
<ab n="18">And the men of
the city said vnto him on the seuenth day before the sunne went
downe, What is sweeter then honie? and what is stronger then a
Lion? And he said vnto them, If ye had not plowed with my heifer,
yee had not found out my riddle.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And the
Spirit of the Lord came vpon him, and hee went downe to Ashkelon,
and slewe thirtie men of them, and tooke their spoile, and gaue
change of garments vnto them which expounded the riddle, and his
anger was kindled; and hee went vp to his fathers
house.<note> Or, apparel.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But Samsons wife
was giuen to his companion, whom hee had vsed as his
friend.</ab>



</div>