<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Of the money that Micah first
stole, then restored, his mother maketh Images, 5 and hee ornaments
for them. 6 He hireth a Leuite to be his Priest.</head>

<ab n="1">And there was a
man of mount Ephraim, whose name was Micah.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he said vnto
his mother, The eleuen hundred shekels of siluer, that were taken
from thee, about which thou cursedst, and spakest of also in mine
eares, behold, the siluer is with mee, I tooke it. And his mother
said, Blessed be thou of the Lord, my sonne.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when hee had
restored the eleuen hundred shekels of siluer to his mother, his
mother said, I had wholly dedicated the siluer vnto the Lord, from
my hand, for my sonne, to make a grauen image and a molten image:
now therefore I will restore it vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Yet hee restored
the money vnto his mother, and his mother tooke two hundred shekels
of siluer, and gaue them to the founder, who made thereof a grauen
image and a molten image, and they were in the house of
Micah.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the man Micah
had an house of gods, and made an Ephod, and Teraphim, and
consecrated one of his sonnes, who became his Priest.<note> Chap.8. 27. , Gen.31.19. ose.3.4. , Hebr. filled the hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In those dayes
there was no king in Israel, but euery man did that which was right
in his owne eyes.<note> Chap.18. 1. and 21. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And there
was a young man out of Bethlehem Iudah, of the family of Iudah, who
was a Leuite, and he soiourned there.</ab>

<fw>Spies of Dan search Laish,</fw>
<ab n="8">And the man
departed out of the citie from Bethlehem Iudah, to soiourne where
he could finde a place: and he came to mount Ephraim to the house
of Micah, as he iourneyed.<note> Heb. in making his way.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Micah said
vnto him, Whence commest thou? And he said vnto him, I am a Leuite,
of Bethlehem Iudah, and I goe to soiourne where I may finde a
place.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Micah said
vnto him, Dwell with me, and be vnto me a father and a Priest, and
I will giue thee ten shekels of siluer by the yeere, and a suite of
apparell, and thy victuals. So the Leuite went in.<note> Or, a double suit, &amp;c. Heb. an order of garments.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the Leuite
was content to dwell with the man, and the yong man was vnto him as
one of his sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Micah
consecrated the Leuite, and the young man became his Priest, and
was in the house of Micah.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then said Micah,
Now know I that the Lord will doe me good, seeing I haue a Leuite
to my Priest.</ab>



</div>