<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Deborah and Barak deliuer them
from Iabin and Sisera. 18 Iael killeth Sisera.</head>

<ab n="1">And the
children of Israel againe did euil in the sight of the Lord, when
Ehud was dead.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
sold them into the hande of Iabin king of Canaan: that reigned in
Hazor, the captaine of whose host was Sisera, which dwelt in
Harosheth of the Gentiles.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the
children of Israel cried vnto the Lord: for he had nine hundred
charets of yron: and twentie yeres hee mightily oppressed the
children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
Deborah a prophetesse, the wife of Lapidoth, shee iudged Israel at
that time.</ab>
<ab n="5">And shee
dwelt vnder the palme tree of Deborah, betweene Ramah and Bethel in
mount Ephraim: and the children of Israel came vp to her for
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="6">And shee sent
and called Barak the sonne of Abinoam, out of Kedesh-Naphtali, and
said vnto him, Hath not the Lord God of Israel commaunded, saying,
Goe, and drawe toward mount Tabor, and take with thee ten thousand
men of the children of Naphtali, and of the children of
Zebulun?</ab>
<ab n="7">And I wil
draw vnto thee to the riuer Kishon, Sisera the captaine of Iabins
army, with his charets, and his multitude, and I will deliuer him
into thine hand.<note> Psal.83. 9, 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Barak
said vnto her, If thou wilt goe with me, then I wil goe: but if
thou wilt not goe with mee, then I will not goe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And she said,
I wil surely go with thee, notwithstanding the iourney that thou
takest, shal not be for thine honor: for the Lord shall sell Sisera
into the hand of a woman. And Deborah arose, &amp; went with Barak
to Kedesh.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And Barak
called Zebulun, and Naphtali to Kedesh, and he went vp with ten
thousand men at his feete: and Deborah went vp with him.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now Heber the
Kenite, which was of the children of Hobab the father in law of
Moses, had seuered himselfe from the Kenites, and pitched his tent
vnto the plaine of Zaanaim, which is by Kedesh.<note> Numb.10 29.</note></ab>

<fw>Sisera is slaine.</fw>
<ab n="12">And they shewed
Sisera, that Barak the sonne of Abinoam was gone vp to mount
Tabor.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Sisera
gathered together all his charets, euen nine hundred charets of
iron, and al the people that were with him, from Harosheth of the
Gentiles, vnto the riuer of Kishon.<note> Hebr. gathered by cry or proclamation.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Deborah said
vnto Barak, Up, for this is the day in which the Lord hath
deliuered Sisera into thine hand: Is not the Lord gone out before
thee? so Barak went downe from mount Tabor, and ten thousand men
after him.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Lord
discomfited Sisera, and all his charets, and all his hoste with the
edge of the sword, before Barak: so that Sisera lighted downe off
his charet, and fled away on his feet.<note> Psal.83. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But Barak pursued
after the charets, and after the hoste vnto Harosheth of the
Gentiles, and all the host of Sisera fell vpon the edge of the
sword; and there was not a man left.<note> Hebr. vnto one.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Howbeit Sisera
fled away on his feet, to the tent of Iael the wife of Heber the
Kenite: for there was peace betweene Iabin the king of Hazor, and
the house of Heber the Kenite.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And Iael
went out to meete Sisera, and said vnto him, Turne in, my lord,
turne in to me, feare not. And when hee had turned in vnto her,
into the tent, shee couered him with a mantle.<note> Or, rugge, or blanket.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And he said vnto
her, Giue me, I pray thee, a litle water to drinke, for I am
thirstie. And she opened a bottle of milke, and gaue him drinke,
and couered him.<note> Chap.5. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Againe he said
vnto her, Stand in the doore of the tent, and it shall bee when any
man doeth come and enquire of thee and say, Is there any man here?
that thou shalt say, No.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then Iael Hebers
wife, tooke a naile of the tent, and tooke an hammer in her hand,
and went softly vnto him, and smote the naile into his temples, and
fastened it into the ground: (for he was fast asleepe, and weary;)
so he died.<note> Hebr. put.</note></ab>

<fw>Thankesgiuing.</fw>
<ab n="22">And behold, as
Barak pursued Sisera, Iael came out to meet him, and said vnto him,
Come, and I will shew thee the man whom thou seekest. And when he
came into her tent, behold, Sisera lay dead, and the naile was in
his temples.</ab>
<ab n="23">So God subdued on
that day, Iabin the king of Canaan, before the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the hand of
the children of Israel prospered, &amp; preuailed against Iabin the
king of Canaan, vntill they had destroyed Iabin king of
Canaan.<note> Hebr. going, went and was hard.</note></ab>



</div>