<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Israel is in the hand of the
Philistines. 2 An Angel appeareth to Manoahs wife. 8 The Angel
appeareth to Manoah. 15 Manoahs sacrifice, whereby the Angel is
discouered. 24 Samson is borne.</head>

<ab n="1">And the children
of Israel did euill againe in the sight of the Lord, and the Lord
deliuered them into the hand of the Philistines forty
yeeres.<note> Hebr. added to commit, &amp;c. , Chap.2.11, and 3.7. and 4.1. and 6.1. and 10.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ And there
was a certaine man of Zorah, of the family of the Danites, whose
name was Manoah, and his wife was barren, and bare not.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the Angel of
the Lord appeared vnto the woman, and said vnto her, Behold now,
thou art barren, and bearest not: but thou shalt conceiue and beare
a sonne.</ab>
<ab n="4">Now therefore
beware I pray thee, and drinke not wine, nor strong drinke, and eat
not any vncleane thing.<note> Num.6. 2,3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For loe, thou
shalt conceiue, and beare a sonne, and no rasor shall come on his
head: for the child shall be a Nazarite vnto God from the wombe:
and he shall begin to deliuer Israel out of the hand of the
Philistines.<note> Num.6.5. 1.sam. 1. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then the
woman came, and told her husband, saying; A man of God came vnto
mee, and his countenance was like the countenance of an Angel of
God, very terrible: but I asked him not whence he was, neither told
he me his name:</ab>
<ab n="7">But he said vnto
mee, Behold, thou shalt conceiue and beare a sonne; and now, drinke
no wine nor strong drinke, neither eate any vncleane thing: for the
childe shal be a Nazarite to God, from the wombe, to the day of his
death.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Then Manoah
entreated the Lord, and said, O my Lord, let the man of God which
thou didst send, come againe vnto vs, &amp; teach vs what we shall
do vnto the childe that shall be borne.</ab>

<fw>Samsons birth is foretolde.</fw>
<ab n="9">And God hearkened
to the voyce of Manoah; and the Angel of God came againe vnto the
woman as shee sate in the field: But Manoah her husband was not
with her.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the woman
made haste, and ranne, and shewed her husband, and said vnto him;
Behold, the man hath appeared vnto me, that came vnto me the other
day.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Manoah arose,
and went after his wife, and came to the man, and said vnto him,
Art thou the man that spakest vnto the woman? And he said, I
am.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Manoah said,
Now let thy words come to passe: How shall wee order the childe,
and how shall we doe vnto him?<note> Hebr. what shall be the maner of the, &amp;c. , Or, what shall he doe? Hebr. What shall be his worke?</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the Angel of
the Lord said vnto Manoah, Of all that I said vnto the woman, let
her beware.</ab>
<ab n="14">She may not eate
of any thing that commeth of the Uine, neither let her drinke wine
or strong drinke, nor eat any vncleane thing: all that I commanded
her, let her obserue.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And Manoah
saide vnto the Angel of the Lord, I pray thee let vs deteine thee,
vntill wee shall haue made ready a kid for thee.<note> Hebr. before thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the Angel of
the Lord said vnto Manoah, Though thou deteine mee, I will not eat
of thy bread: and if thou wilt offer a burnt offering, thou must
offer it vnto the Lord: for Manoah knew not that he was an Angel of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Manoah said
vnto the Angel of the Lord, What is thy name, that when thy sayings
come to passe, we may doe thee honour?</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Angel of
the Lord said vnto him, Why askest thou thus after my name, seeing
it is secret?<note> Or, wonderfull.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">So Manoah tooke a
kid, with a meat offering, and offered it vpon a rocke vnto the
Lord: and the Angel did wonderously, and Manoah and his wife looked
on.</ab>
<ab n="20">For it came to
passe, when the flame went vp toward heauen from off the altar,
that the Angel of the Lord ascended in the flame of the altar: and
Manoah and his wife looked on it, and fell on their faces to the
ground.</ab>
<ab n="21">(But the Angel of
the Lord did no more appeare to Manoah and to his wife:) then
Manoah knewe that he was an Angel of the Lord.</ab>

<fw>Samsons mariage:</fw>
<ab n="22">And Manoah said
vnto his wife, Wee shall surely die, because wee haue seene
God.<note> Exod. 33. 20. chap. 6. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But his wife said
vnto him, If the Lord were pleased to kill vs, he would not haue
receiued a burnt offering and a meat offering at our hands, neither
would hee haue shewed vs all these things, nor would as at this
time haue told vs such things as these.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And the
woman bare a sonne, and called his name Samson: and the child grew,
&amp; the Lord blessed him.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the Spirit of
the Lord beganne to mooue him at times in the campe of Dan,
betweene Zorah and Eshtaol.</ab>



</div>