<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 An Angel rebuketh the people at
Bochim. 6 The wickednesse of the new generation after Ioshua. 14
Gods anger and pitie towards them. 20 The Canaanites are left to
prooue Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">And an Angel
of the Lord came vp from Gilgal to Bochim, and said, I made you to
goe vp out of Egypt, and haue brought you vnto the land which I
sware vnto your fathers, and I said, I will neuer breake my
Couenant with you.<note> Or, messenger.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And yee shall
make no league with the inhabitants of this land, you shal throw
downe their altars: But ye haue not obeyed my voyce; Why haue ye
done this?<note> Deut.7.2. , Deut. 12. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore I
also said, I will not driue them out from before you: but they
shalbe as thornes in your sides, and their gods shalbe a snare vnto
you.<note> Iosh.23. 13. , Exod. 23. 33. and 34. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And it came
to passe when the Angel of the Lord spake these words vnto all the
children of Israel, that the people lift vp their voice, and
wept.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they
called the name of that place Bochim: and they sacrificed there
vnto the Lord.<note> That is, weepers.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
when Ioshua had let the people goe, the children of Israel went
euery man vnto his inheritance, to possesse the land.</ab>

<fw>Ioshuas buriall.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the
people serued the Lord all the dayes of Ioshua, and all the dayes
of the Elders that outliued Ioshua, who had seene all the great
workes of the Lord, that hee did for Israel.<note> Hebr. prolonged dayes after Ioshua.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Ioshua
the sonne of Nun, the seruant of the Lord died, being an hundred
and ten yeeres old.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they
buried him in the border of his inheritance in Timnath-Heres, in
the mount of Ephraim, on the North side of the hill Gaash.</ab>
<ab n="10">And also all that
generation were gathered vnto their fathers: and there arose
another generation after them, which knew not the Lord, nor yet the
woorkes which hee had done for Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
children of Israel did euil in the sight of the Lord, and serued
Baalim:</ab>
<ab n="12">And they forsooke
the Lord God of their fathers, which brought them out of the land
of Egypt, and followed other gods, of the gods of the people that
were round about them, and bowed themselues vnto them, and prouoked
the Lord to anger.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they forsooke
the Lord, and serued Baal and Ashtaroth.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And the
anger of the Lord was hote against Israel, and he deliuered them
into the hands of spoilers that spoiled them, and he sold them into
the hands of their enemies round about, so that they could not any
longer stand before their enemies.<note> Psal.44. 12. isa.50. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Whither soeuer
they went out, the hand of the Lord was against them for euill, as
the Lord had said, and as the Lord had sworne vnto them: and they
were greatly distressed.<note> Leuit.26 deut.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶
Neuerthelesse, the Lord raysed vp Iudges, which deliuered them out
of the hand of those that spoyled them.<note> Hebr. saued.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And yet they would
not hearken vnto their Iudges, but they went a whoring after other
gods, and bowed themselues vnto them: they turned quickly out of
the way, which their fathers walked in, obeying the Commandements
of the Lord; but they did not so.</ab>

<fw>Israel obstinate.</fw>
<ab n="18">And when the Lord
raised them vp Iudges, then the Lord was with the Iudge, and
deliuered them out of the hand of their enemies, all the dayes of
the Iudge (for it repented the Lord, because of their gronings by
reason of them that oppressed them, and vexed them:)</ab>
<ab n="19">And it came to
passe when the Iudge was dead, that they returned, and corrupted
themselues more then their fathers, in following other gods, to
serue them, and to bow downe vnto them: they ceased not from their
owne doings, nor from their stubborne way.<note> Chap.3. 11. , Or, were corrupt. , Hebr. they let nothing fall of their.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And the
anger of the Lord was hote against Israel, and he said, Because
that this people hath transgressed my Couenant which I commanded
their fathers, and haue not hearkened vnto my voice:</ab>
<ab n="21">I also will not
henceforth driue out any from before them of the nations which
Ioshua left when he died:</ab>
<ab n="22">That through them
I may proue Israel, whether they will keepe the way of the Lord, to
walke therein, as their fathers did keepe it, or not.</ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore the Lord
left those nations, without driuing them out hastily, neither
deliuered he them into the hand of Ioshua.<note> Or, suffred.</note></ab>



</div>