<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Abimelech by conspiracie with the
Shechemites, and murder of his brethren, is made King. 7 Iotham by
a parable rebuketh them and foretelleth their ruine. 22 Gaal
conspireth with the Shechemites against him. 30 Zebul reuealeth it.
34 Abimelech ouercommeth them, and soweth the citie with salt. 46
Hee burneth the holde of the god Berith. 50 At Thebez he is slaine
by a piece of a milstone. 56 Iothams curse is
fulfilled.</head>


<fw>Iothams parable.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Abimelech
the sonne of Ierubbaal went to Shechem, vnto his mothers brethren,
and communed with them, and with all the family of the house of his
mothers father, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake, I
pray you, in the eares of all the men of Shechem; Whether is better
for you, either that all the sonnes of Ierubbaal (which are
threescore and ten persons) reigne ouer you, or that one reigne
ouer you? Remember also, that I am your bone, and your
flesh.<note> Heb. What is good? whether &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And his
mothers brethren spake of him in the eares of all the men of
Shechem, all these wordes, and their hearts inclined to follow
Abimelech: for they said, He is our brother.<note> Heb. after.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And they gaue
him threescore and ten pieces of siluer, out of the house of
Baal-Berith, wherewith Abimelech hired vaine &amp; light persons,
which followed him.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee went
vnto his fathers house at Ophrah, and slewe his brethren the sonnes
of Ierubbaal, being threescore and tenne persons, vpon one stone:
notwithstanding, yet Iotham the youngest sonne of Ierubbaal was
left; for he hid himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="6">And all the
men of Shechem gathered together, and all the house of Millo, and
went, and made Abimelech King, by the plaine of the pillar that was
in Shechem.<note> Or, by the oke of the pillar. See Iosh.24. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And
when they told it to Iotham, he went and stood in the top of mount
Gerizim, and lift vp his voice, and cried, and said vnto them,
Hearken vnto mee, you men of Shechem, that God may hearken vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="8">The trees
went foorth on a time to annoint a King ouer them, and they said
vnto the Oliue tree, Reigne thou ouer vs.</ab>
<ab n="9">But the Oliue
tree saide vnto them, Should I leaue my fatnesse, wherewith by mee
they honour God and man, and goe to bee promoted ouer the
trees?<note> Or, goe vp and downe for other trees.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the trees said
to the Figge tree, Come thou, and reigne ouer vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">But the Figge tree
saide vnto them, Should I forsake my sweetenesse, and my good
fruit, and goe to be promoted ouer the trees?</ab>
<ab n="12">Then saide the
trees vnto the Uine, Come thou, and reigne ouer vs.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Uine said
vnto them, Should I leaue my wine, which cheareth God and man, and
goe to bee promoted ouer the trees?</ab>

<fw>Gaal conspireth against
Abimelech:</fw>
<ab n="14">Then said all the
trees vnto the Bramble, Come thou, and reigne ouer vs.<note> Or, thistle.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the Bramble
said vnto the trees, If in trueth ye anoint me King ouer you, then
come, and put your trust in my shadow: and if not, let fire come
out of the Bramble, and deuoure the Cedars of Lebanon.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now therefore, if
yee haue done truely and sincerely, in that yee haue made Abimelech
King, and if yee haue dealt well with Ierubbaal, and his house, and
haue done vnto him according to the deseruing of his hands:</ab>
<ab n="17">(For my father
fought for you, and aduentured his life farre, and deliuered you
out of the hand of Midian:<note> Heb. cast his life.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And yee are risen
vp against my fathers house this day, and haue slaine his sonnes,
threescore aud ten persons, vpon one stone, and haue made Abimelech
the sonne of his maidseruant, king ouer the men of Shechem, because
he is your brother.)</ab>
<ab n="19">If yee then haue
dealt truely and sincerely with Ierubbaal, and with his house this
day, then reioyce yee in Abimelech, aud let him also reioyce in
you.</ab>
<ab n="20">But if not, let
fire come out from Abimelech, and deuoure the men of Shechem and
the house of Millo: and let fire come out from the men of Shechem,
and from the house of Millo, and deuoure Abimeleeh.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Iotham ran
away, and fled, and went to Beer, and dwelt there for feare of
Abimeleeh his brother.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ When
Abimelech had reigned three yeeres ouer Israel,</ab>
<ab n="23">Then God sent an
euill spirit betweene Abimelech &amp; the men of Shechem: and the
men of Shechem dealt treacherously with Abimelech:</ab>
<ab n="24">That the crueltie
done to the threescore and ten sonnes of Ierubbaal might come, and
their blood be laid vpon Abimelech their brother which slew them,
and vpon the men of Shechem which aided him in the killing of his
brethren.<note> Hebr. strengthened his hands to kill.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And the men of
Shechem set lyers in wait for him in the toppe of the mountaines,
and they robbed all that came along that way by them: and it was
told Abimelech.</ab>

<fw>Gaal conspireth against
Abimelech:</fw>
<ab n="26">And Gaal the sonne
of Ebed came with his brethren, and went ouer to Shechem: and the
men of Shechem put their confidence in him.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they went out
into the fields, and gathered their vineyards, and trode the
grapes, and made merry, and went into the house of their god, and
did eate and drinke, and cursed Abimelech.<note> Or, songs.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And Gaal the sonne
of Ebed said, Who is Abimelech, and who is Shechem, that we should
serue him? Is not he the sonne of Ierubbaal? and Zebul his officer?
serue the men of Hamor the father of Shechem: for why should we
serue him?</ab>
<ab n="29">And would to God
this people were vnder my hand; then would I remoue Abimelech. And
he said to Abimelech, Increase thine armie and come out.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And when
Zebul the ruler of the citie heard the wordes of Gaal the sonne of
Ebed, his anger was kindled.<note> Or, hate.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And he sent
messengers vnto Abimelech priuily, saying, Behold, Gaal the sonne
of Ebed, and his brethren, be come to Shechem, and behold, they
fortifie the citie against thee.<note> Heb. craftily, or to Tormah.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Now therefore vp
by night, thou and the people that is with thee, and lie in wait in
the field.</ab>
<ab n="33">And it shalbe,
that in the morning assoone as the Sunne is vp, thou shalt rise
earely, and set vpon the citie: and behold, when he and the people
that is with him, come out against thee, then mayest thou doe to
them as thou shalt finde occasion.<note> Hebr. as thine hand shall find.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">¶ And
Abimelech rose vp, and all the people that were with him, by night,
and they laid wait against Shechem in foure companies.</ab>
<ab n="35">And Gaal the sonne
of Ebed went out, and stood in the entring of the gate of the
citie: and Abimelech rose vp, and the people that were with him,
from lying in waite.</ab>
<ab n="36">And when Gaal saw
the people, he said to Zebul, Behold, there come people downe
frō the top of the mountaines. And Zebul saide vnto him, Thou
seest the shadow of the mountaines, as if they were men.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Gaal spake
againe, and said, See, there come people downe by the middle of the
land, and another companie come along by the plaine of
Meonenim.<note> Heb. nauell , Or, the regarders of times.</note></ab>

<fw>He is ouercome.</fw>
<ab n="38">Then said Zebul
vnto him, Where is now thy mouth, wherwith thou saidst, Who is
Abimelech, that wee should serue him? Is not this the people that
thou hast despised? Goe out, I pray now, and fight with
them.</ab>
<ab n="39">And Gaal went out
before the men of Shechem, and fought with Abimelech.</ab>
<ab n="40">And Abimelech
chased him, and hee fledde before him, and many were ouerthrowen
and wounded, euen vnto the entring of the gate.</ab>
<ab n="41">And Abimelech
dwelt at Arumah: and Zebul thrust out Gaal and his brethren, that
they should not dwell in Shechem.</ab>
<ab n="42">And it came to
passe on the morrow, that the people went out into the field, and
they tolde Abimelech.</ab>
<ab n="43">And he tooke the
people, and diuided them into three companies, and laide waite in
the field, and looked, and behold, the people were come forth out
of the citie, and he rose vp against them, and smote them.</ab>
<ab n="44">And Abimelech, and
the companie that was with him, rushed forward, and stood in the
entring of the gate of the citie: and the two other companies ranne
vpon all the people that were in the fields, and slew them.</ab>
<ab n="45">And Abimelech
fought against the citie all that day, and he tooke the citie, and
slewe the people that was therein, and beat downe the citie, and
sowed it with salt.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ And when
all the men of the tower of Shechem heard that, they entred into an
holde of the house of the god Berith.</ab>
<ab n="47">And it was told
Abimelech, that all the men of the towre of Shechem were gathered
together.</ab>
<ab n="48">And Abimelech gate
him vp to mount Zalmon, hee and all the people that were with him,
&amp; Abimelech tooke an axe in his hand, and cut downe a bough
from the trees, and tooke it, and laide it on his shoulder, and
said vnto the people that were with him, What ye haue seene me doe,
make haste, and doe as I haue done.<note> Heb. I haue done.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">And all the people
likewise cut downe euery man his bough, and followed Abimelech, and
put them to the holde, and set the holde on fire vpon them: so that
all the men of the towre of Shechem died also, about a thousand men
and women.</ab>

<fw>Abimelech slaine.</fw>
<ab n="50">¶ Then went
Abimelech to Thebez, and encamped against Thebez, and tooke
it.</ab>
<ab n="51">But there was a
strong towre within the city, and thither fled all the men and
women, and all they of the citie, and shut it to them, and gate
them vp to the top of the towre.</ab>
<ab n="52">And Abimelech came
vnto the towre, and fought against it, and went hard vnto the doore
of the towre, to burne it with fire.</ab>
<ab n="53">And a certaine
woman cast a piece of a milstone vpon Abimelechs head, and all to
brake his scull.<note> 2.Sam. 11.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">Then hee called
hastily vnto the young man his armour-bearer, and said vnto him,
Draw thy sword, and slay me, that men say not of me, A woman slewe
him: and his young man thrust him through, and he died.</ab>
<ab n="55">And when the men
of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, they departed euery man vnto
his place.</ab>
<ab n="56">¶ Thus God
rendred the wickednesse of Abimelech which hee did vnto his father,
in slaying his seuentie brethren.</ab>
<ab n="57">And all the euill
of the men of Shechem, did God render vpon their heads: and vpon
them came the curse of Iotham the sonne of Ierubbaal.</ab>



</div>