<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Gideon pacifieth the Ephraimites.
4 Succoth and Penuel refuse to relieue Gideons army. 10 Zebah and
Zalmunna are taken. 13 Succoth and Penuel are destroyed. 17 Gideon
reuengeth his brethrens death on Zebah and Zalmunna. 22 Hee
refuseth gouernment. 24 His Ephod cause of Idolatry. 28 Midian
subdued. 29 Gideons children, and death. 33 The Israelites
idolatry, and ingratitude.</head>


<fw>Zebah and Zalmunna slaine.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the men
of Ephraim said vnto him, Why hast thou serued vs thus, that thou
calledst vs not when thou wentest to fight with the Midianites? And
they did chide with him sharpely.<note> Hebr. what thing is this, thou hast done vnto vs? , Hebr. strongly.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he said
vnto them, What haue I done now in comparison of you? Is not the
gleaning of the grapes of Ephraim better then the vintage of
Abiezer?</ab>
<ab n="3">God hath
deliuered into your hands the princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb: and
what was I able to doe in comparison of you? then their anger was
abated toward him, when he had said that.<note> Heb. spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
Gideon came to Iordan, and passed ouer, hee, and the three hundred
men that were with him, faint, yet pursuing them.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he said
vnto the men of Succoth, Giue, I pray you, loaues of bread vnto the
people that follow me, for they bee faint, and I am pursuing after
Zebah and Zalmunna, kings of Midian.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And
the princes of Succoth said, Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna
now in thine hands, that wee should giue bread vnto thine
armie?</ab>
<ab n="7">And Gideon
said, Therfore when the Lord hath deliuered Zebah and Zalmunna into
mine hand, then I wil teare your flesh with the thornes of the
wildernesse, and with briers.<note> Heb. thresh</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And he
went vp thence to Penuel, and spake vnto them likewise: and the men
of Penuel answered him, as the men of Succoth had answered
him.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he spake
also vnto the men of Penuel, saying, When I come againe in peace, I
will breake downe this towre.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Now Zebah
and Zalmunna were in Karkor, and their hostes with them, about
fifteene thousand men, all that were left of all the hosts of the
children of the East: for there fell an hundred and twentie
thousand men that drew sword.<note> Or, an hundreth and twenty thousand, euery one drawing a sword.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And Gideon
went vp by the way of them that dwelt in tents, on the East of
Nobah, and Iogbehah, and smote the host: for the host was
secure.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when Zebah and
Zalmunna fled, he pursued after them, and took the two kings of
Midian, Zebah, and Zalmunna, &amp; discomfited all the
host.<note> Heb. terrified.</note></ab>

<fw>Zebah and Zalmunna slaine.</fw>
<ab n="13">¶ And Gideon
the sonne of Ioash returned from battel before the Sunne was
vp,</ab>
<ab n="14">And caught a yong
man of the men of Succoth, and enquired of him: and he described
vnto him the princes of Succoth and the elders thereof, euen
threescore and seuenteene men.<note> Heb. writ.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he came vnto
the men of Succoth, and said, Behold Zebah and Zalmunna, with whom
ye did vpbraid me, saying, Are the handes of Zebah and Zalmunna now
in thine hand, that we should giue bread vnto thy men that are
wearie?</ab>
<ab n="16">And hee tooke the
Elders of the citie, and thornes of the wildernes, and briers, and
with them hee taught the men of Succoth.<note> Heb. made to know.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And he beat downe
the towre of Penuel, and slew the men of the citie.<note> 1.King.12 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then said
he vnto Zebah and Zalmunna, What maner of men were they whom ye
slew at Tabor? And they answered, As thou art, so were they, ech
one resembled the children of a king.<note> Heb. according to the forme, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And hee said, They
were my brethren, euen the sonnes of my mother: as the Lord liueth,
if yee had saued them aliue, I would not slay you.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he said vnto
Iether his first borne, Up, and slay them: but the youth drew not
his sword: for he feared, because he was yet a youth.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then Zebah and
Zalmunna said, Rise thou, and fall vpon vs: for as the man is, so
is his strength. And Gideon arose, and slewe Zebah and Zalmunna,
&amp; tooke away the ornaments that were on their camels
neckes.<note> Or, ornaments like the moone.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Then the
men of Israel saide vnto Gideon, Rule thou ouer vs, both thou, and
thy sonne, &amp; thy sonnes sonne also: for thou hast deliuered vs
from the hand of Midian.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Gideon said
vnto them, I will not rule ouer you, neither shall my sonne rule
ouer you: the Lord shall rule ouer you.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And Gideon
said vnto them, I would desire a request of you, that you would
giue me euery man the earerings of his pray. For they had golden
eare-rings, because they were Ishmaelites.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they answered,
We will willingly giue them. And they spread a garment, and did
cast therein, euery man the earerings of his pray.</ab>

<fw>Gideon dieth.</fw>
<ab n="26">And the weight of
the golden eare-rings that hee requested, was a thousand and seuen
hundred shekels of gold, beside ornaments, and collars, &amp;
purple raiment that was on the kings of Midian, and beside the
chaines that were about their camels necks.<note> Or, sweete iewels.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And Gideon made an
Ephod thereof, and put it in his citie, euen in Ophrah: and all
Israel went thither a whoring after it; which thing became a snare
vnto Gideon, and to his house.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Thus was
Midian subdued before the children of Israel; so that they lifted
vp their heads no more: and the countrey was in quietnesse fourtie
yeeres, in the dayes of Gideon.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And
Ierubbaal the sonne of Ioash went &amp; dwelt in his owne
house.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Gideon had
threescore and ten sonnes of his body begotten: for he had many
wiues.<note> Heb. going out of his thigh.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And his concubine
that was in Shechem, shee also bare him a sonne, whose name he
called Abimelech.<note> Heb. set.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And Gideon
the sonne of Ioash died, in a good olde age, and was buried in the
sepulchre of Ioash his father, in Ophrah of the
Abi-Ezrites.</ab>
<ab n="33">And it came to
passe as soone as Gideon was dead, that the children of Israel
turned againe, and went a whoring after Baalim, and made
Baal-Berith their god.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the children
of Israel remembred not the Lord their God, who had deliuered them
out of the hands of all their enemies, on euery side:</ab>
<ab n="35">Neither shewed
they kindnesse to the house of Ierubbaal, namely Gideon, according
to all the goodnesse which he had shewed vnto Israel.</ab>



</div>