<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Tola iudgeth Israel in Shamir. 3
Iair, whose thirtie sonnes had thirtie cities. 6 The Philistines
and Ammonites oppresse Israel. 10 In their miserie, God sendeth
them to their false gods. 15 Vpon their repentance, hee pitieth
them.</head>

<ab n="1">And after
Abimelech, there arose to defend Israel, Tola the sonne of Puah,
the sonne of Dodo, a man of Issachar, and he dwelt in Shamir in
mount Ephraim.<note> Or, deliuer. Heb. saue.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he iudged
Israel twenty and three yeeres, and died, and was buried in
Shamir.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And after
him arose Iair a Gileadite, and iudged Israel twentie and two
yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee had
thirtie sonnes that rode on thirtie asse-colts, and they had
thirtie cities, which are called Hauoth-Iair vnto this day, which
are in the land of Gilead.<note> Or, the villages of Iair.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Iair died, and
was buried in Camon.</ab>

<fw>Israel punished.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
children of Israel did euill againe in the sight of the Lord, and
serued Baalim and Ashtaroth, and the gods of Syria, and the gods of
Zidon, and the gods of Moab, and the gods of the children of Ammon,
and the gods of the Philistines, and forsooke the Lord, and serued
not him.<note> Chap.2. 11, and 3.7. and 4.1. &amp; 6.1. &amp; 13.1. , Chap.2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the anger of
the Lord was hot agaiust Israel, and hee solde them into the hands
of the Philistines, and into the hands of the children of
Ammon.</ab>
<ab n="8">And that yere they
vexed and oppressed the children of Israel: eighteene yeeres, all
the children of Israel that were on the other side Iordan, in the
land of the Amorites, which is in Gilead.<note> Hebr. crushed.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Moreouer, the
children of Ammon passed ouer Iordan, to fight also against Iudah,
and against Beniamin, and against the house of Ephraim; so that
Israel was sore distressed.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
children of Israel cried vnto the Lord, saying, Wee haue sinned
against thee, both because wee haue forsaken our God, and also
serued Baalim.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord said
vnto the children of Israel, Did not I deliuer you from the
Egyptians, and from the Amorites, from the children of Ammon, and
from the Philistines?</ab>
<ab n="12">The Zidonians
also and the Amalekites, and the Maonites did oppresse you, and ye
cried to me, and I deliuered you out of their hand.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yet ye haue
forsaken me, and serued other gods: wherefore I will deliuer you no
more.<note> Deut.32. 15. ierem.2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Go, and cry vnto
the gods which ye haue chosen, let them deliuer you in the time of
your tribulation.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And the
children of Israel said vnto the Lord, We haue sinned, doe thou
vnto vs whatsoeuer seemeth good vnto thee, deliuer vs onely, wee
pray thee, this day.<note> Hebr. is good in thine eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And they put away
the strange gods from among them, and serued the Lord: and his
soule was grieued for the misery of Israel.<note> Hebr. gods of strangers. , Hebr. was shortened.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Then the children
of Ammon were gathered together, and encamped in Gilead: and the
children of Israel assembled themselues together, and encamped in
Mizpeh.<note> Hebr. cried together.</note></ab>

<fw>Iephthah expelled.</fw>
<ab n="18">And the people
and Princes of Gilead, said one to another, What man is hee that
will begin to fight against the children of Ammon? he shall be Head
ouer all the inhabitants of Gilead.<note> Chap.11. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>