<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The Israelites for their sinne are
oppressed by Midian. 8 A prophet rebuketh them. 11 An Angel sendeth
Gideon for their deliuerance. 17 Gideons Present is consumed with
fire. 24 Gideon destroyeth Baals altar, and offreth a sacrifice
vpon the altar Iehouah-shalom. 28 Ioash defendeth his son, &amp;
calleth him Ierubbaal. 33 Gideons armie. 36 Gideons
signes.</head>

<ab n="1">And the
children of Israel did euill in the sight of the Lord: and the Lord
deliuered them into the hande of Midian seuen yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the hand
of Midian preuailed against Israel: and because of the Midianites,
the children of Israel made them the dennes which are in the
mountaines, and caues, &amp; strong holds.<note> Heb. was strong.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And so it was
when Israel had sowen, that the Midianites came vp, &amp; the
Amalekites, &amp; the children of the East, euen they came vp
against them,</ab>
<ab n="4">And they
encamped against them, and destroyed the encrease of the earth,
till thou come vnto Gaza, and left no sustenance for Israel,
neither sheepe, nor oxe, nor asse.<note> Or, goate.</note></ab>

<fw>Gideon and the Angel.</fw>
<ab n="5">For they came
vp with their cattell and their tents, and they came as Grashoppers
for multitude, for both they and their camels were without number:
and they entred into the land to destroy it.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Israel
was greatly impouerished, because of the Midianites, and the
children of Israel cryed vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And it
came to passe when the children of Israel cryed vnto the Lord,
because of the Midianites,</ab>
<ab n="8">That the Lord
sent a Prophet vnto the children of Israel, which said vnto them;
Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, I brought you vp from Egypt, and
brought you forth out of the house of bondage,<note> Hebr. a man, a Prophet.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And I
deliuered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand
of al that oppressed you, and draue them out from before you, and
gaue you their land:</ab>
<ab n="10">And I said vnto
you, I am the Lord your God, feare not the gods of the Amorites in
whose land ye dwel: But ye haue not obeyed my voice.<note> 2.King. 17.35,38. ierem.10.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And there
came an Angel of the Lord, and sate vnder an Oake which was in
Ophrah, that pertained vnto Ioash the Abi-Ezrite: and his sonne
Gideon threshed wheat by the winepresse, to hide it from the
Midianites.<note> Heb.11. 32. called Gideon. , Hebr. to cause it to flye.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Angel of
the Lord appeared vnto him, and said vnto him, The Lord is with
thee, thou mightie man of valour.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Gideon said
vnto him, Oh my Lord, if the Lord bee with vs, why then is all this
befallen vs? and where be all his miracles which our fathers tolde
vs of, saying, Did not the Lord bring vs vp from Egypt? But now the
Lord hath forsaken vs, and deliuered vs into the hands of the
Midianites.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the Lord
looked vpon him, and said, Goe in this thy might, and thou shalt
saue Israel from the hand of the Midianites: haue not I sent
thee?</ab>
<ab n="15">And hee said vnto
him, Oh my lord, wherewith shall I saue Israel? behold, my family
is poore in Manasseh, and I am the least in my fathers
house.<note> Or, my thousand is the meanest.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the Lord said
vnto him, Surely I will be with thee, and thou shalt smite the
Midianites, as one man.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said vnto
him, If now I haue found grace in thy sight, then shew me a signe,
that thou talkest with me.</ab>

<fw>Gideon and the Angel. Baals
altar.</fw>
<ab n="18">Depart not hence,
I pray thee, vntil I come vnto thee, and bring forth my Present,
and set it before thee. And hee saide, I will tary vntill thou come
againe.<note> Or, meat offering.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And Gideon
went in, and made ready a kid, and vnleauened cakes of an Ephah of
floure: the flesh he put in a basket, and he put the broth in a
pot, and brought it out vnto him vnder the oake, and presented
it.<note> Hebr. a kid of the goates.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And the Angel of
God sayd vnto him, Take the flesh, and the vnleauened cakes, and
lay them vpon this rocke, and powre out the broth. And he did
so.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then the
Angel of the Lord put foorth the end of the staffe that was in his
hand, and touched the flesh, and the vnleauened cakes, and there
rose vp fire out of the rocke, and consumed the flesh and the
vnleauened cakes: then the Angel of the Lord departed out of his
sight.</ab>
<ab n="22">And when Gideon
perceiued that hee was an Angel of the Lord, Gideon said, Alas, O
Lord God: for because I haue seene an Angel of the Lord face to
face.<note> Exod.33. 20. chap. 13.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the Lord said
vnto him, Peace be vnto thee, feare not, thou shalt not
die.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then Gideon built
an Altar there vnto the Lord, and called it Iehouah shalom: vnto
this day it is yet in Ophrah, of the Abi-Ezrites.<note> That is, The Lord send peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And it came
to passe the same night, that the Lord said vnto him, Take thy
fathers yong bullocke, euen the second bullocke of seuen yeeres
old, and throw downe the altar of Baal that thy father hath, and
cut downe the groue that is by it:<note> Or, and.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And builde an
Altar vnto the Lord thy God vpon the top of this rocke, in the
ordered place, and take the second bullocke, and offer a burnt
sacrifice with the wood of the groue, which thou shalt cut
downe.<note> Hebr. strong place. , Or, in an orderly maner.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Then Gideon tooke
ten men of his seruants, and did as the Lord had said vnto him: And
so it was because hee feared his fathers houshold, and the men of
the city, that he could not doe it by day, that hee did it by
night.</ab>

<fw>Gideons fleece:</fw>
<ab n="28">¶ And when
the men of the citie arose earely in the morning, behold, the altar
of Baal was cast downe, and the groue was cut downe that was by it,
and the second bullocke was offered vpon the altar that was
built.</ab>
<ab n="29">And they said one
to another, Who hath done this thing? And when they enquired and
asked, they said, Gideon the sonne of Ioash hath done this
thing.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then the men of
the citie said vnto Ioash, Bring out thy sonne, that he may die:
because he hath cast downe the altar of Baal, and because hee hath
cut downe the groue that was by it.</ab>
<ab n="31">And Ioash said
vnto all that stood against him, Will ye pleade for Baal? will ye
saue him? He that will plead for him, let him be put to death
whilest it is yet morning: if he be a god, let him plead for
himselfe, because one hath cast down his altar.</ab>
<ab n="32">Therefore on that
day hee called him Ierubbaal, saying, Let Baal plead against him,
because hee hath throwen downe his altar.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Then all
the Midianites, and the Amalekites, and the children of the East
were gathered together, and went ouer, and pitched in the valley of
Iezreel.</ab>
<ab n="34">But the Spirit of
the Lord came vpon Gideon, and hee blewe a trumpet, and Abiezer was
gathered after him.<note> Hebr. clothed. , Num. 10. 3.chap.3. 27. , Heb. was called after him.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And he sent
messengers throughout all Manasseh, who also was gathered after
him, and hee sent messengers vnto Asher, and vnto Zebulun, and vnto
Naphtali, and they came vp to meete them.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And Gideon
said vnto God, If thou wilt saue Israel by mine hand, as thou hast
said,</ab>
<ab n="37">Beholde, I will
put a fleece of wooll in the floore: and if the deaw be on the
fleece onely, and it bee drie vpon all the earth beside, then shall
I know that thou wilt saue Israel by my hande, as thou hast
said.</ab>
<ab n="38">And it was so: for
he rose vp early on the morrow, and thrust the fleece together, and
wringed the deaw out of the fleece, a bowle full of water.</ab>
<ab n="39">And Gideon said
vnto God, Let not thine anger be hote against me, and I will speake
but this once: Let mee prooue, I pray thee, but this once with the
fleece. Let it now be drie onely vpon the fleece, and vpon all the
ground let there be deaw.<note> Gen.18. 32.</note></ab>

<fw>His armie.</fw>
<ab n="40">And God did so
that night: for it was drie vpon the fleece onely, and there was
deaw on all the ground.</ab>



</div>