<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The nations which were left to
prooue Israel. 6 By communion with them they commit idolatrie. 8
Othniel deliuereth them from Chushan-Rishathaim. 12 Ehud from
Eglon. 31 Shamgar from the Philistines.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are
the nations which the Lord left, to prooue Israel by them, (euen as
many of Israel as had not knowen all the warres of Canaan;</ab>
<ab n="2">Onely that
the generations of the children of Israel might know to teach them
warre, at the least such as before knew nothing thereof:)</ab>
<ab n="3">Namely fiue
lords of the Philistines, and all the Canaanites, and the
Sidonians, and the Hiuites that dwelt in mount Lebanon, from mount
Baal-Hermon, vnto the entring in of Hamath.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they were
to prooue Israel by them, to know whether they would hearken vnto
the Commandements of the Lord, which hee commaunded their fathers
by the hand of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And
the children of Israel dwelt among the Canaanites, Hittites, and
Amorites, and Perizzites, and Hiuites, and Iebusites,</ab>

<fw>Othniel. Ehud.</fw>
<ab n="6">And they
tooke their daughters to be their wiues, and gaue their daughters
to their sonnes, and serued their gods.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the
children of Israel did euill in the sight of the Lord, and forgate
the Lord their God, and serued Baalim, and the groues.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶
Therefore the anger of the Lord was hote against Israel, and he
sold them into the hand of Chushan-Rishathaim king of Mesopotamia:
and the children of Israel serued Chushan-Rishathaim eight
yeeres.<note> Hebr. Aram-naharaim.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And when the
children of Israel cryed vnto the Lord, the Lord raised vp a
deliuerer to the children of Israel, who deliuered them, euen
Othniel the sonne of Kenaz, Calebs yonger brother.<note> Hebr. sauiour.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the Spirit of
the Lord came vpon him, and he iudged Israel, and went out to
warre, &amp; the Lord deliuered Chushan-Rishathaim king of
Mesopotamia into his hand; and his hand preuailed against
Chushan-Rishathaim.<note> Hebr. was. , Hebr. Aram.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the land had
rest forty yeres: and Othniel the sonne of Kenaz died.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
children of Israel did euill againe in the sight of the Lord: and
the Lord strengthened Eglon the king of Moab against Israel,
because they had done euill in the sight of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And hee gathered
vnto him the children of Ammon, and Amalek, and went and smote
Israel, and possessed the city of Palme-trees.</ab>
<ab n="14">So the children of
Israel serued Eglon the King of Moab eighteene yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="15">But when the
children of Israel cried vnto the Lord, the Lord raised them vp a
deliuerer, Ehud the sonne of Gera, a Beniamite, a man left handed:
and by him the children of Israel sent a Present vnto Eglon the
king of Moab.<note> Or, the sonne of Iemini. , Hebr. shut of his right hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But Ehud made him
a dagger (which had two edges) of a cubite length, and he did gird
it vnder his raiment, vpon his right thigh,</ab>
<ab n="17">And he brought the
present vnto Eglon king of Moab: and Eglon was a very fat
man.</ab>
<ab n="18">And when he had
made an end to offer the Present, he sent away the people that bare
the Present.</ab>

<fw>Ehud killeth Eglon.</fw>
<ab n="19">But hee himselfe
turned againe from the quarries that were by Gilgal, and said, I
haue a secret errand vnto thee, O king: who said, Keepe silence.
And all that stood by him, went out from him.<note> Or, grauen images.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Ehud came vnto
him, and he was sitting in a Summer parlour, which hee had for
himselfe alone: And Ehud said, I haue a message from God vnto thee.
And he arose out of his seat.<note> Heb. a parlour of cooling.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Ehud put forth
his left hand, and tooke the dagger from his right thigh, and
thrust it into his belly.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the haft also
went in after the blade: and the fatte closed vpon the blade, so
that hee could not drawe the dagger out of his belly, and the dirt
came out.<note> Or, it came out at the fundament.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then Ehud went
forth through the porche, and shut the doores of the parlour vpon
him, and locked them.</ab>
<ab n="24">When he was gone
out, his seruants came, and when they saw, that behold, the doores
of the parlour were locked, they said, Surely he couereth his feet
in his Summer chamber.<note> Or, doth his easement.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And they taried
till they were ashamed: and behold, he opened not the doores of the
parlour, therefore they tooke a key, and opened them: and behold,
their lord was fallen downe dead on the earth.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Ehud escaped
while they taried: and passed beyond the quarries, and escaped vnto
Seirath.</ab>
<ab n="27">And it came to
passe when hee was come, that hee blew a trumpet in the mountaine
of Ephraim, and the children of Israel went downe with him from the
mount, &amp; he before them.</ab>
<ab n="28">And hee said vnto
them, Follow after me: for the Lord hath deliuered your enemies the
Moabites into your hand. And they went downe after him, and tooke
the foords of Iordan toward Moab, and suffered not a man to passe
ouer.</ab>
<ab n="29">And they slewe of
Moab at that time about ten thousand men, all lusty, and all men of
valour, and there escaped not a man.<note> Heb. fat.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">So Moab was
subdued that day vnder the hand of Israel: and the land had rest
fourescore yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And after
him was Shamgar the sonne of Anath, which slew of the Philistines
sixe hundred men with an oxe goad, and he also deliuered
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>