<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Gideons armie of two and thirtie
thousand is brought to three hundred. 9 He is encouraged by the
dreame and interpretation of the barley cake. 16 His stratageme of
trumpets and lampes in pitchers. 24 The Ephraimites take Oreb and
Zeeb.</head>

<ab n="1">Then
Ierubbaal (who is Gideon) and all the people that were with him,
rose vp earely, and pitched beside the well of Harod: so that the
hoste of the Midianites were on the North side of them by the hill
of Moreh, in the valley.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
said vnto Gideon, The people that are with thee, are too many for
me to giue the Midianites into their handes, lest Israel vaunt
themselues against mee, saying, Mine owne hand hath saued
me.</ab>
<ab n="3">Now therefore
go to, proclaime in the eares of the people, saying, Whosoeuer is
fearefull and afraid, let him returne and depart earely from mount
Gilead: and there returned of the people twentie and two thousand,
&amp; there remained ten thousand.<note> Deut.20.8 1.mac.3.56</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
said vnto Gideon, The people are yet too many: bring them downe
vnto the water, and I wil trie them for thee there: and it shall
bee that of whome I say vnto thee, This shall goe with thee, the
same shall goe with thee: and of whomsoeuer I say vnto thee, This
shal not goe with thee, the same shall not goe.</ab>
<ab n="5">So he brought
downe the people vnto the water: and the Lord sayd vnto Gideon,
Euery one that lappeth of the water with his tongue as a dog
lappeth, him shalt thou set by himselfe, likewise euery one that
boweth downe vpon his knees to drinke.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the
number of them that lapped putting their hand to their mouth, were
three hundred men: but all the rest of the people bowed downe vpon
their knees to drinke water.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the Lord
said vnto Gideon, By the three hundred men that lapped, will I saue
you, and deliuer the Midianites into thine hand: and let all the
other people goe euery man vnto his place.</ab>

<fw>A dreame declared.</fw>
<ab n="8">So the people
tooke victuals in their hand, and their trumpets: and he sent all
the rest of Israel, euery man vnto his tent, and reteined those
three hundred men: and the hoste of Midian was beneath him in the
valley.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And it
came to passe the same night, that the Lord sayd vnto him, Arise,
get thee downe vnto the hoste, for I haue deliuered it into thine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="10">But if thou feare
to goe downe, goe thou with Phurah thy seruant downe to the
hoste.</ab>
<ab n="11">And thou shalt
heare what they say, and afterward shall thine handes be
strengthened to goe downe vnto the hoste. Then went hee downe, with
Phurah his seruant, vnto the outside of the armed men, that were in
the hoste.<note> Or, rankes by fiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the
Midianites, and the Amalekites, and all the children of the East,
lay along in the valley like grashoppers for multitude, and their
camels were without number, as the sand by the Sea side for
multitude.<note> Chap.6. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And when Gideon
was come, beholde, there was a man that tolde a dreame vnto his
fellow, and sayd, Behold, I dreamed a dreame, and loe, a cake of
Barley bread tumbled into the hoste of Midian, and came vnto a
tent, and smote it that it fell, and ouerturned it, that the tent
lay along.</ab>
<ab n="14">And his fellow
answered, and said, This is nothing els saue the sword of Gideon
the sonne of Ioash, a man of Israel: for into his hand hath God
deliuered Midian, and all the hoste.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And it was
so, when Gideon heard the telling of the dreame, and the
interpretation thereof, that hee worshipped, and returned into the
host of Israel, and sayd, Arise, for the Lord hath deliuered into
your hand the host of Midian.<note> Hebr. the breaking thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And he diuided the
three hundred men into three companies, and hee put a trumpet in
euery mans hand, with empty pitchers, and lampes within the
pitchers,<note> Hebr. trumpets in the hand of all of them. , Or, firebrands: or torches.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And hee said vnto
them, Looke on mee, and doe likewise; and beholde, when I come to
the outside of the campe, it shall be that as I doe, so shall ye
doe.</ab>

<fw>Midian destroyed.</fw>
<ab n="18">When I blow with a
trumpet, I and all that are with mee, then blow ye the trumpets
also on euery side of all the campe, and say, The sword of the
Lord, and of Gideon.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ So Gideon
and the hundred men that were with him, came vnto the outside of
the campe, in the beginning of the middle watch, and they had but
newly set the watch, and they blew the trumpets, and brake the
pitchers that were in their hands.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the three
companies blew the trumpets, and brake the pitchers, and held the
lampes in their left hands, and the trumpets in their right hands
to blow withall: and they cryed, The sword of the Lord, and of
Gideon.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they stood
euery man in his place, round about the campe: and all the host
ranne, and cried, and fled.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the three
hundred blew the trumpets, and the Lord set euery mans sword
against his fellow, euen throughout all the host: and the host fled
to Beth-shittah, in Zererath, and to the border of Abel Meholah,
vnto Tabbath.<note> Esay 9.4. , Or, towards. , Hebr. lip.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the men of
Israel gathered themselues together out of Naphtali, and out of
Asher, and out of all Manasseh, and pursued after the
Midianites.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And Gideon
sent messengers throughout all mount Ephraim, saying; Come downe
against the Midianites, and take before them the waters vnto
Beth-barah, and Iordan. Then all the men of Ephraim gathered
themselues together, and tooke the waters vnto Beth-barah, and
Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they tooke two
Princes of the Midianites, Oreb, and Zeeb; and they slew Oreb vpon
the rocke Oreb, and Zeeb they slew at the winepresse of Zeeb, and
pursued Midian, and brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb, to Gideon
on the other side Iordan.<note> Psal.83. 11. esa.10. 26.</note></ab>



</div>