<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 Samson at Gaza escapeth, and
carieth away the gates of the city. 4 Delilah corrupted by the
Philistines, entiseth Samson. 6 Thrise she is deceiued. 15 At last
shee ouercommeth him. 21 The Philistines take him, and put out his
eyes. 22 His strength renewing, hee pulleth downe the house vpon
the Philistines, and dieth.</head>

<ab n="1">Then went Samson
to Gaza, and saw there an harlot, and went in vnto her.<note> Heb. a woman an harlot.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it was told
the Gazites, saying, Samson is come hither. And they compassed him
in, and layd wait for him all night in the gate of the citie, and
were quiet all the night, saying, In the morning when it is day, we
shall kill him.<note> Heb. silent.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Samson lay
till midnight, and arose at midnight, and tooke the doores of the
gate of the city, and the two posts, and went away with them, barre
and all, and put them vpon his shoulders, and caried them vp to the
toppe of an hill that is before Hebron.<note> Heb. with the barre.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And it came
to passe afterward, that he loued a woman in the valley of Sorek,
whose name was Delilah.<note> Or, by the brooke.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the lords of
the Philistines came vp vnto her, and said vnto her, Entice him,
and see wherein his great strength lieth, and by what meanes we may
preuaile against him, that we may bind him, to afflict him: and we
will giue thee euery one of vs, eleuen hundreth pieces of
siluer.<note> Or, humble.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Delilah
said to Samson, Tel me, I pray thee, wherein thy great strength
lyeth, and wherewith thou mightest be bound, to afflict
thee.</ab>

<fw>She betrayeth him.</fw>
<ab n="7">And Samson said
vnto her, If they binde mee with seuen greene withs, that were
neuer dried, then shall I be weake, and be as another
man.<note> Or, newe coards. Heb. moist. , Heb. one.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then the lords of
the Philistines brought vp to her seuen greene withs, which had not
bene dried, &amp; she bound him with them.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now there were men
lying in wait, abiding with her in the chamber: and she said vnto
him, The Philistines be vpon thee, Samson. And he brake the withs,
as a threed of tow is broken, when it toucheth the fire: so his
strength was not knowen.<note> Heb. smeleth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Delilah said
vnto Samson, Behold, thou hast mocked me, and told mee lies: now
tell mee, I pray thee, wherewith thou mightest be bound.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he said vnto
her, If they bind me fast with newe ropes that neuer were occupied,
then shall I bee weake, and be as another man.<note> Heb. wherwith worke hath not ben done.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Delilah therfore
tooke new ropes, and bound him therewith, and said vnto him, The
Philistines be vpon thee, Samson. (And there were liers in wait
abiding in the chamber.) and hee brake them from off his armes,
like a threed.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Delilah said
vnto Samson, Hitherto thou hast mocked me, and told me lies: tell
me wherewith thou mightest be bound. And he said vnto her, If thou
weauest the seuen lockes of my head with the web.</ab>
<ab n="14">And she fastened
it with the pinne, and said vnto him, The Philistines be vpon thee,
Samson. And hee awaked out of his sleepe, and went away with the
pinne of the beame, &amp; with the web.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And shee
said vnto him, How canst thou say, I loue thee, when thine heart is
not with mee? Thou hast mocked mee these three times, and hast not
told me wherin thy great strength lieth.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it came to
passe, when she pressed him daily with her wordes, and vrged him so
that his soule was vexed vnto death,<note> Heb. shortned.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">That he told her
all his heart, and said vnto her, There hath not come a rasor vpon
mine head: for I haue bene a Nazarite vnto God from my mothers
wombe: If I bee shauen, then my strength will goe from me, and I
shall become weake, and bee like any other man.</ab>

<fw>Samson is taken:</fw>
<ab n="18">And when Delilah
saw that he had told her all his heart, she sent and called for the
Lords of the Philistines, saying, Come vp this once, for hee hath
shewed me all his heart. Then the lords of the Philistines came vp
vnto her, &amp; brought money in their hand.</ab>
<ab n="19">And she made him
sleepe vpon her knees, and she called for a man, and she caused him
to shaue off the seuen lockes of his head, and she began to afflict
him, and his strength went from him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And she said, The
Philistines be vpon thee, Samson. And hee awoke out of his sleepe,
and said, I will go out as at other times before, and shake my
selfe. And he wist not that the Lord was departed from him.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ But the
Philistines tooke him and put out his eyes, and brought him downe
to Gaza, and bound him with fetters of brasse, and he did grind in
the prison house.<note> Hebr. boared out.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Howbeit, the
haire of his head began to grow againe, after he was
shauen.<note> Or, as when he was shauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then the lords of
the Philistines gathered them together, for to offer a great
sacrifice vnto Dagon their god, and to reioyce: for they said, Our
god hath deliuered Samson our enemy into our hand.</ab>
<ab n="24">And when the
people saw him, they praised their god: for they said, Our god hath
deliuered into our hands our enemy, and the destroyer of our
countrey, which slew many of vs.<note> Hebr. and who multiplied our slaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And it came to
passe when their hearts were merry, that they said, Call for
Samson, that hee may make vs sport. And they called for Samson out
of the prison house, and he made them sport, and they set him
betweene the pillars.<note> Hebr. before them.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And Samson said
vnto the lad that held him by the hand, Suffer mee, that I may
feele the pillars whereupon the house standeth, that I may leane
vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="27">Now the house was
full of men and women, and all the lords of the Philistines were
there: and there were vpon the roofe about three thousand men and
women, that behelde while Samson made sport.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Samson called
vnto the Lord, and said, O Lord God, remember me, I pray thee,
&amp; strengthen mee, I pray thee, onely this once, O God, that I
may be at once auenged of the Philistines, for my two eyes.</ab>

<fw>His death.</fw>
<ab n="29">And Samson tooke
hold of the two middle pillars, vpon which the house stood, and on
which it was borne vp, of the one with his right hand, and of the
other with his left.<note> Or, he leaned on them.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Samson said,
Let me die with the Philistines: &amp; he bowed himselfe with all
his might: and the house fel vpon the lords, and vpon all the
people that were therein: so the dead which he slew at his death,
were moe, then they which he slew in his life.<note> Hebr. my soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Then his
brethren, and all the house of his father, came downe, and tooke
him, and brought him vp, and buried him betweene Zorah and Eshtaol,
in the burying place of Manoah his father: and hee iudged Israel
twentie yeeres.</ab>



</div>