<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The Ephraimites quarrelling with
Iephthah, and discerned by Shibboleth, are slaine by the
Gileadites. 7 Iephthah dieth. 8 Ibzan, who had thirtie sonnes and
thirtie daughters, 11 and Elon, 13 and Abdon who had fourtie
sonnes, and thirtie nephewes, iudged Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">And the men of
Ephraim gathered themselues together, and went Northward, &amp;
said vnto Iephthah, Wherefore passedst thou ouer to fight against
the children of Ammon, and didst not call vs to goe with thee? Wee
will burne thine house vpon thee with fire.<note> Hebr. were called.</note></ab>

<fw>His death.</fw>
<ab n="2">And Iephthah saide
vnto them, I and my people were at great strife with the children
of Ammon: and when I called you, ye deliuered me not out of their
hands.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when I sawe
that ye deliuered me not, I put my life in my handes, and passed
ouer against the children of Ammon, and the Lord deliuered them
into my hand: Wherfore then are ye come vp vnto me this day, to
fight against me?</ab>
<ab n="4">Then Iephthah
gathered together all the men of Gilead, and fought with Ephraim:
and the men of Gilead smote Ephraim, because they said, Yee
Gileadites are fugitiues of Ephraim, among the Ephraimites and
among the Manassites.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Gileadites
tooke the passages of Iordan before the Ephraimites: and it was so
that when those Ephraimites which were escaped saide, Let me go
ouer, that the men of Gilead said vnto him, Art thou an Ephraimite?
If he said, Nay:</ab>
<ab n="6">Then said they
vnto him, Say now, Shibboleth: and he said, Sibboleth: for hee
could not frame to pronounce it right. Then they tooke him, and
slewe him at the passages of Iordan: and there fell at that time of
the Ephraimites, fourtie &amp; two thousand.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Iephthah
iudged Israel sixe yeeres: then died Iephthah the Gileadite, and
was buried in one of the cities of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And after
him Ibzan of Bethlehem iudged Israel.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee had
thirtie sonnes, and thirtie daughters, whome hee sent abroad, and
tooke in thirtie daughters from abroad for his sonnes. And hee
iudged Israel seuen yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then died Ibzan,
and was buried at Bethlehem.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And after
him, Elon, a Zebulonite iudged Israel, and he iudged Israel ten
yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Elon the
Zebulonite died, and was buried in Aiialon in the countrey of
Zebulun.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And after
him, Abdon, the sonne of Hillel a Pirathonite iudged
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he had fourty
sonnes, and thirtie nephewes, that rode on threescore and ten
asse-colts: and he iudged Israel eight yeeres,<note> Heb. sonnes sonnes.</note></ab>

<fw>Samsons birth is foretolde.</fw>
<ab n="15">And Abdon the
sonne of Hillel the Pirathonite died, and was buried in Pirathon in
the land of Ephraim, in the mount of the Amalekites.</ab>



</div>