<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>2 The Song of Deborah and
Barak.</head>

<ab n="1">Then sang
Deborah, and Barak the son of Abinoam, on that day, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Praise ye the
Lord, for the auenging of Israel, when the people willingly offered
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="3">Heare, O ye
kings, giue eare, O ye Princes: I, euen I will sing vnto the Lord,
I wil sing praise to the Lord God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">Lord, when
thou wentest out of Seir, when thou marchedst out of the field of
Edom, the earth trembled, and the heauens dropped, the clouds also
dropped water.<note> Deut.4. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The
mountaines melted from before the Lord, euen that Sinai, from
before the Lord God of Israel.<note> Psal.97.5. , Hebr. flowed. , Exod.19. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In the dayes
of Shamgar the son of Anath, in the dayes of Iael, the high wayes
were vnoccupied, and the traueilers walked thorow
by-wayes.<note> Chap.3. 31. , Chap.4. 18. , Hebr. walkers of paths. , Hebr. crooked wayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The
inhabitants of the villages ceased, they ceased in Israel, vntill
that I Deborah arose, that I arose a mother in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">They chose
new gods; then was warre in the gates: was there a shield or speare
seene among fourtie thousand in Israel?</ab>
<ab n="9">My heart is
toward the gouernours of Israel, that offered themselues willingly
among the people: Blesse ye the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">Speake yee that
ride on white asses, yee that sit in Iudgement, and walke by the
way.<note> Or, meditate.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They that are
deliuered from the noise of Archers in the places of drawing water;
there shall they rehearse the righteous acts of the Lord, euen the
righteous acts towards the inhabitants of his villages in Israel:
then shall the people of the Lord goe downe to the
gates.<note> Hebr. righteousnesses of the Lord.</note></ab>

<fw>The song of Deborah and Barak.</fw>
<ab n="12">Awake, awake
Deborah: awake, awake, vtter a song: arise Barak, and leade thy
captiuitie captiue, thou sonne of Abinoam.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then hee made him
that remaineth, haue dominion ouer the Nobles among the people: the
Lord made me haue dominion ouer the mightie.</ab>
<ab n="14">Out of Ephraim was
there a roote of them against Amalek, after thee Beniamin, among
thy people: Out of Machir came downe gouernours, and out of Zebulun
they that handle the pen of the writer.<note> Heb. drawe with the pen, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the princes of
Issachar were with Deborah: euen Issachar, and also Barak, he was
sent on foot into the valley: for the diuisions of Reuben, there
were great thoughts of heart.<note> Hebr. his feete. , Or, in the diuisions, &amp;c. , Hebr. impressions.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Why abodest thou
among the sheepefolds, to heare the bleatings of the flocks? for
the diuisions of Reuben there were great searchings of
heart.<note> Or, in.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Gilead abode
beyond Iordan: and why did Dan remaine in ships? Asher continued on
the sea shore, and abode in his breaches.<note> Or, port. , Or, creeks.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Zebulun and
Naphtali were a people that ieoparded their liues vnto the death,
in the high places of the field.<note> Heb. exposed to reproch.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The kings came and
fought, then fought the kings of Canaan in Taanach by the waters of
Megiddo, they tooke no gaine of money.</ab>
<ab n="20">They fought from
heauen, the starres in their courses fought against
Sisera.<note> Heb. paths.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The riuer of
Kishon swept them away, that ancient riuer, the riuer Kishon: O my
soule, thou hast troden downe strength.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then were the
horse hoofes broken, by the meanes of the pransings, the pransings
of their mightie ones.<note> Or, tramplings, or plungings.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Curse ye Meroz
(said the Angel of the Lord ) curse ye bitterly the inhabitants
thereof: because they came not to the helpe of the Lord, to the
helpe of the Lord against the mighty.</ab>
<ab n="24">Blessed aboue
women shal Iael the wife of Heber the Kenite be, blessed shall she
be aboue women in the tent.</ab>
<ab n="25">He asked water,
and she gaue him milke, shee brought foorth butter in a lordly
dish.</ab>

<fw>The song of Deborah and Barak.</fw>
<ab n="26">Shee put her hand
to the naile, and her right hand to the workemens hammer: and with
the hammer shee smote Sisera, shee smote off his head, when she had
pearsed &amp; striken through his temples.<note> Heb. hammered.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">At her feete he
bowed, he fell, he lay downe: at her feet he bowed, he fell; where
he bowed, there he fel down dead.<note> Hebr. betweene. , Heb. destroyed.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">The mother of
Sisera looked out at a window, and cried through the lattesse, Why
is his charet so long in comming? Why tarie the wheeles of his
charets?</ab>
<ab n="29">Her wise ladies
answered her, yea she returned answere to her selfe,<note> Heb. words</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Haue they not
sped? haue they not diuided the pray to euery man a damosell or
two? To Sisera a pray of diuers colours, a pray of diuers colours,
of needle worke, of diuers colours of needle worke on both sides,
meet for the necks of them that take the spoile?<note> Heb. to the head of a man. , Hebr. for the neckes of the spoils.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">So let all thine
enemies perish, O Lord: but let them that loue him, be as the Sunne
when he goeth foorth in his might. And the land had rest fourtie
yeeres.</ab>



</div>