<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-20-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 The Leuite in a generall assembly
declareth his wrong. 8 The decree of the assembly. 12 The
Beniamites being cited, make head against the Israelites. 18 The
Israelites in two battels loose fourty thousand. 26 They destroy by
a stratageme all the Beniamites, except sixe hundred.</head>

<ab n="1">Then all the
children of Israel went out, and the Congregation was gathered
together as one man, from Dan euen to Beer-sheba, with the land of
Gilead, vnto the Lord in Mizpeh.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the chiefe of
al the people, euen of all the tribes of Israel, presented
themselues in the assembly of the people of God, foure hundred
thousand footmen that drew sword.</ab>
<ab n="3">(Now the children
of Beniamin heard that the children of Israel were gone vp to
Mizpeh.) Then said the children of Israel, Tell vs, how was this
wickednesse?</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Leuite the
husband of the woman that was slaine, answered and said, I came
into Gibeah that belongeth to Beniamin, I and my concubine, to
lodge.<note> Heb. the man the Leuite.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the men of
Gibeah rose against me, and beset the house round about vpon me by
night, and thought to haue slaine mee, and my concubine haue they
forced that she is dead.<note> Heb. humbled.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I tooke my
concubine, and cut her in pieces, and sent her throughout all the
countrey of the inheritance of Israel: for they haue committed
lewdnesse and folly in Israel.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites complaint.</fw>
<ab n="7">Behold, ye are all
children of Israel, giue here your aduise and counsell.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And all the
people arose as one man, saying, We will not any of vs goe to his
tent, neither will wee any of vs turne into his house:</ab>
<ab n="9">But now, this
shall bee the thing which we will doe to Gibeah, we will goe vp by
lot against it:</ab>
<ab n="10">And we wil take
ten men of a hundred throughout all the tribes of Israel, and an
hundred of a thousand, and a thousand out of ten thousand, to fetch
victuall for the people, that they may doe, when they come to
Gibeah of Beniamin, according to all the folly that they haue
wrought in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">So all the men of
Israel were gathered against the citie, knit together as one
man.<note> Hebr. fellowes.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
tribes of Israel sent men thorow all the tribe of Beniamin, saying,
What wickednesse is this that is done among you?</ab>
<ab n="13">Now therfore
deliuer vs the men, the children of Belial which are in Gibeah,
that wee may put them to death, and put away euill from Israel: but
the children of Beniamin would not hearken to the voice of their
brethren the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="14">But the children
of Beniamin gathered themselues together out of the cities, vnto
Gibeah, to goe out to battell against the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the children
of Beniamin were numbred at that time out of the cities, twentie
and sixe thousand men that drew sword, beside the inhabitants of
Gibeah, which were numbred seuen hundred chosen men.</ab>
<ab n="16">Among all this
people there were seuen hundred chosen men left handed, euery one
could sling stones at an haire breadth, and not misse.<note> Chap. 3. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And the men of
Israel, beside Beniamin, were numbred foure hundred thousand men
that drewe sword; all these were men of warre.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And the
children of Israel arose, and went vp to the house of God, and
asked counsell of God, and saide, Which of vs shall goe vp first to
the battell against the children of Beniamin? And the Lord said,
Iudah shall goe vp first.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the children
of Israel rose vp in the morning, and encamped against
Gibeah.</ab>

<fw>The Israelites warre with Beniamin, and smite
them.</fw>
<ab n="20">And the men of
Israel went out to battell against Beniamin, and the men of Israel
put themselues in aray to fight against them at Gibeah.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the children
of Beniamin came forth out of Gibeah, and destroied downe to the
ground of the Israelites that day, twenty &amp; two thousand
men.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the people
the men of Israel incouraged themselues, &amp; set their battel
againe in aray, in the place where they put themselues in aray the
first day.</ab>
<ab n="23">(And the children
of Israel went vp and wept before the Lord vntill Euen, and asked
counsel of the Lord, saying, Shall I goe vp againe to battell
against the children of Beniamin my brother? And the Lord saide,
Goe vp against him.)</ab>
<ab n="24">And the children
of Israel came neere against the children of Beniamin, the second
day.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Beniamin went
foorth against them out of Gibeah the second day, &amp; destroyed
down to the ground of the children of Israel againe, eighteene
thousand men, all these drew the sword.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Then all
the children of Israel, and all the people went vp, and came vnto
the house of God, and wept, and sate there before the Lord, and
fasted that day vntill Euen, and offered burnt offerings, and peace
offerings before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the children
of Israel enquired of the Lord, (for the Arke of þe
couenant of God was there in those daies,</ab>
<ab n="28">And Phinehas the
sonne of Eleazar the sonne of Aaron stood before it in those
dayes.) saying; Shall I yet againe goe out to battel against the
children of Beniamin my brother, or shall I cease? And the Lord
said, Goe vp; for to morrow I will deliuer them into thine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Israel set
lyers in waite round about Gibeah.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the children
of Israel went vp against the children of Beniamin on the third
day, and put themselues in aray against Gibeah, as at other
times.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the children
of Beniamin went out against the people, and were drawen away from
the citie, and they began to smite of the people and kill as at
other times, in the high wayes, of which one goeth vp to the house
of God, and the other to Gibeah in the field, about thirtie men of
Israel.<note> Hebr. to smite of the people wounded as at &amp;c. , Or, Bethel.</note></ab>

<fw>The Israelites warre with Beniamin, and smite
them.</fw>
<ab n="32">And the children
of Beniamin said, They are smitten downe before vs, as at the
first: But the children of Israel said, Let vs flee, and draw them
from the citie, vnto the high wayes.</ab>
<ab n="33">And all the men
of Israel rose vp out of their place, and put themselues in aray at
Baal Tamar: and the lyers in waite of Israel came foorth out of
their places, euen out of the medowes of Gibeah.</ab>
<ab n="34">And there came
against Gibeah ten thousand chosen men, out of all Israel, and the
battell was sore: but they knew not that euill was neere
them.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the Lord
smote Beniamin before Israel, and the children of Israel destroyed
of the Beniamites that day, twentie and fiue thousand, and an
hundred men; all these drew the sword.</ab>
<ab n="36">So the children
of Beniamin saw that they were smitten: for the men of Israel gaue
place to the Beniamites, because they trusted vnto the lyers in
wait, which they had set beside Gibeah.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the liers in
wait hasted, and rushed vpon Gibeah, and the liers in wait drew
themselues along, and smote all the citie with the edge of the
sword.<note> Or, made a long sound with the trumpet.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Nowe there was an
appointed signe between the men of Israel and the liers in wait,
that they should make a great flame with smoke rise vp out of the
citie.<note> Or, time. , Heb. with. , Heb. eleuation.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And when the men
of Israel retired in the battell, Beniamin began to smite and kill
of the men of Israel about thirtie persons; for they saide, Surely
they are smitten downe before vs, as in the first
battell.<note> Hebr. to smite the wounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">But when the
flame began to arise vp out of the citie, with a pillar of smoke,
the Beniamites looked behind them, and behold, the flame of the
citie ascended vp to heauen.<note> Heb. the whole consumption.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And when the men
of Israel turned againe, the men of Beniamin were amased; for they
saw that euill was come vpon them.<note> Heb. touched them.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">Therefore they
turned their backs before the men of Israel, vnto
þe way of the wildernes, but the battel ouertooke
them: &amp; them which came out of the cities, they destroyed in
the midst of them.</ab>
<ab n="43">Thus they
inclosed the Beniamites round about, and chased them, and trode
them downe with ease ouer against Gibeah toward the sunne
rising.<note> Or, from Menuchah, &amp;c. , Heb. vnto ouer against.</note></ab>

<fw>The Israelites warre with Beniamin, and smite
them.</fw>
<ab n="44">And there fell of
Beniamin eighteene thousand men; all these were men of
valour.</ab>
<ab n="45">And they turned
and fled toward the wildernesse vnto the rocke of Rimmon: and they
gleaned of them in the high wayes fiue thousand men: and pursued
hard after them vnto Gidom, and slew two thousand men of
them.</ab>
<ab n="46">So that all which
fell that day of Beniamin, were twentie and fiue thousand men that
drew the sword; all these were men of valour.</ab>
<ab n="47">But sixe hundred
men turned and fledde to the wildernesse vnto the rocke Rimmon, and
abode in the rocke Rimmon foure moneths.<note> Chap. 21.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And the men of
Israel turned againe vpon the children of Beniamin, and smote them
with the edge of the sword, as well the men of euery citie, as the
beast, and all that came to hand: also they set on fire all the
cities that they came to.<note> Heb. was found. , Heb. were found.</note></ab>



</div>