<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Samson is denied his wife. 3 He
burneth the Philistines corne with foxes and firebrands. 6 His wife
and her father are burnt by the Philistines. 7 Samson smiteth them
hip and thigh. 9 He is bound by the men of Iudah and deliuered to
the Philistines. 14 Hee killeth them with a iawbone. 18 God maketh
the fountaine En-hakkore for him in Lehi.</head>

<ab n="1">But it came to
passe within a while after, in the time of wheat haruest, that
Samson visited his wife with a kid, and he said, I will goe in to
my wife into the chamber. But her father would not suffer him to
goe in.</ab>
<ab n="2">And her father
saide, I verily thought that thou haddest vtterly hated her,
therfore I gaue her to thy companion: is not her younger sister
fairer then she? take her, I pray thee, in stead of
her.<note> Heb. let her be thine.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And Samson
said concerning them, Now shal I be more blamelesse then the
Philistines, though I do them a displeasure.<note> Or, now shall I bee blamelesse from the Philistines, though, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Samson went
and caught three hundred foxes, and tooke firebrands, and turned
taile to taile, and put a firebrand in the midst betweene two
tailes.<note> Or, torches.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And when hee had
set the brands on fire, he let them goe into the standing corne of
the Philistines, and burnt vp both the shockes, and also the
standing corne, with the vineyards and oliues.</ab>

<fw>His iaw-bone.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶ Then the
Philistines saide, Who hath done this? and they answered, Samson
the sonne in law of the Timnite, because hee had taken his wife,
and giuen her to his companion. And the Philistines came vp, and
burnt her and her father with fire.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And Samson
said vnto them, Though ye haue done this, yet will I be auenged of
you, and after that, I wil cease.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he smote them
hip and thigh, with a great slaughter; and hee went down and dwelt
in the top of the rocke Etam.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Then the
Philistines went vp, and pitched in Iudah, and spread themselues in
Lehi.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the men of
Iudah said, Why are ye come vp against vs? and they answered, To
bind Samson are we come vp, to doe to him, as he hath done to
vs.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then three
thousand men of Iudah went to the top of the rocke Etam, and sayd
to Samson; Knowest thou not that the Philistines are rulers ouer
vs? What is this that thou hast done vnto vs? And he said vnto
them, As they did vnto me, so haue I done vnto them.<note> Heb. went downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they said
vnto him, Wee are come downe to binde thee, that we may deliuer
thee into the hand of the Philistines. And Samson said vnto them,
Sweare vnto me, that yee will not fall vpon me your selues.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they spake
vnto him, saying; No: but wee will binde thee fast, and deliuer
thee into their hand: but surely we will not kill thee. And they
bound him with two new cordes, and brought him vp from the
rocke.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And when
he came vnto Lehi, the Philistines shouted against him: and the
Spirit of the Lord came mightily vpon him, and the cordes that were
vpon his armes became as flaxe that was burnt with fire, &amp; his
bands loosed from off his hands.<note> Hebr. were melted.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he found a
new iawbone of an asse, and put foorth his hand, and tooke it, and
slewe a thousand men therewith.<note> Heb. moist.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Samson said,
With the iawbone of an asse, heapes vpon heapes, with the iaw of an
asse haue I slaine a thousand men.<note> Heb. an heape, two heapes</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And it came to
passe when he had made an end of speaking, that hee cast away the
iaw bone out of his hand, and called that place
Ramath-Lehi.<note> That is, The lifting vp of the iaw-bone, or, casting away of the iaw-bone.</note></ab>

<fw>Samson and Delilah:</fw>
<ab n="18">¶ And hee
was sore athirst, and called on the Lord, and said, Thou hast giuen
this great deliuerance into the hand of thy seruant: and now shall
I die for thirst, and fall into the hand of the
vncircumcised?</ab>
<ab n="19">But God claue an
hollow place that was in the iawe, and there came water thereout,
&amp; when he had drunke, his spirit came againe, and he reuiued:
wherefore hee called the name thereof En-hakkore, which is in Lehi,
vnto this day:<note> Or, Lehi. , That is, the well of him that called or cried.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And he iudged
Israel in the dayes of the Philistines twentie yeeres.</ab>



</div>