<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Joshua-Chapter-24-24-Judges.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The actes of Iudah and Simeon. 4
Adonibezek iustly requited. 8 Hierusalem taken. 10 Hebron taken. 11
Othniel hath Achsah to wife for taking of Debir. 16 The Kenites
dwel in Iudah. 17 Hormah, Gaza, Askelon and Ekron taken. 21 The
acts of Beniamin. 22 Of the house of Ioseph, who take Bethel. 30 Of
Zebulun. 31 Of Asher. 33 Of Naphtali. 34 Of Dan.</head>

<ab n="1">Now after the
death of Ioshua, it came to passe, that the children of Israel
asked the Lord, saying, Who shal goe vp for vs against the
Canaanites first, to fight against them?</ab>

<fw>Ioshuas exhortation, His age, and
death.</fw>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
sayd, Iudah shall goe vp: Behold, I haue deliuered the land into
his hand.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Iudah
saide vnto Simeon his brother, Come vp with me into my lot, that
wee may fight against the Canaanites, and I likewise will goe with
thee into thy lot. So Simeon went with him.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iudah
went vp, and the Lord deliuered the Canaanites and the Perizzites
into their hand: and they slew of them in Bezek ten thousand
men.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they
found Adoni-bezek in Bezek: and they fought against him, and they
slew the Canaanites, and the Perizzites.</ab>
<ab n="6">But
Adoni-bezek fled, and they pursued after him, and caught him, and
cut off his thumbes, and his great toes.</ab>

<fw>Anaks sonnes slaine.</fw>
<ab n="7">And
Adoni-bezek said, Threescore &amp; ten kings, hauing their thumbs
and their great toes cut off, gathered their meate vnder my table:
as I haue done, so God hath requited mee, and they brought him to
Ierusalem, and there he died.<note> Hebr. the thumbes of their hands and of their feete. , Or, gleaned</note></ab>
<ab n="8">(Now the
children of Iudah had fought against Ierusalem, and had taken it,
and smitten it with the edge of the sword, and set the citie on
fire)</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And
afterward the children of Iudah went downe to fight against the
Canaanites that dwelt in the moūtaine, &amp; in the South, and
in the valley.<note> Iosh.10. 36. and 11. 21. and 15. 13. , Or, lowe countrey.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Iudah went
against the Canaanites that dwelt in Hebron (nowe the name of
Hebron before was Kiriath-arba) and they slew Sheshai, and Ahiman,
and Talmai.<note> Iosh.15. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And from thence he
went against the inhabitants of Debir, (&amp; the name of Debir
before was Kiriath-sepher)</ab>
<ab n="12">And Caleb said,
Hee that smiteth Kiriath-sepher, and taketh it, to him will I giue
Achsah my daughter to wife.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Othniel the
sonne of Kenaz Calebs yonger brother tooke it: and he gaue him
Achsah his daughter to wife.</ab>
<ab n="14">And it came to
passe when shee came to him, that she moued him to aske of her
father a field: and shee lighted from off her asse, and Caleb said
vnto her, What wilt thou?</ab>
<ab n="15">And she said vnto
him, Giue me a blessing: for thou hast giuen mee a South land, giue
me also springs of water. And Caleb gaue her the vpper springs, and
the nether springs.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
children of the Kenite, Moses father in law, went vp out of the
citie of palme trees, with the children of Iudah into the
wildernesse of Iudah, which lieth in the South of Arad, and they
went and dwelt among the people.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Iudah went
with Simeon his brother, and they slew the Canaanites that
inhabited Zephath, and vtterly destroyed it, (and the name of the
citie was called Hormah.)<note> Num. 21. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Also Iudah tooke
Gaza with the coast thereof, and Askelon with the coast thereof,
and Ekron with the coast thereof.</ab>

<fw>Calebs portion.</fw>
<ab n="19">And the Lord was
with Iudah, and hee draue out the inhabitants of the mountaine, but
could not driue out the inhabitants of the valley, because they had
charets of yron.<note> Or, he possesed the mountaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And they gaue
Hebron vnto Caleb, as Moses saide: and hee expelled thence the
three sonnes of Anak.<note> Num.14. 24. iosh.14 13. &amp; 15. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And the children
of Beniamin did not driue out the Iebusites that inhabited
Ierusalem: but the Iebusites dwel with the children of Beniamin in
Ierusalem, vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
house of Ioseph, they also went vp against Bethel: and the Lord was
with them.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the house of
Ioseph sent to descrie Bethel (now the name of the citie before was
Luz)<note> Gen.28. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the spies sawe
a man come forth out of the citie, and they said vnto him, Shew vs,
wee pray thee, the entrance into the citie, and we will shew thee
mercie.<note> Iosh.2.14</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And when hee
shewed them the entrance into the citie, they smote the citie with
the edge of the sword: but they let goe the man and all his
familie.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the man went
into the lande of the Hittites, and built a citie, and called the
name thereof Luz: which is the name thereof vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Neither did
Manasseh driue out the inhabitants of Bethshean, and her townes,
nor Taanach and her townes, nor the inhabitants of Dor, and her
townes, nor the inhabitants of Ibleam, and her townes, nor the
inhabitants of Megiddo, and her townes: but the Canaanites would
dwel in that land.<note> Iosh.17. 11,12.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And it came to
passe when Israel was strong, that they put the Canaanites to
tribute, and did not vtterly driue them out.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Neither did
Ephraim driue out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gezer: but the
Canaanites dwelt in Gezer among them.<note> Iosh.16. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Neither did
Zebulun driue out the inhabitants of Kitron, nor the inhabitants of
Nahalol: but the Canaanites dwelt among them, and became
tributaries.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Neither did
Asher driue out the inhabitants of Accho, nor the inhabitants of
Zidon, nor of Ahlab, nor Achzib, nor Helbath, nor Aphik, nor of
Rehob:</ab>
<ab n="32">But the Asherites
dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land: for they
did not driue them out.</ab>

<fw>Israel is reproued.</fw>
<ab n="33">¶ Neither did
Naphtali driue out the inhabitants of Bethshemesh, nor the
inhabitants of Bethanath, but hee dwelt among the Canaanites, the
inhabitants of the land: neuerthelesse, the inhabitants of
Bethshemesh, and of Bethanath, became tributaries vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the Amorites
forced the children of Dan into the mountaine: for they would not
suffer them to come downe to the valley.</ab>
<ab n="35">But the Amorites
would dwell in mount Heres in Aiialon, &amp; in Shaalbim: yet the
hand of the house of Ioseph preuailed, so that they became
tributaries.<note> Hebr. was heauy.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And the coast of
the Amorites was from the going vp to Akrabbim, from the rocke, and
vpward.<note> Or, Maale-Akrabbim.</note></ab>



</div>