<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudges_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judges-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 The Danites send fiue men to seeke
out an inheritance. 3 At the house of Micah they consult with
Ionathan, and are incouraged in their way. 7 They search Laish, and
bring backe newes of good hope. 11 Sixe hundred men are sent to
surprize it. 14 In the way they robbe Micah of his Priest and his
consecrate things. 27 They win Laish and call it Dan. 30 They set
vp Idolatrie, wherein Ionathan inherited the
Priesthood.</head>

<ab n="1">In those dayes
there was no king in Israel: and in those daies the tribe of the
Danites sought them an inheritance to dwel in: for vnto that day,
all their inheritance had not fallen vnto them, among the tribes of
Israel.<note> Chap.17. 6.and 21. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the children
of Dan sent of their family, fiue men from their coasts, men of
valour, from Zorah, and from Eshtaol, to spy out the land, and to
search it, and they said vnto them, Goe, search the land: Who when
they came to mount Ephraim, to the house of Micah, they lodged
there.<note> Hebr. sonnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">When they were by
the house of Micah, they knew the voice of the yong man the Leuite:
and they turned in thither, &amp; said vnto him, Who brought thee
hither? And what makest thou in this place? and what hast thou
here?</ab>

<fw>Spies of Dan search Laish,</fw>
<ab n="4">And hee said vnto
them, Thus and thus dealeth Micah with me, and hath hired me, and I
am his Priest.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they sayd vnto
him, Aske counsell, we pray thee, of God, that we may know, whether
our way which we goe, shall be prosperous.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Priest
said vnto them, Goe in peace: before the Lord is your way wherein
ye goe.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Then the
fiue men departed, and came to Laish, and saw the people that were
therein, how they dwelt carelesse, after the maner of the
Zidonians, quiet and secure, and there was no magistrate in the
land that might put them to shame in any thing, and they were farre
from the Zidonians, and had no businesse with any man.<note> Heb. possessour, or heire of restraint.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And they came vnto
their brethren to Zorah, and Eshtaol: and their brethren said vnto
them, What say yee?</ab>
<ab n="9">And they said,
Arise, that we may goe vp against them: for we haue seene the land,
and behold, it is very good: and are ye still? Bee not slothfull to
goe, and to enter to possesse the land.</ab>
<ab n="10">When ye goe, ye
shall come vnto a people secure, and to a large land: for God hath
giuen it into your handes: a place where there is no want of any
thing, that is in the earth.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And there
went from thence of the family of the Danites out of Zorah, and out
of Eshtaol, sixe hundred men, appoynted with weapons of
warre.<note> Heb. girded.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they went vp,
and pitched in Kiriath-iearim, in Iudah: Wherefore they called that
place Mahaneh-Dan, vnto this day: behold, it is behinde
Kiriath-iearim.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they passed
thence vnto mount Ephraim, and came vnto the house of
Micah.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then
answered the fiue men that went to spie out the countrey of Laish,
and saide vnto their brethren, Doe ye know that there is in these
houses an Ephod, and Teraphim, and a grauen image, and a molten
image? Now therefore consider what ye haue to doe.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they turned
thitherward, and came to the house of the yong man the Leuite, euen
vnto the house of Micah, and saluted him.<note> Heb. asked him of peace.</note></ab>

<fw>Spies of Dan rob Micah, and set vp
idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="16">And the six
hundred men appointed with their weapons of war, which were of the
children of Dan, stood by the entring of the gate.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the fiue men
that went to spie out the land, went vp and came in thither, and
tooke the grauen image, and the Ephod, and the Teraphim, and the
molten image: and the Priest stood in the entring of the gate, with
the sixe hundreth men that were appointed with weapons of
warre.</ab>
<ab n="18">And these went
into Micahs house, and fetched the carued image, the Ephod, and the
Teraphim, and the molten image: then said the Priest vnto them,
What doe ye?</ab>
<ab n="19">And they said
vnto him, Hold thy peace, lay thine hand vpon thy mouth, and goe
with vs, and bee to vs a father and a Priest: Is it better for thee
to bee a Priest vnto the house of one man, or that thou be a Priest
vnto a tribe and a family in Israel?</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Priests
heart was glad, and he tooke the Ephod, and the Teraphim, and the
grauen image, and went in the middest of the people.</ab>
<ab n="21">So they turned,
and departed, and put the little ones, and the cattell, and the
cariage before them.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And when
they were a good way from the house of Micah, the men that were in
the houses neere to Micahs house, were gathered together, and
ouertooke the children of Dan.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they cried
vnto the children of Dan: and they turned their faces, and said
vnto Micah, What aileth thee, that thou commest with such a
company?<note> Heb. that thou art gathered together?</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And he said, Yee
haue taken away my gods which I made, and the Priest, and ye are
gone away: and what haue I more? and what is this that yee say vnto
me, What aileth thee?</ab>
<ab n="25">And the children
of Dan said vnto him, Let not thy voyce bee heard among vs, lest
angry fellowes run vpon thee, and thou lose thy life, with the
liues of thy houshold.<note> Heb. bitter of soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And the children
of Dan went their way: and when Micah sawe that they were too
strong for him, he turned and went backe vnto his house.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they tooke
the things which Micah had made, and the Priest which hee had, and
came vnto Laish, vnto a people that were at quiet, and secure, and
they smote them with the edge of the sword, and burnt the citie
with fire.</ab>

<fw>Spies of Dan rob Micah, and set vp
idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="28">And there was no
deliuerer, because it was farre from Zidon, and they had no
businesse with any man: and it was in the valley that lieth by
Beth-rehob, and they built a citie, and dwelt therein.</ab>
<ab n="29">And they called
the name of the city, Dan, after the name of Dan their father, who
was borne vnto Israel: howbeit the name of the citie was Laish at
the first.<note> Iosh, 19.47.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And the
children of Dan set vp the grauen image: and Ionathan the sonne of
Gershom, the sonne of Manasseh, hee and his sonnes, were Priests to
the tribe of Dan, vntill the day of the captiuitie of the
land.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they set them
vp Micahs grauen image, which hee made, all the time that the house
of God was in Shiloh.</ab>



</div>