<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>3 Iudeth doth set forth herselfe. 10
She and her maide goe forth into the campe. 17 The watch take and
conduct her to Olofernes.</head>

<ab n="1">Now after that she
had ceased to cry vnto the God of Israel, and had made an end of
all these words,</ab>
<ab n="2">She rose where she
had fallen downe, and called her maide, and went downe into the
house, in the which she abode in the Sabbath dayes and in her feast
dayes,</ab>
<ab n="3">And pulled off the
sackcloth which she had on, and put off the garments of her
widowhood, and washed her body all ouer with water, and annointed
herselfe with precious ointment, and braided the haire of her head,
and put on a tire vpon it, and put on her garments of gladnesse,
wherewith she was clad during the life of Manasses her
husband.<note> Gre. miter.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And she tooke
sandals vpon her feete, and put about her, her bracelets and her
chaines, and her rings, and her earerings, and all her ornaments,
and decked her selfe brauely to allure the eyes of all men that
should see her.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then she gaue her
mayd a bottle of wine, and a cruse of oyle, and filled a bagge with
parched corne, and lumpes of figs, and with fine bread, so she
folded all these things together, and layd them vpon
her.<note> Wrapped, or packed.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thus they went
forth to the gate of the citie of Bethulia, and found standiug
there Ozias, and the ancients of the city Chabris, and
Charmis.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when they saw
her, that her countenance was altered, and her apparel was changed,
they wondered at her beautie very greatly, and said vnto
her,</ab>
<ab n="8">The God, the God
of our fathers giue thee fauour, and accomplish thine enterprises
to the glory of the children of Israel, and to the exaltation of
Ierusalem: then they worshipped God.</ab>
<ab n="9">And she said vnto
them, Command the gates of the city to be opened vnto me, that I
may goe forth to accomplish the things, whereof you haue spoken
with me; so they commanded the yong men to open vnto her, as shee
had spoken.</ab>
<ab n="10">And when they had
done so, Iudeth went out, she and her mayd with her, and the men of
the citie looked after her, vntill shee was gone downe the
mountaine, and till she had passed the valley, and could see her no
more.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus they went
straight foorth in the valley: and the first watch of the Assyrians
met her;</ab>
<ab n="12">And tooke her,
and asked her, Of what people art thou? and whence cōmest
thou? and whither goest thou? And she said, I am a woman of the
Hebrewes, and am fled from them: for they shalbe giuen you to be
consumed:</ab>
<ab n="13">And I am comming
before Olofernes the chiefe captaine of your army, to declare words
of trueth, and I will shew him a way, whereby he shall goe, and
winne all the hil countrey, without loosing the body or life of any
one of his men.</ab>
<ab n="14">Now when the men
heard her wordes, and beheld her countenance, they wondered greatly
at her beautie, and said vnto her;</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou hast saued
thy life, in that thou hast hasted to come downe to the presence of
our lord: now therfore come to his tent, and some of vs shall
conduct thee, vntill they haue deliuered thee to his hands.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when thou
standest before him, bee not afraid in thine heart: but shew vnto
him according to thy word, and he will intreat thee well.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then they chose
out of them an hundred men, to accompany her and her mayd, and they
brought her to the tent of Olofernes.<note> Or, and they prepared a chariot for her.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Then was there a
concourse throughout all the campe: for her comming was noised
among the tents, and they came about her, as she stood without the
tent of Olofernes, till they told him of her.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they wondered
at her beautie, and admired the children of Israel because of her,
and euery one said to his neighbour; Who would despise this people,
that haue among them such women, surely it is not good that one man
of them be left, who being let goe, might deceiue the whole
earth.</ab>
<ab n="20">And they that lay
neere Olofernes, went out, and all his seruants, and they brought
her into the tent.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now Olofernes
rested vpon his bed vnder a canopie which was wouen with purple,
and gold, and emeraudes, and precious stones.</ab>
<ab n="22">So they shewed
him of her, and he came out before his tent, with siluer lampes
going before him.</ab>
<ab n="23">And when Iudeth
was come before him and his seruants, they all marueiled at the
beautie of her countenance; and she fel downe vpon her face, and
did reuerence vnto him; and his seruants tooke her vp.</ab>



</div>