<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Iudeth humbleth herselfe, 2 and
prayeth God to prosper her purpose against the enemies of his
sanctuarie.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iudeth
fell vpon her face, and put ashes vpon her head, and vncouered the
sackcloth wherewith she was clothed, and about the time, that the
incense of that euening was offered in Ierusalem, in the house of
the Lord, Iudeth cryed with a loud voyce, and said,</ab>
<ab n="2">O Lord God of
my father Simeon, to whom thou gauest a sword to take vengeance of
the strangers, who loosened the girdle of a maide to defile her,
and discouered the thigh to her shame, and polluted her virginity
to her reproch, (for thou saidst it shall not be so, and yet they
did so.)<note> Gen.34. 2,23.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Wherefore
thou gauest their rulers to be slaine, so that they died their bed
in blood, being deceiued, and smotest the seruants with their
Lords, and the Lords vpon their thrones:</ab>
<ab n="4">And hast
giuen their wiues for a pray, and their daughters to bee captiues,
and all their spoiles to be diuided amongst thy deere children:
which were mooued with thy zeale, and abhorred the pollution of
their blood, and called vpon thee for aide: O God, O my God, heare
me also a widow.</ab>
<ab n="5">For thou hast
wrought not onely those things, but also the things which fell out
before, and which ensewed after, thou hast thought vpon the things
which are now, and which are to come.</ab>
<ab n="6">Yea what
things thou didst determine were redy at hand, and said, loe we are
heere; for all thy wayes are prepared, and thy iudgements are in
thy foreknowledge.</ab>
<ab n="7">For behold,
the Assyrians are multiplyed in their power: they are exalted with
horse and man: they glory in the strength of their footemen: they
trust in shield and speare, and bow, and sling, and know not that
thou art the Lord that breakest the battels: the Lord is thy
name.</ab>
<ab n="8">Throw downe
their strength in thy power, and bring downe their force in thy
wrath; for they haue purposed to defile thy Sanctuary, and to
pollute the Tabernacle, where thy glorious name resteth, and to
cast downe with sword the horne of thy altar.</ab>
<ab n="9">Behold their
pride, and send thy wrath vpon their heads: giue into mine hand
which am a widow, the power that I haue conceiued.</ab>
<ab n="10">Smite by the
deceit of my lips the seruant with the prince, and the prince with
the seruant: breake downe their statelinesse by the hand of a
woman.<note> Iudg.4. 21. &amp; 5.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For thy power
standeth not in multitude, nor thy might in strong men, for thou
art a God of the afflicted, an helper of the oppressed, an vpholder
of the weake, a protector of the forelorne, a sauiour of them that
are without hope.<note> Iudg.7.2. 2.chro.14. 11. and 16. 8. &amp; 20.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I pray thee, I
pray thee, O God of my father, and God of the inheritance of
Israel, Lord of the heauens, and earth, creator of the waters, king
of euery creature: heare thou my prayer:</ab>
<ab n="13">And make my speech
and deceit to be their wound &amp; stripe, who haue purposed cruell
things against thy couenant, and thy hallowed house, and against
the top of Sion, and against the house of the possession of thy
children.</ab>
<ab n="14">And make euery
nation and tribe to acknowledge that thou art the God of all power
and might, and that there is none other that protecteth the people
of Israel but thou.</ab>



</div>