<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 The Assyrians are chased and
slaine. 8 The high Priest commeth to see Iudeth. 11 The stuffe of
Olofernes is giuen to Iudeth. 13 The women crowne her with a
garland.</head>

<ab n="1">And when they that
were in the tents heard, they were astonished at the thing that was
done.</ab>
<ab n="2">And feare and
trembling fell vpon them, so that there was no man that durst abide
in the sight of his neighbour, but rushing out altogether, they
fled into euery way of the plaine, and of the hill
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="3">They also that had
camped in the mountaines, round about Bethulia, fled away. Then the
children of Israel euery one that was a warriour among them, rushed
out vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then sent Ozias to
Bethomasthem, and to Bebai, and Chobai, and Cola, and to all the
coasts of Israel, such as should tell the things that were done,
and that all should rush forth vpon their enemies to destroy
them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now when the
children of Israel heard it, they all fell vpon them with one
consent, and slewe them vnto Choba: likewise also they that came
from Ierusalem, and from all the hill country, for men had told
them what things were done in the campe of their enemies, and they
that were in Galaad and in Galile chased them with a great
slaughter, vntill they were past Damascus, and the borders
thereof.<note> Or, ouercame.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the residue
that dwelt at Bethulia, fell vpon the campe of Assur, and spoiled
them, &amp; were greatly enriched.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the children
of Israel that returned from the slaughter, had that which
remained, and the villages, and the cities that were in the
mountaines, and in the plaine, gate many spoiles: for the multitude
was very great.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then Ioacim the
high Priest, and the Ancients of the children of Israel that dwelt
in Ierusalem, came to behold the good things that God had shewed to
Israel, and to see Iudeth, and to salute her.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when they came
vnto her, they blessed her with one accord, and said vnto her, Thou
art the exaltation of Ierusalem: thou art the great glory of
Israel: thou art the great reioycing of our nation.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou hast done
all these things by thine hand: thou hast done much good to Israel,
and God is pleased therewith: blessed bee thou of the Almightie
Lord for euermore: and all the people said, So be it.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the people
spoiled the campe, the space of thirty dayes, and they gaue vnto
Iudeth Olofernes his tent, and all his plate, and beds, and
vessels, and all his stuffe: and she tooke it, and laide it on her
mule, and made ready her carts, and laid them thereon.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then all the
women of Israel ran together to see her, and blessed her, and made
a dance among them for her: and shee tooke branches in her hand,
&amp; gaue also to the women that were with her.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they put a
garland of oliue vpon her, and her maid that was with her, and shee
went before the people in the dance, leading all the women: and all
the men of Israel followed in their armor with garlands, and with
songs in their mouthes.</ab>



</div>