<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>2 Iudeth will not eate of Olofernes
meate. 7 She taried three dayes in the campe, and euerie night went
forth to pray. 13 Bagoas doth moue her to be merry with Olofernes,
20 who for ioy of her companie drunke much.</head>

<ab n="1">Then hee
commaunded to bring her in, where his plate was set, and bad that
they should prepare for her of his owne meats, and that she should
drinke of his owne wine.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Iudeth said, I
will not eat thereof, lest there bee an offence: but prouision
shall be made for mee of the things that I haue
brought.<note> Gen.43. 32. dan. 1.8 tob.1.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then Olofernes
said vnto her, If thy prouision should faile, howe should we giue
thee the like? for there be none with vs of thy nation.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then said Iudeth
vnto him, As thy soule liueth, my lord, thine handemaid shall not
spend those things that I haue, before the Lord worke by mine hand,
the things þ<note/> he hath determined.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then the seruants
of Olofernes brought her into the tent, and shee slept til
midnight, and she arose when it was towards the morning
watch,</ab>
<ab n="6">And sent to
Olofernes, saying, Let my lord now command, that thine handmaid may
goe forth vnto prayer.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then Olofernes
commaunded his guard that they should not stay her: thus she abode
in the camp three dayes, and went out in the night into the valley
of Bethulia, and washed her selfe in a fountaine of water by the
campe.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when she came
out, shee besought the Lord God of Israel to direct her way, to the
raising vp of the children of her people.</ab>
<ab n="9">So she came in
cleane, and remained in the tent, vntill shee did eate her meat at
euening.</ab>
<ab n="10">And in the fourth
day Olofernes made a feast to his owne seruants only, and called
none of the officers to the banquet.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then said he to
Bagoas the Eunuch, who had charge ouer all that he had: Goe now,
and perswade this Ebrewe woman which is with thee, that she come
vnto vs, and eate and drinke with vs.</ab>
<ab n="12">For loe, it will
be a shame for our person, if we shall let such a woman go, not
hauing had her company: for if we draw her not vnto vs, she will
laugh vs to scorne.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then went Bagoas
from the presence of Olofernes, and came to her, and he said, Let
not this faire damosell feare to come to my lord, and to bee
honoured in his presence, and drink wine, and be merry with vs, and
be made this day as one of the daughters of the Assyrians, which
serue in the house of Nabuchodonosor.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then said Iudeth
vnto him, Who am I now, that I should gainesay my lord? surely
whatsoeuer pleaseth him, I will doe speedily, and it shall bee my
ioy vnto the day of my death.</ab>
<ab n="15">So she arose, and
decked her selfe with her apparell, and all her womans attire, and
her maid went and laid soft skinnes on the ground for her, ouer
against Olofernes, which she had receiued of Bagoas for her daily
vse, that she might sit, and eate vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now when Iudeth
came in, and sate downe, Olofernes his heart was rauished with her,
and his minde was moued, and he desired greatly her company, for
hee waited a time to deceiue her, from the day that he had seene
her.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then said
Olofernes vnto her, Drinke now, and be merry with vs.</ab>
<ab n="18">So Iudeth saide,
I will drinke now my lord, because my life is magnified in me this
day, more then all the dayes since I was borne.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then she tooke
and ate and dranke before him what her maide had prepared.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Olofernes
tooke great delight in her, &amp; dranke much more wine, then he
had drunke at any time in one day, since he was borne.</ab>



</div>