<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>2 Iudeth is left alone with
Olofernes in his tent. 4 She prayeth God to giue her strength 8 She
cut off his head while hee slept. 10 And returned with it to
Bethulia; 17 They saw it, and commend her.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when the
euening was come, his seruants made haste to depart, and Bagoas
shut his tent without, and dismissed the waiters from the presence
of his lord, and they went to their beds: for they were all weary,
because the feast had bene long.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Iudeth was
left alone in the tent, and Olofernes lying along vpon his bed, for
hee was filled with wine.<note> Eccless. 31 20.25</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now Iudeth had
commanded her maide to stand without her bedchamber, and to waite
for her comming forth as she did daily: for she said, she would goe
forth to her prayers, and she spake to Bagoas, according to the
same purpose.</ab>
<ab n="4">So all went forth,
and none was left in the bedchamber, neither little, nor great.
Then Iudeth standing by his bed, said in her heart: O Lord God of
all power, looke at this present vpon the workes of mine hands for
the exaltation of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="5">For now is the
time to helpe thine inheritance, and to execute mine enterprises,
to the destruction of the enemies, which are risen against
vs.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then she came to
the pillar of the bed, which was at Olofernes head, and tooke downe
his fauchin from thence,</ab>
<ab n="7">And approched to
his bed, and tooke hold of the haire of his head, and said,
Strengthen mee, O Lord God of Israel, this day.</ab>
<ab n="8">And she smote
twise vpon his necke with all her might, and she tooke away his
head from him,</ab>
<ab n="9">And tumbled his
body downe from the bed, and pulled downe the canopy from the
pillars, and anon after she went forth, and gaue Olofernes his head
to her maide.</ab>
<ab n="10">And she put it in
her bag of meate, so they twaine went together according to their
custome vnto prayer, and when they passed the campe, they compassed
the valley, and went vp the mountaine of Bethulia, and came to the
gates thereof.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then said Iudeth
a farre off to the watchmen at the gate, Open, open now the gate:
God, euen our God is with vs, to shew his power yet in Ierusalem,
and his forces against the enemie, as he hath euen done this
day.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now when the men
of her citie heard her voyce, they made haste to goe downe to the
gate of their citie, and they called the Elders of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="13">And then they
ranne altogether both small and great, for it was strange vnto them
that she was come: so they opened the gate, and receiued them, and
made a fire for a light, and stood round about them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then she said to
them with a loud voyce, Praise, praise God, praise God, (I say) for
hee hath not taken away his mercy from the house of Israel, but
hath destroyed our enemies by mine hands this night.</ab>
<ab n="15">So she tooke the
head out of the bag, and shewed it, and said vnto them, Behold the
head of Olofernes the chiefe captaine of the armie of Assur, and
behold the canopy wherein he did lie in his drunkennesse, and the
Lord hath smitten him by the hand of a woman.</ab>
<ab n="16">As the Lord
liueth, who hath kept me in my way that I went, my countenance hath
deceiued him to his destruction, and yet hath hee not committed
sinne with mee, to defile and shame mee.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then all the
people were wonderfully astonished, and bowed themselues, and
worshipped God, and said with one accord: Blessed be thou, O our
God, which hast this day brought to nought the enemies of thy
people.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then said Ozias
vnto her, O daughter, blessed art thou of the most high God, aboue
all the women vpon the earth, and blessed be the Lord God, which
hath created the heauens, and the earth, which hath directed thee
to the cutting off of the head of the chiefe of our
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="19">For this thy
confidence shall not depart from the heart of men, which remember
the power of God for euer.</ab>
<ab n="20">And God turne
these things to thee for a perpetuall praise, to visite thee in
good things, because thou hast not spared thy life for
þe affliction of our nation, but hast reuenged our
ruine, walking a straight way before our God: and all the people
said, So be it, so be it.</ab>



</div>