<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-14-14-Judith.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>2 Arphaxad doeth fortifie Ecbatane.
5 Nabuchodonosor maketh warre against him, 7 and craueth aide. 12
Hee threatneth those that would not aide him, 15 and killeth
Arphaxad, 16 and returneth to Nineue.</head>

<ab n="1">In the
twelfth yeere of þ<note/> reigne of Nabuchodonosor, who
reigned in Nineue the great citie, (in the dayes of Arphaxad, which
reigned ouer the Medes in Ecbatane,</ab>
<ab n="2">And built in
Ecbatane walles round about of stones hewen, three cubites broad,
and sixe cubites long, and made the height of the wall seuenty
cubites, and the breadth thereof fiftie cubites:</ab>
<ab n="3">And set the
towers thereof vpon the gates of it, an hundred cubites high, and
the breadth thereof in the foundation threescore cubites.</ab>
<ab n="4">And he made
the gates thereof, euen gates that were raised to the height of
seuentie cubites, &amp; the breadth of them was fourtie cubites,
for the going foorth of his mightie armies, and for the setting in
aray of his footmen.)</ab>
<ab n="5">Euen in those
dayes, king Nabuchodonosor made warre with king Arphaxad in the
great plaine, which is the plaine in the borders of Ragau.</ab>
<ab n="6">And there
came vnto him, all they that dwelt in the hill countrey, and all
that dwelt by Euphrates, and Tigris, and Hydaspes, and the plaine
of Arioch the king of the Elimeans, and very many nations of the
sonnes of Chelod, assembled themselues to the battell.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then
Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians, sent vnto all that dwelt in
Persia, and to all that dwelt Westward, and to those that dwelt in
Cilicia, and Damascus and Libanus, and Antilibanus, and to all that
dwelt vpon the Sea coast,</ab>
<ab n="8">And to those
amongst the nations that were of Carmel, and Galaad, and the higher
Galile, and the great plaine of Esdrelon,</ab>
<ab n="9">And to all
that were in Samaria, and the cities thereof: and beyond Iordan
vnto Ierusalem, and Betane, and Chellus, and Kades, and the riuer
of Egypt, and Taphnes, and Ramesse, and all the land of
Gesem,</ab>
<ab n="10">Untill you come
beyond Tanis, and Memphis, and to all the inhabitants of Egypt,
vntill you come to the borders of Ethiopia.</ab>
<ab n="11">But all the
inhabitants of the land made light of the commandement of
Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians, neither went they with him to
the battell: for they were not afraid of him: yea he was before
them as one man, and they sent away his Ambassadours from them
without effect, and with disgrace.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore
Nabuchodonosor was very angry with all this countrey, and sware by
his throne and kingdome, that hee would surely be auenged vpon all
those coasts of Cilicia, and Damascus, and Syria, and that he would
slay with the sword all the inhabitants of the land of Moab, and
the children of Ammon, and all Iudea, and all that were in Egypt,
till you come to the borders of the two Seas.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then he marched in
battell aray with his power against king Arphaxad in the
seuenteenth yeere, and he preuailed in his battell: for he
ouerthrew all the power of Arphaxad, and all his horsemen and all
his chariots,</ab>
<ab n="14">And became Lord of
his cities, and came vnto Ecbatane, and tooke the towers, and
spoiled the streetes thereof, and turned the beauty thereof into
shame.</ab>
<ab n="15">Hee tooke also
Arphaxad in the mountaines of Ragau, and smote him through with his
dartes, and destroyed him vtterly that day.</ab>
<ab n="16">So he returned
afterward to Nineue, both he and all his company of sundry nations:
being a very great multitude of men of warre, and there he tooke
his ease and banketted, both he and his armie an hundred and twenty
dayes.</ab>




</div>