<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The state and behauiour of Iudeth
a widow. 12 She blameth the gouernors for their promise to yeeld:
17 and aduiseth them to trust in God. 28 They excuse their promise.
32 She promiseth to doe something for them.</head>

<ab n="1">Now at that
time Iudeth heard thereof, which was the daughter of Merari the
sonne of Ox, the sonne of Ioseph, the sonne of Oziel, the sonne of
Elcia, the sonne of Ananias, the sonne of Gedeon, the sonne of
Raphaim, the son of Acitho, the sonne of Eliu, the sonne of Eliab,
the sonne of Nathanael, the sonne of Samael, the sonne of
Salasadai, the son of Israel.<note> Or, Samaliel.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Manasses
was her husband of her tribe and kinred, who died in the barley
haruest.</ab>
<ab n="3">For as hee
stood ouerseeing them that bound sheaues in the field, the heat
came vpon his head, and hee fell on his bed, and died in the city
of Bethulia, and they buried him with his fathers, in the field
betweene Dothaim and Balamo.</ab>
<ab n="4">So Iudeth was
a widow in her house three yeeres, and foure moneths.</ab>
<ab n="5">And she made
her a tent vpon the top of her house, and put on sackecloth on her
loynes, and ware her widowes apparell.</ab>
<ab n="6">And she
fasted all the dayes of her widowhood, saue the eues of the
Sabbath, and the Sabbaths, and the eues of the newe Moones, and the
newe Moones, and the Feasts, and solemne dayes of the house of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">Shee was also
of a goodly countenance, and very beautifull to behold: and her
husband Manasses had left her golde and siluer, and men seruants
and maide seruants, and cattell, and lands, and she remained vpon
them.<note> Or, and she kept them.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And there was
none that gaue her an ill worde; for shee feared God
greatly.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now when shee
heard the euill wordes of the people against the gouernor, that
they fainted for lacke of water (for Iudeth had heard all the
wordes that Ozias had spoken vnto them, and that he had sworne to
deliuer the citie vnto the Assyrians after fiue dayes)<note> Chap.7.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then shee sent her
waiting woman that had the gouernment of all things that she had,
to call Ozias, and Chabris, and Charmis, the ancients of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they came vnto
her, and she said vnto them, Heare me now, O yee gouernours of the
inhabitants of Bethulia: for your wordes that you haue spoken
before the people this day are not right, touching this othe which
ye made, and pronounced betweene God and you, and haue promised to
deliuer the citie to our enemies, vnlesse within these daies the
Lord turne to helpe you.</ab>
<ab n="12">And now who are
you, that haue tempted God this day, &amp; stand in stead of God
amongst the children of men?</ab>
<ab n="13">And now trie the
Lord Almighty, but you shall neuer know any thing.</ab>
<ab n="14">For you cannot
find the depth of the heart of man, neither can ye perceiue the
things that he thinketh: then how can you search out God, that hath
made all these things, and knowe his minde, or comprehend his
purpose? Nay my brethren, prouoke not the Lord our God to
anger.</ab>
<ab n="15">For if he will not
helpe vs within these few dayes, he hath power to defend vs when he
will, euen euery day, or to destroy vs before our enemies.</ab>
<ab n="16">Doe not binde the
counsels of the Lord our God, for God is not as man, that he may be
threatned, neither is he as the sonne of man that he should bee
wauering.<note> Or, ingage. , Numb.23 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Therefore let vs
waite for saluation of him, and call vpon him to helpe vs, and he
will heare our voyce if it please him.</ab>
<ab n="18">For there arose
none in our age, neither is there any now in these daies, neither
tribe, nor familie, nor people, nor city among vs, which worship
gods made with hands, as hath bene aforetime.<note> Or, towne.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For the which
cause our fathers were giuen to the sword, &amp; for a spoile, and
had a great fall before our enemies.<note> Iudg.2.11 and 4.1. and 6.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But we know none
other god: therefore we trust that he will not despise vs, nor any
of our nation.</ab>
<ab n="21">For if we be taken
so, all Iudea shall lie waste, and our Sanctuarie shal be spoiled,
and he will require the prophanation thereof, at our mouth.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the slaughter
of our brethren, and the captiuitie of the countrey, and the
desolation of our inheritance, will he turne vpon our heads among
the Gentiles, wheresoeuer we shall bee in bondage, and we shall be
an offence and a reproch to all them that possesse vs.<note> Or, feare.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For our seruitude
shall not be directed to fauour: but the Lord our God shall turne
it to dishonour.</ab>
<ab n="24">Now therefore, O
brethren, let vs shew an example to our brethren, because their
hearts depend vpon vs, and the Sanctuary, and the house, and the
Altar rest vpon vs.</ab>
<ab n="25">Moreouer, let vs
giue thankes to the Lord our God, which trieth vs, euen as he did
our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="26">Remember what
things he did to Abraham, and how he tried Isaac, and what happened
to Iacob in Mesopotamia of Syria, when he kept the sheepe of Laban
his mothers brother.<note> Gen.22.1 , Gen.28.7</note></ab>
<ab n="27">For, hee hath not
tried vs in the fire as he did them, for the examination of their
hearts, neither hath hee taken vengeance on vs: but the Lord doeth
scourge them that come neere vnto him to admonish them.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then said Ozias to
her, All that thou hast spoken, hast thou spoken with a good heart,
and there is none that may gainesay thy words.</ab>
<ab n="29">For this is not
the first day wherin thy wisedome is manifested, but from the
beginning of thy dayes all thy people haue knowen thy
vnderstanding, because the disposition of thine heart is
good.</ab>
<ab n="30">But the people
were very thirsty, and compelled vs to doe vnto them as we haue
spoken, and to bring an othe vpon our selues, which wee will not
breake.</ab>
<ab n="31">Therefore now pray
thou for vs, because thou art a godly woman, and the Lord will send
vs raine to fill our cisternes, and we shall faint no more.</ab>
<ab n="32">Then said Iudeth
vnto them, Heare me, and I wil doe a thing, which shall goe
throughout all generations, to the children of our nation.</ab>
<ab n="33">You shall stand
this night in the gate, and I will goe foorth with my waiting
woman: and within the dayes that you haue promised to deliuer the
citie to our enemies, the Lord will visit Israel by mine
hand.</ab>
<ab n="34">But inquire not
you of mine act: for I will not declare it vnto you, til the things
be finished that I doe.</ab>
<ab n="35">Then said Ozias
and the princes vnto her, Goe in peace, and the Lord God be before
thee, to take vengeance on our enemies.</ab>
<ab n="36">So they returned
from the tent, and went to their wards.</ab>



</div>