<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>4 Olofernes is appointed generall,
11 and charged to spare none, that will not yeeld. 15 His armie and
prouision, 23 the places which he wonne and wasted, as he
went.</head>

<ab n="1">And in the
eighteenth yeere, the two and twentieth day of the first month,
there was talke in the house of Nabuchodonosor king of the
Assyrians, that he should as he said auenge himselfe on all the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="2">So he called
vnto him all his officers, and all his nobles, and communicated
with them his secret counsell, and concluded the afflicting of the
whole earth out of his owne mouth.<note> 1.Sam.20 7. and 25. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then they
decreed to destroy all flesh that did not obey the commaundement of
his mouth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when he
had ended his counsell, Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians called
Olofernes the chiefe captaine of his army, which was next vnto him,
and said vnto him,<note> Gre. second man.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thus saith
the great king, the Lord of the whole earth: behold, thou shalt goe
forth from my presence, and take with thee men that trust in their
owne strength, of footemen an hundred and twenty thousand, and the
number of horses with their riders twelue thousand.</ab>
<ab n="6">And thou
shalt goe against all the West countrey, because they disobeyed my
commandement.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thou
shalt declare vnto them that they prepare for me earth and water:
for I will goe forth in my wrath against them, and will couer the
whole face of the earth with the feete of mine armie, and I will
giue them for a spoile vnto them.<note> Or, after the maner of the kings of Persia, to whom earth and water was wont to be giuen to acknowledge that they were Lords of land and sea. Herodotus.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">So that their
slaine shall fill their vallies, and brookes, and the riuer shall
be filled with their dead, til it ouerflow.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I will
lead them captiues to the vtmost parts of all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou therefore
shalt goe foorth, and take before hand for me all their coasts, and
if they will yeeld themselues vnto thee, thou shalt reserue them
for me till the day of their punishment.</ab>
<ab n="11">But concerning
them that rebell, let not thine eye spare them: but put them to the
slaughter, and spoile them wheresoeuer thou goest.</ab>
<ab n="12">For as I liue, and
by the power of my kingdome, whatsoeuer I haue spoken, that will I
doe by mine hand.</ab>
<ab n="13">And take thou
heede that thou transgresse none of the Commaundements of thy Lord,
but accomplish them fully, as I haue commaunded thee, and deferre
not to doe them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then Olofernes
went foorth from the presence of his Lord, and called all the
gouernours and Captaines, and the officers of the army of
Assur.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he mustered
the chosen men for the battell, as his Lord had commaunded him,
vnto an hundred and twenty thousand, &amp; twelue thousand archers
on Horsebacke.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he ranged them
as a great army is ordered for the warre.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he tooke
Camels, and Asses for their cariages a very great number, and
sheepe, and Oxen, &amp; Goates without number, for their
prouision,</ab>
<ab n="18">And plenty of
vittaile for euery man of the army, and very much gold, and siluer,
out of the Kings house.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then he went
foorth and all his power to go before King Nabuchodonosor in the
voyage, and to couer al the face of the earth Westward with their
charets, and horsemen, and their chosen footmen.</ab>
<ab n="20">A great multitude
also of sundry countries came with them, like locusts, and like the
sand of the earth: for the multitude was without number.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they went
foorth of Nineue, three dayes iourney toward the plaine of
Bectileth, and pitched from Bectileth neere the mountaine, which is
at the left hand of the vpper Cilicia.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then he tooke all
his armie, his footmen, and horsemen and chariots, and went from
thence into the hill countrey,</ab>
<ab n="23">And destroyed
Phud, and Lud: and spoiled all the children of Rasses, and the
children of Ismael, which were toward the wildernesse at the South
of the land of the Chellians.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then he went ouer
Euphrates, and went through Mesopotamia, and destroyed all the high
cities that were vpon the riuer Arbonai, till you come to the
sea.</ab>
<ab n="25">And hee tooke the
borders of Cilicia, and killed all that resisted him, and came to
the borders of Iapheth, which were toward the South, ouer against
Arabia.</ab>
<ab n="26">He compassed also
all the children of Madian, and burnt vp their tabernacles, and
spoiled their sheepcoats.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then hee went
downe into the plaine of Damascus in the time of wheat haruest, and
burnt vp all their fieldes, and destroyed their flockes, and
heards, also he spoiled their cities, and vtterly wasted their
countreys, and smote all their yong men with the edge of the
sword.</ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore the
feare and dread of him, fell vpon all the inhabitants of the sea
coastes, which were in Sidon and Tyrus, and them that dwelt in Sur,
and Ocina, and all that dwelt in Ienmaan, and they that dwelt in
Azotus, and Aschalon feared him greatly.</ab>



</div>