<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-16-16-Additions-to-Esther.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The song of Iudeth. 19 She
dedicateth the stuffe of Olofernes. 23 Shee died at Bethulia a
widow of great honour. 24 All Israel did lament her
death.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Iudeth began
to sing this thankesgiuing in all Israel, and all the people sang
after her this song of praise.<note> Or, this praising.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Iudeth said,
Begin vnto my God with timbrels, sing vnto my Lord with cymbals:
tune vnto him a newe Psalme: exalt him, &amp; cal vpon his
name.<note> Or, Psalme and praise.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For God breaketh
the battels: for amongst the campes in the midst of the people hee
hath deliuered me out of the hands of them that persecuted
me.</ab>
<ab n="4">Assur came out of
the mountains from the North, he came with ten thousands of his
army, the multitude wherof stopped the torrents, and their horsemen
haue couered the hilles.<note> Chap.2. 11,15.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">He bragged that he
would burne vp my borders, and kill my young men with the sword,
and dash the sucking children against the ground, and make mine
infants as a pray, and my virgins as a spoile.</ab>
<ab n="6">But the Almighty
Lord hath disappointed them by the hand of a woman.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the mighty one
did not fall by the yong men, neither did the sonnes of the Titans
smite him, nor high gyants set vpon him: but Iudeth the daughter of
Merari weakned him with the beautie of her countenance.</ab>
<ab n="8">For she put off
the garment of her widowhood, for the exaltation of those that were
oppressed in Israel, and anointed her face with oyntment, &amp;
bound her haire in a tyre, and tooke a linnen garment to deceiue
him.<note> Gr. or miter.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Her sandals
rauished his eyes, her beautie tooke his minde prisoner, and the
fauchin passed through his necke.</ab>
<ab n="10">The Persians
quaked at her boldnesse, and the Medes were daunted at her
hardinesse.<note> Or, confounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then my afflicted
shouted for ioy, and my weake ones cryed aloude; but they were
astonished: these lifted vp their voices, but they were
ouerthrowen.<note> The Assyrians.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The sonnes of the
damosels haue pierced them through, and wounded them as fugitiues
children: they perished by the battell of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">I will sing vnto
the Lord a new song, O Lord thou art great and glorious, wonderful
in strength &amp; inuincible.<note> Or, a song of praise.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Let all creatures
serue thee: for thou spakest, and they were made, thou didst send
forth thy spirit, and it created them, and there is none that can
resist thy voyce.</ab>
<ab n="15">For the
mountaines shall be mooued from their foundations with the waters,
the rockes shall melt as waxe at thy presence: yet thou art
mercifull to them that feare thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">For all sacrifice
is too little for a sweete sauour vnto thee, and all the fat is not
sufficient, for thy burnt offering: but he that feareth the Lord is
great at all times.</ab>
<ab n="17">Woe to the
nations that rise vp against my kinred: the Lord almighty will take
vengeance of them in the day of iudgement in putting fire &amp;
wormes in their flesh, and they shall feele them and weepe for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now assoone as
they entred into Ierusalem, they worshipped the Lord, and assoone
as the people were purified, they offered their burnt offerings,
and their free offerings, and their gifts.</ab>
<ab n="19">Iudeth also
dedicated all the stuffe of Olofernes, which the people had giuen
her, and gaue the canopy which she had taken out of his bed
chamber, for a gift vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">So the people
continued feasting in Ierusalem before the Sanctuarie, for the
space of three moneths, and Iudeth remained with them.</ab>
<ab n="21">After this time,
euery one returned to his owne inheritance, and Iudeth went to
Bethulia, and remained in her owne possession, and was in her time
honourable in all the countrey.</ab>
<ab n="22">And many desired
her, but none knew her all the dayes of her life, after that
Manasses her husband was dead, and was gathered to his
people.</ab>
<ab n="23">But she encreased
more and more in honour, and waxed olde in her husbands house,
being an hundred and fiue yeeres olde, and made her maide free, so
shee died in Bethulia: and they buried her in the caue of her
husband Manasses.<note> Or, sepulchre.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the house of
Israel lamented her seauen dayes, and before shee dyed, she did
distribute her goods to all them that are neerest of kinred to
Manasses her husband: and to them that were the neerest of her
kinred.<note> Gen.50. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And there was
none that made the children of Israel any more afraide, in the
dayes of Iudeth, nor a long time after her death.</ab>



</div>