<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>3 Olofernes asketh Iudeth the cause
of her comming. 6 She telleth him how, and when hee may preuaile.
20 Hee is much pleased with her wisedome and beautie.</head>

<ab n="1">Then said
Olofernes vnto her, Woman, bee of good comfort, feare not in thine
heart: for I neuer hurt any, that was willing to serue
Nabuchodonosor the king of all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="2">Now therefore if
thy people that dwelleth in the mountaines, had not set light by
me, I would not haue lifted vp my speare against them: but they
haue done these things to themselues.</ab>
<ab n="3">But now tell me
wherefore thou art fled from them, and art come vnto vs: for thou
art come for safeguard, be of good comfort, thou shalt liue this
night, and hereafter.</ab>
<ab n="4">For none shall
hurt thee, but intreat thee well, as they doe the seruants of king
Nabuchodonosor my lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then Iudeth said
vnto him, Receiue the words of thy seruant, and suffer thine
handmaid to speake in thy presence, and I will declare no lie to my
lord this night.</ab>
<ab n="6">And if thou wilt
follow the words of thine handmaid, God will bring the thing
perfectly to passe by thee, and my lord shall not faile of his
purposes,</ab>
<ab n="7">As Nabuchodonosor
king of all the earth liueth, and as his power liueth, who hath
sent thee for the vpholding of euery liuing thing: for not only men
shall serue him by thee, but also the beasts of the field, and the
cattell, and the foules of the aire shall liue by thy power, vnder
Nabuchodonosor and all his house.</ab>
<ab n="8">For wee haue heard
of thy wisedome, and thy policies, and it is reported in all the
earth, that thou onely art excellent in all the kingdome, and
mightie in knowledge, and wonderfull in feates of
warre.<note> Or, in fauour.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Now as concerning
the matter which Achior did speake in thy counsell, we haue heard
his words; for the men of Bethulia saued him, and hee declared vnto
them all that hee had spoken vnto thee.<note> Or, gate him.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Therefore, O lord
and gouernor, reiect not his word, but lay it vp in thine heart,
for it is true, for our nation shall not be punished, neither can
the sword preuaile against them, except they sinne against their
God.</ab>
<ab n="11">And now, that my
lord be not defeated, and frustrate of his purpose, euen death is
now fallen vpon them, and their sinne hath ouertaken them,
wherewith they will prouoke their God to anger, whensoeuer they
shall doe that which is not fit to be done.</ab>
<ab n="12">For their
victuals faile them, and all their water is scant, and they haue
determined to lay hands vpon their cattell, and purposed to consume
all those things, that God hath forbidden them to eate by his
Lawes,</ab>
<ab n="13">And are resolued
to spend the first fruits of the corne, &amp; the tenths of wine
and oyle, which they had sanctified, and reserued for the Priests
that serue in Ierusalem, before the face of our God, the which
things it is not lawfull for any of the people so much as to touch
with their hands.</ab>
<ab n="14">For they haue
sent some to Ierusalem, because they also that dwelt there haue
done the like, to bring them a license from the Senate.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now when they
shall bring them word, they will forthwith doe it, and they shall
be giuen thee to be destroyed the same day.</ab>
<ab n="16">Wherefore I thine
handmaide knowing all this, am fledde from their presence, &amp;
God hath sent me to worke things with thee, whereat all the earth
shalbe astonished, and whosoeuer shall heare it.</ab>
<ab n="17">For thy seruant
is religious, and serueth the God of heauen day &amp; night: now
therefore, my lord, I will remaine with thee, and thy seruant will
goe out by night into the valley, and I will pray vnto God, and he
wil tel me when they haue committed their sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="18">And I will come,
and shew it vnto thee: then thou shalt goe forth with all thine
army, and there shall be none of them that shall resist
thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I will leade
thee through the midst of Iudea, vntill thou come before Ierusalem,
and I will set thy throne in the midst thereof, and thou shalt
driue them as sheep that haue no shepheard, and a dogge shall not
so much as open his mouth at thee: for these things were tolde mee,
according to my foreknowledge, and they were declared vnto me, and
I am sent to tell thee.<note> Or, barke , Or, these things haue I spoken.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then her wordes
pleased Olofernes, and all his seruants, and they marueiled at her
wisedome, and said,</ab>
<ab n="21">There is not such
a woman from one end of the earth to the other, both for beautie of
face, and wisedome of wordes.</ab>
<ab n="22">Likewise
Olofernes said vnto her, God hath done well to send thee before the
people, that strength might be in our hands, and destruction vpon
them that lightly regard my lord:</ab>
<ab n="23">And now thou art
both beautifull in thy countenance, and wittie in thy wordes;
surely if thou doe as thou hast spoken, thy God shall be my God,
and thou shalt dwel in the house of king Nabuchodonosor, and shalt
be renowmed through the whole earth.</ab>



</div>