<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>8 Achior heareth Iudeth shewe what
she had done, and is circumcised, 11 the head of Olofernes is
hanged vp, 15 hee is found dead, and much lamented.</head>

<ab n="1">Then saide Iudeth
vnto them, Heare me now, my brethren, &amp; take this head, and
hang it vpon the highest place of your walles.<note> 2.Mac.15. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And so soone as
the morning shall appeare and the Sunne shal come forth vpon the
earth, take you euery one his weapons, and goe forth euery valiant
man out of the city, &amp; set you a captaine ouer them, as though
you would goe downe into the field toward the watch of the
Assyrians, but goe not downe.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then they shal
take their armour, and shal goe into their campe, and raise vp the
captaines of the armie of Assur, and they shall runne to the tent
of Olofernes, but shall not finde him, then feare shall fall vpon
them, and they shall flee before your face.</ab>
<ab n="4">So you, and all
that inhabite the coast of Israel, shall pursue them, and ouerthrow
them as they goe.</ab>
<ab n="5">But before you doe
these things, call me Achior the Ammonite, that hee may see and
know him that despised the house of Israel, and that sent him to vs
as it were to his death.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then they called
Achior out of the house of Ozias, and when hee was come, and saw
the head of Olofernes in a mans hand, in the assembly of the
people, he fell downe on his face, and his spirit failed.</ab>
<ab n="7">But when they had
recouered him, hee fell at Iudeths feete, and reuerenced her, and
said: Blessed art thou in all the tabernacle of Iuda, and in all
nations, which hearing thy name shall be astonished.</ab>
<ab n="8">Now therefore tell
mee all the things that thou hast done in these dayes: Then Iudeth
declared vnto him in the midst of the people, all that shee had
done from the day that shee went foorth, vntill that houre she
spake vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="9">And when shee had
left off speaking, the people shouted with a lowd voice, &amp; made
a ioyful noise in their citie.</ab>
<ab n="10">And when Achior
had seene all that the God of Israel had done, hee beleeued in God
greatly, and circumcised the foreskinne of his flesh, and was
ioyned vnto the house of Israel vnto this day.</ab>
<ab n="11">And assoone as
the morning arose, they hanged the head of Olofernes vpon the wall,
and euery man took his weapons, and they went foorth by bandes vnto
the straits of the mountaine.<note> Or, ascents</note></ab>
<ab n="12">But when the
Assyrians sawe them, they sent to their leaders, which came to
their Captaines, and tribunes, and to euery one of their
rulers.</ab>
<ab n="13">So they came to
Olofernes tent, and said to him that had the charge of all his
things, Waken now our lord: for the slaues haue beene bold to come
downe against vs to battell, that they may be vtterly
destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then went in
Bagoas, and knocked at the doore of the tent: for he thought that
he had slept with Iudeth.</ab>
<ab n="15">But because none
answered, he opened it, and went into the bedchamber, and found him
cast vpon the floore dead, &amp; his head was taken from
him.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore he
cried with a lowd voice, with weeping, and sighing, and a mighty
cry, and rent his garments.<note> Then.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">After, hee went
into the tent, where Iudeth lodged, and when hee found her not, he
leaped out to the people, and cried,</ab>
<ab n="18">These slaues haue
dealt treacherously, one woman of the Hebrewes hath brought shame
vpon the house of king Nabuchodonosor: for behold, Olofernes lieth
vpon the ground without a head.</ab>
<ab n="19">When the
captaines of the Assyrians armie heard these words, they rent their
coats, and their minds were wonderfully troubled, and there was a
cry, and a very great noise throughout the campe.</ab>



</div>