<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 They of the Sea-coasts entreat for
peace. 7 Olofernes is receiued there: 8 Yet he destroyeth their
gods, that they might worship onely Nabuchodonosor. 9 He commeth
neere to Iudea.</head>

<ab n="1">So they sent
Embassadours vnto him, to treat of peace, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Behold, we
the seruants of Nabuchodonosor the great king lie before thee; vse
vs as shall be good in thy sight.</ab>
<ab n="3">Behold, our
houses, and all our places, and all our fieldes of wheat, and
flockes, and heards, and all the lodges of our tents, lie before
thy face: vse them as it pleaseth thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Behold, euen
our cities and the inhabitants thereof are thy seruants, come and
deale with them, as seemeth good vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="5">So the men
came to Holofernes, &amp; declared vnto him after this
maner.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then came hee
downe toward the Sea coast, both hee and his armie, and set
garisons in the high cities, and tooke out of them chosen men for
aide.</ab>
<ab n="7">So they and
all the countrey round about, receiued them with garlands, with
dances, and with timbrels.</ab>
<ab n="8">Yet hee did
cast downe their frontiers, and cut downe their groues: for hee had
decreed to destroy all the gods of the land, that all nations
should worship Nabuchodonosor onely, and that all tongues and
tribes should call vpon him as God.</ab>
<ab n="9">Also he came
ouer against Esdraelon neere vnto Iudea, ouer against the great
strait of Iudea.<note> Or, Esdrelom. , Or, Doæa, Dothan. Iunius. Genes. 37.17. , Gr, great saw.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And hee pitched
betweene Geba, and Scythopolis, and there hee taried a whole
moneth, that he might gather together all the cariages of his
armie.</ab>



</div>