<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Holofernes besiegeth Bethulia, 7
and stoppeth the water from them. 22 They faint and murmure against
the gouernours, 30 Who promise to yeeld within fiue
dayes.</head>

<ab n="1">The next day
Holofernes commanded all his army, and all his people which were
come to take his part, that they should remooue their campe against
Bethulia, to take aforehand the ascents of the hill countrey, and
to make warre against the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then their
strong men remoued their campes in that day, and the armie of the
men of warre was, an hundred and seuenty thousand footmen, and
twelue thousand horsemen, beside the baggage, &amp; other men that
were afoot amongst them, a very great multitude.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they
camped in the valley neere vnto Bethulia, by the fountaine, and
they spred themselues in breadth ouer Dothaim, euen to Belmaim, and
in length from Bethulia vnto Cyamon which is ouer against
Esdraelon.<note> From Dothaim. Iunius. , Greek. beane field.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Now the
children of Israel when they saw the multitude of them, were
greatly troubled, and said euery one to his neighbour: Now will
these men licke vp the face of the earth; for neither the high
mountaines, nor the valleys, nor the hils, are able to beare their
waight.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then euery
man tooke vp his weapons of warre, and when they had kindled fires
vpon their towers, they remained and watched all that
night.</ab>
<ab n="6">But in the
second day Holofernes brought foorth all his horsemen, in the sight
of the children of Israel which were in Bethulia,</ab>
<ab n="7">And viewed
the passages vp to the city, and came to the fountaine of their
waters, and tooke them, and set garrisons of men of warre ouer
them, and he himselfe remooued towards his people.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then came
vnto him all the chiefe of the children of Esau, and al the
gouernours of the people of Moab, and the captaines of the sea
coast, and said,</ab>
<ab n="9">Let our lord
now heare a word, that there be not an ouerthrow in thine
armie.</ab>
<ab n="10">For this people of
the children of Israel do not trust in their speares, but in the
height of the mountaines wherein they dwell, because it is not
easie to come vp to the tops of their mountains.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now therefore my
lord, fight not against them in battell aray, and there shall not
so much as one man of thy people perish.</ab>
<ab n="12">Remaine in thy
campe, and keepe all the men of thine army, and let thy seruants
get into their hands the fountaine of water which issueth foorth of
the foot of the mountaine.</ab>
<ab n="13">For all the
inhabitants of Bethulia haue their water thence: so shall thirst
kil them, &amp; they shall giue vp their citie, and we and our
people shal goe vp to the tops of the mountaines that are neere,
and will campe vpon them, to watch that none goe out of the
city.</ab>
<ab n="14">So they and their
wiues, and their children shalbe consumed with famine, and before
the sword come against them, they shall be ouerthrowen in the
streets where they dwel.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thus shalt thou
render them an euil reward: because they rebelled and met not thy
person peaceably.</ab>
<ab n="16">And these words
pleased Holofernes, and al his seruants, and he appointed to doe as
they had spoken.</ab>
<ab n="17">So the campe of
the children of Ammon departed, and with them fiue thousand of the
Assyrians, and they pitched in the valley, and tooke the waters,
and the fountaines of the waters of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then the children
of Esau went vp, with the children of Ammon, and camped in the hil
countrey ouer against Dotha-em: and they sent some of them toward
the South, &amp; toward the East ouer against Ekrebel, which is
neere vnto Chusi, that is vpon the brooke Mochmur, and the rest of
the army of the Assyrians camped in the plaine, and couered the
face of the whole land, and their tents and cariages were pitched
to a very great multitude.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then the children
of Israel cried vnto the Lord their God, because their heart
failed, for all their enemies had compassed them round about, &amp;
there was no way to escape out from among them.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thus all the
company of Assur remained about them, both their footmen, charets
and horsemen, foure and thirtie dayes, so that all their vessels of
water failed all the inhabitants of Bethulia.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the cisternes
were emptied, and they had not water to drinke their fill, for one
day; for they gaue them drinke by measure.<note> Or, pits.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore their
young children were out of heart, and their women and yong men
fainted for thirst, and fell downe in the streetes of the city, and
by the passages of the gates, and there was no longer any strength
in them.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then all the
people assembled to Ozias, and to the chiefe of the city, both
young men, and women, and children, and cryed with a loude voice,
and saide before all the Elders;</ab>
<ab n="24">God be Iudge
betweene vs and you: for you haue done vs great iniury in that you
haue not required peace of the children of Assur.<note> Exo.5.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For now we haue no
helper: but God hath sold vs into their hands, that wee should be
throwen downe before them with thirst, and great
destruction.</ab>
<ab n="26">Now therefore call
them vnto you, and deliuer the whole citie for a spoile to the
people of Olofernes, and to all his armie.</ab>
<ab n="27">For it is better
for vs to be made a spoile vnto them, then to die for thirst: for
wee will be his seruants, that our soules may liue, and not see the
death of our infants before our eyes, nor our wiues nor our
children to die.</ab>
<ab n="28">We take to
witnesse against you, the heauen and the earth, and our God, and
Lord of our fathers, which punisheth vs according to our sinnes,
and the sinnes of our fathers, that hee doe not according as we
haue said this day.<note> Or, lest he doe: meaning, Olofernes.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Then there was
great weeping with one consent in the middest of the assembly, and
they cryed vnto the Lord God with a loude voice.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then said Ozias to
them, Brethren, be of good courage, let vs yet endure fiue dayes,
in the which space the Lord our God may turne his mercy toward vs,
for he will not forsake vs vtterly.</ab>
<ab n="31">And if these dayes
passe, and there come no helpe vnto vs, I wil doe according to your
word.</ab>
<ab n="32">And he dispersed
the people euery one to their owne charge, and they went vnto the
walles and towres of their citie, and sent the women and children
into their houses, and they were very low brought in the
city.</ab>



</div>