<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>4 The Iewes are afraid of
Holofernes, 5 and fortifie the hilles. 6 They of Bethulia take
charge of the passages. 9 All Israel fall to fasting and
prayer.</head>

<ab n="1">Now the
children of Israel that dwelt in Iudea, heard all that Holofernes
the chiefe captaine of Nabuchodonosor king of the Assyrians had
done to the nations, and after what manner hee had spoiled all
their Temples, and brought them to nought.</ab>
<ab n="2">Therefore
they were exceedingly afraid of him, and were troubled for
Ierusalem, and for the Temple of the Lord their God.</ab>
<ab n="3">For they were
newly returned from the captiuitie, and all the people of Iudea
were lately gathered together: and the vessels, and the Altar, and
the house, were sanctified after the profanation.<note> Or, out of Iudea.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore
they sent into all the coasts of Samaria, and the villages, and to
Bethoron, and Belmen, and Iericho, and to Choba, and Esora, and to
the valley of Salem,</ab>
<ab n="5">And possessed
themselues beforehand of all the tops of the high mountaines, and
fortified the villages that were in them, and laid vp victuals for
the prouision of warre: for their fieldes were of late
reaped.</ab>
<ab n="6">Also Ioacim
the hie Priest which was in those daies in Ierusalem, wrote to them
that dwelt in Bethulia, and Betomestham which is ouer against
Esdraelon toward the open countrey neere to Dothaim,<note> Or, Esdrelom. , Or, plaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Charging them
to keepe the passages of the hill countrey: for by them there was
an entrance into Iudea, and it was easie to stoppe them that would
come vp, because the passage was strait for two men at the
most.<note> Or, two against all.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the
children of Israel did as Ioacim the hie Priest had commanded them,
with the ancients of all the people of Israel, which dwelt at
Ierusalē.<note> Or, gouernours.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then euery
man of Israel cryed to God with great feruencie, and with great
vehemency did they humble their soules:</ab>
<ab n="10">Both they and
their wiues, and their children, and their cattell, and euery
stranger and hireling, and their seruants bought with money, put
sackecloth vpon their loynes.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus euery man and
woman, and the little children, &amp; the inhabitants of Ierusalem
fell before the temple, and cast ashes vpon their heads, and spread
out their sackcloth before the face of the Lord: also they put
sackecloth about the Altar,</ab>
<ab n="12">And cryed to the
God of Israel all with one consent earnestly, that hee would not
giue their children for a pray, and their wiues for a spoile, and
the cities of their inheritance to destruction, and the Sanctuary
to profanation and reproch, &amp; for the nations to reioyce
at.</ab>
<ab n="13">So God heard their
prayers, and looked vpon their afflictions: for the people fasted
many dayes in all Iudea, and Ierusalem, before the Sanctuary of the
Lord Almighty.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Ioacim the
high Priest, and all the Priestes that stood before the Lord, and
they which ministred vnto the Lord, had their loines girt with
sackecloth, and offered the daily burnt offerings, with the vowes
and free gifts of the people,</ab>
<ab n="15">And had ashes on
their miters, and cried vnto the Lord with all their power, that
hee would looke vpon all the house of Israel graciously.</ab>



</div>