<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CJudith_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Judith-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>3 Holofernes despiseth God. 7 He
threatneth Achior and sendeth him away. 14 The Bethulians receiue
and heare him. 18 They fall to prayer, and comfort
Achior.</head>

<ab n="1">And when the
tumult of men that were about the councell was ceased, Holofernes
the chiefe captaine of the armie of Assur, said vnto Achior and all
the Moabites, before all the company of other nations,</ab>
<ab n="2">And who art
thou Achior and the hirelings of Ephraim, that thou hast prophesied
amongst vs as to day, and hast said, that we should not make warre
with the people of Israel, because their God will defend them? and
who is God but Nabuchodonosor?</ab>
<ab n="3">He will send
his power, and will destroy them from the face of the earth, and
their God shall not deliuer them: but we his seruants will destroy
them as one man, for they are not able to sustaine the power of our
horses.</ab>
<ab n="4">For with them
we will tread them vnder foote, and their mountains shall be
drunken with their blood, and their fields shall be filled with
their dead bodies, and their footesteps shall not be able to stand
before vs, for they shal vtterly perish, saith king Nabuchodonosor
Lord of all the earth; for hee said, none of my words shall be in
vaine.</ab>
<ab n="5">And thou
Achior, an hireling of Ammon, which hast spoken these words in the
day of thine iniquity, shalt see my face no more, from this day
vntill I take vengeance of this nation that came out of
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="6">And then
shall the sword of mine armie, and the multitude of them that serue
me, passe through thy sides, and thou shalt fal among their slaine,
when I returne.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now therefore
my seruants shall bring thee backe into the hill countrey, and
shall set thee in one of the cities of the passages.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou
shalt not perish till thou be destroyed with them.</ab>
<ab n="9">And if thou
perswade thy selfe in thy minde, that they shall not be taken, let
not thy countenance fall: I haue spoken it, and none of my words
shall be in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then Holofernes
commanded his seruants that waited in his tent, to take Achior and
bring him to Bethulia, and deliuer him into the hands of the
children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">So his seruants
tooke him, and brought him out of the campe into the plaine, and
they went from the midst of the plaine into the hill countrey, and
came vnto the fountaines that were vnder Bethulia.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when the men
of the citie saw them, they tooke vp their weapons, and went out of
the citie to the toppe of the hill, and euery man that vsed a sling
from comming vp by casting of stones against them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Neuerthelesse
hauing gotten priuily vnder the hill, they bound Achior and cast
him downe, and left him at the foote of the hill, and returned to
their Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">But the Israelites
descended from their citie, and came vnto him, and loosed him, and
brought him into Bethulia, and presented him to the gouernours of
the citie,</ab>
<ab n="15">Which were in
those dayes Ozias the sonne of Micha of the tribe of Simeon, and
Chabris the sonne of Gothoniel, and Charmis the sonne of
Melchiel.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they called
together all the ancients of the citie, and all their youth ranne
together, and their women to the assembly, and they set Achior in
the midst of all their people. Then Ozias asked him of that which
was done.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he answered
and declared vnto them the words of the counsell of Holofernes, and
all the words that he had spoken in the midst of the princes of
Assur, and whatsoeuer Holofernes had spoken proudly against the
house of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then the people
fell downe, and worshipped God, and cryed vnto God, saying,</ab>
<ab n="19">O Lord God of
heauen, behold their pride, and pity the low estate of our nation,
and looke vpon the face of those that are sanctified vnto thee this
day.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then they
comforted Achior and praised him greatly.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Ozias tooke
him out of the assembly vnto his house, and made a feast to the
Elders, &amp; they called on the God of Israel all that night for
helpe.</ab>




</div>