<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLamentations_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Zion bewaileth her pitifull
estate. 13 She confesseth her sinnes. 21 Edom is threatned. 22 Zion
is comforted.</head>

<ab n="1">How is the
gold become dimme! how is the most fine gold changed! the stones of
the sanctuarie are powred out in the top of euery streete.</ab>
<ab n="2">The precious
sonnes of Zion, comparable to fine gold, how are they esteemed as
earthen pitchers, the worke of the hands of the potter!</ab>
<ab n="3">Euen the
sea-monsters draw out the breast, they giue sucke to their young
ones: the daughter of my people is become cruell, like the
ostriches in the wildernesse.<note> Or, sea calues.</note></ab>

<fw>The miseries of Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="4">The tongue of
the sucking child cleaueth to the roofe of his mouth for thirst:
the young children aske bread, and no man breaketh it vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="5">They that did
feede delicatly, are desolate in the streetes: they that were
brought vp in scarlet, embrace dounghilles.</ab>
<ab n="6">For the
punishment of the iniquitie of the daughter of my people, is
greater then the punishment of the sinne of Sodom, that was
ouerthrowen as in a moment, and no hands stayed on her.<note> Or, iniquitie. , Gen.19.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Her Nazarites
were purer then snow, they were whiter then milke, they were more
ruddie in body then rubies, their polishing was of Saphir.</ab>
<ab n="8">Their visage
is blacker then a cole: they are not knowen in the streets: their
skinne cleaueth to their bones: it is withered, it is become like a
sticke.<note> Heb. darker then blacknesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">They that bee
slaine with the sword, are better then they that be slain with
hunger: for these pine away, stricken through for want of the
fruits of the field.<note> Heb. flow out.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The hands of
the pitifull women haue sodden their owne children, they were their
meate in the destruction of the daughter of my people.<note> 2.Kings 6.29. deut. 28.57.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord
hath accomplished his furie, he hath powred out his fierce anger,
and hath kindled a fire in Zion, and it hath deuoured the
foundations thereof.</ab>
<ab n="12">The kings of
the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world would not haue
beleeued, that the aduersarie and the enemie should haue entred
into the gates of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ For
the sinnes of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, that
haue shed the blood of the iust in the middest of her:<note> Ier.5.31. and 23. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">They haue
wandred as blind men in the streetes, they haue polluted themselues
with blood, so that men could not touch their garments.<note> Or, in that they could not but touch.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">They cryed
vnto them; Depart yee, it is vncleane, depart, depart, touch not,
when they fled away and wandred: they said among the heathen, They
shall no more soiourne there.<note> Or, yee polluted.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The anger of
the Lord hath diuided them, he will no more regard them: they
respected not the persons of the priests, they fauoured not the
elders.<note> Or, face.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">As for vs,
our eyes as yet failed for our vaine helpe: in our watching we haue
watched for a nation that could not saue vs.</ab>

<fw>The great miserie of the
people.</fw>
<ab n="18">They hunt
our steps that we cannot goe in our streets: our end is neere, our
dayes are fulfilled, for our ende is come.</ab>
<ab n="19">Our
persecutours are swifter then the eagles of the heauen: they
pursued vs vpon the mountaines, they laide waite for vs in the
wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="20">The breath
of our nostrels, the anointed of the Lord was taken in their pits,
of whom we said, Under his shadowe we shall liue among the
heathen.<note> Gen.2.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶
Reioyce and be glad, O daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the lande
of Uz, the cup also shall passe through vnto thee: thou shalt be
drunken, and shalt make thy selfe naked.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ The
punishment of thine iniquitie is accomplished, O daughter of Zion,
he will no more carie thee away into captiuitie: hee will visit
thine iniquitie, O daughter of Edom, hee will discouer thy
sinnes.<note> Or, thine iniquitie. , Or, carie thee captiue for thy sinnes</note></ab>



</div>