<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLamentations_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jeremiah-Chapter-52-52b-Lamentations.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The miserable estate of Ierusalem
by reason of her sinne, 12 Shee complaineth of her griefe, 18 and
confesseth Gods iudgement to be righteous.</head>

<ab n="1">How doeth the
citie sit solitarie that was full of people? How is she become as a
widow? She that was great among the nations, and princesse among
the prouinces, how is she become tributarie?</ab>
<ab n="2">Shee weepeth
sore in the night, and her teares are on her cheekes: among all her
louers she hath none to comfort her, all her friends haue dealt
treacherously with her, they are become her enemies.<note> Ier.13.17. , Iob.7.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Iudah is gone
into captiuitie, because of affliction, and because of great
seruitude: she dwelleth among the heathen, she findeth no rest: all
her persecutors ouertook her betweene the straits.<note> Heb. for the greatnesse of seruitude.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The wayes of
Zion do mourne, because none come to the solemne feasts: all her
gates are desolate: her priests sigh: her virgins are afflicted,
and she is in bitternesse.</ab>
<ab n="5">Her
aduersaries are the chiefe, her enemies prosper: for the Lord hath
afflicted her; for the multitude of her transgressions, her
children are gone into captiuitie before the enemie.<note> Deut. 28. 13. , Ier. 52. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And from the
daughter of Zion all her beautie is departed: her princes are
become like Harts that find no pasture, &amp; they are gone without
strength before the pursuer.</ab>
<ab n="7">Ierusalem
remembred in the dayes of her affliction, and of her miseries, all
her pleasant things that she had in the dayes of old, when her
people fell into the hand of the enemie, and none did helpe her,
the aduersaries saw her, and did mocke at her Sabbaths.<note> Or, desireable.</note></ab>

<fw>The yoke of sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="8">Ierusalem
hath grieuously sinned, therefore she is remoued: all that honoured
her, despise her, because they haue seene her nakednesse: yea, shee
sigheth and turneth backward.<note> Heb. is become a remouing or wandering.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Her filthines
is in her skirts, she remembreth not her last end, therfore she
came downe wonderfully: shee had no comforter: O Lord, behold my
affliction: for þe enemie hath magnified
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="10">The
aduersarie hath spread out his hand vpon all her pleasant things:
for she hath seene that the heathen entred into her Sanctuarie,
whom thou didst command that they should not enter into thy
congregation.<note> Or, desireable. , Deu.23.3</note></ab>
<ab n="11">All her
people sigh, they seek bread, they haue giuen their pleasant things
for meate to relieue the soule: see, O Lord, &amp; consider: for I
am become vile.<note> Or, to make the soule to come againe.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Is it
nothing to you, all ye that passe by? Behold and see, if there be
any sorow like vnto my sorowe, which is done vnto me, wherewith the
Lord hath afflicted me, in the day of his fierce anger.<note> Or, it is nothing. , Heb. passe by the way.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">From aboue
hath he sent fire into my bones, and it preuaileth against them: he
hath spread a net for my feete, he hath turned me backe: he hath
made me desolate, and faint all the day.</ab>
<ab n="14">The yoke of
my transgressions is bound by his hand: they are wreathed, and come
vp vpon my necke: he hath made my strength to fall, the Lord hath
deliuered me into their hands, from whom I am not able to rise
vp.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Lord
hath troden vnder foot all my mightie men in the midst of me: he
hath called an assembly against mee, to crush my yong men. The Lord
hath troden the virgine, the daughter of Iudah, as in a wine
presse.<note> Or, the winepresse of the virgine, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For these
things I weepe, mine eye, mine eye runneth downe with water,
because the comforter that should relieue my soule is farre from
me: my children are desolate, because the enemy
preuailed.<note> Ier.13.17 and 14.17. chap. 2.18. , Heb. bring backe.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Zion
spreadeth forth her hands, and there is none to comfort her: the
Lord hath commanded concerning Iacob, that his aduersaries should
bee round about him: Ierusalem is as a menstruous woman among
them.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ The
Lord is righteous, for I haue rebelled against his commandement:
heare, I pray you, all people, and behold my sorow: my virgins and
my yong men are gone into captiuitie.<note> Dan.9.7. , Heb. mouth.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods wrath.</fw>
<ab n="19">I called for
my louers, but they deceiued me: my priests and mine elders gaue vp
the ghost in the citie, while they sought their meat to relieue
their soules</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, O
Lord: for I am in distresse: my bowels are troubled: mine heart is
turned within mee, for I haue grieuously rebelled: abroad the sword
bereaueth, at home there is as death.<note> Isa.16.11. iere.48.36.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">They haue
heard that I sigh, there is none to comfort me: all mine enemies
haue heard of my trouble, they are glad that thou hast done it:
thou wilt bring the day that thou hast called, and they shall be
like vnto me.<note> Or, proclaimed.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Let all
their wickednes come before thee: and doe vnto them, as thou hast
done vnto me for all my transgressions: for my sighes are many, and
my heart is faint.</ab>



</div>