<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLamentations_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The faithfull bewaile their
calamities. 22 By the mercies of God they nourish their hope. 37
They acknowledge Gods iustice. 55 They pray for deliuerance, 64 and
vengeance on their enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">I Am the man
that hath seene affliction by the rod of his wrath.</ab>
<ab n="2">He hath led
me and brought mee into darkenesse, but not into light.</ab>

<fw>The mercies of the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="3">Surely
against me is he turned, he turneth his hand against me all the
day.</ab>
<ab n="4">My flesh and
my skinne hath he made old, he hath broken my bones.</ab>
<ab n="5">He hath
builded against me, and compassed me with gall and trauel.</ab>
<ab n="6">He hath set
me in darke places, as they that be dead of old.</ab>
<ab n="7">He hath
hedged me about, that I cannot get out: hee hath made my chaine
heauie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Also when I
cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer.</ab>
<ab n="9">Hee hath
inclosed my wayes with hewen stone: he hath made my pathes
crooked.</ab>
<ab n="10">He was vnto
me as a Beare lying in waite, and as a Lion in secret
places.</ab>
<ab n="11">Hee hath
turned aside my wayes, and pulled me in pieces: hee hath made me
desolate.</ab>
<ab n="12">He hath bent
his bow, and set me as a marke for the arrow.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hee hath
caused the arrowes of his quiuer to enter into my
reines.<note> Heb. sons.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I was a
derision to all my people, and their song all the day.<note> Iere.20.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hee hath
filled me with bitternesse, hee hath made me drunken with
wormewood.<note> Heb. bitternesses.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">He hath also
broken my teeth with grauell stones, hee hath couered me with
ashes.<note> Or, rolled me in the ashes.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And thou
hast remoued my soule farre off from peace: I forgate
prosperitie.<note> Heb. good.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And I said,
My strength and my hope is perished from the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="19">Remembring
mine affliction and my miserie, the wormewood &amp; the
gall.<note> Or, remember.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">My soule
hath them still in remembrance, and is humbled in me.<note> Heb. bowed</note></ab>
<ab n="21">This I
recall to my mind, therefore haue I hope.<note> Heb. make to returne to my heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ It is
of the Lords mercies that wee are not consumed, because his
compassions faile not.</ab>
<ab n="23">They are
newe euery morning: great is thy faithfulnesse.</ab>
<ab n="24">The Lord is
my portion, sayth my soule, therefore will I hope in
him.<note> Psal. 16.5. and 73.26. and 119.57. iere. 10.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The Lord is
good vnto them that waite for him, to the soule that seeketh
him.</ab>
<ab n="26">It is good
that a man should both hope and quietly wait for the saluation of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="27">It is good
for a man that he beare the yoke in his youth.</ab>

<fw>The mercies of the Lord.</fw>
<ab n="28">Hee sitteth
alone and keepeth silence, because hee hath borne it vpon
him.</ab>
<ab n="29">He putteth
his mouth in the dust, if so be there may be hope.</ab>
<ab n="30">Hee giueth
his cheeke to him that smiteth him, hee is filled full with
reproch.</ab>
<ab n="31">For the Lord
will not cast off for euer.</ab>
<ab n="32">But though
hee cause griefe, yet will hee haue compassion according to the
multitude of his mercies.</ab>
<ab n="33">For he doth
not afflict willingly, nor grieue the children of men.<note> Heb. from his heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">To crush
vnder his feete all the prisoners of the earth,</ab>
<ab n="35">To turne
aside the right of a man before the face of the most
high,<note> Or, a superiour.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">To subuert a
man in his cause, the Lord approoueth not.<note> Or, seeth not.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">¶ Who
is hee that sayth, and it commeth to passe, when the Lord
commandeth it not?<note> Psal.33.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Out of the
mouth of the most hie proceedeth not euill and good?<note> Amos 3.6</note></ab>
<ab n="39">Wherefore
doeth a liuing man complaine, a man for the punishment of his
sinnes?<note> Or, murmure.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Let vs
search and try our waies, and turne againe to the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="41">Let vs lift
vp our heart with our hands vnto God in the heauens.</ab>
<ab n="42">We haue
transgressed, and haue rebelled, thou hast not pardoned.</ab>
<ab n="43">Thou hast
couered with anger, and persecuted vs: thou hast slaine, thou hast
not pitied.</ab>
<ab n="44">Thou hast
couered thy selfe with a cloud, that our prayer should not passe
through.</ab>
<ab n="45">Thou hast
made vs as the offscouring and refuse in the middest of the
people.<note> 1.Cor.4.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">All our
enemies haue opened their mouthes against vs.</ab>
<ab n="47">Feare and a
snare is come vpon vs, desolation and destruction.<note> Isai.24.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Mine eye
runneth downe with riuers of water, for the destruction of the
daughter of my people.</ab>
<ab n="49">Mine eye
trickleth downe and ceaseth not, without any intermission:</ab>
<ab n="50">Till the
Lord looke downe, and behold from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="51">Mine eye
affecteth mine heart, because of all the daughters of my
city.<note> Heb. my soule. , Or, more then all.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Mine enemies
chased me sore like a bird, without cause.</ab>

<fw>The miseries of Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="53">They haue
cut off my life in the dungeon, and cast a stone vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="54">Waters
flowed ouer mine head, then I sayd, I am cut off.</ab>
<ab n="55">¶ I
called vpon thy name, O Lord, out of the low dungeon.</ab>
<ab n="56">Thou hast
heard my voice, hide not thine eare at my breathing, at my
crie.</ab>
<ab n="57">Thou drewest
neere in the day that I called vpon thee: thou saidst, Feare
not.</ab>
<ab n="58">O Lord, thou
hast pleaded the causes of my soule, thou hast redeemed my
life.</ab>
<ab n="59">O Lord, thou
hast seene my wrong, iudge thou my cause.</ab>
<ab n="60">Thou hast
seene all their vengeance; and all their imaginations against
me.</ab>
<ab n="61">Thou hast
heard their reproch, O Lord, and all their imaginations against
me:</ab>
<ab n="62">The lippes
of those that rose vp against me, and their deuice against me all
the day.</ab>
<ab n="63">Behold,
their sitting downe and their rising vp, I am their
musicke.</ab>
<ab n="64">¶
Render vnto them a recompense, O Lord, according to the worke of
their hands.</ab>
<ab n="65">Giue them
sorrow of heart, thy curse vnto them.<note> Or, obstinacie of heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="66">Persecute
and destroy them in anger, from vnder the heauens of the
Lord.<note> Psal.8.4.</note></ab>



</div>