<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLamentations_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Lamentations-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>A pitifull complaint of Zion, in
prayer vnto God.</head>

<ab n="1">Remember, O
Lord, what is come vpon vs: consider and beholde our
reproch.</ab>
<ab n="2">Our
inheritance is turned to strangers, our houses to aliants.</ab>
<ab n="3">We are
orphanes and fatherlesse, our mothers are as widowes.</ab>
<ab n="4">We haue
drunken our water for money, our wood is sold vnto vs.<note> Heb. commeth for price.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Our neckes
are vnder persecution: we labour and haue no rest.<note> Heb. on our necks are we persecuted.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">We haue giuen
the hand to the Egyptians, and to the Assyrians, to be satisfied
with bread.</ab>

<fw>The great miserie of the
people.</fw>
<ab n="7">Our fathers
haue sinned and are not, and wee haue borne their
iniquities.<note> Ier.31.29 ezek.18.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Seruants haue
ruled ouer vs: there is none that doeth deliuer vs out of their
hand.</ab>
<ab n="9">We gate our
bread with the perill of our liues, because of the sword of the
wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="10">Our skinne
was blacke like an ouen, because of the terrible
famine.<note> Psal.11.38 , Or, terrors or stormes.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They
rauished the women in Zion, and the maides in the cities of
Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="12">Princes are
hanged vp by their hand: the faces of Elders were not
honoured.</ab>
<ab n="13">They tooke
the young men to grinde, and the children fell vnder the
wood.</ab>
<ab n="14">The Elders
haue ceased from the gate, the young men from their
musicke.</ab>
<ab n="15">The ioy of
our heart is ceased, our daunce is turned into mourning.</ab>
<ab n="16">The crowne
is fallen from our head: Woe vnto vs, that wee haue
sinned.<note> Hebr. the crowne of our head is fallen.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For this our
heart is faint, for these things our eyes are dimme.</ab>
<ab n="18">Because of
the mountaine of Zion, which is desolate, the foxes walke vpon
it.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thou, O
Lord, remainest for euer: thy throne from generation to
generation.<note> Psal.9.8. and 29.10. and 102.13. &amp; 145.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Wherefore
doest thou forget vs for euer, and forsake vs so long
time?<note> Heb. for length of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Turne thou
vs vnto thee, O Lord, and we shall be turned: renew our dayes as of
old.<note> Ier.31.18</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But thou
hast vtterly reiected vs: thou art very wroth against
vs.<note> Or, for wilt thou vtterly reiect vs?</note></ab>



</div>