<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The meate offering of flower with
oile and incense, 4 either baken in the ouen, 5 or on a plate, 7 or
in a frying pan, 12 Or of the first fruits in the eare. 13 The salt
of the meate offering.</head>

<ab n="1">And when any
will offer a meate offering vnto the Lord, his offring shall be of
fine flowre: and hee shall powre oyle vpon it, and put frankincense
thereon.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he shall
bring it to Aarons sonnes the Priests: and hee shall take thereout
his handfull of the flowre thereof, and of the oile thereof, with
all the frankincense thereof, and the Priest shall burne the
memoriall of it vpon the altar, to be an offering made by fire of a
sweet sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the remnant
of the meat offering shall be Aarons and his sonnes: it is a thing
most holy of the offerings of the Lord made by fire.<note> Ecclus.7. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And if
thou bring an oblation of a meate offering baken in the ouen, it
shall bee an vnleauened cake of fine flowre mingled with oyle, or
vnleauened wafers anointed with oyle.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And if
thy oblation be a meate offering baken in a panne, it shall bee of
fine flowre vnleauened, mingled with oyle.<note> Or, on a flat plate or, slice.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou shalt part
it in pieces, and powre oyle thereon: it is a meate
offering.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And if
thy oblation be a meate offering baken in the frying pan, it shalbe
made of fine flowre with oyle.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou shalt
bring the meat offering that is made of these things vnto the Lord,
and when it is presented vnto the Priest, he shall bring it vnto
the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the Priest
shall take from the meat offering a memoriall thereof, and shall
burne it vpon the Altar, it is an offering made by fire of a sweet
sauour vnto the Lord.<note> Verse 2. , Exod.29. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And that which
is left of the meat offering, shalbe Aarons and his sonnes: It is a
thing most holy, of the offerings of the Lord made by fire.</ab>

<fw>Meat offering.</fw>
<ab n="11">No meat
offering, which ye shall bring vnto the Lord, shall be made with
leauen: For ye shall burne no leauen, nor any hony, in any offering
of the Lord made by fire.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ As for
the oblation of the first fruits, yee shall offer them vnto the
Lord, but they shall not be burnt on the Altar for a sweet
sauour.<note> Hebr. ascend.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And euery
oblation of thy meat offering shalt thou season with salt; neither
shalt thou suffer the salt of the Couenant of thy God to bee
lacking from thy meat offering: with all thine offerings thou shalt
offer salt.<note> Marke 9. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And if thou
offer a meat offering of thy first fruits vnto the Lord, thou shalt
offer for the meat offering of thy first fruits, greene eares of
corne dried by the fire, euen corne beaten out of full
eares.</ab>
<ab n="15">And thou shalt
put oyle vpon it, and lay frankincense theron; it is a meat
offering.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Priest
shall burne the memoriall of it, part of the beaten corne thereof,
and part of the oyle thereof, with all the frankincense thereof: it
is an offering made by fire vnto the Lord.</ab>



</div>