<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 The oyle for the lampes. 5 The
Shewbread. 10 Shelomiths sonne blasphemeth. 13 The Law of
Blasphemie. 17 Of Murther. 18 Of Damage. 23 The blasphemer is
stoned.</head>


<fw>The Shewbread.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Command the
children of Israel, that they bring vnto thee pure oyle Oliue,
beaten, for the light, to cause the lampes to burne
continually.<note> Hebr. to cause to ascend.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Without the
Uaile of the Testimonie, in the Tabernacle of the Congregation,
shal Aaron order it from the euening vnto the morning, before the
Lord continually: It shall be a Statute for euer in your
generations.</ab>
<ab n="4">He shall order
the lampes vpon the pure Candlesticke before the Lord
continually.<note> Exo. 31.8</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And thou
shalt take fine flowre, and bake twelue cakes thereof: two tenth
deales shall be in one cake.<note> Exod. 25. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And thou shalt
set them in two rowes, sixe on a row vpon the pure Table, before
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thou shalt
put pure frankincense vpon ech row, that it may bee on the bread
for a memorial, euen an offering made by fire vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">Euery Sabbath
he shall set it in order before the Lord continually, being taken
from the children of Israel by an euerlasting couenant.</ab>
<ab n="9">And it shall be
Aarons and his sonnes, and they shall eate it in the holy place:
for it is most holy vnto him, of the offerings of the Lord made by
fire, by a perpetuall statute.<note> Exod. 29. 33. chap.8. 31. mat.12. 1, 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
sonne of an Israelitish woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went
out among the children of Israel: and this sonne of the Israelitish
woman, and a man of Israel stroue together in the campe.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the
Israelitish womans sonne blasphemed the name of the Lord, and
cursed, and they brought him vnto Moses: and his mothers name was
Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they put
him in ward, that the minde of the Lord might bee shewed
them.<note> Numb.15 34. , Heb. to expound vnto them according to the mouth of the LORD.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="14">Bring forth
him that hath cursed, without the Campe, and let all that heard
him, lay their hands vpon his head, and let all the Congregation
stone him.<note> Deut. 13. 9. and 17.7</note></ab>

<fw>Against murder.</fw>
<ab n="15">And thou shalt
speake vnto the children of Israel, saying, Whosoeuer curseth his
God, shall beare his sinne.</ab>
<ab n="16">And hee that
blasphemeth the Name of the Lord, he shall surely be put to death,
and all the Congregation shall certainely stone him: Aswell the
stranger, as he that is borne in the land, when he blasphemeth the
Name of the Lord, shall be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And he
that killeth any man, shall surely be put to death.<note> Exod. 21. 12. deu.19. 21. , Hebr. smiteth the life of a man.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And he that
killeth a beast, shall make it good; beast for beast.<note> Hebr. life for life.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And if a man
cause a blemish in his neighbour; as he hath done, so shal it be
done to him:<note> Exod. 21. 24. deu.19. 21. matth. 5.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Breach, for
breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth: as he hath caused a blemish
in a man, so shall it be done to him againe.</ab>
<ab n="21">And hee that
killeth a beast, hee shall restore it: and hee that killeth a man,
he shall be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="22">Ye shall haue
one maner of law, aswell for the stranger, as for one of your owne
countrey: for I am the Lord your God.<note> Exod. 12. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
Moses spake to the children of Israel, that they should bring
foorth him that had cursed, out of the Campe, and stone him with
stones: and the children of Israel did as the Lord commanded
Moses.</ab>



</div>