<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The first offerings of Aaron, for
himselfe and the people. 8 The sinne-offering, 12 and the burnt
offering for himselfe. 15 The offerings for the people. 23 Moses
and Aaron blesse the people. 24 Fire commeth from the Lord, vpon
the Altar.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe on the eight day, that Moses called Aaron and his sonnes, and
the elders of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee saide
vnto Aaron, Take thee a yong calfe for a sinne offering, and a
ramme for a burnt offering, without blemish, and offer them before
the Lord.<note> Exod. 29. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And vnto the
children of Israel thou shalt speake, saying, Take ye a kid of the
goats, for a sinne offering, and a calfe, and a lambe, both of the
first yeere without blemish, for a burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="4">Also a bullocke
and a ramme, for peace offerings, to sacrifice before the Lord, and
a meat offring mingled with oyle: for to day the Lord will appeare
vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And they
brought that which Moses commanded, before the Tabernacle of the
Congregation: and all the Congregation drew neere and stood before
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses said,
This is the thing which the Lord commanded that ye should doe: and
the glory of the Lord shall appeare vnto you.</ab>

<fw>Aarons offerings.</fw>
<ab n="7">And Moses said
vnto Aaron, Goe vnto the Altar, and offer thy sinne offering, and
thy burnt offering, and make an atonement for thy selfe, and for
the people: and offer the offering of the people, and make an
atonement for them, as the Lord commanded.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Aaron
therefore went vnto the Altar, and slew the calfe of the sinne
offering, which was for himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the sonnes
of Aaron brought the blood vnto him, and he dipt his finger in the
blood, and put it vpon the hornes of the Altar, and powred out the
blood at the bottome of the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="10">But the fat and
the kidneys, and the caule aboue the liuer of the sinne offering he
burnt vpon the Altar, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the flesh
and the hide he burnt with fire, without the campe.</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee slew
the burnt offering, and Aarons sonnes presented vnto him the blood,
which he sprinckled round about vpon the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they
presented the burnt offering vnto him, with the pieces thereof, and
the head: and he burnt them vpon the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he did wash
the inwards, and the legs, and burnt them vpon the burnt offering
on the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And he
brought the peoples offering, and tooke the goat, which was the
sinne offering for the people, and slew it, and offered it for
sinne, as the first.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he brought
the burnt offring, and offered it according to the
maner.<note> Or, ordinance.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And he brought
the meat offring, and tooke an handfull thereof, and burnt it vpon
the Altar, beside the burnt sacrifice of the morning.<note> Hebr. filled his hand out of it. , Exod. 29. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">He slew also
the bullocke and the ramme, for a sacrifice of peace offerings,
which was for the people: And Aarons sonnes presented vnto him the
blood, (which hee sprinckled vpon the Altar round about)</ab>
<ab n="19">And the fat of
the bullocke and of the ramme, the rumpe, and that which couereth
the inwards, and the kidneys, and the caule aboue the
liuer,</ab>
<ab n="20">And they put
the fat vpon the brests, &amp; he burnt the fat vpon the
altar:</ab>
<ab n="21">And the breasts
and the right shoulder, Aaron waued for a waue offering before the
Lord, as Moses commanded.</ab>

<fw>His sonnes burnt.</fw>
<ab n="22">And Aaron lift
up his hand towards the people, and blessed them, and came downe
from offering of the sinne offering, and the burnt offering, and
peace offerings.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Moses and
Aaron went into the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and came out,
and blessed the people: and the glory of the Lord appeared vnto all
the people.</ab>
<ab n="24">And there came
a fire out from before the Lord, and consumed vpon the Altar the
burnt offering, and the fat: which when all the people saw, they
shouted, and fell on their faces.<note> Gen. 4.4. 1.king.18. 38. 2.chro.7.1. 2.macc. 10.11.</note></ab>



</div>