<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Nadab and Abihu, for offering of
strange fire, are burnt by fire. 6 Aaron and his sonnes are
forbidden to mourne for them. 8 The Priests are forbidden wine when
they are to goe into the Tabernacle. 12 The law of eating the holy
things. 16 Aarons excuse for transgressing thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">And Nadab and
Abihu, the sonnes of Aaron, tooke either of them his censer, and
put fire therein, and put incense thereon, and offered strange fire
before the Lord, which hee commaunded them not.<note> Num.3.4. and 26.61. 1.chron.24 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And there went
out fire from the Lord and deuoured them, and they died before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then Moses said
vnto Aaron, This is it that the Lord spake, saying, I will bee
sanctified in them that come nigh me, and before all the people I
will be glorified: And Aaron held his peace.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Moses
called Mishael and Elzaphan the sonnes of Uzziel, the vncle of
Aaron, and said vnto them, Come neere, cary your brethren from
before the Sanctuary, out of the campe.</ab>
<ab n="5">So they went
neere, and caried them in their coats out of the campe, as Moses
had said.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses said
vnto Aaron, and vnto Eleazar and vnto Ithamar his sonnes, Uncouer
not your heads, neither rend your clothes, lest you die, and lest
wrath come vpon all the people: But let your brethren, the whole
house of Israel, bewaile the burning which the Lord hath
kindled.</ab>

<fw>Wine forbidden.</fw>
<ab n="7">And ye shal not
goe out from the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, lest
you die: for the anointing oyle of the Lord is vpon you: and they
did according to the word of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="9">Doe not drinke
wine nor strong drinke, thou, nor thy sonnes with thee, when ye goe
into the Tabernacle of the Congregation, lest yee die: It shall bee
a statute for euer, throughout your generations:</ab>
<ab n="10">And that ye
may put difference betweene holy and vnholy, and betweene vncleane
and cleane:</ab>
<ab n="11">And that ye
may teach the children of Israel all the statutes which the Lord
hath spoken vnto them by the hand of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
Moses spake vnto Aaron, and vnto Eleazar and vnto Ithamar his
sonnes that were left, Take the meate offering that remaineth of
the offerings of the Lord made by fire, and eate it without leauen,
beside the altar: for it is most holy.</ab>
<ab n="13">And ye shal
eat it in the holy place, because it is thy due, and thy sonnes due
of the sacrifices of the Lord, made by fire: for so I am
commanded.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the waue
breast and heaue shoulder shall ye eate in a cleane place, thou,
and thy sonnes, and thy daughters with thee: For they be thy due
and thy sonnes due, which are giuen out of the sacrifice of peace
offerings, of the children of Israel.<note> Exod. 29. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The heaue
shoulder, and the waue breast shal they bring, with the offrings
made by fire of the fat, to waue it for a waue offering before the
Lord: and it shall bee thine, and thy sonnes with thee, by a
statute for euer, as the Lord hath commanded.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
Moses diligently sought the goate of the sinne offering, and
behold, it was burnt: and he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar,
the sonnes of Aaron, which were left aliue, saying,</ab>
<ab n="17">Wherefore haue
ye not eaten the sinne offering in the holy place, seeing it is
most holy, and God hath giuen it you to beare the iniquitie of the
Congregation, to make atonement for them, before the Lord?</ab>

<fw>Beasts cleane, &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="18">Behold, the
blood of it was not brought in, within the holy place: yee should
indeed haue eaten it in the holy place, as I commanded.<note> Chap.6. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Aaron said
vnto Moses, Behold, this day haue they offered their sinne
offering, and their burnt offering before the Lord: and such things
haue befallen me: and if I had eaten the sinne offering to day,
should it haue bin accepted in the sight of the Lord?</ab>
<ab n="20">And when Moses
heard that, he was content.</ab>



</div>