<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 How the hie Priest must enter into
the Holy place. 11 The sinne-offering for himselfe. 15 The
sinne-offering for the people. 20 The Scape Goat. 29 The yeerely
Feast of the Expiations.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, after the death of the two sonnes of Aaron, when
they offered before the Lord, and died.<note> Leuit. 10. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
sayd vnto Moses, Speake vnto Aaron thy brother, that hee come not
at all times in to the Holy place within the Uaile, before the
Mercy seat, which is vpon the Arke, that hee die not: for I will
appeare in the cloud vpon the Mercy seat.<note> Exod. 30. 10. Heb.9. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thus shall
Aaron come into the Holy place: with a yong bullocke for a sinne
offering, and a ramme for a burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="4">Hee shall put
on the holy linnen coate, and he shall haue the linnen breeches
vpon his flesh, and shall be girded with a linnen girdle, and with
the linnen Miter shall hee be attired. These are holy garments:
therefore shall he wash his flesh in water, and so put them
on.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he shall
take of the Congregation of the children of Israel, two kiddes of
the Goates for a sinne offering, and one ramme for a burnt
offering.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Aaron shall
offer his bullocke of the sinne offering, which is for himselfe,
and make an atonement for himselfe, and for his house.<note> Hebr.9. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And he shall
take the two goats, and present them before the Lord at the doore
of the Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Aaron shall
cast lottes vpon the two Goates: one lot for the Lord, and the
other lot for the Scape goat.<note> Hebr. Azazel.</note></ab>

<fw>The Scape goat.</fw>
<ab n="9">And Aaron shall
bring the goate vpon which the Lords lot fell, and offer him for a
sinne offering.<note> Hebr. went vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But the goat
on which the lot fell to be the Scape goate, shalbe presented aliue
before the Lord, to make an atonement with him, and to let him goe
for a Scape goate into the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Aaron shal
bring the bullocke of the sinne offering, which is for himselfe,
and shall make an atonement for himselfe, and for his house, and
shal kill the bullocke of the sinne offering which is for
himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he shall
take a censer full of burning coales of fire from off the Altar
before the Lord, and his handes full of sweet incense beaten small,
and bring it within the vaile.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he shall
put the incense vpon the fire before the Lord, that the cloud of
the incense may couer the mercie seate that is vpon the testimonie,
that he die not.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he shall
take of the blood of the bullocke, and sprinkle it with his finger
vpon the Mercie seat Eastward: and before the Mercie seate shall
hee sprinkle of the blood with his finger seuen times.<note> Heb.9.13 and 10.4. , Chap.4.6</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then
shall he kill the goate of the sinne offering that is for the
people, and bring his blood within the Uaile, and doe with that
blood as he did with the blood of the bullocke, and sprinkle it
vpon the Mercie seat, and before the Mercie seat.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he shall
make an atonement for the holy place, because of the vncleannesse
of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions in
all their sinnes: and so shall hee doe for the Tabernacle of the
Congregation that remaineth among them, in the middest of their
vncleannesse.<note> Heb. dwelleth.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And there
shall bee no man in the Tabernacle of the Congregation, when hee
goeth in to make an atonement in the holy place, vntill hee come
out, and haue made an atonement for himselfe, and for his houshold,
and for all the Congregation of Israel.<note> Luk.1.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And he shall
goe out vnto the Altar that is before the Lord, and make an
atonement for it, &amp; shall take of the blood of the bullocke,
and of the blood of the goate, and put it vpon the hornes of the
Altar round about.</ab>

<fw>A sinne offring for atonement.</fw>
<ab n="19">And he shall
sprinkle of the blood vpon it with his finger seuen times, and
clense it, and hallow it from the vncleannesse of the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
when hee hath made an end of reconciling the holy place, and the
Tabernacle of the Congregation, and the Altar, hee shall bring the
liue goate.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Aaron
shall lay both his hands vpon the head of the liue goate, and
confesse ouer him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and
all their transgressions in all their sinnes, putting them vpon the
head of the goate, and shall send him away by the hand of a fit man
into the wildernesse.<note> Hebr. a man of opportunitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And the goate
shall beare vpon him all their iniquities, vnto a land not
inhabited; and he shall let goe the goat in the
wildernesse.<note> Heb. of separation.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Aaron
shall come into the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and shal put
off the linnen garments which he put on, when he went in to the
holy place, and shall leaue them there.</ab>
<ab n="24">And he shall
wash his flesh with water in the holy place, and put on his
garments, and come foorth, and offer his burnt offering, and the
burnt offering of the people, and make an atonement for himselfe,
and for the people.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the fat of
the sinne offering shall he burne vpon the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="26">And he that
let goe the goat for the Scape-goat, shal wash his clothes, and
bathe his flesh in water, and afterward come into the
Campe.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the
bullocke for the sinne offering, and the goat for the sin offering,
whose blood was brought in, to make atonement in the holy place,
shall one cary foorth without the Campe, and they shal burne in the
fire their skinnes and their flesh, and their doung.<note> Leuit.6. 30. Heb.13. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And he that
burneth them, shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water,
and afterward he shall come into the Campe.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And
this shall be a statute for euer vnto you: that in the seuenth
moneth, on the tenth day of the moneth, ye shall afflict your
soules, &amp; doe no worke at all, whether it bee one of your owne
countrey, or a stranger that soiourneth among you.</ab>

<fw>A sinne offring for atonement.</fw>
<ab n="30">For on that
day shal the Priest make an atonement for you, to cleanse you, that
yee may bee cleane from all your sinnes before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="31">It shall be a
Sabbath of rest vnto you, and ye shall afflict your soules by a
statute for euer.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the Priest
whom he shall anoynt, and whom he shall consecrate to minister in
the Priests office in his fathers stead, shall make the atonement,
and shal put on the linnen clothes, euen the holy
garments.<note> Hebr. fill his hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And he shall
make an atonement for the holy Sanctuary, and hee shall make an
atonement for the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and for the
Altar: and he shall make an atonement for the Priests, and for all
the people of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="34">And this shall
be an euerlasting statute vnto you, to make an atonement for the
children of Israel, for all their sinnes once a yeere. And he did
as the Lord commanded Moses.<note> Exod. 30. 10. heb 9. 7.</note></ab>



</div>