<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 One language in the world. 3 The
building of Babel. 5 The confusion of tongues. 10 The generations
of Shem. 27 The generations of Terah the father of Abram. 31 Terah
goeth from Vr to Haran.</head>

<ab n="1">And the whole
earth was of one language, and of one speach.<note> Wis.10.5. , Hebr. lippe. , Heb. words.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And it came to
passe as they iourneyed from the East, that they found a plaine in
the land of Shinar, and they dwelt there.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they sayd one
to another; Goe to, let vs make bricke, and burne them thorowly.
And they had bricke for stone, and slime had they for
morter.<note> Heb. a man said to his neighbour. , Heb. burne them to a burning.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And they said;
Goe to, let vs build vs a city and a tower, whose top may reach
vnto heauen, and let vs make vs a name, lest we be scattered abroad
vpon the face of the whole earth.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the LORD came
downe to see the city and the tower, which the children of men
builded.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the LORD
said; Behold, the people is one, and they haue all one language:
and this they begin to doe: and now nothing will be restrained from
them, which they haue imagined to doe.</ab>
<ab n="7">Goe to, let vs go
downe, and there cōfound their language, that they may not
vnderstand one anothers speech.</ab>
<ab n="8">So the LORD
scattered them abroad from thence, vpon the face of all the earth:
and they left off to build the Citie.</ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore is the
name of it called Babel, because the LORD did there confound the
language of all the earth: and from thence did the LORD scatter
them abroad vpon the face of all the earth.<note> That is, Confusion.</note></ab>

<fw>The generations of Terah.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ These are
the generations of Shem. Shem was an hundred yeres old, and begate
Arphaxad two yeeres after the Flood.<note> 1. Chron. 1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Shem liued,
after he begate Arphaxad, fiue hundred yeeres, and begate sonnes
and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Arphaxad
liued fiue and thirtie yeeres, and begate Salah.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Arphaxad
liued, after he begate Salah, foure hundred and three yeeres, and
begate sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Salah liued
thirtie yeeres, and begate Eber.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Salah liued,
after hee begate Eber, foure hundred and three yeeres, and begate
sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Eber liued
foure and thirty yeeres, and begate Peleg.<note> 1.Chron. 1.19. , Called Luke 3.35. Phalec.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Eber liued,
after hee begate Peleg, foure hundred and thirtie yeres, and begate
sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Peleg liued
thirtie yeeres, and begate Reu.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Peleg liued,
after hee begate Reu, two hundred and nine yeeres, and begate
sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Reu liued
two and thirtie yeeres, and begate Serug.<note> Luc.5.35 Saruch.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Reu liued,
after hee begate Serug, two hundreth and seuen yeres, and begate
sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Serug liued
thirtie yeeres, and begate Nahor.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Serug liued,
after he begate Nahor, two hundred yeeres, and begat sonnes and
daughters.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Nahor liued
nine and twentie yeeres, and begate Terah.<note> Luc.3.34. Thara.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Nahor liued,
after he begate Terah, an hundred &amp; nineteene yeeres, and
begate sonnes and daughters.</ab>
<ab n="26">And Terah liued
seuenty yeeres, and begate Abram, Nahor, &amp; Haran.<note> Iosh.24.2 1.Chron.1. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Now these
are the generations of Terah: Terah begate Abram, Nahor, and Haran:
And Haran begate Lot.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Haran died,
before his father Terah in the land of his natiuity, in Ur of the
Chaldees.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Abram and
Nahor tooke them wiues: the name of Abrams wife was Sarai, and the
name of Nahors wife, Milcah, the daughter of Haran, the father of
Milcah, and the father of Iscah.</ab>
<ab n="30">But Sarai was
barren; she had no childe.</ab>

<fw>The generations of Terah.
Abram.</fw>
<ab n="31">And Terah tooke
Abram his sonne, and Lot the sonne of Haran his sonnes sonne, and
Sarai his daughter in lawe, his sonne Abrams wife, and they went
foorth with them from Ur of the Chaldees, to goe into the land of
Canaan: and they came vnto Haran, and dwelt there.<note> Nehem. 9.7. iudith. 5.7. acts.7. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And the dayes of
Terah, were two hundred and fiue yeres: and Terah died in
Haran.</ab>



</div>