<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 The vncleannes of men in their
issues. 13 The clensing of them. 19 The vncleannesse of women in
their issues. 28 Their clensing.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, and to Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, when any man hath a running
issue out of his flesh, because of his issue he is
vncleane.<note> Or, running of the reines.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And this shall
be his vncleannesse in his issue: whether his flesh run with his
issue, or his flesh be stopped from his issue, it is his
vncleannesse.</ab>
<ab n="4">Euery bed
whereon he lieth, that hath the issue, is vncleane: and euery thing
whereon he sitteth, shall bee vncleane.<note> Heb. vessel.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And whosoeuer
toucheth his bed, shall wash his clothes, and bath himselfe in
water, and bee vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>

<fw>How to purge vncleane issues.</fw>
<ab n="6">And hee that
sitteth on any thing whereon hee sate that hath the issue, shall
wash his clothes, and bath himselfe in water, and bee vncleane
vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he that
toucheth the flesh of him that hath the issue, shall wash his
clothes, and bathe himselfe in water, and be vncleane vntill the
Euen.</ab>
<ab n="8">And if he that
hath the issue, spit vpon him that is cleane, then hee shall wash
his clothes, and bathe himselfe in water, and bee vncleane vntill
the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="9">And what saddle
soeuer he rideth vpon, that hath the issue, shall bee
vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="10">And whosoeuer
toucheth any thing that was vnder him, shall be vncleane vntil the
Euen: And he that beareth any of those things, shall wash his
clothes, and bathe himselfe in water, and be vncleane vntill the
Euen.</ab>
<ab n="11">And whomsoeuer
hee toucheth that hath the issue (and hath not rinsed his hands in
water) he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himselfe in water, and
be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the
vessell of earth that hee toucheth which hath the issue, shall bee
broken: and euery vessell of wood shall be rinsed in
water.<note> Chap.6. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And when hee
that hath an issue, is cleansed of his issue, then hee shall number
to himselfe seuen dayes for his cleansing, and wash his clothes,
and bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be cleane.</ab>
<ab n="14">And on the
eight day hee shall take to him two turtle doues, or two yong
pigeons, and come before the Lord, vnto the doore of the Tabernacle
of the Congregation, and giue them vnto the Priest.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Priest
shall offer them, the one for a sinne offering, and the other for a
burnt offering, and the Priest shall make an atonement for him
before the Lord for his issue.</ab>
<ab n="16">And if any
mans seede of copulation goe out from him, then hee shall wash all
his flesh in water, and bee vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="17">And euery
garment and euery skinne whereon is the seede of copulation, shall
be washed with water, and be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="18">The woman also
with whom man shall lie with seed of copulation, they shall both
bath themselues in water, and be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>

<fw>Vncleane issues.</fw>
<ab n="19">¶ And if
a woman haue an issue, and her issue in her flesh be blood, shee
shall bee put apart seuen dayes: and whosoeuer toucheth her, shall
bee vncleane vntil the Euen.<note> Hebr. in her separation.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And euery
thing that she lieth vpon in her separation, shall be vncleane:
euery thing also that she sitteth vpon, shalbe vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="21">And whosoeuer
toucheth her bed, shall wash his clothes, and bathe himselfe in
water, and be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="22">And whosoeuer
toucheth any thing that she sate vpon, shall wash his clothes, and
bathe himselfe in water, and be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="23">And if it be
on her bed, or on any thing whereon she sitteth, when hee toucheth
it, he shall be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="24">And if any man
lye with her at all, and her flowers be vpon him, hee shall be
vncleane seuen dayes: and all the bed whereon he lyeth, shall be
vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="25">And if a woman
haue an issue of her blood many dayes out of the time of her
separation, or if it runne beyond the time of her separation, all
the dayes of the issue of her vncleannesse, shall be as the dayes
of her separation: she shalbe vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="26">Euery bed
whereon she lyeth all the dayes of her issue, shall be vnto her as
the bed of her separation: and whatsoeuer shee sitteth vpon, shall
bee vncleane, as the vncleannesse of her separation.</ab>
<ab n="27">And whosoeuer
toucheth those things, shalbe vncleane, and shall wash his clothes,
and bathe himselfe in water, and be vncleane vntill the
Euen.</ab>
<ab n="28">But if she be
cleansed of her issue, then she shall number to her selfe seuen
dayes: and after that, she shalbe cleane.</ab>
<ab n="29">And on the
eight day she shall take vnto her two turtles or two yong pigeons,
&amp; bring them vnto the Priest, to the doore of the Tabernacle of
the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the Priest
shall offer the one for a sinne offering, and the other for a burnt
offering, and the Priest shall make an atonement for her before the
Lord, for the issue of her vncleannesse.</ab>

<fw>The Scape goat.</fw>
<ab n="31">Thus shall yee
separate the children of Israel from their vncleannesse, that they
die not in their vncleannesse, when they defile my Tabernacle that
is among them.</ab>
<ab n="32">This is the
law of him that hath an issue, and of him whose seed goeth from
him, and is defiled therewith;</ab>
<ab n="33">And of her
that is sicke of her flowers, and of him that hath an issue, of the
man, and of the woman, &amp; of him that lyeth with her which is
vncleane.</ab>



</div>