<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The sinne offering of ignorance, 3
for the Priest, 13 for the Congregation, 22 for the Ruler, 27 for
any of the people.</head>


<fw>Offerings for sinnes of
ignorance.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, saying, If a soule shall sinne through
ignorance against any of the commandements of the Lord (concerning
things which ought not to bee done) and shall do against any of
them:</ab>
<ab n="3">If the Priest
that is anointed, doe sinne according to the sinne of the people,
then let him bring for his sinne which he hath sinned, a yong
bullocke without blemish, vnto the Lord for a sinne
offering.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee shall
bring the bullocke vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation before the Lord, and shall lay his hand vpon the
bullockes head, and kill the bullocke before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Priest
that is anointed, shall take of the bullocks blood, and bring it to
the Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Priest
shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle of the blood seuen
times before the Lord, before the Uaile of the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the Priest
shall put some of the blood vpon the hornes of the Altar of sweet
incense before the Lord, which is in the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, and shal powre all the blood of the bullocke at the
bottome of the altar of the burnt offering, which is at the doore
of the Tabernacle of the Congregation.<note> Chap.5.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And he shall
take off from it all the fat of the bullocke for the sinne
offering: the fat that couereth the inwards, and all the fat that
is vpon the inwards.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the two
kidneis, and the fat that is vpon them, which is by the flankes,
and the caule aboue the liuer with the kidneis, it shall he take
away,</ab>
<ab n="10">As it was taken
off from the bullocke of the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the
Priest shall burne them vpon the altar of the burnt
offering.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the skinne
of the bullocke, and all his flesh, with his head, and with his
legs, and his inwards, and his doung,<note> Exod. 29. 14. numb. 19.5.</note></ab>

<fw>Offerings for sinnes of
ignorance.</fw>
<ab n="12">Euen the whole
bullocke shall he carie foorth without the campe, vnto a cleane
place, where the ashes are powred out, and burne him on the wood
with fire: where the ashes are powred out, shall he be
burnt.<note> Hebr. To without the campe. , Heb.13. 11. , Heb. at the powring out of the ashes.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And if
the whole Congregation of Israel sinne through ignorance, and the
thing be hid from the eyes of the assembly, and they haue done
somewhat against any of the Commandements of the Lord, concerning
things which should not be done, and are guiltie:<note> Chap.5. 2,3,4.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">When the sinne
which they haue sinned against it, is knowen, then the Congregation
shall offer a yong bullocke for the sinne, and bring him before the
Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Elders
of the Congregation shall lay their hands vpon the head of the
bullocke, before the Lord: and the bullocke shall be killed before
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Priest
that is anointed, shall bring of the bullockes blood to the
Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Priest
shall dip his finger in some of the blood, and sprinkle it seuen
times before the Lord, euen before the vaile.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he shal put
some of the blood vpon the hornes of the altar, which is before the
Lord, that is in the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and shall
powre out all the blood at the bottome of the altar of the burnt
offring, which is at the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he shall
take all his fat from him, and burne it vpon the altar.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he shall do
with the bullocke as he did with the bullocke for a sinne offring,
so shall he do with this: And the Priest shall make an atonement
for them, and it shall be forgiuen them.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he shall
carie foorth the bullocke without the campe, and burne him as he
burned the first bullocke: it is a sinne offering for the
Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ When a
ruler hath sinned and done somewhat through ignorance against any
of the Commandements of the Lord his God, concerning things which
should not be done, and is guilty:</ab>
<ab n="23">Or if his sinne
wherein hee hath sinned, come to his knowledge: he shall bring his
offering, a kid of the goates, a male without blemish.</ab>
<ab n="24">And hee shall
lay his hand vpon the head of the goate, and kill it in the place
where they kill the burnt offering before the Lord: it is a sinne
offring.</ab>

<fw>Sinne of ignorance.</fw>
<ab n="25">And the Priest
shall take of the blood of the sinne offering with his finger, and
put it vpon the hornes of the Altar of burnt offring, and shall
powre out his blood at the bottome of the Altar of burnt
offering.</ab>
<ab n="26">And he shall
burne all his fat vpon the Altar, as the fat of the sacrifice of
peace offerings: and the Priest shall make an atonement for him, as
concerning his sinne, and it shall be forgiuen him.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And if
any one of the common people sinne through ignorance, while he
doeth somewhat against any of the commandements of the Lord,
concerning things which ought not to be done, and be
guiltie:<note> Hebr. any soule. , Hebr. people of the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Or if his sinne
which he hath sinned come to his knowledge, then hee shall bring
his offering, a kidde of the goats, a female without blemish, for
his sinne which he hath sinned.</ab>
<ab n="29">And he shall
lay his hand vpon the head of the sinne offering, and slay the sin
offering in the place of the burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the Priest
shall take of the blood thereof with his finger, and put it vpon
the hornes of the Altar of burnt offering, and shall powre out all
the blood thereof at the bottome of the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="31">And he shall
take away all the fat thereof, as the fat is taken away from off
the sacrifice of peace offerings: and the Priest shall burne it
vpon the Altar, for a sweet sauour vnto the Lord, and the Priest
shall make an atonement for him, and it shall be forgiuen
him.<note> Leuit. 3, 14. , Exod. 29. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And if he bring
a lambe for a sinne offering, he shall bring it a female without
blemish.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he shall
lay his hand vpon the head of the sinne offering, and slay it for a
sinne offering, in the place where they kill the burnt
offering.</ab>
<ab n="34">And the Priest
shall take of the blood of the sinne offering with his finger, and
put it vpon the hornes of the Altar of burnt offring, and shall
powre out all the blood thereof at the bottome of the
Altar.</ab>

<fw>A rash vow.</fw>
<ab n="35">And he shall
take away all the fat thereof, as the fat of the lambe is taken
away from the sacrifice of the peace offerings: and the Priest
shall burnt them vpon the Altar, according to the offerings made by
fire vnto the Lord, and the Priest shall make an atonement for his
sinne that he hath committed, and it shalbe forgiuen him.</ab>



</div>