<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 The rites and sacrifices in
clensing of the Leper. 33 The signes of leprosie in a house. 48 The
clensing of that house.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">This shalbe the
law of the leper, in the day of his cleansing: he shall be brought
vnto the Priest.<note> Matt.8.2. mark.1.40. luke 5.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the Priest
shall goe forth out of the campe, and the Priest shall looke: and
beholde, if the plague of leprosie be healed in the leper,</ab>
<ab n="4">Then shall the
Priest command to take for him that is to bee cleansed, two birds
aliue, and cleane, and Cedar wood, and scarlet, and
hysope.<note> Or, sparrowes.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the Priest
shall command that one of the birds bee killed in an earthen
vessell, ouer running water.</ab>
<ab n="6">As for the
liuing bird, he shal take it, and the Cedar wood, and the scarlet,
and the hysope, and shall dip them and the liuing bird in the blood
of the bird that was killed ouer the running water.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he shall
sprinckle vpon him that is to be cleansed from the leprosie, seuen
times, and shall pronounce him cleane, and shall let the liuing
bird loose into the open field.<note> Hebr. vpon the face of the field.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And he that is
to be cleansed shall wash his clothes, and shaue off all his haire,
and wash himselfe in water, that he may be cleane: And after that
hee shall come into the Campe, and shall tary abroad out of his
tent seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="9">But it shall be
on the seuenth day, that he shall shaue all his haire off his head
and his beard, and his eyebrowes, euen all his haire he shal shaue
off: And he shall wash his clothes, also he shall wash his flesh in
water, and he shall be cleane.</ab>
<ab n="10">And on the
eight day he shall take two hee lambes without blemish, and one
ewe-lambe of the first yeere, without blemish, and three tenth
deales of fine flowre for a meat offering, mingled with oyle, and
one log of oyle.<note> Hebr. the daughter of her yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the Priest
that maketh him cleane, shall present the man that is to be made
cleane, and those things before the Lord, at the doore of the
Tabernacle of the Congregation:</ab>

<fw>Cleansing of the Leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="12">And the Priest
shall take one hee lambe, and offer him for a trespasse offering,
and the log of oile, and waue them for a waue offering before the
Lord.<note> Exod.29. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he shall
slay the lambe in the place where he shall kil the sin-offering,
and the burnt offring in the holy place: for as the sinne offering
is the Priests, so is the trespasse offering: it is most
Holy.<note> Chap.7.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the Priest
shall take some of the blood of the trespasse offering, and the
Priest shall put it vpon the tip of the right eare of him that is
to be cleansed, and vpon the thumbe of his right hand, and vpon the
great toe of his right foot.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Priest
shall take some of the log of oile, and powre it into the palme of
his owne left hand:</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Priest
shall dip his right finger in the oile that is in his left hand,
and shall sprinckle of the oile with his finger, seuen times before
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">And of the
rest of the oile that is in his hand, shall the Priest put vpon the
tip of the right eare of him that is to be cleansed, and vpon the
thumbe of his right hande, and vpon the great toe of his right
foot, vpon the blood of the trespasse offering.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
remnant of the oile that is in the Priests hand, he shall powre
vpon the head of him that is to be cleansed: and the Priest shall
make an atonement for him before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the Priest
shal offer the sinne offering, and make an atonement for him that
is to be cleansed from his vncleannesse, and afterward he shall
kill the burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Priest
shall offer the burnt offering, and the meat offering vpon the
Altar: and the Priest shall make an atonement for him, and he
shalbe cleane.</ab>
<ab n="21">And if he be
poore, and cannot get so much, then hee shall take one lambe for a
trespasse offring to be waued, to make an atonement for him, and
one tenth deale of fine flowre mingled with oile, for a meat
offering, and a log of oile,<note> Hebr. his hand reach not. , Hebr. For a wauing.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And two turtle
doues, or two yong pigeons, such as he is able to get: and the one
shalbe a sinne offering, and the other a burnt offering.</ab>

<fw>Cleansing of the leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="23">And hee shall
bring them on the eight day, for his cleansing vnto the Priest,
vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the Priest
shall take the lambe of the trespasse offering, and the log of
oile, and the Priest shall waue them for a waue offering before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he shall
kill the lambe of the trespasse offering, and the Priest shall take
some of the blood of the trespasse offering, and put it vpon the
tip of the right eare of him that is to be cleansed, and vpon the
thumbe of his right hand, and vpon the great toe of his right
foote.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the Priest
shall powre of the oyle into the palme of his owne left
hand.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the Priest
shal sprinkle with his right finger, some of the oile that is in
his left hand, seuen times before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the Priest
shall put of the oile that is in his hand, vpon the tip of the
right eare of him that is to be cleansed, and vpon the thumbe of
his right hand, and vpon the great toe of his right foot; vpon the
place of the blood of the trespasse offering.</ab>
<ab n="29">And the rest
of the oile that is in the Priests hand, he shall put vpon the head
of him that is to bee cleansed, to make an atonement for him before
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="30">And he shall
offer the one of the turtle doues, or of the yong pigeons, such as
he can get:</ab>
<ab n="31">Euen such as
he is able to get, the one for a sinne offering, and the other for
a burnt offering, with the meat offering. And the Priest shall make
an atonement for him that is to be cleansed, before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="32">This is the
law of him in whom is the plague of leprosie, whose hand is not
able to get that which pertaineth to his cleansing.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="34">When ye be
come into the land of Canaan, which I giue to you for a possession,
and I put the plague of leprosie in a house of the land of your
possession;</ab>
<ab n="35">And hee that
oweth the house shall come, and tell the Priest, saying, It seemeth
to me there is as it were a plague in the house:</ab>

<fw>Cleansing of the leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="36">Then the
Priest shall command that they emptie the house, before the Priest
goe into it to see the plague, that all that is in the house be not
made vncleane: and afterward the Priest shall goe in, to see the
house.<note> Or, prepare.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And he shal
looke on the plague: and behold, if the plague be in the walls of
the house, with hollow strakes, greenish or reddish, which in sight
are lower then the wall;</ab>
<ab n="38">Then the
Priest shall goe out of the house, to the doore of the house, and
shut vp the house seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the Priest
shall come againe the seuenth day, and shall looke: and behold, if
the plague bee spread in the walls of the house;</ab>
<ab n="40">Then the
Priest shall command that they take away the stones in which the
plague is, and they shall cast them into an vncleane place without
the Citie.</ab>
<ab n="41">And hee shall
cause the house to be scraped within round about, and they shall
powre out the dust that they scrape off, without the citie into an
vncleane place.</ab>
<ab n="42">And they shall
take other stones, and put them in the place of those stones; and
hee shall take other morter, and shall plaister the house.</ab>
<ab n="43">And if the
plague come againe, and breake out in the house, after that he hath
taken away the stones, and after he hath scraped the house, and
after it is plastered;</ab>
<ab n="44">Then the
Priest shall come and looke, and behold, if the plague bee spread
in the house, it is a fretting leprosie in the house: it is
vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="45">And he shall
breake downe the house, the stones of it, and the timber thereof,
and all the morter of the house: and he shall cary them foorth out
of the city into an vncleane place.</ab>
<ab n="46">Moreouer, he
that goeth into the house all the while that it is shut vp, shalbe
vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="47">And hee that
lieth in the house, shall wash his clothes: and hee that eateth in
the house, shall wash his clothes.</ab>
<ab n="48">And if the
Priest shall come in, and looke vpon it, and behold, the plague
hath not spread in the house, after the house was plastered: then
the Priest shall pronounce the house cleane, because the plague is
healed.<note> Hebr. in comming in, shall come in, &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>How to purge vncleane issues.</fw>
<ab n="49">And he shall
take to cleanse the house, two birds, and Cedar wood, and scarlet,
and hyssope.</ab>
<ab n="50">And he shall
kill the one of the birds in an earthen vessell, ouer running
water.</ab>
<ab n="51">And he shall
take the Cedar-wood and the hyssope, and the scarlet, and the
liuing bird, and dip them in the blood of the slaine bird, and in
the running water, and sprinkle the house seuen times.</ab>
<ab n="52">And he shall
clense the house with the blood of the bird, and with the running
water, and with the liuing bird, and with the Cedar wood, and with
the hyssope, and with the scarlet.</ab>
<ab n="53">But hee shall
let goe the liuing bird out of the citie into the open fields, and
make an atonement for the house: and it shall be cleane.</ab>
<ab n="54">This is the
law for all manner plague of leprosie and skall,<note> Chap. 13. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And for the
leprosie of a garment, and of an house,</ab>
<ab n="56">And for a
rising, and for a scabbe, and for a bright spot:</ab>
<ab n="57">To teach when
it is vncleane, and when it is cleane: this is the lawe of
leprosie.<note> Heb. in the day of the vncleane, and in the day of the cleane.</note></ab>



</div>