<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Exodus-Chapter-40-40-Leviticus.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The burnt offerings 3 Of the herd,
10 Of the flockes, 13 Of the foules.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
called vnto Moses, and spake vnto him out of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, If any man of you bring an
offering vnto the Lord, ye shall bring your offering of the
cattell, euen of the herd, and of the flocke.</ab>
<ab n="3">If his offering
be a burnt sacrifice of the herd, let him offer a male without
blemish: he shall offer it of his owne voluntary will, at the doore
of the Tabernacle of the Congregation before the Lord.<note> Exod. 29. 10.</note></ab>

<fw>The burnt offring.</fw>
<ab n="4">And he shall put
his hand vpon the head of the burnt offering: and it shall be
accepted for him to make atonement for him.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he shall
kill the bullocke before the Lord: and the Priests Aarons sonnes
shall bring the blood, and sprinkle the blood round about vpon the
altar, that is by the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee shall
slay the burnt offering, and cut it into his pieces.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the sonnes
of Aaron the Priest shall put fire vpon the Altar, and lay the wood
in order vpon the fire.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the Priests
Aarons sonnes shall lay the parts, the head and the fat in order
vpon the wood that is in the fire which is vpon the altar.</ab>
<ab n="9">But the inwards
and his legges shall he wash in water, and the Priest shall burne
all on the altar, to be a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by
fire, of a sweet sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And if
his offring be of the flocks, namely of the sheepe, or of the
goates for a burnt sacrifice, he shall bring it a male without
blemish.</ab>
<ab n="11">And hee shall
kill it on the side of the Altar Northward, before the Lord: and
the Priestes Aarons sonnes shall sprinkle his blood round about
vpon the altar.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he shall
cut it into his pieces, with his head and his fat: and the Priest
shall lay them in order on the wood that is on the fire, which is
vpon the altar:</ab>
<ab n="13">But hee shall
wash the inwards and the legs with water, and the Priest shall
bring it all, and burne it vpon the altar: it is a burnt sacrifice,
an offering made by fire, of a sweet sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And if
the burnt sacrifice for his offring to the Lord be of foules, then
he shall bring his offering of turtle doues, or of yong
pigeons.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Priest
shall bring it vnto the altar, and wring off his head, and burne it
on the altar: and the blood thereof shall be wrung out at the side
of the altar.<note> Or, pinch off the head with the naile.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And he shall
plucke away his crop with his feathers, and cast it beside the
altar on the East part, by the place of the ashes.<note> Or the filth thereof.</note></ab>

<fw>The meat offring.</fw>
<ab n="17">And hee shall
cleane it with the wings thereof, but shall not diuide it asunder:
And the Priest shall burne it vpon the altar, vpon the wood that is
vpon the fire: it is a burnt sacrifice, an offering made by fire of
a sweet sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>



</div>