<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Moses consecrateth Aaron and his
sonnes. 14 Their sinne offering. 18 Their burnt offring. 22 The ram
of consecrations. 31 The place and time of their
consecration.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Take Aaron and
his sonnes with him, and the garments, and the anointing oyle, and
a bullocke for the sinne offering, and two rammes, and a basket of
vnleauened bread.<note> Exod.28. 2.4. , Exod. 30. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And gather thou
all the Congregation together vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of
the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Moses did as
the Lord commanded him, &amp; the assembly was gathered together
vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Moses saide
vnto the Congregation, This is the thing which the Lord commanded
to be done.<note> Exod. 29. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses
brought Aaron and his sonnes, and washed them with water.</ab>

<fw>The consecration of Aaron, and of his
sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="7">And he put vpon
him the coate, and girded him with the girdle, and clothed him with
the robe, and put the Ephod vpon him, and he girded him with the
curious girdle of the Ephod, and bound it vnto him
therewith.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee put the
brest plate vpon him: also he put in the brest plate the Urim and
the Thummim.<note> Exod.28. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And he put the
miter vpon his head; also vpon the miter, euen vpon his forefront
did hee put the golden plate, the holy crowne, as the Lord
commanded Moses.<note> Exod.28. 39. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Moses tooke
the anointing oile, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was
therein, and sanctified them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he
sprinkled thereof vpon the altar seuen times, and anointed the
altar and all his vessels, both the lauer and his foot, to
sanctifie them.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he powred
of the anointing oile vpon Aarons head, and anointed him, to
sanctifie him.<note> Ecclus. 45.15. psal. 133. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Moses
brought Aarons sonnes, and put coats vpon them, and girded them
with girdles, and put bonnets vpon them, as the Lord commanded
Moses.<note> Heb. bound</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And he brought
the bullocke for the sinne offering, and Aaron and his sonnes laid
their hands vpon the head of the bullocke for the sinne
offering.<note> Exod. 29. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he slew it,
and Moses tooke the blood, and put it vpon the hornes of the altar
round about with his finger, and purified the altar, and powred the
blood at the bottome of the altar, and sanctified it, to make
reconciliation vpon it.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he tooke
all the fat that was vpon the inwards, and the kall aboue the
liuer, and the two kidneis, and their fat, and Moses burned it vpon
the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="17">But the
bullocke, and his hide, his flesh and his doung, he burnt with fire
without the campe, as the Lord commanded Moses.<note> Exod. 29. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And he
brought the ramme for the burnt offring: and Aaron and his sonnes
laid their hands vpon the head of the ramme.</ab>
<ab n="19">And he killed
it, and Moses sprinkled the blood vpon the Altar round
about.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he cut the
ramme into pieces, and Moses burnt the head, and the pieces, and
the fat.</ab>

<fw>The consecration of Aaron, and of his
sonnes.</fw>
<ab n="21">And he washed
the inwards and the legges in water, and Moses burnt the whole
ramme vpon the Altar: It was a burnt sacrifice for a sweet sauour,
and an offering made by fire vnto the Lord, as the Lord commanded
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And hee
brought the other ramme, the ramme of consecration: and Aaron and
his sonnes layd their hands vpon the head of the ramme.<note> Exod. 29. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And he slew it,
and Moses tooke of the blood of it, and put it vpon the tip of
Aarons right eare, and vpon the thumbe of his right hand, and vpon
the great toe of his right foot.</ab>
<ab n="24">And he brought
Aarons sonnes, and Moses put of the blood vpon the tippe of their
right eare, and vpon the thumbs of their right hands, and vpon the
great toes of their right feete: and Moses sprinkled the blood vpon
the Altar round about.</ab>
<ab n="25">And hee tooke
the fat, and the rumpe, and all the fat that was vpon the inwards,
and the caule aboue the liuer, and the two kidneys and their fat,
and the right shoulder.</ab>
<ab n="26">And out of the
basket of vnleauened bread, that was before the Lord, he tooke one
vnleauened cake, and a cake of oyled bread, and one wafer, and put
them on the fat, and vpon the right shoulder.</ab>
<ab n="27">And hee put all
vpon Aarons hands, and vpon his sonnes hands, and waued them for a
waue offering before the Lord.<note> Exod. 29. 24. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And Moses tooke
them from off their hands, and burnt them on the Altar, vpon the
burnt offering: They were consecrations for a sweet sauour: It is
an offering made by fire vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Moses tooke
the brest, and waued it for a waue offering before the Lord: For of
the ramme of consecration it was Moses part, as the Lord commanded
Moses.<note> Exod. 29. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Moses tooke
of the anoynting oyle, and of the blood which was vpon the Altar,
and sprinckled it vpon Aaron, and vpon his garments, and vpon his
sonnes, and vpon his sunnes garments with him: and sanctified
Aaron, and his garments, and his sonnes, and his sonnes garments
with him.</ab>

<fw>Aarons offrings.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ And
Moses said vnto Aaron and to his sonnes, Boile the flesh at the
doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation: and there eat it with
the bread that is in the basket of consecrations, as I commanded,
saying, Aaron and his sonnes shall eat it.<note> Exod. 29. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And that which
remaineth of the flesh, and of the bread, shall yee burne with
fire.</ab>
<ab n="33">And ye shall
not goe out of the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation in
seuen dayes, vntill the dayes of your consecration be at an end:
for seuen dayes shall he consecrate you.<note> Exod. 29. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">As he hath done
this day, so the Lord hath commanded to doe, to make an atonement
for you.</ab>
<ab n="35">Therefore shall
ye abide at the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation day and
night, seuen dayes, and keepe the charge of the Lord, that ye die
not: for so I am commanded.</ab>
<ab n="36">So Aaron and
his sonnes did all things which the Lord commanded by the hand of
Moses.</ab>



</div>