<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Of the Priests mourning. 6 Of
their holinesse. 8 Of their estimation. 7. 13 Of their Mariages. 16
The Priests that haue blemishes must not minister in the
Sanctuarie.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
said vnto Moses; Speake vnto the Priests the sonnes of Aaron, and
say vnto them, There shall none be defiled for the dead among his
people:</ab>
<ab n="2">But for his
kinne, that is neere vnto him, that is, for his mother, and for his
father, and for his sonne, and for his daughter, and for his
brother,</ab>
<ab n="3">And for his
sister a virgin, that is nigh vnto him, which hath had no husband:
for her may he be defiled.</ab>
<ab n="4">But hee shall
not defile himselfe being a chiefe man among his people, to
prophane himselfe.<note> Or, being an husband among his people hee shall not defile himselfe for his wife &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">They shall not
make baldnesse vpon their head, neither shall they shaue off the
corner of their beard, nor make any cuttings in their
flesh:<note> Chap. 19. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">They shalbe
holy vnto their God, and not profane the name of their God: for the
offrings of the Lord made by fire, and the bread of their God they
doe offer: therefore they shall be holy.</ab>
<ab n="7">They shall not
take a wife that is a whore, or profane, neither shall they take a
woman put away from her husband: for he is holy vnto his
God.</ab>
<ab n="8">Thou shalt
sanctifie him therfore, for he offereth the bread of thy God: he
shalbe holy vnto thee: for I the Lord which sanctifie you, am
holy.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
daughter of any Priest, if she profane her selfe, by playing the
whore, she profaneth her father: shee shall be burnt with
fire.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he that is
the high Priest among his brethren, vpon whose head the anointing
oyle was powred, and that is consecrated to put on the garments,
shall not vncouer his head, nor rent his clothes:</ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="11">Neither shall
he goe in to any dead body, nor defile himselfe for his father, or
for his mother:</ab>
<ab n="12">Neither shall
hee goe out of the Sanctuary, nor prophane the Sanctuary of his
God; for the crowne of the anointing oile of his God is vpon him: I
am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he shall
take a wife in her virginitie.</ab>
<ab n="14">A widow, or a
diuorced woman, or prophane, or an harlot, these shall he not take:
but he shall take a virgine of his owne people to wife.</ab>
<ab n="15">Neither shal
he prophane his seed among his people: for I the Lord doe sanctifie
him.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="17">Speake vnto
Aaron, saying, Whosoeuer he be of thy seed in their generations,
that hath any blemish, let him not approche to offer the bread of
his God:<note> Or, food.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For whatsoeuer
man hee be that hath a blemish, he shall not approche: a blind man,
or a lame, or he that hath a flat nose, or any thing
superfluous,<note> Chap. 22. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Or a man that
is broken footed, or broken handed,</ab>
<ab n="20">Or crooke
backt, or a dwarfe, or that hath a blemish in his eye, or be
scuruy, or scabbed, or hath his stones broken:<note> Or, too slender.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">No man that
hath a blemish, of the seed of Aaron the Priest, shall come nigh to
offer the offrings of the Lord made by fire: he hath a blemish; he
shall not come nigh to offer the bread of his God.</ab>
<ab n="22">He shall eat
the bread of his God, both of the most Holy, and of the
holy:</ab>
<ab n="23">Onely he shall
not goe in vnto the Uaile, nor come nigh vnto the Altar, because he
hath a blemish, that he prophane not my Sanctuaries: for I the Lord
doe sanctifie them.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Moses told
it vnto Aaron, and to his sonnes, and vnto all the children of
Israel.</ab>



</div>