<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 The Priests in their vncleannesse
must abstaine from the holy things. 6 How they shall bee cleansed.
10 Who of the Priests house may eate of the holy things. 17 The
sacrifices must be without blemish. 26 The age of the sacrifice. 29
The law of eating the sacrifice of thankesgiuing.</head>


<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto
Aaron, and to his sonnes, that they separate themselues from the
holy things of the children of Israel, and that they prophane not
my holy Name, in those things which they halow vnto me: I am the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">Say vnto them,
Whosoeuer he be of all your seed, among your generations, that
goeth vnto the holy things, which the children of Israel hallow
vnto the Lord, hauing his vncleannesse vpon him, that soule shalbe
cut off from my presence: I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">What man soeuer
of the seed of Aaron is a leper, or hath a running issue, he shall
not eat of the holy things, vntill he be cleane. And who so
toucheth any thing that is vncleane by the dead, or a man whose
seed goeth from him:<note> Hebr. running of the reines. , Chap. 15. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Or whosoeuer
toucheth any creeping thing, whereby he may be made vncleane, or a
man of whom hee may take vncleannesse, whatsoeuer vncleannesse he
hath:</ab>
<ab n="6">The soule which
hath touched any such, shalbe vncleane vntill Euen, and shall not
eate of the holy things, vnlesse he wash his flesh with
water.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when the
Sunne is downe, he shall be cleane, and shall afterward eate of the
holy things, because it is his food.</ab>
<ab n="8">That which
dieth of it selfe, or is torne with beasts, hee shall not eate to
defile himselfe therewith: I am the Lord.<note> Exod. 22. 31. ezech. 44.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">They shall
therefore keepe mine Ordinance, lest they beare sinne for it, and
die therefore, if they prophane it: I the Lord doe sanctifie
them.</ab>
<ab n="10">There shall no
stranger eat of the holy thing; a soiourner of the Priests, or an
hired seruant shall not eate of the holy thing.</ab>
<ab n="11">But if the
Priest buy any soule with his money, he shall eat of it, and he
that is borne in his house: they shall eat of his meat.<note> Hebr. with the purchase of his money.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If the Priests
daughter also bee married vnto a stranger, she may not eate of an
offering of the holy things.<note> Heb. a man a stranger.</note></ab>

<fw>VVhat oblations must be offred.</fw>
<ab n="13">But if the
Priests daughter be a widow, or diuorced, and haue no childe, and
is returned vnto her fathers house, as in her youth, she shall eat
of her fathers meat, but there shall no stranger eate
thereof.<note> Chap.10. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And if
a man eate of the holy thing vnwittingly, then he shall put the
fift part thereof vnto it; and shall giue it vnto the Priest, with
the holy thing.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they shall
not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they
offer vnto the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="16">Or suffer them
to beare the iniquitie of trespasse, when they eate their holy
things: for I the Lord do sanctifie them.<note> Or, lade themselues with the iniquity of trespasse in their eating.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">Speake vnto
Aaron and to his sonnes, and vnto all the children of Israel, and
say vnto them, Whatsoeuer he be of the house of Israel, or of the
strangers in Israel, that will offer his oblation for all his
vowes, and for all his free will offerings, which they will offer
vnto the Lord for a burnt offering:</ab>
<ab n="19">Ye shal offer
at your owne wil a male without blemish, of the beeues, of the
sheepe, or of the goats.</ab>
<ab n="20">But whatsoeuer
hath a blemish, that shall ye not offer: for it shall not be
acceptable for you.</ab>
<ab n="21">And whosoeuer
offereth a sacrifice of peace offerings vnto the Lord, to
accomplish his vow, or a free will offring in beeues or sheepe, it
shalbe perfect, to be accepted: there shall be no blemish
therein.<note> Deut. 15. 21. &amp; 17.1. , Or, goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Blind, or
broken, or maimed, or hauing a wenne, or scuruie, or scabbed, ye
shal not offer these vnto the Lord, nor make an offring by fire of
them vpon the Altar vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">Either a
bullocke, or a lambe that hath any thing superfluous or lacking in
his parts, that mayest thou offer for a free will offring: but for
a vow it shal not be accepted.<note> Or, kidde. , Chap. 21. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Ye shal not
offer vnto the Lord that which is bruised, or crushed, or broken,
or cut, neither shall you make any offering thereof in your
land.</ab>
<ab n="25">Neither from a
strangers hand shall ye offer the bread of your God of any of
these; because their corruption is in them, and blemishes bee in
them: they shall not be accepted for you.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>VVhat oblations must be offred.</fw>
<ab n="27">When a
bullocke, or a sheepe, or a goat is brought forth, then it shall
bee seuen dayes vnder the damme, and from the eight day and
thencefoorth, it shal be accepted for an offering made by fire vnto
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="28">And whether it
be cowe or ewe, ye shall not kill it, and her yong, both in one
day.<note> Or, shee goat. , Deu.22.6</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And when yee
will offer a sacrifice of thankesgiuing vnto the Lord, offer it at
your owne will.</ab>
<ab n="30">On the same
day it shall be eaten vp, ye shall leaue none of it vntill the
morrow: I am the Lord.<note> Chap.7. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Therefore
shall ye keepe my Commandements, and doe them: I am the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="32">Neither shal
ye profane my holy Name, but I will be hallowed among the children
of Israel: I am the Lord which hallow you,<note> Leuit.10. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">That brought
you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am the
Lord.</ab>



</div>