<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-25-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 The Sabbath of the seuenth yeere.
8 The Iubile in the fiftieth yeere. 14 Of oppression. 18 A blessing
of obedience. 23 The redemption of land, 29 Of houses. 35
Compassion of the poore. 39 The vsage of bondmen. 47 The redemption
of seruants.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses in Mount Sinai, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them: when yee come into the land
which I giue you, then shall the land keepe a Sabbath vnto the
Lord.<note> Hebr. rest. , Exod. 23. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Sixe yeeres
thou shalt sow thy field, and sixe yeeres thou shalt prune thy
Uineyard, and gather in the fruit thereof.</ab>
<ab n="4">But in the
seuenth yeere shalbe a Sabbath of rest vnto the land, a Sabbath for
the Lord: thou shalt neither sow thy field, nor prune thy
Uineyard.</ab>

<fw>The Iubile.</fw>
<ab n="5">That which
groweth of it owne accord of thy haruest, thou shalt not reape,
neither gather the grapes of thy Uine vndressed: for it is a yeere
of rest vnto the land.<note> Hebr. of thy separations.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the Sabbath
of the land shall be meat for you; for thee, and for thy seruant,
and for thy mayd, and for thy hired seruant, and for the stranger
that soiourneth with thee,</ab>
<ab n="7">And for thy
cattel, and for the beast that are in thy land, shall all the
encrease thereof be meat.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And thou
shalt number seuen Sabbaths of yeeres vnto thee, seuen times seuen
yeeres, and the space of the seuen Sabbaths of yeeres, shall be
vnto thee fourtie and nine yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then shalt thou
cause the trumpet of the Iubile to sound, on the tenth day of the
seuenth moneth; in the day of atonement shall ye make the trumpet
sound throughout all your land.<note> Hebr. lowde of sound.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And ye shall
hallow the fiftieth yeere, and proclaime libertie throughout all
the land, vnto al the inhabitants thereof: It shalbe a Iubile vnto
you, and ye shall returne euery man vnto his possession, and ye
shall returne euery man vnto his family.</ab>
<ab n="11">A Iubile shall
that fiftieth yeere be vnto you: Ye shall not sow, neither reape
that which groweth of it selfe in it, nor gather the grapes in it
of thy Uine vndressed.</ab>
<ab n="12">For it is the
Iubile, it shall be holy vnto you: ye shall eate the encrease
thereof out of the field.</ab>
<ab n="13">In the yeere
of this Iubile yee shall returne euery man vnto his
possession.</ab>
<ab n="14">And if thou
sell ought vnto thy neighbour, or buyest ought of thy neighbours
hand, ye shall not oppresse one another.</ab>
<ab n="15">According to
the number of yeres after the Iubile, thou shalt buy of thy
neighbour, and according vnto the number of yeeres of the fruits,
he shall sell vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">According to
the multitude of yeeres, thou shalt encrease the price thereof, and
according to the fewnesse of yeeres, thou shalt diminish the price
of it: for according to the number of the yeeres of the fruites
doeth hee sell vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="17">Yee shall not
therefore oppresse one another; but thou shalt feare thy God: For I
am the Lord your God.</ab>

<fw>Redeeming of lands and houses.</fw>
<ab n="18">¶
Wherefore ye shall do my Statutes, and keepe my Iudgements, and doe
them, and ye shall dwell in the land in safetie.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the land
shall yeeld her fruit, and ye shal eat your fill, and dwell therin
in safetie.</ab>
<ab n="20">And if ye
shall say, What shall we eate the seuenth yeere? Behold, we shall
not sow, nor gather in our increase:</ab>
<ab n="21">Then I will
command my blessing vpon you in the sixt yeere, and it shall bring
forth fruit for three yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="22">And ye shall
sow the eight yeere, and eat yet of old fruit, vntill the ninth
yeere: vntill her fruits come in, ye shall eate of the old
store.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ The
land shall not be sold for euer: for the land is mine, for ye were
strangers and soiourners with me.<note> Or, to bee quite cut off. Hebr. for cutting off.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And in all the
land of your possession, ye shall grant a redemption for the
land.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ If thy
brother be waxen poore, and hath sold away some of his possession,
and if any of his kinne come to redeeme it, then shall hee redeeme
that which his brother sold.</ab>
<ab n="26">And if the man
haue none to redeeme it, and himselfe bee able to redeeme
it:<note> Hebr. his hand hath attained, and found sufficiencie.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Then let him
count the yeeres of the sale therof, and restore the ouerplus vnto
the man, to whom he sold it, that he may returne vnto his
possession.</ab>
<ab n="28">But if he be
not able to restore it to him, then that which is sold, shall
remaine in the hand of him that hath bought it, vntill the yeere of
Iubile: and in the Iubile it shall goe out, and he shall returne
vnto his possession.</ab>
<ab n="29">And if a man
sell a dwelling house in a walled citie, then he may redeeme it
within a whole yeere after it is solde: within a full yeere may he
redeeme it.</ab>
<ab n="30">And if it be
not redeemed within the space of a full yeere, then the house that
is in the walled citie, shall be stablished for euer to him that
bought it, throughout his generations: it shall not goe out in the
Iubile.</ab>
<ab n="31">But the houses
of the villages which haue no walles round about them, shall bee
counted as the fields of the countrey: they may ee redeemed, and
they shall goe out in the Iubile.<note> Hebr. redemption belongeth vnto it.</note></ab>

<fw>Redeeming of lands and houses.</fw>
<ab n="32">Notwithstanding,
the cities of the Leuites, and the houses of the cities of their
possession, may the Leuites redeeme at any time.</ab>
<ab n="33">And if a man
purchase of the Leuites, then the house that was sold, and the
citie of his possession shall goe out in the yeere of Iubile: for
the houses of the cities of the Leuites are their possession among
the children of Israel.<note> Or, one of the Leuites redeeme them.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But the field
of the suburbs of their cities may not be sold, for it is their
perpetuall possession.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And if
thy brother bee waxen poore, and fallen in decay with thee, then
thou shalt relieue him, yea though he be a stranger, or a
soiourner, that hee may liue with thee.<note> Hebr. his hand faileth , Hebr. strengthen.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Take thou no
vsurie of him, or increase: but feare thy God, that thy brother may
liue with thee.<note> Exod. 22. 25. deut.23 19. pro.28.8 ezek.18.8 and 22.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Thou shalt not
giue him thy money vpon vsurie, nor lend him thy victuals for
increase.</ab>
<ab n="38">I am the Lord
your God, which brought you foorth out of the land of Egypt, to
giue you the land of Canaan, and to be your God.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And if
thy brother that dwelleth by thee be waxen poore, and be sold vnto
thee, thou shalt not compell him to serue as a bond
seruant.<note> Exo.21.2. deut.15.12 ierem.34. 14. , Heb. serue thy selfe with him with the seruice, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">But as an
hired seruant, and as a soiourner he shall be with thee, and shall
serue thee vnto the yere of Iubile.</ab>
<ab n="41">And then shall
hee depart from thee, both he and his children with him, and shall
returne vnto his owne familie, and vnto the possession of his
fathers shall he returne.</ab>
<ab n="42">For they are
my seruants, which I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: they
shall not be sold as bond men.<note> Hebr. with the sale of a bondman.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Thou shalt not
rule ouer him with rigour, but shalt feare thy God.<note> Ephe.6.9. coloss.4.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">Both thy
bondmen, and thy bondmaids, which thou shalt haue, shall be of the
Heathen, that are round about you: of them shall ye buy bondmen and
bondmaids.</ab>
<ab n="45">Moreouer, of
the children of the strangers that do soiourne among you, of them
shall ye buy, and of their families that are with you, which they
begat in your land: and they shalbe your possession.</ab>

<fw>Of redemption.</fw>
<ab n="46">And ye shall
take them as an inheritance for your children after you, to
inherite them for a possession, they shal bee your bondmen for
euer: but ouer your brethren the children of Israel, ye shall not
rule one ouer another with rigour.<note> Hebr. ye shall serue your selues with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">¶ And if
a soiourner or stranger waxe rich by thee, and thy brother that
dwelleth by him waxe poore, and sell himselfe vnto the stranger or
soiourner by thee, or to the stocke of the strangers
family:<note> Hebr. his hand obteine, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">After that he
is sold, hee may be redeemed againe: one of his brethren may
redeeme him.</ab>
<ab n="49">Either his
vncle, or his vncles sonne may redeeme him, or any that is nigh of
kinne vnto him, of his family, may redeeme him: or if he be able,
hee may redeeme himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="50">And he shall
reckon with him that bought him, from the yeere that he was sold to
him, vnto the yeere of Iubile, and the price of his sale shalbe
according vnto the number of yeeres, according to the time of an
hired seruant shall it be with him.</ab>
<ab n="51">If there be
yet many yeeres behinde, according vnto them hee shall giue againe
the price of his redemption, out of the money that hee was bought
for.</ab>
<ab n="52">And if there
remaine but few yeeres vnto the yeere of Iubile, then he shall
count with him, and according vnto his yeeres shall he giue him
againe the price of his redemption.</ab>
<ab n="53">And as a
yeerely hired seruant shall he be with him: and the other shall not
rule with rigour ouer him in thy sight.</ab>
<ab n="54">And if hee be
not redeemed in these yeeres, then he shall goe out in the yeere of
Iubile, both he, and his children with him.<note> Or, by these meanes.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">For vnto me
the children of Israel are seruants, they are my seruants whom I
brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I am the Lord your
God.</ab>



</div>