<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-27-27-Numbers.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 He that maketh a singular vow must
bee the Lords. 2 The estimation of the person. 9 Of a beast giuen
by vow. 14 Of a house. 16 Of a field and the redemption thereof. 28
No deuoted thing may be redeemed. 32 The tithe may not be
changed.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When a man shal make a
singular vow, the persons shall be for the Lord, by thy
estimation.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thy
estimation shall be: Of the male from twentie yeeres old, euen vnto
sixtie yeeres old: euen thy estimation shall be fiftie shekels of
siluer, after the shekel of the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="4">And if it be a
female, then thy estimation shall be thirtie shekels.</ab>
<ab n="5">And if it be
from fiue yeeres olde, euen vnto twentie yeeres old, then thy
estimation shall be of the male twentie shekels, and for the female
ten shekels.</ab>
<ab n="6">And if it be
from a moneth old, euen vnto fiue yeeres old, then thy estimation
shall be of the male, fiue shekels of siluer, and for the female,
thy estimation shall be three shekels of siluer.</ab>
<ab n="7">And if it be
from sixtie yeeres old, and aboue, if it be a male, then thy
estimation shall be fifteene shekels, and for the female ten
shekels.</ab>

<fw>Of vowes, and their redemption.</fw>
<ab n="8">But if he bee
poorer then thy estimation, then he shall present himselfe before
the Priest, and the Priest shall value him: according to his
abilitie that vowed, shall the Priest value him.</ab>
<ab n="9">And if it be a
beast whereof men bring an offering vnto the Lord, all that any man
giueth of such vnto the Lord, shall be holy.</ab>
<ab n="10">He shall not
alter it, nor change it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good: And
if hee shall at all change beast for beast, then it, and the
exchange thereof shall be holy.</ab>
<ab n="11">And if it be
any vncleane beast, of which they doe not offer a sacrifice vnto
the Lord, then he shall present the beast before the
Priest:</ab>
<ab n="12">And the Priest
shall value it, whether it be good or bad: as thou valuest it who
art the Priest: so shall it be.<note> Hebr. according to thy estimation, O Priest, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But if hee
will at all redeeme it, then he shall adde a fift part thereof vnto
thy estimation.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
when a man shall sanctifie his house to be holy vnto the Lord, then
the Priest shal estimate it, whether it be good or bad: as the
Priest shall estimate it, so shall it stand.</ab>
<ab n="15">And if he that
sanctified it, will redeeme his house, then he shall adde the fift
part of the money of thy estimation vnto it, and it shall be
his.</ab>
<ab n="16">And if a man
shall sanctifie vnto the Lord some part of a field of his
possession, then thy estimation shall be according to the seed
thereof: An Homer of barley seed shall be valued at fiftie shekels
of siluer.<note> Or, the land of an Homer, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">If hee
sanctifie his field from the yeere of Iubile, according to thy
estimation it shall stand.</ab>
<ab n="18">But if hee
sanctifie his field after the Iubile, then the Priest shall reckon
vnto him the money, according to the yeeres that remaine, euen vnto
the yeere of the Iubile, and it shall be abated from thy
estimation.</ab>
<ab n="19">And if he that
sanctified the field, will in any wise redeeme it, then he shal
adde the fift part of the money of thy estimation vnto it, and it
shall be assured to him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And if hee
will not redeeme the field, or if he haue sold the field to another
man, it shall not be redeemed any more.</ab>
<ab n="21">But the field,
when it goeth out in the Iubile, shall be holy vnto the Lord, as a
field deuoted: the possession thereof shalbe the Priests.</ab>

<fw>Redeeming of the Tythes.</fw>
<ab n="22">And if a man
sanctifie vnto the Lord a field which he hath bought, which is not
of the fieldes of his possession:</ab>
<ab n="23">Then the
Priest shall reckon vnto him the worth of thy estimation, euen vnto
the yeere of the Iubile, and hee shall giue thine estimation in
that day, as a holy thing vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">In the yeere
of the Iubile, the field shall returne vnto him of whom it was
bought, euen to him to whom the possession of the land did
belong.</ab>
<ab n="25">And all thy
estimations shall be according to the shekel of the Sanctuarie:
twentie Gerahs shall bee the shekel.<note> Exod. 30. 13. num. 3. 47. ezech. 45.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Onely
the firstling of the beasts which should be the Lords firstling, no
man shall sanctifie it, whether it bee oxe, or sheepe: It is the
Lords.<note> Hebr. first borne, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And if it be
of an vncleane beast, then hee shall redeeme it according to thine
estimation, and shall adde a fifth part of it thereto: Or if it be
not redeemed, then it shalbe sold according to thy
estimation.</ab>

<fw>Redeeming of the Tythes.</fw>
<ab n="28">Notwithstanding,
no deuoted thing that a man shall deuote vnto the Lord, of all that
he hath, both of man and beast, and of the field of his possession,
shall be sold or redeemed: euery deuoted thing is most holy vnto
the Lord.<note> Iosh.6. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">None deuoted,
which shalbe deuoted of men, shall be redeemed: but shall surely be
put to death.</ab>
<ab n="30">And all the
tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land, or of the fruit
of the tree, is the Lords: it is holy vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="31">And if a man
will at all redeeme ought of his tithes, he shall adde thereto the
fifth part thereof.</ab>
<ab n="32">And concerning
the tithe of the herde, or of the flocke, euen of whatsoeuer
passeth vnder the rod, the tenth shalbe holy vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="33">He shall not
search whether it be good or bad, neither shall he change it: and
if he change it at all, then both it, and the change thereof, shall
be holy; it shall not be redeemed.</ab>
<ab n="34">These are the
Commandements which the Lord commanded Moses, for the children of
Israel in mount Sinai.</ab>



</div>