<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 The blood of all slaine beasts
must be offered to the Lord at the doore of the Tabernacle. 7 They
must not offer to deuils. 10 All eating of blood is forbidden, 15
and all that dieth alone, or is torne.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto
Aaron and vnto his sonnes, and vnto all the children of Israel, and
say vnto them; This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded,
saying;</ab>
<ab n="3">What man soeuer
there bee of the house of Israel, that killeth an oxe, or lambe, or
goat in the Campe, or that killeth it out of the Campe,</ab>
<ab n="4">And bringeth it
not vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, to offer
an offering vnto the Lord before the Tabernacle of the Lord, blood
shall be imputed vnto that man; he hath shed blood, and that man
shall be cut off from among his people:</ab>
<ab n="5">To the end that
the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they offer
in the open field, euen that they may bring them vnto the Lord,
vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation vnto the
Priest, and offer them for peace offerings vnto the Lord.</ab>

<fw>No blood eaten.</fw>
<ab n="6">And the Priest
shall sprinckle the blood vpon the Altar of the Lord, at the doore
of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and burne the fat for a
sweet sauour vnto the Lord.<note> Exod. 29. 18. chap. 4. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they shall
no more offer their sacrifices vnto deuils, after whom they haue
gone a whoring: This shall be a statute for euer vnto them
throughout their generations.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And thou
shalt say vnto them, whatsoeuer man there be of the house of
Israel, or of the strangers which soiourne among you, that offreth
a burnt offering or sacrifice,</ab>
<ab n="9">And bringeth it
not vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, to offer
it vnto the Lord, euen that man shall be cut off from among his
people.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
whatsoeuer man there be of the house of Israel, or of the strangers
that soiourne among you, that eateth any maner of blood, I will
euen set my face against that soule that eateth blood, and will cut
him off from among his people.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the life
of the flesh is in the blood, and I haue giuen it to you vpon the
Altar, to make an atonement for your soules: for it is the blood,
that maketh an atonement for the soule.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore I
said vnto the children of Israel, No soule of you shall eat blood,
neither shall any stranger that soiourneth among you, eat
blood.</ab>
<ab n="13">And whatsoeuer
man there be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers that
soiourne among you, which hunteth and catcheth any beast or foule
that may be eaten, he shall euen powre out the blood thereof, and
couer it with dust.<note> Heb. that hunteth any hunting.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For it is the
life of all flesh, the blood of it is for the life thereof:
therefore I said vnto the children of Israel, Ye shall not eat the
blood of no maner of flesh: for the life of all flesh is the blood
thereof: whosoeuer eateth it, shalbe cut off.<note> Gen. 9. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And euery
soule that eateth that which died of it selfe, or that which was
torne with beasts, whether it bee one of your owne countrey, or a
stranger, he shall both wash his clothes, and bathe himselfe in
water, and be vncleane vntill the Euen: then shall he be
cleane.<note> Heb. a carcaise.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But if he wash
them not, nor bathe his flesh, then he shal beare his
iniquity.</ab>



</div>