<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-23-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 The feasts of the Lord. 3 The
Sabbath. 4 The Passeouer. 9 The Sheafe of first fruits. 15 The
Feast of Pentecost. 22 Gleanings to be left for the poore. 23 The
Feast of Trumpets. 26 The day of atonement. 33 The Feast of
Tabernacles.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, Concerning the feasts of the
Lord, which yee shall proclaime to be holy conuocations, euen these
are my feasts.</ab>
<ab n="3">Sixe dayes
shall worke be done, but the seuenth day is the Sabbath of rest, an
holy conuocation; ye shall doe no worke therein: it is the Sabbath
of the Lord in all your dwellings.<note> Exo.20.9 deut.5. 13. luke 13.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ These
are the feastes of the Lord, euen holy conuocations, which ye shall
proclaime in their seasons.</ab>
<ab n="5">In the
fourteenth day of the first moneth at euen, is the Lords
Passeouer.<note> Exod.12. 18. num.28 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And on the
fifteenth day of the same moneth, is the feast of vnleauened bread
vnto the Lord: seuen dayes ye must eate vnleauened bread.</ab>
<ab n="7">In the first
day ye shall haue an holy conuocation: ye shall do no seruile worke
therein.</ab>

<fw>The first fruites.</fw>
<ab n="8">But ye shal
offer an offring made by fire vnto the Lord seuen dayes: in the
seuenth day is an holy conuocation, Ye shall doe no seruile worke
therein.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="10">Speake vnto
the children of Israel, and say vnto them, When yee be come into
the land which I giue vnto you, and shal reape the haruest thereof,
then ye shall bring a sheafe of the first fruits of your haruest
vnto the Priest:<note> Or, handfull: Hebr. an Omer.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And hee shall
waue the sheafe before the Lord to be accepted for you: on the
morrow after the Sabbath the Priest shall waue it.</ab>
<ab n="12">And ye shall
offer that day, when ye waue the sheafe, an hee lambe without
blemish of the first yeere, for a burnt offering vnto the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the meat
offring thereof shall be two tenth deales of fine flowre, mingled
with oile, an offering made by fire vnto the Lord, for a sweet
sauour: and the drinke offering thereof shalbe of wine, the fourth
part of an Hin.</ab>
<ab n="14">And ye shall
eate neither bread, nor parched corne, nor greene eares, vntill the
selfe same day that yee haue brought an offering vnto your God: It
shalbe a statute for euer, throughout your generations, in all your
dwellings.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And ye
shall count vnto you from the morrow after the Sabbath, from the
day that ye brought the sheafe of the waue offering; seuen Sabbaths
shalbe complete.<note> Deut. 16. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Euen vnto the
morrow after the seuenth Sabbath, shall ye number fifty dayes, and
ye shall offer a new meat offering vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">Ye shall bring
out of your habitations two waue-loaues, of two tenth deales: they
shalbe of fine flowre, they shall be baken with leauen, they are
the first fruits vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">And ye shall
offer with the bread seuen lambes without blemish, of the first
yeere, and one yong bullocke and two rammes: they shall be for a
burnt offering vnto the Lord, with their meat offring and their
drinke offrings, euen an offering made by fire of sweet sauour vnto
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then ye shall
sacrifice one kid of the goates, for a sinne offering, and two
lambes of the first yeere, for a sacrifice of peace
offerings.</ab>

<fw>Solemne feasts, and holy
conuocations.</fw>
<ab n="20">And the Priest
shall waue them with the bread of the first fruits, for a
waue-offring before the Lord, with the two lambs: they shalbe holy
to the Lord for the Priests.</ab>
<ab n="21">And ye shal
proclaime on the selfe same day, that it may be an holy conuocation
vnto you: ye shall doe no seruile worke therein: it shall be a
statute for euer in all your dwellings throughout your
generations.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
when ye reape the haruest of your land, thou shalt not make cleane
riddance of the corners of the field, when thou reapest, neither
shalt thou gather any gleaning of thy haruest: thou shalt leaue
them vnto the poore, and to the stranger: I am the Lord your
God.<note> Chap. 19. 9. , Deut. 24 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="24">Speake vnto
the children of Israel, saying, In the seuenth moneth, in the first
day of the moneth shall yee haue a Sabbath, a memoriall of blowing
of trumpets, an holy conuocation.<note> Num. 29. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Ye shall do no
seruile worke therein; but ye shall offer an offering made by fire
vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="27">Also on the
tenth day of this seuenth moneth, there shalbe a day of atonement,
it shalbe an holy conuocation vnto you, &amp; ye shall afflict your
soules, and offer an offering made by fire vnto the
Lord.<note> Chap. 16. 30. num. 29.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And ye shall
doe no worke in that same day: for it is a day of atonement, to
make an atonement for you, before the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="29">For whatsoeuer
soule it bee that shall not bee afflicted in that same day, hee
shall bee cut off from among his people.</ab>
<ab n="30">And whatsoeuer
soule it bee that doeth any worke in that same day, the same soule
will I destroy from among his people.</ab>
<ab n="31">Ye shall doe
no maner of worke: it shall be a statute for euer throughout your
generations, in all your dwellings.</ab>
<ab n="32">It shalbe vnto
you a Sabbath of rest, and yee shall afflict your soules in the
ninth day of the moneth at Euen, from Euen vnto Euen shall ye
celebrate your Sabbath.<note> Hebr. rest.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>Solemne feasts, and holy
conuocations.</fw>
<ab n="34">Speake vnto
the children of Israel, saying, The fifteenth day of this seuenth
moneth, shall be the feast of Tabernacles for seuen dayes vnto the
Lord.<note> Num. 29. 12. iohn 7. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">On the first
day shalbe an holy conuocation: ye shall doe no seruile worke
therein.</ab>
<ab n="36">Seuen dayes ye
shall offer an offring made by fire vnto the Lord, on the eight day
shall be an holy conuocation vnto you, and ye shall offer an
offering made by fire vnto the Lord: It is a solemne assembly, and
ye shall doe no seruile worke therein.<note> Heb. day of restraint.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">These are the
feasts of the Lord which ye shall proclaime to be holy
conuocations, to offer an offering made by fire vnto the Lord, a
burnt offering, and a meat offering, a sacrifice, &amp; drinke
offerings, euery thing vpon his day;</ab>
<ab n="38">Beside the
Sabbaths of the Lord, and beside your gifts, and beside all your
vowes, and beside all your free will offerings, which ye giue vnto
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="39">Also in the
fifteenth day of the seuenth moneth when yee haue gathered in the
fruit of the land, ye shall keepe a feast vnto the Lord seuen
dayes. On the first day shall bee a Sabbath, and on the eight day
shall bee a Sabbath.</ab>
<ab n="40">And ye shall
take you on the first day the boughes of goodly trees, branches of
Palme trees, and the boughes of thicke trees, and willowes of the
brooke, and yee shall reioyce before the Lord your God seuen
dayes.<note> Heb. fruit.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And yee shall
keepe it a feast vnto the Lord seuen dayes in the yeere: It shalbe
a Statute for euer in your generations, ye shall celebrate it in
the seuenth moneth.</ab>
<ab n="42">Ye shall dwell
in boothes seuen dayes: all that are Israelites borne, shall dwell
in boothes;</ab>
<ab n="43">That your
generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in
boothes, when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am the
Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="44">And Moses
declared vnto the children of Israel the feastes of the
Lord.</ab>



</div>