<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 A repetition of sundry
Lawes.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto all
the Congregation of the children of Israel, and say vnto them, Ye
shalbe holy: for I the Lord your God am holy.<note> Chap. 11. 44. &amp; 20.7. 1.pet.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Yee
shall feare euery man his mother, and his father, and keepe my
Sabbaths: I am the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Turne ye
not vnto idoles, nor make to your selues molten gods: I am the Lord
your God.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And if
ye offer a sacrifice of peace offerings vnto the Lord, ye shall
offer it, at your owne will.</ab>
<ab n="6">It shall be
eaten the same day ye offer it, and on the morrow: and if ought
remaine vntill the third day, it shalbe burnt in the fire.</ab>
<ab n="7">And if it be
eaten at all on the third day, it is abominable; it shall not be
accepted.</ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore euery
one that eateth it, shal beare his iniquitie, because he hath
prophaned the halowed thing of the Lord; and that soule shalbe cut
off from among his people.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And when
ye reape the haruest of your land, thou shalt not wholly reape the
corners of thy field, neither shalt thou gather the gleanings of
thy haruest.<note> Chap. 23. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
not gleane thy vineyard, neither shalt thou gather euery grape of
thy vineyard; thou shalt leaue them for the poore and stranger: I
am the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Ye
shall not steale, neither deale falsly, neither lie one to
another.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And ye
shall not sweare by my Name falsly, neither shalt thou prophane the
Name of thy God: I am the Lord.<note> Exod. 20. 7. deut. 5. 11. matt. 5. 34. iam.5. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Thou
shalt not defraud thy neighbour, neither rob him: the wages of him
that is hired, shal not abide with thee all night, vntill the
morning.<note> Eccles.10. 7. deut.24. 14. tobi. 4 15.</note></ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ Thou
shalt not curse the deafe, nor put a stumbling blocke before the
blind, but shalt feare thy God: I am the Lord.<note> Deut. 27. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Ye
shall doe no vnrighteousnes in iudgement; thou shalt not respect
the person of the poore, nor honour the person of the mightie: but
in righteousnesse shalt thou iudge thy neighbour.<note> Exod.23. 3. deut.1. 17.and 16. 16. prou.24 23. iam.2.9</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Thou
shalt not goe vp and downe as a tale-bearer among thy people:
neither shalt thou stand against the blood of thy neighbour: I am
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Thou
shalt not hate thy brother in thine heart: thou shalt in any wise
rebuke thy neighbour, and not suffer sinne vpon him.<note> 1.Ioh.2. 11. mat.8.5 ecclu.19.13 , Or, that thou beare not sinne for him.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Thou
shalt not auenge nor beare any grudge against the children of thy
people, but thou shalt loue thy neighbor as thy selfe: I am the
Lord.<note> Matt.5.43 and 22.39. rom.13.9. galat. 5.14. iam. 2.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Yee
shall keepe my Statutes: Thou shalt not let thy cattell gender with
a diuerse kinde: Thou shalt not sowe thy field with mingled seed:
Neither shall a garment mingled of linnen and woollen come vpon
thee.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And
whosoeuer lieth carnally with a woman that is a bondmaid, she shall
be scourged: they shall not be put to death, because she was not
free:<note> Or, abused by any. Heb. reproched by [or for] man. , Or, they. Heb. there shall bee a scourging.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And he shall
bring his trespasse offering vnto the Lord, vnto the doore of the
Tabernacle of the Congregation, euen a ramme for a trespasse
offering.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Priest
shall make an atonement for him with the ramme of the trespasse
offering before the Lord for his sinne which hee hath done: and the
sinne which he hath done shall bee forgiuen him.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
when yee shall come in to the land, and shall haue planted all
maner of trees for food, then ye shall count the fruit therof as
vncircumcised: three yeeres shall it be as vncircumcised vnto you:
it shall not be eaten of.</ab>
<ab n="24">But in the
fourth yeere all the fruit thereof shall be holy to praise the Lord
withall.<note> Holines of praises to the LORD.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And in the
fift yeere shall ye eate of the fruit thereof, that it may yeelde
vnto you the increase thereof: I am the Lord your God.</ab>

<fw>Diuers lawes, and ordinances.</fw>
<ab n="26">¶ Ye
shall not eate any thing with the blood, neither shall ye vse
inchantment, nor obserue times.</ab>
<ab n="27">Ye shall not
round the corners of your heads, neither shalt thou marre the
corners of thy beard.<note> Chap. 21. 5</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Ye shall not
make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor print any markes
vpon you: I am the Lord.<note> Deut. 14. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ Doe not
prostitute thy daughter, to cause her to be a whore, lest the land
fall to whoredome, and the land become full of
wickednesse.<note> Hebr. prophane.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Ye
shall keepe my Sabbaths, and reuerence my Sanctuary: I am the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Regard
not them that haue familiar spirits, neither seeke after Wizards,
to be defiled by them: I am the Lord your God.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ Thou
shalt rise vp before the hoary head, and honour the face of the old
man, and feare thy God: I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And if
a stranger soiourne with thee in your land, yee shall not vexe
him.<note> Exod. 22. 21. , Or, oppresse.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But the
stranger that dwelleth with you, shalbe as one borne amongst you,
and thou shalt loue him as thy selfe, for ye were strangers in the
land of Egypt: I am the Lord your God.<note> Exod. 22. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">¶ Ye
shall doe no vnrighteousnes in iudgment, in meteyard, in weight, or
in measure.</ab>
<ab n="36">Iust
ballances, iust weights, a iust Ephah, and a iust Hin shall ye
haue: I am the Lord your God, which brought you out of the land of
Egypt.<note> Prou. 11. 1. and 16. 11. and 20. 10. , Heb. stones.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Therefore
shall ye obserue all my Statutes, and all my Iudgements, and doe
them: I am the Lord.</ab>



</div>