<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The meat offering of the herde, 6
of the flocke, 7 either a lambe, 12 or a goat.</head>

<ab n="1">And if his
oblation be a sacrifice of peace offering, if hee offer it of the
herd, whether it be a male or female, he shal offer it without
blemish before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he shall lay
his hand vpon the head of his offering, and kil it at the doore of
the Tabernacle of the Congregation: and Aarons sonnes the Priests
shall sprinckle the blood vpon the Altar round about.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he shall
offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering, an offering made by
fire vnto the Lord; the fat that couereth the inwards, and all the
fat that is vpon the inwards.<note> Exod.29. 22. , Or, suet.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the two
kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the flanks: and
the caule aboue the liuer with the kidneys, it shall he take
away.<note> Or, Midrisse ouer the liuer, and ouer the kidneys.</note></ab>

<fw>Peace offering.</fw>
<ab n="5">And Aarons
sonnes shall burne it on the Altar vpon the burnt sacrifice, which
is vpon the wood that is on the fire: it is an offering made by
fire of a sweet sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And if
his offering for a sacrifice of peace offering vnto the Lord, be of
the flocke, male or female, he shall offer it without
blemish.</ab>
<ab n="7">If hee offer a
lambe for his offering, then shall he offer it before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he shall lay
his hand vpon the head of his offering, and kill it before the
Tabernacle of the Congregation: And Aarons sonnes shall sprinkle
the blood thereof, round about vpon the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he shall
offer of the sacrifice of the peace offering, an offering made by
fire vnto the Lord: the fat thereof and the whole rumpe, it shall
he take off hard by the backe bone: and the fat that couereth the
inwards, and all the fat that is vpon the inwards.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the two
kidneys, and the fat that is vpon them, which is by the flankes,
and the caule aboue the liuer, with the kidneys, it shall he take
away.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Priest
shall burne it vpon the Altar: it is the food of the offering made
by fire vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And if
his offering be a goat, then he shall offer it before the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he shall
lay his hand vpon the head of it, and kill it before the Tabernacle
of the Congregation: and the sonnes of Aaron shall sprinckle the
blood thereof vpon the Altar, round about.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he shall
offer thereof his offering, euen an offering made by fire vnto the
Lord; the fat that couereth the inwards, and al the fat that is
vpon the inwards.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the two
kidneys, and the fat that is vpon them, which is by the flancks,
and the caule aboue the liuer with the kidneys, it shall he take
away.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Priest
shall burne them vpon the Altar: it is the food of the offering
made by fire, for a sweet sauour: All the fat is the
Lords.<note> Chap.7. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">It shall be a
perpetuall statute for your generations, throughout all your
dwellings, that ye eat neither fat, nor blood.<note> Gene.9. 4. chap.7. 26. and 17. 14.</note></ab>



</div>