<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-13-13b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 The Lawes and tokens whereby the
Priest is to be guided in discerning the Leprosie.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses and Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">When a man
shall haue in the skinne of his flesh, a rising, a scabbe, or
bright spot, and it bee in the skinne of his flesh like the plague
of leprosie, then he shall bee brought vnto Aaron the Priest, or
vnto one of his sonnes the Priests.<note> Or, swelling.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the Priest
shall looke on the plague in the skinne of the flesh: and when the
haire in the plague is turned white, and the plague in sight be
deeper then the skin of his flesh, it is a plague of leprosie: and
the Priest shall looke on him, and pronounce him vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="4">If the bright
spot be white in the skinne of his flesh, and in sight bee not
deeper then the skinne, and the haire thereof be not turned white,
then the Priest shall shut vp him that hath the plague, seuen
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Priest
shall looke on him the seuenth day: and beholde, if the plague in
his sight be at a stay, and the plague spread not in the skinne,
then the Priest shall shut him vp seuen dayes more.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Priest
shall looke on him againe the seuenth day: and beholde, if the
plague be somewhat darke, and the plague spread not in the skin;
the Priest shall pronounce him cleane: it is but a scab: and he
shall wash his clothes, and be cleane.</ab>
<ab n="7">But if the scab
spread much abroad in the skinne after that hee hath beene seene of
the Priest, for his cleansing hee shall be seene of the Priest
againe.</ab>

<fw>How to discerne the Leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="8">And if the
Priest see, that behold, the scab spreadeth in the skin, then the
Priest shall pronounce him vncleane: it is a leprosie.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ When the
plague of leprosie is in a man, then he shall be brought vnto the
Priest;</ab>
<ab n="10">And the Priest
shall see him: and behold, if the rising be white in the skin, and
it haue turned the haire white, and there be quicke raw flesh in
the rising:<note> Hebr. the quickening of liuing flesh.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">It is an old
leprosie in the skinne of his flesh, and the Priest shall pronounce
him vncleane, and shal not shut him vp: for he is vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="12">And if a
leprosie breake out abroad in the skin, and the leprosie couer all
the skin of him that hath the plague, from his head euen to his
foot, wheresoeuer the Priest looketh:</ab>
<ab n="13">Then the
Priest shall consider: and behold, if the leprosie haue couered al
his flesh, he shal pronounce him cleane that hath the plague, it is
all turned white; he is cleane.</ab>
<ab n="14">But when raw
flesh appeareth in him, he shall be vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the Priest
shall see the raw flesh, and pronounce him to bee vncleane: for the
raw flesh is vncleane: it is a leprosie.</ab>
<ab n="16">Or if the raw
flesh turne againe, and bee changed vnto white, hee shall come vnto
the Priest:</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Priest
shall see him: and beholde, if the plague bee turned into white,
then the Priest shall pronounce him cleane that hath the plague;
hee is cleane.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ The
flesh also, in which, euen in the skinne thereof was a bile, and is
healed,</ab>
<ab n="19">And in the
place of the bile there be a white rising, or a bright spot white,
and somewhat reddish, and it be shewed to the Priest:</ab>
<ab n="20">And if when
the Priest seeth it, behold, it be in sight lower then the skinne,
and the haire thereof be turned white, the Priest shall pronounce
him vncleane: it is a plague of leprosie broken out of the
bile.</ab>
<ab n="21">But if the
Priest looke on it, and behold, there be no white haires therein,
and if it be not lower then the skin, but be somewhat darke; then
the Priest shall shut him vp seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="22">And if it
spread much abroad in the skinne, then the Priest shall pronounce
him vncleane; it is a plague.</ab>

<fw>How to discerne the Leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="23">But if the
bright spot stay in his place, and spread not, it is a burning
bile; and the Priest shall pronounce him cleane.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Or if
there be any flesh in the skin whereof there is a hot burning, and
the quicke flesh that burneth haue a white bright spot, somewhat
reddish, or white;<note> Hebr. a burning of fire.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then the
Priest shall looke vpon it: and behold, if the haire in the bright
spot be turned white, and it bee in sight deeper then the skinne,
it is a leprosie broken out of the burning: wherefore the Priest
shal pronounce him vncleane: it is the plague of leprosie.</ab>
<ab n="26">But if the
Priest looke on it, and behold, there be no white haire in the
bright spot, and it be no lower then the other skin, but be
somewhat darke, then the Priest shal shut him vp seuen
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the Priest
shall looke vpon him the seuenth day: and if it be spread much
abroad in the skin, then the Priest shall pronounce him vncleane;
it is the plague of leprosie.</ab>
<ab n="28">And if the
bright spot stay in his place, and spread not in the skin, but it
be somewhat darke; it is a rising of the burning, and the Priest
shall pronounce him cleane: for it is an inflammation of the
burning.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ If a
man or woman hath a plague vpon the head or the beard,</ab>
<ab n="30">Then the
Priest shall see the plague: and behold, if it be in sight deeper
then the skin, and there be in it a yellow thin haire, then the
Priest shall pronounce him vncleane, it is a dry skall, euen a
leprosie vpon the head or beard.</ab>
<ab n="31">And if the
Priest looke on the plague of the skall, and behold, it be not in
sight deeper then the skin, and that there is no blacke haire in
it; then the Priest shall shut vp him that hath the plague of the
skall, seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="32">And in the
seuenth day the Priest shall looke on the plague: and behold, if
the skall spread not, and there be in it no yellow haire, and the
skall be not in sight deeper then the skin;</ab>
<ab n="33">He shall be
shauen, but the skall shall he not shaue: and the Priest shall shut
vp him that hath the skall, seuen dayes more.</ab>

<fw>Discerning of the leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="34">And in the
seuenth day the Priest shall looke on the skall: and behold, if the
skall be not spread in the skin, nor be in sight deeper then the
skin, then the Priest shall pronounce him cleane: and he shall wash
his clothes, and be cleane.</ab>
<ab n="35">But if the
skall spread much in the skinne after his cleansing,</ab>
<ab n="36">Then the
Priest shall looke on him, and behold, if the skall be spread in
the skinne, the Priest shall not seeke for yellow haire: he is
vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="37">But if the
skall be in his sight at a stay, and that there is blacke haire
growen vp therein: the skall is healed, he is cleane, and the
Priest shall pronounce him cleane.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ If a
man also or a woman haue in the skinne of their flesh bright spots,
euen white bright spots,</ab>
<ab n="39">Then the
Priest shall looke: and behold, if the bright spots in the skinne
of their flesh bee darkish white, it is a freckled spot that
groweth in the skin: he is cleane.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the man
whose haire is fallen off his head, he is bald: yet is hee
cleane.<note> Hebr. head is pilled.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And he that
hath his haire fallen off from the part of his head toward his
face, he is forehead-bald: yet is hee cleane.</ab>
<ab n="42">And if there
be in the bald head, or bald forehead a white reddish sore, it is a
leprosie sprung vp in his bald-head, or his bald forehead.</ab>
<ab n="43">Then the
Priest shall looke vpon it: and beholde, if the rising of the sore
bee white reddish in his balde head, or in his bald forehead, as
the leprosie appeareth in the skinne of the flesh,</ab>
<ab n="44">Hee is a
leprous man, he is vncleane: the Priest shall pronounce him vtterly
vncleane, his plague is in his head.</ab>
<ab n="45">And the leper
in whom the plague is, his clothes shall be rent, and his head
bare, and he shall put a couering vpon his vpper lip, and shall
cry, Uncleane, vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="46">All the dayes
wherein the plague shall bee in him, he shall bee defiled, hee is
vncleane: he shall dwell alone, without the campe shall his
habitation be.<note> Num.5.2. 2.king.15. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">¶ The
garment also, that the plague of leprosie is in, whether it bee a
woollen garment, or a linnen garment,</ab>
<ab n="48">Whether it bee
in the warpe, or woofe of linnen or of woollen, whether in a skin,
or in any thing made of skinne:<note> Hebr. worke of.</note></ab>

<fw>Discerning of the leprosie.</fw>
<ab n="49">And if the
plague be greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin,
either in the warpe, or in the woofe, or in any thing of skinne, it
is a plague of leprosie, and shall be shewed vnto the
Priest.<note> Heb. vessell or instrument.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">And the Priest
shall looke vpon the plague, and shut vp it that hath the plague,
seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="51">And he shall
looke on the plague on the seuenth day: if the plague be spread in
the garment, either in the warpe, or in the woofe, or in a skin, or
in any worke that is made of skinne, the plague is a fretting
leprosie; it is vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="52">Hee shall
therefore burne that garment, whether warpe or woofe, in wollen or
in linnen, or any thing of skinne, wherein the plague is: for it is
a fretting leprosie; it shall bee burnt in the fire.</ab>
<ab n="53">And if the
Priest shall looke, and behold the plague be not spread in the
garment, either in the warpe, or in the woofe, or in any thing of
skinne;</ab>
<ab n="54">Then the
Priest shall command that they wash the thing wherein the plague
is, and he shall shut it vp seuen dayes more.</ab>
<ab n="55">And the Priest
shall looke on the plague after that it is washed: and behold, if
the plague haue not changed his colour, and the plague be not
spread, it is vncleane, thou shalt burne it in the fire, it is fret
inward, whether it be bare within or without.<note> Heb. whether it be bauld in the head thereof or in the forehead thereof.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">And if the
Priest looke, and behold, the plaine be somewhat darke after the
washing of it, then he shall rend it out of the garment, or out of
the skin, or out of the warpe, or out of the woofe.</ab>
<ab n="57">And if it
appeare still in the garment, either in the warpe, or in the woofe,
or in any thing of skinne, it is a spreading plague, thou shalt
burne that wherein the plague is, with fire.</ab>
<ab n="58">And the
garment, either warpe, or woofe, or whatsoeuer thing of skin it
bee, which thou shalt wash, if the plague be departed from them,
then it shall be washed the second time, and shalbe cleane.</ab>
<ab n="59">This is the
law of the plague of leprosie in a garment of woollen or linnen,
either in the warpe, or woofe, or any thing of skinnes, to
pronounce it cleane, or to pronounce it vncleane.</ab>



</div>