<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 What beasts may, 4 and what may
not bee eaten. 9 What fishes. 13 What foules. 29 The creeping
things which are vncleane.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, and to Aaron, saying vnto them,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, saying, These are the beasts which ye shal eat
among all the beasts that are on the earth:<note> Deut. 14. 4. act. 10. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Whatsoever
parteth the hoofe, and is clouen footed, &amp; cheweth cud among
the beasts, that shall ye eate.</ab>
<ab n="4">Neuerthelesse,
these shall ye not eate, of them that chewe the cud, or of them
that diuide the hoofe: as the camel, because hee cheweth the cud,
but diuideth not the hoofe, he is vncleane vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the conie,
because he cheweth the cud, but diuideth not the hoofe, he is
vncleane vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the hare,
because he cheweth the cud, but diuideth not the hoofe, he is
vncleane vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the swine,
though he diuide the hoofe, and be clouen footed, yet hee cheweth
not the cud: he is vncleane to you.<note> 2.Macc. 6.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Of their flesh
shall ye not eat, and their carcase shall ye not touch: they are
vncleane to you.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ These
shal ye eat, of all that are in the waters: whatsoeuer hath finnes
and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the riuers, them
shall ye eate.</ab>
<ab n="10">And all that
haue not finnes nor scales in the seas, and in the riuers, of all
that moue in the waters, and of any liuing thing which is in the
waters, they shalbe an abomination vnto you:</ab>
<ab n="11">They shalbe
euen an abomination vnto you: ye shall not eat of their flesh, but
you shall haue their carcases in abomination.</ab>

<fw>Meates cleane, and vncleane.</fw>
<ab n="12">Whatsoeuer
hath no finnes nor scales in the waters, that shalbe an abomination
vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
these are they which ye shall haue in abomination among the foules,
they shall not be eaten, they are an abomination: The Eagle, and
the Ossifrage, and the Ospray,</ab>
<ab n="14">And the
Uulture, and the Kite, after his kinde:</ab>
<ab n="15">Euery Rauen
after his kinde:</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Owle,
and the nighthauke, &amp; the Cuckow, and the Hawke after his
kinde,</ab>
<ab n="17">And the little
Owle, and the Cormorant, and the great Owle,</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
Swanne, and the Pellicane, and the Gier-eagle,</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
Storke, the Heron after her kinde, and the Lapwing, and the
Batte.</ab>
<ab n="20">All foules
that creepe, going vpon all foure, shalbe an abomination vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="21">Yet these may
ye eat, of euery flying creeping thing that goeth vpon all foure,
which haue legges aboue their feet, to leape withall vpon the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="22">Euen these of
them ye may eate: the Locust, after his kinde, and the Bald-locust
after his kinde, and the Beetle after his kinde, and the
Grassehopper after his kinde.</ab>
<ab n="23">But al other
flying creeping things which haue foure feet, shall be an
abomination vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="24">And for these
ye shalbe vncleane: whosoeuer toucheth the carkasse of them, shall
be vncleane vntill the euen.</ab>
<ab n="25">And whosoeuer
beareth ought of the carkasse of them, shall wash his clothes,
&amp; be vncleane vntill the euen.</ab>
<ab n="26">The carkasses
of euery beast which diuideth the hoofe, and is not clouen footed,
nor cheweth the cud, are vncleane vnto you: euery one that toucheth
them, shalbe vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="27">And whatsoeuer
goeth vpon his pawes, among all maner of beasts, that goe on all
foure, those are vncleane vnto you: who so toucheth their carkasse,
shall be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he that
beareth the carkasse of them, shall wash his clothes, and be
vncleane vntill the Euen: they are vncleane vnto you.</ab>

<fw>Meates cleane, and vncleane.</fw>
<ab n="29">¶ These
also shalbe vncleane vnto you, among the creeping things that
creepe vpon the earth: the Weasell, and the Mouse, and the Tortois,
after his kinde,</ab>
<ab n="30">And the
Ferret, and the Cameleon, and the Lyzard, and the Snaile, and the
Molle.</ab>
<ab n="31">These are
vncleane to you among all that creepe: whosoeuer doth touch them
when they bee dead, shall be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="32">And vpon
whatsoeuer any of them, when they are dead, doeth fall, it shalbe
vncleane, whether it be any vessel of wood, or raiment, or skinne,
or sacke, whatsoeuer vessell it be, wherein any worke is done, it
must be put into water, and it shall be vncleane vntill the Euen;
so it shalbe cleansed.</ab>
<ab n="33">And euery
earthen vessel, whereinto any of them falleth, whatsoeuer is in it
shall bee vncleane; and yee shall breake it.<note> Chap.6. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Of all meat
which may be eaten, that on which such water commeth, shall be
vncleane: And all drinke that may be drunkein euery such vessell,
shalbe vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="35">And euery
thing, whereupon any part of their carkasse falleth, shall be
vncleane, whether it be ouen, or ranges for pots, they shalbe
broken downe: for they are vncleane, and shall be vncleane vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="36">Neuerthelesse,
a fountaine or pit, wherein there is plenty of water, shalbe
cleane: but that which toucheth their carkasse shalbe
vncleane.<note> Hebr. a gathering together of waters.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And if any
part of their carkasse fall vpon any sowing seed which is to be
sowen, it shalbe cleane:</ab>
<ab n="38">But if any
water be put vpon the seed, and any part of their carkasse fall
thereon, it shalbe vncleane vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="39">And if any
beast of which ye may eat, die, he that toucheth the carkasse
thereof, shall be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="40">And hee that
eateth of the carkasse of it, shall wash his clothes, and be
vncleane vntil the Euen: he also that beareth the carkasse of it,
shal wash his clothes, and bee vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>
<ab n="41">And euery
creeping thing that creepeth vpon the earth, shalbe an abomination:
it shall not be eaten.</ab>

<fw>The purification of women.</fw>
<ab n="42">Whatsoeuer
goeth vpon the bellie, and whatsoeuer goeth vpon all foure, or
whatsoeuer hath more feet among all creeping things that creepe
vpon the earth, them ye shall not eate, for they are an
abomination.<note> Hebr. doth multiply feet.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Yee shall not
make your selues abominable with any creeping thing that creepeth,
neither shall ye make your selues vncleane with them, that ye
should be defiled thereby.<note> Heb. soules</note></ab>
<ab n="44">For I am the
Lord your God: yee shall therefore sanctifie your selues, and ye
shall be holy, for I am holy: neither shall ye defile your selues
with any maner of creeping thing that creepeth vpon the
earth.<note> Chap.19. 2. and 20.7. 1.pet. 1.15</note></ab>
<ab n="45">For I am the
Lord that bringeth you vp out of the land of Egypt to be your God:
ye shal therefore be holy, for I am holy.</ab>
<ab n="46">This is the
law of the beasts, and of the foule, and of euery liuing creature
that moueth in the waters, and of euerie creature that creepeth
vpon the earth:</ab>
<ab n="47">To make a
difference betweene the vncleane and the cleane, &amp; betweene the
beast that may be eaten, and the beast that may not be
eaten.</ab>



</div>