<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLeviticus_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The purification of women after
childbirth. 6 Her offerings for her purifying.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, saying, If a woman haue conceiued seed, and
borne a man child, then she shal be vncleane seuen dayes: according
to the dayes of the separation for her infirmitie shall she be
vncleane.<note> Chap. 15. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And in the
eight day, the flesh of his foreskinne shall be
circumcised.<note> Luk.2.21. iohn 7.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And she shal
then continue in the blood of her purifying three and thirtie
dayes: Shee shall touch no hallowed thing, nor come into the
Sanctuary, vntill the dayes of her purifying be fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="5">But if she
beare a maid child, then she shalbe vncleane two weekes, as in her
separation: and she shall continue in the blood of her purifying
threescore and sixe dayes.</ab>

<fw>The purification of women.</fw>
<ab n="6">And when the
dayes of her purifying are fulfilled, for a sonne, or for a
daughter, she shall bring a lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offring, &amp; a yong pigeon, or a turtle doue for a sinne
offering, vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation,
vnto the Priest:<note> Heb. sonne of his yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Who shall offer
it before the Lord, and make an atonement for her, and she shall be
cleansed from the issue of her blood. This is the law for her that
hath borne a male or a female.</ab>
<ab n="8">And if she be
not able to bring a lambe, then she shall bring two turtles, or two
yong pigeons, the one for the burnt offering, and the other for a
sinne offering: and the Priest shall make an atonement for her, and
shee shall bee cleane.<note> Luke 2. 24. , Hebr. her hand find not sufficiencie of.</note></ab>



</div>