<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>3 Women minister vnto Christ of
their substance 4 Christ after he had preached from place to place,
attended with his Apostles, propoundeth the parable of the sower,
16 and of the candle: 21 declareth who are his mother, and
brethren: 22 rebuketh the winds: 26 casteth the Legion of deuils
out of the man, into the heard of swine: 37 is reiected of the
Gadarenes: 43 healeth the woman of her bloodie issue, 49 and
raiseth frō death Iairus daughter</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe afterward, þe he went throughout euery citie
and village preaching, and shewing the glad tidings of the kingdome
of God: and the twelue were with him,</ab>
<ab n="2">And certaine
women which had bene healed of euill spirits and infirmities, Mary
called Magdalene out of whom went seuen deuils,<note> Mar.16.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Ioanna the
wife of Chuza, Herods steward, and Susanna, and many others which
ministred vnto him of their substance.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And when
much people were gathered together, and were come to him out of
euery citie, he spake by a parable:<note> Mat.13.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">A Sower went
out to sowe his seed: and as he sowed, some fell by the wayes side,
and it was troden downe, and the foules of the aire deuoured
it.</ab>
<ab n="6">And some fell
vpon a rocke, and assoone as it was sprung vp, it withered away,
because it lacked moisture.</ab>
<ab n="7">And some fell
among thornes, and the thornes sprang vp with it, and choked
it.</ab>

<fw>The parable of the seed,
expounded.</fw>
<ab n="8">And other fell
on good ground, and sprang vp, and bare fruite an hundred fold. And
when hee saide these things, he cryed, He that hath eares to heare,
let him heare.</ab>
<ab n="9">And his
disciples asked him, saying, What might this parable be?</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said,
Unto you it is giuen to know the mysteries of the kingdome of God:
but to others in parables, that seeing, they might not see, and
hearing, they might not vnderstand.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now the
parable is this: The seed is the word of God.<note> Mat. 13. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Those by the
way side, are they that heare: then commeth the deuil, and taketh
away the word out of their hearts, least they should beleeue, and
be saued.</ab>
<ab n="13">They on the
rocke, are they which when they heare, receiue the word with ioy;
and these haue no roote, which for a while beleeue, and in time of
temptation fall away.</ab>
<ab n="14">And that which
fell among thornes, are they, which when they haue heard, goe
forth, and are choked with cares and riches, and pleasures of this
life, and bring no fruite to perfection.</ab>
<ab n="15">But that on
the good ground, are they, which in an honest and good heart hauing
heard the word, keepe it, and bring foorth fruite with
patience.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ No man
when he hath lighted a candle, couereth it with a vessell, or
putteth it vnder a bed: but setteth it on a candlesticke, that they
which enter in, may see the light.<note> Mat. 5. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For nothing is
secret, that shall not be made manifest: neither any thing hid,
that shall not be knowen, and come abroad.<note> Mat. 10. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Take heede
therefore how yee heare: for whosoeuer hath, to him shall bee
giuen; and whosoeuer hath not, from him shall be taken, euen that
which he seemeth to haue.<note> Mat. 13. 12. , Or, thinketh that he hath.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Then
came to him his mother and his brethren, and could not come at him
for the prease.<note> Mat. 12. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And it was
told him by certaine which saide, Thy mother and thy brethren stand
without, desiring to see thee.</ab>
<ab n="21">And hee
answered and said vnto them, My mother and my brethren are these
which heare the word of God, and doe it.</ab>

<fw>The sea stilled.</fw>
<ab n="22">¶ Now it
came to passe on a certaine day, that he went into a ship, with his
disciples: and hee said vnto them, Let vs goe ouer vnto the other
side of the lake, and they lanched foorth.<note> Mat.8.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But as they
sailed, he fell asleepe, and there came downe a storme of wind on
the lake, and they were filled with water, and were in
ieopardie.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they came
to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish. Then he
rose, and rebuked the wind, and the raging of the water: and they
ceased, and there was a calme.</ab>
<ab n="25">And he saide
vnto them, Where is your faith? And they being afraide wondred,
saying one to another, What maner of man is this? For he commandeth
euen the winds and water, and they obey him.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And
they arriued at the countrey of the Gadarenes, which is ouer
against Galilee.<note> Mat.8.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And when he
went forth to land, there met him out of the citie a certaine man
which had deuils long time, and ware no clothes, neither abode in
any house, but in the tombes.</ab>
<ab n="28">When he saw
Iesus, he cried out, and fell downe before him, and with a loud
voyce said, What haue I to doe with thee, Iesus, thou sonne of God
most high? I beseech thee torment me not.</ab>
<ab n="29">(For he had
commanded the vncleane spirit to come out of the man: For
oftentimes it had caught him, and he was kept bound with chaines,
and in fetters: and he brake the bands, and was driuen of the deuil
into the wildernesse.)</ab>
<ab n="30">And Iesus
asked him, saying, What is thy name? And he said, Legion: because
many deuils were entred into him.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they
besought him, that he would not command them to goe out into the
deepe.</ab>
<ab n="32">And there was
there an herd of many swine feeding on the mountaine: and they
besought him that he would suffer them to enter into them: and he
suffered them.</ab>
<ab n="33">Then went the
deuils out of the man, and entred into the swine: and the herd ran
violently downe a steepe place into the lake, and were
choked.</ab>

<fw>Iairus daughter is restored to
life.</fw>
<ab n="34">When they that
fed them saw what was done, they fled, and went, and tolde it in
the citie, and in the countrey.</ab>
<ab n="35">Then they went
out to see what was done, and came to Iesus, and found the man, out
of whom the deuils were departed, sitting at the feete of Iesus,
clothed, and in his right minde: and they were afraid.</ab>
<ab n="36">They also
which saw it, told them by what meanes he that was possessed of the
deuils, was healed.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ Then
the whole multitude of the countrey of the Gadarenes round about,
besought him to depart from them, for they were taken with great
feare: and he went vp into the ship, and returned back
againe.</ab>
<ab n="38">Now the man,
out of whom the deuils were departed, besought him that he might be
with him: but Iesus sent him away, saying,</ab>
<ab n="39">Returne to
thine owne house, and shew how great things God hath done vnto
thee. And he went his way, and published throughout the whole citie
how great things Iesus had done vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="40">And it came to
passe, that when Iesus was returned, the people gladly receiued
him: for they were all waiting for him.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And
behold, there came a man named Iairus, and hee was a ruler of the
Synagogue, and hee fell downe at Iesus feete, and besought him that
hee would come into his house:<note> Matth. 9. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">For hee had
one onely daughter about twelue yeeres of age, and she lay a dying.
(But as hee went the people thronged him.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ And a
woman hauing an issue of blood twelue yeres, which had spent all
her liuing vpon Phisitions, neither could be healed of any,</ab>
<ab n="44">Came behinde
him, and touched the border of his garment: and immediatly her
issue of blood stanched.</ab>
<ab n="45">And Iesus
saide, Who touched mee? When all denied, Peter and they that were
with him, said, Master, the multitude throng thee, and preasse
thee, and sayest thou, Who touched me?</ab>
<ab n="46">And Iesus
saide, Some body hath touched mee: for I perceiue that vertue is
gone out of me.</ab>

<fw>Iairus daughter is restored to
life.</fw>
<ab n="47">And when the
woman saw that she was not hid, shee came trembling, and falling
downe before him, shee declared vnto him before all the people, for
what cause shee had touched him, and how she was healed
immediatly.</ab>
<ab n="48">And he said
vnto her, Daughter, be of good comfort, thy faith hath made thee
whole, goe in peace.)</ab>
<ab n="49">¶ While
hee yet spake, there commeth one from the ruler of the Synagogues
house, saying to him, Thy daughter is dead, trouble not the
Master.</ab>
<ab n="50">But when Iesus
heard it, he answered him, saying, Feare not, beleeue onely, and
she shalbe made whole.</ab>
<ab n="51">And when hee
came into the house, hee suffered no man to goe in, saue Peter, and
Iames, and Iohn, and the father and the mother of the
mayden.</ab>
<ab n="52">And all wept,
and bewailed her: but he said, Weepe not, she is not dead, but
sleepeth.</ab>
<ab n="53">And they
laughed him to scorne, knowing that she was dead.</ab>
<ab n="54">And hee put
them all out, and tooke her by the hand, and called, saying, Mayd,
arise.</ab>
<ab n="55">And her spirit
came againe, and shee arose straightway: and hee commanded to giue
her meat.</ab>
<ab n="56">And her
parents were astonished: but hee charged them that they should tell
no man what was done.</ab>



</div>