<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Christ preacheth repentance vpon
the punishment of the Galileans, and others. 6 The fruitlesse figge
tree may not stand. 11 Hee healeth the crooked woman: 18 sheweth
the powerfull working of the word in the hearts of his chosen, by
the parable of the graine of mustard seed, and of leuen: 24
exhorteth to enter in at the straite gate, 31 and reproueth Herode,
and Hierusalem.</head>

<ab n="1">There were
present at that season, some that told him of the Galileans, whose
blood Pilate had mingled with their sacrifices.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Iesus
answering, said vnto them, Suppose ye that these Galileans were
sinners aboue all the Galileans, because they suffered such
things?</ab>
<ab n="3">I tell you,
Nay: but except yee repent, ye shall all likewise perish.</ab>
<ab n="4">Or those
eighteene, vpon whom the towre in Siloe fell, and slew them, thinke
ye that they were sinners aboue all men that dwelt in
Hierusalem?<note> Or, debters.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">I tell you,
Nay; but except yee repent, ye shall all likewise perish.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Hee
spake also this parable, A certaine man had a figtree planted in
his Uineyard, and he came and sought fruit thereon, and found
none.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then said hee
vnto the dresser of his Uineyard, Beholde, these three yeeres I
come seeking fruit on this figtree, and finde none: cut it downe,
why cumbreth it the ground?</ab>
<ab n="8">And he
answering, said vnto him, Lord, let it alone this yeere also, till
I shall digge about it, and doung it:</ab>
<ab n="9">And if it
beare fruit, Well: and if not, then after that, thou shalt cut it
downe.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he was teaching
in one of the Synagogues on the Sabbath.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And beholde,
there was a woman which had a spirit of infirmitie eighteene
yeeres, and was bowed together, and could in no wise lift vp her
selfe.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when Iesus saw
her, he called her to him, and said vnto her, Woman, thou art
loosed frō thy infirmitie.</ab>
<ab n="13">And hee layd his
handes on her, and immediatly she was made straight, and glorified
God.</ab>

<fw>The strait gate.</fw>
<ab n="14">And the ruler of
the Synagogue answered with indignation, because that Iesus had
healed on the Sabbath day, and said vnto the people, There are sixe
dayes in which men ought to worke: in them therefore come and be
healed, and not on the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Lord then
answered him, and said, Thou hypocrite, doeth not each one of you
on the Sabbath loose his oxe or his asse from the stall, and leade
him away to watering?</ab>
<ab n="16">And ought not this
woman being a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan hath bound, loe these
eighteene yeeres, be loosed from this bond on the Sabbath
day?</ab>
<ab n="17">And when hee had
said these things, all his aduersaries were ashamed: &amp; all the
people reioyced for all the glorious things that were done by
him.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then said
he, Unto what is the kingdome of God like? and whereunto shall I
resemble it?<note> Mat. 13. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">It is like a graine
of mustard seed, which a man tooke, and cast into his garden, and
it grew, and waxed a great tree: and the foules of the aire lodged
in the branches of it.</ab>
<ab n="20">And againe hee
said, Whereunto shall I liken the kingdome of God?</ab>
<ab n="21">It is like leauen,
which a woman tooke and hidde in three measures of meale, till the
whole was leauened.<note> See Mat. 13. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And he went thorow
the cities and villages, teaching and iourneying towards
Hierusalem.<note> Mat. 9. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Then said one vnto
him, Lord, are there few that be saued? And he said vnto
them,</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Striue to
enter in at the strait gate: for many, I say vnto you, will seeke
to enter in, and shall not be able.<note> Mat.7.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">When once the
master of the house is risen vp, &amp; hath shut to the doore, and
ye begin to stand without, &amp; to knocke at the doore, saying,
Lord, Lord, open vnto vs, and he shal answere, &amp; say vnto you,
I know you not whence you are:</ab>
<ab n="26">Then shall ye begin
to say, Wee haue eaten and drunke in thy presence, and thou hast
taught in our streets.</ab>
<ab n="27">But he shall say, I
tell you, I know you not whence you are; depart from me all ye
workers of iniquitie.<note> Mat.7.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">There shall be
weeping and gnashing of teeth, when yee shall see Abraham, and
Isaac, and Iacob, and all the Prophets in the kingdome of God, and
you your selues thrust out.</ab>

<fw>Dropsie healed.</fw>
<ab n="29">And they shall come
from the East, and from the West, and from the North, and from the
South, and shall sit downe in the kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="30">And behold, there
are last, which shall be first; and there are first, which shall be
last.<note> Mat.19. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ The same day
there came certaine of the Pharises, saying vnto him, Get thee out,
and depart hence; for Herode will kill thee.</ab>
<ab n="32">And he said vnto
them, Go ye and tell that Foxe, behold, I cast out deuils, and I
doe cures to day and to morrow, and the third day I shall be
perfected.</ab>
<ab n="33">Neuerthelesse, I
must walke to day and to morrow, and the day following: for it
cannot be that a Prophet perish out of Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="34">O Hierusalem,
Hierusalem, which killest the Prophets, and stonest them that are
sent vnto thee; how often would I haue gathered thy children
together, as a henne doeth gather her brood vnder her wings, &amp;
ye would not?<note> Mat.23. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Behold, your house
is left vnto you desolate. And verely I say vnto you, ye shall not
see me, vntill the time come when yee shall say, Blessed is hee
that commeth in the Name of the Lord.</ab>



</div>