<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Christ findeth a greater faith in
the Centurion a Gentile, then in any of the Iewes: 10 Healeth his
seruant being absent: 11 Raiseth from death the widowes sonne at
Naim: 19 Answereth Iohns messengers with the declaration of his
miracles: 24 Testifieth to the people what opinion hee held of
Iohn: 30 Inueigheth against the Iewes, who with neither the maners
of Iohn, nor of Iesus could be wonne: 36 and sheweth by occasion of
Marie Magdalene, how he is a friend to sinners, not to maintaine
them in sinnes, but to forgiue them their sinnes, vpon their faith
and repentance.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when hee
had ended all his sayings in the audience of the people, hee entred
into Capernaum.<note> Matth.8. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And a certaine
Centurions seruant, who was deare vnto him, was sicke and ready to
die.</ab>

<fw>The Centurions faith.</fw>
<ab n="3">And when he
heard of Iesus, he sent vnto him the Elders of the Iewes,
beseeching him that he would come and heale his seruant.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when they
came to Iesus, they besought him instantly, saying, that hee was
worthy for whome hee should doe this.</ab>
<ab n="5">For he loueth
our nation, and hee hath built vs a Synagogue.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Iesus went
with them. And when he was now not farre from the house, the
Centurion sent friends to him, saying vnto him, Lord, trouble not
thy selfe: for I am not worthy that thou shouldest enter vnder my
roofe.</ab>
<ab n="7">Wherefore
neither thought I my selfe worthy to come vnto thee: but say in a
worde, and my seruant shall bee healed.</ab>
<ab n="8">For I also am a
man set vnder authoritie, hauing vnder mee souldiers: and I say
vnto one, Goe, and he goeth: and to another, Come, and hee commeth:
and to my seruant, Doe this, and he doeth it.</ab>
<ab n="9">When Iesus
heard these things, hee marueiled at him, and turned him about, and
saide vnto the people that followed him, I say vnto you, I haue not
found so great faith, no, not in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they that
were sent, returning to the house, found the seruant whole that had
bene sicke.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And it
came to passe the day after, that he went into a citie called Naim:
and many of his disciples went with him, and much people.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now when he
came nigh to the gate of the citie, behold, there was a dead man
caried out, the onely sonne of his mother, and shee was a widow:
and much people of the citie was with her.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when the
Lord saw her, he had compassion on her, and saide vnto her, Weepe
not.</ab>
<ab n="14">And hee came
and touched the beere (and they that bare him, stood still.) And he
said, Yong man, I say vnto thee, Arise.<note> Or, coffin.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he that
was dead, sate vp, and began to speake: and he deliuered him to his
mother.</ab>
<ab n="16">And there came
a feare on all, and they glorified God, saying, that a great
Prophet is risen vp among vs, and that God hath visited his
people.</ab>

<fw>Of Iohn Baptist.</fw>
<ab n="17">And this
rumour of him went foorth throughout all Iudea, and throughout all
the region round about.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
disciples of Iohn shewed him of all these things.<note> Mat. 11. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And
Iohn calling vnto him two of his disciples, sent them to Iesus,
saying, Art thou hee that should come, or looke we for
another?</ab>
<ab n="20">When the men
were come vnto him, they said, Iohn Baptist hath sent vs vnto thee,
saying, Art thou hee that should come, or looke we for
another?</ab>
<ab n="21">And in that
same houre hee cured many of their infirmities and plagues, and of
euill spirits, and vnto many that were blind, he gaue
sight.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then Iesus
answering, said vnto them, Go your way, and tell Iohn what things
ye haue seene and heard, how that the blind see, the lame walke,
the lepers are clensed, the deafe heare, the dead are raised, to
the poore the Gospel is preached.</ab>
<ab n="23">And blessed is
he whosoeuer shall not be offended in me.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And
when the messengers of Iohn were departed, hee beganne to speake
vnto þ<note/> people concerning Iohn: What went ye out
into the wildernesse for to see? A reede shaken with the
winde?</ab>
<ab n="25">But what went
ye out for to see? A man clothed in soft raiment? Behold, they
which are gorgeously apparelled, and liue delicately, are in kings
courts.</ab>
<ab n="26">But what went
ye out for to see? A Prophet? Yea, I say vnto you, and much more
then a Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="27">This is he of
whome it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face,
which shall prepare thy way before thee.</ab>
<ab n="28">For I say vnto
you, among those that are borne of women, there is not a greater
Prophet then Iohn the Baptist: but he that is least in the kingdome
of God, is greater then he.</ab>
<ab n="29">And all the
people that heard him, and the Publicanes, iustified God, being
baptized with the baptisme of Iohn.</ab>
<ab n="30">But the
Pharisees and Lawyers reiected the counsell of God against
themselues, being not baptized of him.<note> Or, frustrated. , Or, within themselues.</note></ab>

<fw>Wisedome iustified.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ And the
Lord said, whereunto then shall I liken the men of this generation?
and to what are they like?<note> Mat. 11.16</note></ab>
<ab n="32">They are like
vnto children sitting in the market place, &amp; calling one to
another, and saying, We haue piped vnto you, and ye haue not
danced: wee haue mourned to you, and yee haue not wept.</ab>
<ab n="33">For Iohn the
Baptist came, neither eating bread, nor drinking wine, and ye say,
He hath a deuill.</ab>
<ab n="34">The sonne of
man is come, eating, and drinking, and ye say, Behold a gluttonous
man, and a wine bibber, a friend of Publicanes and sinners.</ab>
<ab n="35">But wisedome
is iustified of all her children.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And one
of the Pharisees desired him that he would eat with him. And he
went into the Pharisees house, and sate downe to meat.<note> Mar. 14.3</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And behold, a
woman in the citie which was a sinner, when shee knew that Iesus
sate at meat in the Pharisees house, brought an Alabaster boxe of
ointment,</ab>
<ab n="38">And stood at
his feet behind him, weeping, and began to wash his feete with
teares, and did wipe them with the haires of her head, and kissed
his feet, and anointed them with the oyntment.</ab>
<ab n="39">Now when the
Pharisee which had bidden him, saw it, he spake within himselfe,
saying, This man, if he were a Prophet, would haue knowen who, and
what maner of woman this is that toucheth him: for she is a
sinner.</ab>
<ab n="40">And Iesus
answering, said vnto him, Simon, I haue somewhat to say vnto thee.
And he saith, Master, say on.</ab>
<ab n="41">There was a
certaine creditour, which had two debtors: the one ought fiue
hundred pence, and the other fiftie.<note> See Mat. 18. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And when they
had nothing to pay, he frankly forgaue them both. Tell me
therefore, which of them will loue him most?</ab>
<ab n="43">Simon
answered, and saide, I suppose, that hee to whome he forgaue most.
And he said vnto him, Thou hast rightly iudged.</ab>
<ab n="44">And hee turned
to the woman, and said vnto Simon, Seest thou this woman? I entred
into thine house, thou gauest me no water for my feete: but shee
hath washed my feete with teares, and wiped them with the haires of
her head.</ab>

<fw>The parable of the seed,
expounded.</fw>
<ab n="45">Thou gauest me
no kisse: but this woman, since the time I came in, hath not ceased
to kisse my feet.</ab>
<ab n="46">Mine head with
oile thou didst not anoint: but this woman anointed my feet with
oyntment.</ab>
<ab n="47">Wherefore, I
say vnto thee, her sinnes, which are many, are forgiuen, for she
loued much: but to whom litle is forgiuen, the same loueth
litle.</ab>
<ab n="48">And he said
vnto her, Thy sinnes are forgiuen.</ab>
<ab n="49">And they that
sate at meat with him, began to say within themselues, Who is this
that forgiueth sinnes also?</ab>
<ab n="50">And he said to
the woman, Thy faith hath saued thee, goe in peace.</ab>



</div>