<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Christ preacheth to his disciples
to auoid hypocrisie, and fearefulnesse in publishing his doctrine:
13 Warneth the people to beware of couetousnes, by the parable of
the rich man who set vp greater barnes. 22 We must not be ouer
carefull of earthly things, 31 but seeke the kingdome of God, 33
giue almes, 36 bee ready at a knocke to open to our Lord whensoeuer
he commeth. 41 Christs ministers are to see to their charge, 49 and
looke for persecution. 54 The people must take this time of grace,
58 because it is a fearefull thing to die without
reconciliation.</head>


<fw>Whom to feare.</fw>
<ab n="1">In the meane
time, when there were gathered together an innumerable multitude of
people, insomuch that they trode one vpon another, he began to say
vnto his disciples first of all, Beware yee of the leauen of the
Pharisees, which is hypocrisie.<note> Mat. 16.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For there is
nothing couered, that shall not be reuealed, neither hid, that
shall not be knowen.<note> Matth. 10. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore,
whatsoeuer yee haue spoken in darkenesse, shall bee heard in the
light: and that which yee haue spoken in the eare, in closets, shal
be proclaimed vpon the house tops.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I say vnto
you my friends, Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after
that, haue no more that they can doe.<note> Matth. 10 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But I will
forewarne you whom you shall feare: Feare him, which after he hath
killed, hath power to cast into hell, yea, I say vnto you, Feare
him.</ab>
<ab n="6">Are not fiue
sparrowes solde for two farthings, and not one of them is forgotten
before God?<note> See Matt. 10.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But euen the
very haires of your head are all numbred: Feare not therefore, ye
are of more value then many sparrowes.</ab>
<ab n="8">Also I say
vnto you, Whosoeuer shall confesse me before men, him shall the
Sonne of man also confesse before the Angels of God.<note> Matth. 10 32. 2.tim. 2. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But he that
denieth me before men, shalbe denied before the Angels of
God.</ab>
<ab n="10">And whosoeuer shall
speake a word against the Sonne of man, it shall be forgiuen him:
but vnto him that blasphemeth against the holy Ghost, it shal not
be forgiuen.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when they bring
you vnto the Synagogues, and vnto Magistrates, &amp; powers, take
yee no thought how or what thing ye shall answere, or what ye shall
say:<note> Matth.10. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For the holy Ghost
shal teach you in the same houre, what ye ought to say.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And one of
the company saide vnto him, Master, speake to my brother, that he
diuide the inheritance with me.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he said vnto
him, Man, who made mee a iudge, or a diuider ouer you?</ab>

<fw>Take no thought.</fw>
<ab n="15">And he said vnto
them, Take heed and beware of couetousnes: for a mans life
consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he
possesseth.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he spake a
parable vnto them, saying, The ground of a certaine rich man
brought foorth plentifully.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he thought
within himselfe, saying, What shall I doe, because I haue no roome
where to bestow my fruits?</ab>
<ab n="18">And he said, This
will I doe, I will pull downe my barnes, and build greater, and
there will I bestow all my fruits, and my goods.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I will say to
my soule, Soule, thou hast much goods layd vp for many yeeres, take
thine ease, eate, drinke, and be merry.</ab>
<ab n="20">But God said vnto
him, Thou foole, this night thy soule shal be required of thee:
then whose shal those things be which thou hast
prouided?<note> Gre. doe they require thy soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">So is he that
laieth vp treasure for himselfe, and is not rich towards
God.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And he said
vnto his disciples, Therefore I say vnto you, Take no thought for
your life what yee shall eate, neither for the body what yee shall
put on.<note> Mat. 6. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The life is more
then meate, and the body is more then raiment.</ab>
<ab n="24">Consider the
rauens, for they neither sow nor reape, which neither haue
storehouse nor barne, and God feedeth them: How much more are yee
better then the foules?</ab>
<ab n="25">And which of you
with taking thought can adde to his stature one cubite?</ab>
<ab n="26">If yee then bee not
able to doe that thing which is least, why take yee thought for the
rest?</ab>
<ab n="27">Consider the
Lillies how they growe, they toile not; they spinne not: and yet I
say vnto you, that Solomon in all his glory, was not arayed like
one of these.</ab>
<ab n="28">If then God so
clothe the grasse, which is to day in the field, and to morrow is
cast into the ouen: how much more will he clothe you, O ye of litle
faith?</ab>
<ab n="29">And seeke not yee
what yee shall eate, or what ye shall drinke, neither be ye of
doubtfull minde.<note> Or, liue not in carefull suspence.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">For all these
things doe the nations of the world seeke after: and your father
knoweth that yee haue neede of these things.</ab>

<fw>A wise steward.</fw>
<ab n="31">¶ But rather
seeke yee the kingdome of God, and all these things shall be added
vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="32">Feare not, litle
flocke, for it is your fathers good pleasure to giue you the
kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="33">Sell that yee haue,
and giue almes: prouide your selues bagges which waxe not old, a
treasure in the heauens that faileth not, where no theefe
approcheth, neither moth corrupteth.<note> Mat. 6. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">For where your
treasure is, there will your heart be also.</ab>
<ab n="35">Let your loines be
girded about, and your lights burning,<note> 1.Pet.1. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And ye your selues
like vnto men that waite for their Lord, when he will returne from
the wedding, that when he commeth and knocketh, they may open vnto
him immediately.</ab>
<ab n="37">Blessed are those
seruants, whom the Lord when he commeth, shall find watching:
Uerily, I say vnto you, That he shall girde himselfe, and make them
to sit downe to meate, and will come foorth and serue them.</ab>
<ab n="38">And if he shall
come in the second watch, or come in the third watch, and find them
so, blessed are those seruants.</ab>
<ab n="39">And this know, that
if the good man of the house had knowen what houre the theefe would
come, he would haue watched, and not haue suffred his house to be
broken thorow.<note> Mat. 24. 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Be yee therefore
ready also: for the sonne of man commeth at an houre when yee
thinke not.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ Then Peter
said vnto him, Lord, speakest thou this parable vnto vs, or euen to
all?</ab>
<ab n="42">And the Lord said,
Who then is that faithfull and wise steward, whom his Lord shall
make ruler ouer his houshold, to giue them their portion of meate
in due season?</ab>
<ab n="43">Blessed is that
seruant, whom his Lord when he commeth, shall find so
doing.</ab>
<ab n="44">Of a trueth, I say
vnto you, that hee will make him ruler ouer all that he
hath.</ab>
<ab n="45">But and if that
seruant say in his heart, My Lord delayeth his comming and shall
beginne to beat the men seruants, and maidens, and to eate and
drinke, and to be drunken:</ab>

<fw>The euill seruant.</fw>
<ab n="46">The Lord of that
seruant will come in a day when hee looketh not for him, and at an
houre when hee is not ware, and will cut him in sunder, and will
appoint him his portion with the vnbeleeuers.<note> Or, cut him off.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And that seruant
which knew his Lords will, and prepared not himselfe, neither did
according to his will, shalbe beaten with many stripes.</ab>
<ab n="48">But hee that knew
not, and did commit things worthy of stripes, shall bee beaten with
few stripes. For vnto whomsoeuer much is giuen, of him shal bee
much required: and to whom men haue committed much, of him they
will aske the more.</ab>
<ab n="49">¶ I am come to
send fire on the earth, and what will I, if it be already
kindled?</ab>
<ab n="50">But I haue a
baptisme to be baptized with, and how am I straitned till it be
accomplished?<note> Or, pained.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">Suppose yee that I
am come to giue peace on earth? I tell you, Nay, but rather
diuision.<note> Matt. 10. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">For from henceforth
there shalbe fiue in one house diuided, three against two, and two
against three.</ab>
<ab n="53">The father shall
bee diuided against the sonne, and the sonne against the father:
the mother against the daughter, and the daughter against the
mother: the mother in lawe against her daughter in lawe, and the
daughter in law against her mother in lawe.</ab>
<ab n="54">¶ And he said
also to the people, When ye see a cloud rise out of the West,
straightway yee say, There commeth a showre, and so it
is.<note> Matt. 16. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And when ye see the
Southwind blow, ye say, There will be heat, and it commeth to
passe.</ab>
<ab n="56">Ye hypocrites, ye
can discerne the face of the skie, and of the earth: but how is it
that yee doe not discerne this time?</ab>
<ab n="57">Yea, and why euen
of your selues iudge ye not what is right?</ab>
<ab n="58">¶ When thou
goest with thine aduersary to the magistrate, as thou art in the
way, giue diligence that thou mayest be deliuered from him, lest
hee hale thee to the Iudge, and the Iudge deliuer thee to the
officer, and the officer cast thee into prison.<note> Matth. 5. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">I tell thee, Thou
shalt not depart thence, till thou hast payd the very last
mite.<note> See Mar. 12.42.</note></ab>



</div>