<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Christ commendeth the poore widow.
5 Hee foretelleth the destruction of the Temple, and of the citie
Hierusalem: 25 The signes also which shall be before the last day.
34 He exhorteth them to be watchfull.</head>

<ab n="1">And he looked
vp, and saw the rich men casting their giftes into the
treasurie.<note> Marke 12. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee saw
also a certaine poore widow, casting in thither two
mites.<note> See Marke 12.42.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And he said,
Of a truth, I say vnto you, that this poore widow hath cast in more
then they all.</ab>
<ab n="4">For all these
haue of their abundance cast in vnto the offerings of God, but shee
of her penurie hath cast in all the liuing that she had.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And as
some spake of the Temple, how it was adorned with goodly stones,
and gifts, he said,<note> Mat.24.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">As for these
things which yee behold, the dayes will come, in the which there
shal not be left one stone vpon another, that shal not be throwen
downe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they asked
him, saying, Master, but when shall these things be? and what signe
wil there be, when these things shall come to passe?</ab>
<ab n="8">And he said,
Take heede that yee be not deceiued: for many shall come in my
Name, saying, I am Christ, and the time draweth neere: goe yee not
therefore after them.</ab>
<ab n="9">But when ye
shall heare of wars, and commotions, be not terrified: for these
things must first come to passe, but the end is not by and
by.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then said he vnto
them, Nation shall rise against nation, and kingdome against
kingdome:<note> Matt.24. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And great
earthquakes shall be in diuers places, and famines, and
pestilences: and fearefull sights and great signes shall there be
from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="12">But before all
these, they shall lay their hands on you, and persecute you,
deliuering you vp to the Synagogues, and into prisons, being
brought before Kings and rulers for my Names sake.</ab>

<fw>The worlds end.</fw>
<ab n="13">And it shall turne
to you for a testimony.</ab>
<ab n="14">Settle it therfore
in your hearts, not to meditate before what ye shall
answere.<note> Matth.10. 19</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For I will giue you
a mouth and wisedome, which all your aduersaries shall not be able
to gainsay, nor resist.</ab>
<ab n="16">And yee shall be
betrayed both by parents and brethren, and kinsefolkes and friends,
and some of you shall they cause to be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="17">And ye shalbe hated
of all men for my Names sake.</ab>
<ab n="18">But there shall not
a haire of your head perish.<note> Matth.10. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">In your patience
possesse ye your soules.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when yee shall
see Hierusalem compassed with armies, then know that the desolation
thereof is nigh.<note> Matth.24. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Then let them which
are in Iudea, flee to the mountaines, and let them which are in the
midst of it, depart out, and let not them that are in the
countreys, enter thereinto.</ab>
<ab n="22">For these be the
dayes of vengeance, that all things which are written may be
fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="23">But woe vnto them
that are with childe, and to them that giue sucke in those dayes,
for there shalbe great distresse in the land, and wrath vpon this
people.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they shall fall
by the edge of the sword, and shall bee led away captiue into all
nations, and Hierusalem shall be troden downe of the Gentiles,
vntill the times of the Gentiles bee fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And there
shalbe signes in the Sunne, and in the Moone, and in the Starres,
and vpon the earth distresse of nations, with perplexity, the Sea
and the waues roaring,<note> Matth.24. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Mens hearts failing
them for feare, and for looking after those things which are
comming on the earth; For the powers of heauen shall be
shaken.</ab>
<ab n="27">And then shall they
see the sonne of man comming in a cloud with power and great
glory.</ab>
<ab n="28">And when these
things begin to come to passe, then looke vp, and lift vp your
heads, for your redemptiou draweth nigh.</ab>
<ab n="29">And he spake to
them a parable, Behold the figge tree, and all the trees,</ab>

<fw>Watch and pray.</fw>
<ab n="30">When they now shoot
foorth, yee see and know of your owne selues, that summer is now
nigh at hand.</ab>
<ab n="31">So likewise yee,
when yee see these things come to passe, know ye that the kingdome
of God is nigh at hand.</ab>
<ab n="32">Uerily I say vnto
you, this generation shall not passe away, till all be
fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="33">Heauen and earth
shall passe away, but my words shall not passe away.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ And take
heed to your selues, least at any time your hearts be ouercharged
with surfetting, and drunkennesse, and cares of this life, and so
that day come vpon you vnawares.</ab>
<ab n="35">For as a snare
shall it come on all them that dwell on the face of the whole
earth.</ab>
<ab n="36">Watch ye therefore,
and pray alwayes, that ye may be accompted worthy to escape all
these things that shall come to passe, and to stand before the
sonne of man.</ab>
<ab n="37">And in the day time
he was teaching in the Temple, and at night hee went out, and abode
in the mount that is called the mount of Oliues.</ab>
<ab n="38">And all the people
came earely in the morning to him in the Temple, for to heare
him.</ab>



</div>