<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Of Zacheus a Publicane. 11 The ten
pieces of money. 28 Christ rideth into Hierusalem with triumph: 41
weepeth ouer it: 45 driueth the buiers and sellers out of the
Temple: 47 teaching dayly in it. The rulers would haue destroyed
him, but for feare of the people.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iesus
entred, and passed thorow Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="2">And behold,
there was a man named Zacheus, which was the cheefe among the
Publicanes, and he was rich.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he sought
to see Iesus who he was, and could not for the prease, because he
was litle of stature.</ab>
<ab n="4">And he ranne
before, and climed vp into a sycomore tree to see him, for he was
to passe that way.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when Iesus
came to the place, he looked vp and saw him, and said vnto him,
Zacheus, make haste, &amp; come downe, for to day I must abide at
thy house.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he made
haste, and came downe, and receiued him ioyfully.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when they
saw it, they all murmured, saying, That he was gone to be guest
with a man that is a sinner.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Zacheus
stood, and said vnto the Lord, Behold, Lord, the halfe of my goods
I giue to the poore, &amp; if I haue taken any thing from any man
by false accusation, I restore him foure fold.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Iesus said
vnto him, This day is saluation come to this house, forsomuch as he
also is the sonne of Abraham.</ab>
<ab n="10">For the sonne of
man is come to seeke, and to saue that which was lost.<note> Matt.18. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And as they heard
these things, he added, and spake a parable, because he was nigh to
Hierusalem, and because they thought that the kingdome of God
should immediately appeare.</ab>
<ab n="12">He said therefore,
A certaine noble man went into a farre countrey, to receiue for
himselfe a kingdome, and to returne.<note> Matt.25. 14.</note></ab>

<fw>Money giuen out.</fw>
<ab n="13">And hee called his
ten seruants, and deliuered them ten pounds, and said vnto them,
Occupy till I come.<note> Mina here translated a pound, is twelue ounces and an halfe, which according to fiue shillings the ounce, is 3. pounds two shillings sixe pence.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But his citizens
hated him, and sent a message after him, saying, We wil not haue
this man to reigne ouer vs.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe, that when he was returned, hauing receiued the kingdome,
then hee commaunded these seruants to be called vnto him, to whom
he had giuen the money, that hee might know how much euery man had
gained by trading.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then came the
first, saying, Lord, thy pound hath gained ten pounds.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said vnto
him, Well, thou good seruant: because thou hast bene faithfull in a
very little, haue thou authoritie ouer ten cities.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the second
came, saying, Lord, thy pound hath gained fiue pounds.</ab>
<ab n="19">And hee said
likewise to him, Bee thou also ouer fiue cities.</ab>
<ab n="20">And another came,
saying, Lord, behold, here is thy pound which I haue kept layd vp
in a napkin:</ab>
<ab n="21">For I feared thee,
because thou art an austere man: thou takest vp that thou layedst
not downe, and reapest that thou didst not sow.</ab>
<ab n="22">And hee saith vnto
him, Out of thine owne mouth will I iudge thee, thou wicked
seruant: Thou knewest that I was an austere man, taking vp that I
layde not downe, and reaping that I did not sow.</ab>
<ab n="23">Wherefore then
gauest not thou my money into the bancke, that at my comming I
might haue required mine owne with vsury?</ab>
<ab n="24">And he said vnto
them that stood by, Take from him the pound, and giue it to him
that hath ten pounds.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they said vnto
him, Lord, he hath ten pounds.</ab>
<ab n="26">For I say vnto you,
That vnto euery one which hath, shalbe giuen, and from him that
hath not, euen that hee hath shalbe taken away from
him.<note> Matth.13. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">But those mine
enemies which would not that I should reigne ouer them, bring
hither, and slay them before mee.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And when he
had thus spoken, he went before, ascending vp to
Hierusalem.</ab>

<fw>Stones would cry.</fw>
<ab n="29">And it came to
passe when he was come nigh to Bethphage and Bethanie, at the mount
called the mount of Oliues, he sent two of his
disciples,<note> Matth.21. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Saying, Goe ye into
the village ouer against you, in the which at your entring ye shall
find a Colt tied, whereon yet neuer man sate: loose him, and bring
him hither.</ab>
<ab n="31">And if any man aske
you, Why do ye loose him? Thus shall ye say vnto him, Because the
Lord hath neede of him.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they that were
sent, went their way, and found euen as hee had said vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="33">And as they were
loosing the colt, the owners thereof said vnto them, Why loose ye
the Colt?</ab>
<ab n="34">And they said, The
Lord hath need of him.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they brought
him to Iesus: and they cast their garments vpon the Colt, and they
set Iesus thereon.</ab>
<ab n="36">And as he went,
they spread their clothes in the way.</ab>
<ab n="37">And when he was
come nigh euen now at the descent of the mount of Oliues, the whole
multitude of the disciples began to reioyce and praise God with a
loud voice, for all the mighty workes that they had seene,</ab>
<ab n="38">Saying, Blessed bee
the King that commeth in the Name of the Lord, peace in heauen, and
glory in the Highest.</ab>
<ab n="39">And some of the
Pharisees from among the multitude saide vnto him, Master, rebuke
thy disciples.</ab>
<ab n="40">And he answered,
and said vnto them, I tell you, that if these should holde their
peace, the stones would immediatly cry out.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And when he
was come neere, he beheld the city and wept ouer it,</ab>
<ab n="42">Saying, If thou
hadst knowen, euen thou, at least in this thy day, the things which
belong vnto thy peace! but now they are hid from thine
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="43">For the dayes shall
come vpon thee, that thine enemies shall cast a trench about thee,
and compasse thee round, and keepe thee in on euery side,</ab>
<ab n="44">And shall lay thee
euen with the ground, and thy children within thee: and they shall
not leaue in thee one stone vpon another, because thou knewest not
the time of thy visitation.</ab>
<ab n="45">And he went into
the Temple, and began to cast out them that solde therein, and them
that bought,<note> Matth.21. 12.</note></ab>

<fw>The parable of the Vineyard let
out.</fw>
<ab n="46">Saying vnto them,
It is written, My house is the house of prayer: but ye haue made it
a denne of theeues.</ab>
<ab n="47">And he taught daily
in the Temple. But the chiefe Priestes and the Scribes, and the
chiefe of the people sought to destroy him,</ab>
<ab n="48">And could not finde
what they might doe: for all the people were very attentiue to
heare him.<note> Or, hanged on him.</note></ab>



</div>