<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-4-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The temptation and fasting of
Christ: 13 He ouercommeth the deuill: 14 Beginneth to preach: 16
The people of Nazareth admire his gratious words: 33 he cureth one
possessed of a deuill, 38 Peters mother in law, 40 and diuers other
sicke persons. 41 The deuils acknowledge Christ, and are reproued
for it: 43 he preacheth through the cities.</head>


<fw>Christ is tempted, He
preacheth.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Iesus being
full of the holy Ghost, returned from Iordane, and was led by the
spirit into the wildernesse,<note> Matth.4. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Being fourtie
dayes tempted of the deuil, and in those dayes he did eat nothing:
and when they were ended, he afterward hungred.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the deuil
saide vnto him, If thou be the Sonne of God, command this stone
that it be made bread.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iesus
answered him, saying, It is written, that man shall not liue by
bread alone, but by euery word of God.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the deuil
taking him vp into an high mountaine, shewed vnto him all the
kingdomes of the world in a moment of time.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the deuil
said vnto him, All this power will I giue thee, and the glory of
them; for that is deliuered vnto me, &amp; to whomsoeuer I will, I
giue it.</ab>
<ab n="7">If thou
therefore wilt worship me, all shalbe thine.<note> Or, fall downe before me.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Iesus
answered and said vnto him, Get thee behinde me, Satan: for it is
written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him onely shalt
thou serue.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee brought
him to Hierusalem, and set him on a pinacle of the Temple, and said
vnto him, If thou be the Sonne of God, cast thy selfe downe from
hence.</ab>
<ab n="10">For it is
written, He shall giue his Angels charge ouer thee, to keepe
thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">And in their
handes they shall beare thee vp, lest at any time thou dash thy
foot against a stone.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Iesus
answering, said vnto him, It is said, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord
thy God.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when the
deuil had ended all the temptation, hee departed from him for a
season.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
Iesus returned in the power of the Spirit into Galilee, and there
went out a fame of him through all the region round about.</ab>

<fw>Christ is tempted, He
preacheth.</fw>
<ab n="15">And hee taught
in their Synagogues, being glorified of all.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And hee
came to Nazareth, where he had bene brought vp, and as his custome
was, he went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and stood vp
for to reade.<note> Matt. 13. 54.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And there was
deliuered vnto him the booke of the Prophet Esaias, and when he had
opened the Booke, he found the place where it was written,</ab>
<ab n="18">The Spirit of
the Lord is vpon mee, because hee hath anointed mee, to preach the
Gospel to the poore, he hath sent mee to heale the broken hearted,
to preach deliuerance to the captiues, and recouering of sight to
the blinde, to set at libertie them that are bruised,<note> Esay 61.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">To preach the
acceptable yeere of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he closed
the booke, and hee gaue it againe to the minister, and sate downe:
and the eyes of all them that were in the Synagogue were fastened
on him.</ab>
<ab n="21">And hee began
to say vnto them, This day is this Scripture fulfilled in your
eares.</ab>
<ab n="22">And all bare
him witnesse, and wondered at the gracious wordes, which proceeded
out of his mouth. And they said, Is not this Iosephs sonne?</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee said
vnto them, Yee will surely say vnto me this prouerbe, Physition,
heale thy selfe: Whatsoeuer wee haue heard done in Capernaum, doe
also here in thy countrey.</ab>
<ab n="24">And hee said,
Verely I say vnto you, no Prophet is accepted in his owne
countrey.<note> Matth.13. 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But I tell you
of a trueth, many widowes were in Israel in the dayes of Elias,
when the heauen was shut vp three yeres and sixe moneths: when
great famine was throughout all the land:<note> 1.King. 17.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But vnto none
of them was Elias sent, saue vnto Sarepta a citie of Sidon, vnto a
woman that was a widow.</ab>
<ab n="27">And many
lepers were in Israel in the time of Elizeus the Prophet: and none
of them was cleansed, sauing Naaman the Syrian.<note> 2.King.5. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And all they
in the Synagogue, when they heard these things, were filled with
wrath,</ab>
<ab n="29">And rose vp,
and thrust him out of the citie, &amp; led him vnto the brow of the
hill (whereon their city was built) that they might cast him downe
headlong.<note> Or, edge.</note></ab>

<fw>The feuer healed.</fw>
<ab n="30">But he passing
thorow the mids of them, went his way:</ab>
<ab n="31">And came downe
to Capernaum, a citie of Galile, and taught them on the Sabbath
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they were
astonished at his doctrine: for his worde was with
power.<note> Mat. 7. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And in
the Synagogue there was a man which had a spirit of an vncleane
deuill, and cryed out with a loud voice,<note> Mat. 1.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Saying, Let vs
alone, what haue wee to doe with thee, thou Iesus of Nazareth? art
thou come to destroy vs? I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of
God.<note> Or, away.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And Iesus
rebuked him, saying, Holde thy peace, and come out of him. And when
the deuill had throwen him in the middes, hee came out of him, and
hurt him not.</ab>
<ab n="36">And they were
all amazed, and spake among themselues, saying, What a word is
this? for with authoritie and power hee commaundeth the vncleane
spirits, and they come out.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the fame
of him went out into euery place of the countrey round
about.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ And he
arose out of the Synagogue, and entred into Simons house: and
Simons wiues mother was taken with a great feuer, and they besought
him for her.<note> Mat. 8. 14</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And he stood
ouer her, and rebuked the feuer, &amp; it left her. And immediatly
she arose, &amp; ministred vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="40">¶ Now
when the Sunne was setting, all they that had any sicke with diuers
diseases, brought them vnto him: and hee laid his handes on euery
one of them, and healed them.</ab>
<ab n="41">And deuils
also came out of many, crying out, and saying, Thou art Christ the
Sonne of God. And hee rebuking them, suffered them not to speake:
for they knewe that hee was Christ.<note> Mat. 1. 34. , Or, to say that they knew him to be Christ.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And when it
was day, he departed, and went into a desert place: and the people
sought him, and came vnto him, and stayed him, that he should not
depart from them.</ab>
<ab n="43">And hee said
vnto them, I must preach the kingdome of God to other cities also:
for therefore am I sent.</ab>
<ab n="44">And hee
preached in the Synagogues of Galile.</ab>



</div>