<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-24-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-24-24b-John.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Christs Resurrection is declared
by two Angels, to the women that come to the Sepulchre. 9 These
report it to others. 13 Christ himselfe appeareth to the two
disciples that went to Emmaus: 36 Afterwards he appeareth to the
Apostles, and reproueth their vnbeleefe: 47 Giueth them a charge:
49 Promiseth the holy Ghost: 51 And so ascendeth into
heauen.</head>

<ab n="1">Now vpon the
first day of the weeke, very earely in the morning, they came vnto
the Sepulchre, bringing the spices which they had prepared, and
certaine others with them.<note> Mat.28.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And they found
the stone rolled away from the Sepulchre.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they
entred in, and found not the body of the Lord Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="4">And it came to
passe, as they were much perplexed thereabout, behold, two men
stood by them in shining garments.</ab>
<ab n="5">And as they
were afraid, and bowed downe their faces to the earth, they said
vnto them, Why seek ye the liuing among the dead?<note> Or, him that liueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He is not
heere, but is risen: Remember how he spake vnto you when he was yet
in Galilee,<note> Mat.17. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Saying, The
Sonne of man must be deliuered into the hands of sinfull men, and
be crucified, and the third day rise againe.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they
remembred his words,</ab>
<ab n="9">And returned
from the Sepulchre, and told all these things vnto the eleuen, and
to all the rest.</ab>

<fw>Christ talketh with two
disciples.</fw>
<ab n="10">It was Marie
Magdalene, &amp; Ioanna, &amp; Mary the mother of Iames, and other
women that were with them, which tolde these things vnto the
Apostles.</ab>
<ab n="11">And their words
seemed to them as idle tales, and they beleeued them not.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then arose Peter,
and ranne vnto the Sepulchre, and stowping downe, hee behelde the
linnen clothes layd by themselues, and departed, wondering in
himselfe at that which was come to passe.<note> Iohn 20. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And behold,
two of them went that same day to a village called Emaus, which was
from Hierusalem about threescore furlongs.<note> Marke 16. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And they talked
together of all these things which had happened.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe, that while they communed together, and reasoned, Iesus
himselfe drew neere, and went with them.</ab>
<ab n="16">But their eyes were
holden, that they should not know him.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he said vnto
them, What maner of communications are these that yee haue one to
another as yee walke, and are sad?</ab>
<ab n="18">And the one of
them, whose name was Cleophas, answering, saide vnto him, Art thou
onely a stranger in Hierusalem, and hast not knowen the things
which are come to passe there in these dayes?</ab>
<ab n="19">And hee saide vnto
them, What things? And they said vnto him, Concerning Iesus of
Nazareth, which was a Prophet, mighty in deede and word before God,
and all the people.</ab>
<ab n="20">And how the chiefe
Priests and our rulers deliuered him to be condemned to death, and
haue crucified him.</ab>
<ab n="21">But wee trusted
that it had bene hee, which should haue redeemed Israel: and beside
all this, to day is the third day since these things were
done.</ab>
<ab n="22">Yea, and certaine
women also of our company made vs astonished, which were early at
the Sepulchre:</ab>
<ab n="23">And when they found
not his bodie, they came, saying, that they had also seene a vision
of Angels, which saide that he was aliue.</ab>
<ab n="24">And certaine of
them which were with vs, went to the Sepulchre, and found it euen
so as the women had said, but him they saw not.</ab>

<fw>Christ talketh with two
disciples.</fw>
<ab n="25">Then hee saide vnto
them, O fooles, and slow of heart to beleeue all that the Prophets
haue spoken:</ab>
<ab n="26">Ought not Christ to
haue suffered these things, and to enter into his glorie?</ab>
<ab n="27">And beginning at
Moses, and all the Prophets, hee expounded vnto them in all the
Scriptures, the things concerning himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="28">And they drew nigh
vnto the village, whither they went, and hee made as though hee
would haue gone further.</ab>
<ab n="29">But they
constrained him, saying, Abide with vs, for it is towards euening,
and the day is farre spent: And he went in, to tarrie with
them.</ab>
<ab n="30">And it came to
passe, as hee sate at meate with them, hee tooke bread, and blessed
it, and brake, and gaue to them.</ab>
<ab n="31">And their eyes were
opened, and they knew him, and he vanished out of their
sight.<note> Or, ceased to be seene of them.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And they said one
vnto another, Did not our heart burne within vs, while hee talked
with vs by the way, and while hee opened to vs the
Scriptures?</ab>
<ab n="33">And they rose vp
the same houre, and returned to Hierusalem, and found the eleuen
gathered together, and them that were with them,</ab>
<ab n="34">Saying, The Lord is
risen indeed, and hath appeared to Simon.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they told what
things were done in the way, &amp; how he was knowen of them in
breaking of bread.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And as they
thus spake, Iesus himselfe stood in the midst of them, and sayeth
vnto them, Peace bee vnto you.<note> Marke 16. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">But they were
terrified, and afrighted, and supposed that they had seene a
spirit.</ab>
<ab n="38">And he said vnto
them, Why are yee troubled, and why doe thoughts arise in your
hearts?</ab>
<ab n="39">Beholde my hands
and my feete, that it is I my selfe: handle me, and see, for a
spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me haue.</ab>
<ab n="40">And when hee had
thus spoken, hee shewed them his handes and his feete.</ab>
<ab n="41">And while they yet
beleeued not for ioy, and wondered, hee saide vnto them, Haue ye
here any meat?</ab>
<ab n="42">And they gaue him a
piece of a broyled fish, and of an hony combe.</ab>

<fw>The true light.</fw>
<ab n="43">And he tooke it,
and did eate before them.</ab>
<ab n="44">And hee said vnto
them, These are the words which I spake vnto you, while I was yet
with you, þ<note/> all things must be fulfilled, which
were written in the Law of Moses, &amp; in the Prophets, and in the
Psalmes concerning me.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then opened he
their vnderstanding, that they might vnderstand the
Scriptures,</ab>
<ab n="46">And said vnto them,
Thus it is written, &amp; thus it behoued Christ to suffer, &amp;
to rise from the dead the third day:</ab>
<ab n="47">And that repentance
and remission of sinnes should be preached in his Name, among all
nations, beginning at Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="48">And yee are
witnesses of these things.</ab>
<ab n="49">¶ And behold,
I send the promise of my Father vpon you: but tarie ye in the citie
of Hierusalem, vntill ye be indued with power from on
high.<note> Iohn 15. 26. actes 1.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">¶ And he led
them out as farre as to Bethanie, and hee lift vp his hands, and
blessed them.</ab>
<ab n="51">And it came to
passe, while hee blessed them, hee was parted from them, and caried
vp into heauen.<note> Mar.16. 19. actes 1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">And they worshipped
him, and returned to Hierusalem, with great ioy:</ab>
<ab n="53">And were
continually in the Temple, praising and blessing God. Amen.</ab>



</div>