<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The parable of the vniust steward.
14 Christ reprooueth the hypocrisie of the couetous Pharisees. 19
The rich glutton, and Lazarus the begger.</head>


<fw>An vniust steward.</fw>
<ab n="1">And hee said
also vnto his disciples, There was a certaine rich man which had a
Steward, and the same was accused vnto him that he had wasted his
goods.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee called
him, and said vnto him, How is it that I heare this of thee? Giue
an accompt of thy stewardship: for thou mayest bee no longer
Steward.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then the
Steward said within himselfe, What shall I doe, for my lord taketh
away from mee the Stewardship? I cannot digge, to begge I am
ashamed.</ab>
<ab n="4">I am resolued
what to doe, that when I am put out of the stewardship, they may
receiue me into their houses.</ab>
<ab n="5">So hee called
euery one of his lords detters vnto him, and said vnto the first,
How much owest thou vnto my lord?</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee said,
An hundred measures of oyle. And hee saide vnto him, Take thy bill,
and sit downe quickly, and write fiftie.<note> The word Batus in the originall conteineth nine gallons 3. quarts.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then said hee
to another, And how much owest thou? And hee said, An hundred
measures of wheat. And hee saide vnto him, Take thy bill and write
fourescore.<note> The word here interpreted a measure, in the originall conteineth about foureteene bushels and a pottle.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the lord
commended the vniust Steward, because he had done wisely: for the
children of this world are in their generation wiser then the
children of light.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I say vnto
you, Make to your selues friends of the Mammon of vnrighteousnesse,
that when ye faile, they may receiue you into euerlasting
habitations.<note> Or, riches.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee that is
faithfull in that which is least, is faithfull also in much: and he
that is vniust in the least, is vniust also in much.</ab>
<ab n="11">If therefore yee
haue not bene faithfull in the vnrighteous Mammon, who will commit
to your trust the true riches?<note> Or, riches.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And if ye haue not
bene faithful in that which is another mans, who shall giue you
that which is your owne?</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ No seruant
can serue two masters, for either he will hate the one, and loue
the other: or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other:
yee cannot serue God and Mammon.<note> Matth. 6. 24.</note></ab>

<fw>The rich glutton.</fw>
<ab n="14">And the Pharisees
also who were couetous, heard all these things: and they derided
him.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he said vnto
them, Ye are they which iustifie your selues before men, but God
knoweth your hearts: for that which is highly esteemed amongst men,
is abomination in the sight of God.</ab>
<ab n="16">The law and the
Prophets were vntill Iohn: since that time the kingdome of God is
preached, and euery man preasseth into it.<note> Matth.11. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And it is easier
for heauen and earth to passe, then one title of the law to
faile.<note> Matth.5. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Whosoeuer putteth
away his wife, &amp; marrieth another, committeth adultery: and
whosoeuer marrieth her that is put away from her husband,
committeth adultery.<note> Matth.5. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ There was a
certaine rich man, which was clothed in purple and fine linnen, and
fared sumptuously euery day.</ab>
<ab n="20">And there was a
certaine begger named Lazarus, which was layde at his gate full of
sores,</ab>
<ab n="21">And desiring to bee
fed with the crummes which fel from the rich mans table: moreouer
the dogges came and licked his sores.</ab>
<ab n="22">And it came to
passe that the begger died, and was caried by the Angels into
Abrahams bosome: the rich man also died, and was buried.</ab>
<ab n="23">And in hell he lift
vp his eyes being in torments, and seeth Abraham afarre off, and
Lazarus in his bosome:</ab>
<ab n="24">And he cried, and
said, Father Abraham, haue mercy on mee, and send Lazarus, that he
may dip the tip of his finger in water, and coole my tongue, for I
am tormented in this flame.</ab>
<ab n="25">But Abraham saide,
Sonne, remember that thou in thy life-time receiuedst thy good
things, and likewise Lazarus euill things, but now he is comforted,
and thou art tormented.</ab>
<ab n="26">And besides all
this, betweene vs and you there is a great gulfe fixed, so that
they which would passe from hence to you, cannot, neither can they
passe to vs, that would come from thence.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then he said, I
pray thee therefore father, that thou wouldest send him to my
fathers house:</ab>
<ab n="28">For I haue fiue
brethren, that he may testifie vnto them, lest they also come into
this place of torment.</ab>

<fw>Of forgiuenesse.</fw>
<ab n="29">Abraham saith vnto
him, They haue Moses and the Prophets, let them heare them.</ab>
<ab n="30">And hee said, Nay,
father Abraham: but if one went vnto them from the dead, they will
repent.</ab>
<ab n="31">And hee said vnto
him, If they heare not Moses and the Prophets, neither will they be
perswaded, though one rose from the dead.</ab>



</div>