<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-22-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-22-22b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 The Iewes conspire against Christ.
3 Satan prepareth Iudas to betray him. 7 The Apostles prepare the
Passeouer. 19 Christ instituteth his holy supper, 21 couertly
foretelleth of the traitour, 24 dehorteth the rest of his Apostles
from ambition, 31 assureth Peter his faith should not faile: 34 and
yet he should denie him thrise. 39 He prayeth in the mount, and
sweateth blood, 47 is betrayed with a kisse: 50 hee healeth Malchus
eare, 54 he is thrise denied of Peter, 63 shamefully abused, 66 and
confesseth himselfe to be the sonne of God.</head>

<ab n="1">Now
þ<note/> feast of vnleuened bread drew nigh, which is
called the Passeouer.<note> Matth.26. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the chiefe
Priests and Scribes sought how they might kill him; for they feared
the people.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Then
entred Satan into Iudas surnamed Iscariot, being of the number of
the twelue.<note> Matth.26. 14.</note></ab>

<fw>The last Supper.</fw>
<ab n="4">And he went
his way, and communed with the chiefe Priests and captaines, how he
might betray him vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they were
glad, and couenanted to giue him money.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
promised, and sought opportunitie to betray him vnto them in the
absence of the multitude.<note> Or, without tumult.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Then
came the day of vnleauened bread, when the Passeouer must be
killed.<note> Matth.26. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And he sent
Peter and Iohn, saying, Goe and prepare vs the Passeouer, that we
may eate.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they said
vnto him, Where wilt thou that we prepare?</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said vnto
them, Behold, when ye are entred into the citie, there shall a man
meet you, bearing a pitcher of water, follow him into the house
where he entreth in.</ab>
<ab n="11">And yee shall say
vnto the goodman of the house, The Master saith vnto thee, Where is
the ghest-chamber where I shall eate the Passeouer with my
disciples?</ab>
<ab n="12">And he shall shew
you a large vpper roume furnished, there make ready.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they went, and
found as hee had said vnto them, and they made readie the
Passeouer.</ab>
<ab n="14">And when the houre
was come, he sate downe, and the twelue Apostles with
him.<note> Matth.26. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he said vnto
them, With desire I haue desired to eate this Passeouer with you
before I suffer.<note> Or, I haue heartily desired.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For I say vnto you,
I will not any more eate thereof, vntill it be fulfilled in the
kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="17">And hee tooke the
cup, and gaue thanks, and said, Take this, and diuide it among your
selues.</ab>
<ab n="18">For I say vnto you,
I will not drinke of the fruit of the Uine, vntill the kingdome of
God shall come.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ And hee
tooke bread, and gaue thankes, and brake it, and gaue vnto them,
saying, This is my body which is giuen for you, this doe in
remembrance of me.<note> Matth.26. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Likewise also the
cup after supper, saying, This cup is the New Testament in my
blood, which is shed for you.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ But beholde,
the hand of him that betrayeth mee, is with mee on the
table.<note> Matth.26. 21.</note></ab>

<fw>Against ambition.</fw>
<ab n="22">And truly the Sonne
of man goeth as it was determined, but woe vnto that man by whom he
is betraied.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they began to
enquire among themselues, which of them it was that should doe this
thing.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And there
was also a strife among them, which of them should bee accompted
the greatest.</ab>
<ab n="25">And hee saide vnto
them, The Kings of the Gentiles exercise lordship ouer them, &amp;
they that exercise authoritie vpon them, are called
benefactors.<note> Matth.20. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But ye shall not be
so; but he that is greatest among you, let him be as the yonger,
and he that is chiefe, as he that doeth serue.</ab>
<ab n="27">For whether is
greater, hee that sitteth at meat, or hee that serueth? Is not he
that sitteth at meat? But I am among you as he that
serueth.</ab>
<ab n="28">Ye are they which
haue continued with me in my temptations.</ab>
<ab n="29">And I appoint vnto
you a kingdome, as my Father hath appointed vnto me,</ab>
<ab n="30">That yee may eate
and drinke at my table in my kingdome, and sit on thrones iudging
the twelue Tribes of Israel.<note> Matth.19. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And the Lord
said, Simon, Simon, beholde, Satan hath desired to haue you, that
he may sift you as wheat:<note> 1.Pet.5.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">But I haue prayed
for thee, that thy faith faile not; and when thou art conuerted,
strengthen thy brethren.</ab>
<ab n="33">And hee said vnto
him, Lord, I am ready to goe with thee both into prison, and to
death.</ab>
<ab n="34">And hee said, I
tell thee Peter, the cocke shall not crow this day, before that
thou shalt thrise denie that thou knowest me.<note> Matth.26. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And he said vnto
them, When I sent you without purse, and scrip, and shooes, lacked
ye any thing? And they said, Nothing.<note> Matth.10. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Then saide hee vnto
them, But now he that hath a purse, let him take it, and likewise
his scrip: and hee that hath no sword, let him sel his garment, and
buy one.</ab>
<ab n="37">For I say vnto you,
that this that is written, must yet be accomplished in me, And he
was reckoned among the transgressors: For the things concerning me
haue an end.<note> Esay.53. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And they said,
Lord, behold, here are two swords. And hee saide vnto them, It is
ynough.</ab>

<fw>Christ is betrayed.</fw>
<ab n="39">¶ And he came
out, and went, as hee was wont, to the mount of Oliues, and his
disciples also followed him.<note> Matth.26. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">And when he was at
the place, he said vnto them, Pray, that yee enter not into
temptation.<note> Mat.26. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And he was
withdrawen from them about a stones cast, and kneeled downe, and
prayed,</ab>
<ab n="42">Saying, Father, if
thou be willing, remooue this cup from me: neuerthelesse, not my
will, but thine be done.</ab>
<ab n="43">And there appeared
an Angel vnto him from heauen, strengthening him.</ab>
<ab n="44">And being in an
agonie, he prayed more earnestly, and his sweat was as it were
great drops of blood falling downe to the ground.</ab>
<ab n="45">And when he rose vp
from prayer, and was come to his disciples, hee found them sleeping
for sorrow,</ab>
<ab n="46">And said vnto them,
Why sleepe yee? Rise, and pray, lest yee enter into
temptation.</ab>
<ab n="47">¶ And while he
yet spake, behold, a multitude, and hee that was called Iudas, one
of the twelue, went before them, and drewe neere vnto Iesus, to
kisse him.<note> Mat.26. 47.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">But Iesus said vnto
him, Iudas, betrayest thou the sonne of man with a kisse?</ab>
<ab n="49">When they which
were about him, saw what would follow, they said vnto him, Lord,
shall wee smite with the sword?</ab>
<ab n="50">¶ And one of
them smote the seruant of the high Priest, and cut off his right
eare.</ab>
<ab n="51">And Iesus answered,
and said, Suffer ye thus farre. And he touched his eare, and healed
him.</ab>
<ab n="52">Then Iesus said
vnto the chiefe Priests, and captaines of the Temple, and the
Elders which were come to him, Be ye come out as against a thiefe,
with swords and staues?</ab>
<ab n="53">When I was daily
with you in the Temple, yee stretched foorth no hands against mee:
but this is your houre, and the power of darkenesse.</ab>
<ab n="54">¶ Then tooke
they him, and led him, and brought him into the high Priests house,
and Peter followed afarre off.<note> Mat.26. 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And when they had
kindled a fire in the middes of the hall, and were set downe
together, Peter sate downe among them.<note> Mat.26. 69.</note></ab>

<fw>Peters deniall.</fw>
<ab n="56">But a certaine
maide beheld him as he sate by the fire, and earnestly looked vpon
him, and said, This man was also with him.</ab>
<ab n="57">And he denied him,
saying, Woman, I know him not.</ab>
<ab n="58">And after a little
while another saw him, &amp; said, Thou art also of them. And Peter
said, Man, I am not.</ab>
<ab n="59">And about the space
of one houre after, another confidently affirmed, saying, Of a
trueth this fellow also was with him; for he is a Galilean.</ab>
<ab n="60">And Peter said,
Man, I know not what thou sayest. And immediately while he yet
spake, the cocke crew.</ab>
<ab n="61">And the Lord
turned, and looked vpon Peter; and Peter remembred the word of the
Lord, how he had said vnto him, Before the cocke crow, thou shalt
deny me thrise.</ab>
<ab n="62">And Peter went out,
and wept bitterly.</ab>
<ab n="63">¶ And the men
that helde Iesus, mocked him, and smote him.</ab>
<ab n="64">And when they had
blindfolded him, they stroke him on the face, and asked him,
saying, Prophesie, who is it that smote thee?</ab>
<ab n="65">And many other
things blasphemously spake they against him.</ab>
<ab n="66">¶ And assoone
as it was day, the Elders of the people, &amp; the chiefe Priests
and the Scribes came together, and led him into their Councell,
saying,<note> Mat.27.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="67">Art thou the
Christ? Tell vs. And hee said vnto them, If I tell you, you will
not beleeue.</ab>
<ab n="68">And if I also aske
you, you will not answere me, nor let me goe.</ab>
<ab n="69">Hereafter shal the
sonne of man sit on the right hand of the power of God.</ab>
<ab n="70">Then said they all,
Art thou then the Sonne of God? And hee said vnto them, Ye say that
I am.<note> Mark.14. 62.</note></ab>
<ab n="71">And they said, What
need we any further witnesse? For wee our selues haue heard of his
owne mouth.</ab>



</div>