<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-10-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Christ sendeth out at once,
seuenty disciples to worke miracles, and to preach: 17 Admonisheth
them to be humble, and wherin to reioyce: 21 Thanketh his father
for his grace: 23 Magnifieth the happy estate of his Church: 25
Teacheth the Lawyer, how to attaine eternall life, and to take
euery one for his neighbour, that needeth his mercy: 41
Reprehendeth Martha, and commendeth Mary her sister.</head>


<fw>The haruest great.</fw>
<ab n="1">After these
things, the Lord appointed other seuenty also, and sent them two
and two before his face, into euery citie and place, whither hee
himselfe would come.<note> Mat. 10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Therefore said
hee vnto them, The haruest truly is great, but the labourers are
few; pray ye therefore the Lord of the haruest, that he would send
foorth labourers into his haruest.<note> Mat.9.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Go your wayes:
Behold, I send you forth as lambes among wolues.<note> Mat.10. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Cary neither
purse nor scrip, nor shoes, and salute no man by the way.</ab>
<ab n="5">And into
whatsoeuer house yee enter, first say, Peace bee to this
house.<note> Mat. 10. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And if the
sonne of peace be there, your peace shall rest vpon it: if not, it
shall turne to you againe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And in the
same house remaine, eating and drinking such things as they giue:
For the labourer is worthy of his hire. Goe not from house to
house.</ab>
<ab n="8">And into
whatsoeuer citie yee enter, and they receiue you, eate such things
as are set before you:</ab>
<ab n="9">And heale the
sicke that are therein, and say vnto them, The kingdome of God is
come nigh vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="10">But into whatsoeuer
citie yee enter, and they receiue you not, goe your waies out into
the streetes of the same, and say,</ab>
<ab n="11">Euen the very dust
of your citie which cleaueth on vs, we doe wipe off against you:
notwithstanding, be yee sure of this, that the kingdome of God is
come nigh vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="12">But I say vnto you,
That it shall be more tolerable in that day for Sodome, then for
that citie.</ab>
<ab n="13">Woe vnto thee
Chorazin, wo vnto thee Bethsaida: For if the mighty workes had
beene done in Tyre and Sidon, which haue beene done in you, they
had a great while agoe repented, sitting in sackcloth and
ashes.<note> Mat. 11. 21.</note></ab>

<fw>Satans fall.</fw>
<ab n="14">But it shall be
more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the iudgment, then for
you.</ab>
<ab n="15">And thou Capernaum,
which art exalted to heauen, shalt be thrust downe to hell.</ab>
<ab n="16">Hee that heareth
you, heareth me: and he that despiseth you, despiseth me: and he
that despiseth me, despiseth him that sent me.<note> Mat. 10. 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
seuenty returned againe with ioy, saying, Lord, euen the deuils are
subiect vnto vs through thy name.</ab>
<ab n="18">And he said vnto
them, I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="19">Behold, I giue vnto
you power to tread on serpents and scorpions, and ouer all the
power of the enemie: and nothing shall by any meanes hurt
you.</ab>
<ab n="20">Notwithstanding in
this reioyce not, that the spirits are subiect vnto you: but rather
reioyce, because your names are written in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ In that
houre Iesus reioyced in spirit, and said, I thanke thee, O father,
Lord of heauen and earth, that thou hast hid these things from the
wise and prudent, and hast reuealed them vnto babes: euen so
father, for so it seemed good in thy sight.</ab>
<ab n="22">All things are
deliuered to me of my father: and no man knoweth who the sonne is,
but the father: and who the father is, but the sonne, and he to
whom the sonne will reueale him.<note> Many ancient copies adde these words, And turning to his Disciples he said.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And he
turned him vnto his disciples, and said priuately, Blessed are the
eyes which see the things that yee see.<note> Mat. 13. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For I tell you,
that many Prophets, and kings haue desired to see those things
which yee see, and haue not seene them: &amp; to heare those things
which yee heare, and haue not heard them.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And behold,
a certaine Lawyer stood vp, and tempted him, saying, Master, what
shall I doe to inherite eternall life? He said vnto
him,<note> Mat. 22. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">What is written in
the law? how readest thou?</ab>
<ab n="27">And he answering,
said, Thou shalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with
all thy soule, and with all thy strength, and with all thy minde,
and thy neighbour as thy selfe.</ab>

<fw>Who is a neighbour.</fw>
<ab n="28">And he said vnto
him, Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt
liue.</ab>
<ab n="29">But he willing to
iustifie himselfe, said vnto Iesus, And who is my
neighbour?</ab>
<ab n="30">And Iesus
answering, said, A certaine man went downe from Hierusalem to
Iericho, and fel among theeues, which stripped him of his raiment,
and wounded him, and departed, leauing him halfe dead.</ab>
<ab n="31">And by chaunce
there came downe a certaine Priest that way, and when he saw him,
he passed by on the other side.</ab>
<ab n="32">And likewise a
Leuite, when hee was at the place, came and looked on him, and
passed by on the other side.</ab>
<ab n="33">But a certaine
Samaritane as he iourneyed, came where he was; and when hee saw
him, hee had compassion on him,</ab>
<ab n="34">And went to him,
and bound vp his wounds, powring in oile and wine, and set him on
his owne beast, and brought him to an Inne, and tooke care of
him.</ab>
<ab n="35">And on the morrow
when he departed, hee tooke out two pence, and gaue them to the
hoste, and saide vnto him, Take care of him, and whatsoeuer thou
spendest more, when I come againe I will repay thee.<note> See Matt. 20. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Which now of these
three, thinkest thou, was neighbour vnto him that fell among the
theeues?</ab>
<ab n="37">And he said, He
that shewed mercie on him. Then said Iesus vnto him, Goe, and doe
thou likewise.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ Now it came
to passe, as they went, that he entred into a certaine village: and
a certaine woman named Martha, receiued him into her house.</ab>
<ab n="39">And shee had a
sister called Mary, which also sate at Iesus feet, and heard his
word:</ab>
<ab n="40">But Martha was
cumbred about much seruing, and came to him, and said, Lord, doest
thou not care that my sister hath left mee to serue alone? Bid her
therefore that she helpe me.</ab>
<ab n="41">And Iesus answered,
and saide vnto her, Martha, Martha, thou art carefull, and troubled
about many things:</ab>
<ab n="42">But one thing is
needefull, and Mary hath chosen that good part, which shall not bee
taken away from her.</ab>



</div>