<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-9-9b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Christ sendeth his Apostles to
worke miracles, and to preach. 7 Herod desired to see Christ.
Christ feedeth fiue thousand: 38 inquireth what opinion the world
had of him: foretelleth his passion: 23 proposeth to all, the
paterne of his patience. 28 The transfiguration. 37 Hee healeth the
lunaticke: 43 Againe forewarneth his disciples of his Passion: 46
commendeth humilitie: 51 biddeth them to shew mildnesse towards
all, without desire of reuenge. 57 Diuers would follow him, but
vpon conditions.</head>

<ab n="1">Then he called
his twelue disciples together, and gaue them power and authority
ouer all deuils, and to cure diseases.<note> Matth. 10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee sent
them to preach the Kingdome of God, and to heale the sicke.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he said
vnto them, Take nothing for your iourney, neither staues, nor
scrip, neither bread, neither money, neither haue two coates
apeece.</ab>

<fw>Fiue thousand fed.</fw>
<ab n="4">And whatsoeuer
house yee enter into, there abide, and thence depart.</ab>
<ab n="5">And whosoeuer
will not receiue you, when ye goe out of that city, shake off the
very dust from your feete, for a testimonie against them.</ab>
<ab n="6">And they
departed, and went through the townes, preaching the Gospel, and
healing euery where.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Now
Herode the Tetrarch heard of all that was done by him: and hee was
perplexed, because that it was said of some, that Iohn was risen
from the dead:<note> Mat. 14. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And of some,
that Elias had appeared: and of others, that one of the olde
Prophets was risen againe.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Herode
said, Iohn haue I beheaded: but who is this of whom I heare such
things? And hee desired to see him.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
Apostles when they were returned, tolde him all that they had done.
And hee tooke them, and went aside priuately into a desert place,
belonging to the citie called Bethsaida.<note> Mat. 14. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the people
when they knew it, followed him, and he receiued them, and spake
vnto them of the kingdome of God, and healed them that had need of
healing.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when the
day beganne to weare away, then came the twelue, and said vnto him,
Send the multitude away, that they may go into the townes and
countrey round about, and lodge, and get victuals: for we are here
in a desert place.<note> Mat. 14. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But he said
vnto them, Giue yee them to eate. And they said, Wee haue no more
but fiue loaues and two fishes, except we should goe and buy meate
for all this people.</ab>
<ab n="14">For they were
about fiue thousand men. And he said to his disciples, Make them
sit downe by fifties in a company.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they did
so, and made them all sit downe.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then he tooke
the fiue loaues and the two fishes, and looking vp to heauen, hee
blessed them, and brake, and gaue to the disciples to set before
the multitude.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they did
eate, and were all filled. And there was taken vp of fragments that
remained to them, twelue baskets.</ab>

<fw>Christ transfigured.</fw>
<ab n="18">¶ And it
came to passe, as he was alone praying, his disciples were with
him: and he asked them, saying, Whom say the people that I
am?<note> Mat. 16. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">They
answering, said, Iohn the Baptist: but some say, Elias: and others
say, that one of the old Prophets is risen againe.</ab>
<ab n="20">He said vnto
them, But whom say yee that I am? Peter answering, said, The Christ
of God.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he
straitly charged them, and commanded them to tell no man that
thing,</ab>
<ab n="22">Saying, The
Sonne of man must suffer many things, and be reiected of the
Elders, and chiefe Priests, and Scribes, and be slaine, and be
raised the third day.<note> Mat. 17. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And he
said to them all, If any man will come after me, let him denie
himselfe, and take vp his crosse daily, and follow me.<note> Mat.10. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For whosoeuer
will saue his life, shall lose it: but whosoeuer will lose his life
for my sake, the same shall saue it.</ab>
<ab n="25">For what is a
man aduantaged, if hee gaine the whole world, and lose himselfe, or
be cast away?<note> Mat. 16. 26. marke 8.36.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For whosoeuer
shall bee ashamed of me, and of my wordes, of him shall the Sonne
of man be ashamed, when he shall come in his owne glory, and in his
Fathers, and of the holy Angels.<note> Matt.10. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">But I tell you
of a trueth, there be some standing here, which shall not taste of
death, till they see the kingdome of God.<note> Matt. 16. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And it
came to passe, about an eight dayes after these sayings, hee tooke
Peter, and Iohn, and Iames, and went vp into a mountaine to
pray:<note> Mat. 17. 1. , Or, things.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And as hee
prayed, the fashion of his countenance was altered, and his raiment
was white and glistering.</ab>
<ab n="30">And behold,
there talked with him two men, which were Moses and Elias,</ab>
<ab n="31">Who appeared
in glory, and spake of his decease, which he should accomplish at
Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="32">But Peter, and
they that were with him, were heauie with sleepe: and when they
were awake, they saw his glory, and the two men that stood with
him.</ab>

<fw>The lunatike healed.</fw>
<ab n="33">And it came to
passe, as they departed from him, Peter said vnto Iesus, Master, it
is good for vs to be here, and let vs make three tabernacles, one
for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias: not knowing what he
said.</ab>
<ab n="34">While he thus
spake, there came a cloud, and ouershadowed them, &amp; they
feared, as they entred into the cloude.</ab>
<ab n="35">And there came
a voice out of the cloud, saying, This is my beloued Son, heare
him.</ab>
<ab n="36">And when the
voyce was past, Iesus was found alone, and they kept it close,
&amp; told no man in those dayes any of those things which they had
seene.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ And it
came to passe, that on the next day, when they were come downe from
the hill, much people met him.<note> Mat.17.14</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And behold, a
man of the companie cried out, saying, Master, I beseech thee looke
vpon my sonne, for he is mine onely child.</ab>
<ab n="39">And loe, a
spirit taketh him, and hee suddenly crieth out, and it teareth him
that he fometh againe, and bruising him, hardly departeth from
him.</ab>
<ab n="40">And I besought
thy disciples to cast him out, and they could not.</ab>
<ab n="41">And Iesus
answering, said, O faithlesse, and peruerse generation, how long
shal I be with you, and suffer you? bring thy sonne hither.</ab>
<ab n="42">And as he was
yet a comming, the deuill threw him downe, and tare him: and Iesus
rebuked the vncleane spirit, and healed the child, and deliuered
him againe to his father.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ And
they were al amazed at the mightie power of God: But while they
wondred euery one at all things which Iesus did, he said vnto his
disciples,</ab>
<ab n="44">Let these
sayings sinke downe into your eares: for the Sonne of man shall bee
deliuered into the handes of men.<note> Matth. 17. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">But they
vnderstood not this saying, and it was hid from them, that they
perceiued it not: and they feared to aske him of that
saying.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ Then
there arose a reasoning among them, which of them should be
greatest.<note> Mat. 18. 1 mark.9.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And Iesus
perceiuing þ<note/> thought of their heart, tooke a
child, and set him by him,</ab>

<fw>The least, great.</fw>
<ab n="48">And said vnto
them, Whosoeuer shall receiue this child in my Name, receiueth me:
and whosoeuer shal receiue me, receiueth him that sent me: For hee
that is least among you all, the same shalbe great.</ab>
<ab n="49">¶ And
Iohn answered, and said, Master, we saw one casting out deuils in
thy Name, and we forbade him, because he followeth not with
vs.<note> Mar.9.38</note></ab>
<ab n="50">And Iesus said
vnto him, Forbid him not: for he that is not against vs, is for
vs.</ab>
<ab n="51">¶ And it
came to passe, when the time was come that he should bee receiued
vp, he stedfastly set his face to goe to Hierusalem,</ab>
<ab n="52">And sent
messengers before his face, and they went and entred into a village
of the Samaritanes to make ready for him.</ab>
<ab n="53">And they did
not receiue him, because his face was as though he would goe to
Hierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="54">And when his
disciples, Iames and Iohn sawe this, they said, Lord, wilt thou
that wee command fire to come downe from heauen, and consume them,
euen as Elias did?<note> 2.Kings 1. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">But he turned,
and rebuked them, and said, Ye know not what maner spirit ye are
of.</ab>
<ab n="56">For the Sonne
of man is not come to destroy mens liues, but to saue them. And
they went to another village.</ab>
<ab n="57">¶ And it
came to passe that as they went in the way, a certaine man said
vnto him, Lord, I wil follow thee whithersoeuer thou
goest.<note> Mat.8.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">And Iesus said
vnto him, Foxes haue holes, and birds of the aire haue nests, but
the Sonne of man hath not where to lay his head.</ab>
<ab n="59">And he said
vnto another, Follow me: But he said, Lord, suffer mee first to goe
and bury my father.<note> Mat.8.21</note></ab>
<ab n="60">Iesus said
vnto him, Let the dead bury their dead: but go thou and preach the
kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="61">And another
also said, Lord, I will follow thee: but let me first goe bid them
farewel, which are at home at my house.</ab>
<ab n="62">And Iesus said
vnto him, No man hauing put his hand to the plough, and looking
backe, is fit for the kingdome of God.</ab>



</div>