<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>3 Of the importunate widow. 9 Of the
Pharisee and the Publicane. 15 Children brought to Christ. 18 A
ruler that would folow Christ but is hindred by his riches. 28 The
reward of them, that leaue all for his sake. 31 Hee foresheweth his
death, 35 and restoreth a blinde man to his sight.</head>

<ab n="1">And he spake a
parable vnto them, to this ende, that men ought alwayes to pray,
and not to faint,<note> 1.Thes.5. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Saying, There
was in a city a Iudge, which feared not God neither regarded
man.</ab>
<ab n="3">And there was
a widowe in that citie, and she came vnto him, saying, Auenge me of
mine aduersarie:</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee would
not for a while. But afterward he said within himselfe, Though I
feare not God, nor regard man,</ab>
<ab n="5">Yet because
this widow troubleth me, I will auenge her, lest by her continuall
comming, she wearie me.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Lord
said, Heare what the vniust iudge saith.</ab>
<ab n="7">And shall not
God auenge his owne elect, which crie day and night vnto him, thogh
he beare long with them?</ab>

<fw>Of litle children.</fw>
<ab n="8">I tell you
that he wil auenge them speedily. Neuerthelesse, when the Son of
man commeth, shall hee find faith on the earth?</ab>
<ab n="9">And he spake
this parable vnto certaine which trusted in themselues that they
were righteous, &amp; despised other:<note> Or, as being righteous</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Two men went vp
into the Temple to pray, the one a Pharisee, and the other a
Publicane.</ab>
<ab n="11">The Pharisee stood
and prayed thus with himselfe, God, I thank thee, that I am not as
other men are, extortioners, vniust, adulterers, or euen as this
Publicane.</ab>
<ab n="12">I fast twise in the
weeke, I giue tithes of all that I possesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Publicane
standing afarre off, would not lift vp so much as his eyes vnto
heauen: but smote vpon his breast, saying, God me mercifull to mee
a sinner.</ab>
<ab n="14">I tell you, this
man went downe to his house iustified rather then the other: For
euery one that exalteth himselfe, shall be abased: and hee that
humbleth himselfe, shall be exalted.<note> Matth.23 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And they brought
vnto him also infants, that he would touch them: but when his
disciples saw it, they rebuked them.</ab>
<ab n="16">But Iesus called
them vnto him, and said, Suffer litle children to come vnto me, and
forbid them not: for of such is the kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="17">Uerely I say vnto
you, whosoeuer shall not receiue the kingdome of God as a litle
child, shal in no wise enter therein.</ab>
<ab n="18">And a certaine
ruler asked him, saying, Good master, what shall I doe to inherit
eternall life?</ab>
<ab n="19">And Iesus said vnto
him, Why callest thou mee good? None is good saue one, that is
God.<note> Matth.19. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Thou knowest the
commaundements, Doe not commit adulterie, Doe not kill, Doe not
steale, Doe not beare false witnesse, Honour thy father and thy
mother.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he said, All
these haue I kept from my youth vp.</ab>
<ab n="22">Now when Iesus
heard these things, hee said vnto him, Yet lackest thou one thing:
Sell all that thou hast, and distribute vnto the poore, and thou
shalt haue treasure in heauen, and come, follow me.</ab>
<ab n="23">And when he heard
this, he was very sorowfull, for he was very rich.</ab>

<fw>The blind receiueth sight.
Zacheus.</fw>
<ab n="24">And when Iesus saw
that hee was very sorrowfull, he said, How hardly shal they that
haue riches, enter into the kingdome of God?</ab>
<ab n="25">For it is easier
for a camel to goe thorow a needles eye, then for a rich man to
enter into the kingdom of God.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they that heard
it, said, Who then can be saued?</ab>
<ab n="27">And he said, The
things which are vnpossible with men, are possible with
God.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then Peter said,
Loe, we haue left all, and followed thee.<note> Mat.19. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And he said vnto
them, Uerily, I say vnto you, there is no man that hath left house,
or parents, or brethren, or wife, or children, for the kingdome of
Gods sake,</ab>
<ab n="30">Who shall not
receiue manifold more in this present time, and in the world to
come life euerlasting.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Then hee
tooke vnto him the twelue, and said vnto them, Behold, we goe vp to
Hierusalem, and al things that are written by the Prophets
concerning the sonne of man, shall be accomplished.<note> Mat.20. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For he shall be
deliuered vnto the Gentiles, and shall be mocked, and spitefully
intreated, and spitted on:</ab>
<ab n="33">And they shall
scourge him, and put him to death, and the third day he shall rise
againe.</ab>
<ab n="34">And they vnderstood
none of these things: and this saying was hid from them, neither
knew they the things which were spoken.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And it came
to passe, that as he was come nigh vnto Iericho, a certaine blinde
man sate by the way side, begging,<note> Mat.20. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And hearing the
multitude passe by, he asked what it meant.</ab>
<ab n="37">And they tolde him
that Iesus of Nazareth passeth by.</ab>
<ab n="38">And he cried,
saying, Iesus thou sonne of Dauid, haue mercie on me.</ab>
<ab n="39">And they which went
before, rebuked him, that hee should holde his peace: but hee cried
so much the more, Thou Sonne of Dauid, haue mercie on mee.</ab>
<ab n="40">And Iesus stood and
commanded him to be brought vnto him: and when he was come neere,
he asked him,</ab>
<ab n="41">Saying, What wilt
thou that I shall doe vnto thee? And he said, Lord, that I may
receiue my sight.</ab>

<fw>The blind receiueth sight.
Zacheus.</fw>
<ab n="42">And Iesus said vnto
him, Receiue thy sight, thy faith hath saued thee.</ab>
<ab n="43">And immediately he
receiued his sight, and followed him, glorifying God: and all the
people when they saw it, gaue praise vnto God.</ab>



</div>