<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Christ teacheth to pray, and that
instantly: 11 assuring that God so will giue vs good things. 14 He
casting out a dumbe deuil, rebuketh the blasphemous Pharisees: 28
and sheweth who are blessed: 29 preacheth to the people, 37 and
reprehendeth the outward shew of holinesse in the Pharisees,
Scribes and Lawyers.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, that as he was praying in a certaine place, when hee ceased,
one of his disciples said vnto him, Lord, teach vs to pray, as Iohn
also taught his disciples.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee said
vnto them, When ye pray, say, Our Father which art in heauen,
Halowed be thy Name, Thy kingdome come, Thy will be done as in
heauen, so in earth.<note> Matth 6. 9</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Giue vs day by
day our dayly bread.<note> Or, for the day.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And forgiue vs
our sinnes: for we also forgiue euery one that is indebted to vs.
And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he said
vnto them, Which of you shall haue a friend, and shall goe vnto him
at midnight, and say vnto him, Friend, lend me three
loaues.</ab>
<ab n="6">For a friend
of mine in his iourney is come to me, and I haue nothing to set
before him,<note> Or, out of his way.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And he from
within shal answere and say, Trouble mee not, the doore is now
shut, and my children are with me in bed: I cannot rise and giue
thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">I say vnto
you, Though he will not rise, and giue him, because he is his
friend: yet because of his importunitie, hee will rise and giue him
as many as he needeth.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I say vnto
you, Aske, and it shalbe giuen you: seeke, and ye shal find:
knocke, and it shalbe opened vnto you.<note> Matth.7. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For euery one that
asketh, receiueth: and he that seeketh, findeth: and to him that
knocketh, it shalbe opened.</ab>
<ab n="11">If a sonne shall
aske bread of any of you that is a father, will hee giue him a
stone? Or if he aske a fish, will he for a fish giue him a
serpent?<note> Matth.7. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Or if he shall aske
an egge, will he offer him a scorpion?</ab>

<fw>Who are blessed.</fw>
<ab n="13">If ye then, being
euill, know how to giue good gifts vnto your children: how much
more shall your heauenly Father giue the holy Spirit to them that
aske him?</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And he was
casting out a deuil, and it was dumbe. And it came to passe, when
the deuill was gone out, the dumbe spake: and the people
wondred.</ab>
<ab n="15">But some of them
said, Hee casteth out deuils through Beelzebub the chiefe of the
deuils.<note> Mat.9. 34. and 12. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And other tempting
him, sought of him a signe from heauen.</ab>
<ab n="17">But he knowing
their thoughts, said vnto them, Euery kingdome diuided against it
selfe, is brought to desolation: and a house diuided against a
house, falleth.</ab>
<ab n="18">If Satan also be
diuided against himselfe, how shall his kingdom stand? Because yee
say that I cast out deuils through Beelzebub.</ab>
<ab n="19">And if I by
Beelzebub cast out deuils, by whom doe your sonnes cast them out?
therefore shall they be your iudges.</ab>
<ab n="20">But if I with the
finger of God cast out deuils, no doubt the kingdome of God is come
vpon you.</ab>
<ab n="21">When a strong man
armed keepeth his palace, his goods are in peace:</ab>
<ab n="22">But when a stronger
then he shal come vpon him, and ouercome him, hee taketh from him
all his armour wherein he trusted, and diuideth his
spoiles.</ab>
<ab n="23">He that is not with
me, is against me: and hee that gathereth not with me,
scattereth.</ab>
<ab n="24">When the vncleane
spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through drie places,
seeking rest: and finding none, he sayth, I will returne vnto my
house whence I came out.<note> Mat. 12. 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And when hee
commeth, hee findeth it swept and garnished.</ab>
<ab n="26">Then goeth he, and
taketh to him seuen other spirits more wicked then himselfe, and
they enter in, and dwell there, and the last state of that man is
worse then the first.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And it came
to passe as hee spake these things, a certaine woman of the company
lift vp her voice, and said vnto him, Blessed is the wombe that
bare thee, and the pappes which thou hast sucked.</ab>
<ab n="28">But hee said, Yea,
rather blessed are they that heare the word of God, and keepe
it.</ab>

<fw>Ionas a signe.</fw>
<ab n="29">¶ And when the
people were gathered thicke together, hee began to say, This is an
euill generation, they seeke a signe, and there shall no signe be
giuen it, but the signe of Ionas the Prophet:<note> Matt. 12. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">For as Ionas was a
signe vnto the Nineuites, so shall also the Sonne of man be to this
generation.</ab>
<ab n="31">The Queene of the
South shall rise vp in the iudgement with the men of this
generation, &amp; condemne them: for shee came from the vtmost
parts of the earth, to heare the wisedome of Solomon: and behold, a
greater then Solomon is here.</ab>
<ab n="32">The men of Nineue
shall rise vp in the iudgement with this generation, and shall
condemne it: for they repented at the preaching of Ionas, and
behold, a greater then Ionas is here.</ab>
<ab n="33">No man when he hath
lighted a candle, putteth it in a secret place, neither vnder a
bushell, but on a candlesticke, that they which come in may see the
light.<note> Mat.5.15. , See Matt. 5. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">The light of the
body is the eye: therefore when thine eye is single, thy whole body
also is full of light: but when thine eye is euill, thy body also
is full of darkenesse.<note> Mat.6. 22</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Take heede
therefore, that the light which is in thee, be not
darknesse.</ab>
<ab n="36">If thy whole body
therefore be full of light, hauing no part darke, the whole shalbe
full of light, as when the bright shining of a candle doeth giue
thee light.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ And as he
spake, a certaine Pharise besought him to dine with him: and he
went in, and sate downe to meate.</ab>
<ab n="38">And when the
Pharise saw it, he marueiled that he had not first washed before
dinner.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the Lord said
vnto him, Now doe ye Pharises make cleane the outside of the cup
and the platter: but your inward part is full of rauening and
wickednesse.<note> Mat. 23. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">Yee fooles, did not
he that made that which is without, make that which is within
also?</ab>
<ab n="41">But rather giue
almes of such things as you haue: and behold, all things are cleane
vnto you.<note> Or, as you are able.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">But woe vnto you
Pharises: for ye tythe Mint and Rue, and all maner of herbes, and
passe ouer iudgement, and the loue of God: these ought yee to haue
done, and not to leaue the other vndone.</ab>

<fw>Key of knowledge.</fw>
<ab n="43">Woe vnto you
Pharisees: for ye loue the vppermost seats in the Synagogues, and
greetings in the markets.<note> Mat.23.6</note></ab>
<ab n="44">Woe vnto you
Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites: for ye are as graues which
appeare not, and the men that walk ouer them, are not aware of
them.</ab>
<ab n="45">¶ Then
answered one of the Lawyers, and said vnto him, Master, thus
saying, thou reprochest vs also.</ab>
<ab n="46">And he said, Woe
vnto you also ye lawyers: for ye lade men with burdens grieuous to
be borne, and ye your selues touch not the burdens with one of your
fingers.<note> Mat. 23. 4</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Woe vnto you: for
ye build the sepulchres of the Prophets, and your fathers killed
them.<note> Matth. 23 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Truely ye beare
witnesse that ye allowe the deeds of your fathers: for they indeed
killed them, and yee build their sepulchres.</ab>
<ab n="49">Therefore also said
the wisedome of God, I wil send them Prophets and Apostles, and
some of them they shal slay and persecute:</ab>
<ab n="50">That the blood of
all the Prophets, which was shed from the foundation of the world,
may be required of this generation,</ab>
<ab n="51">From the blood of
Abel vnto the blood of Zacharias, which perished betweene the Altar
and the Temple: Uerely I say vnto you, it shall be required of this
generation.<note> Gen. 4. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Woe vnto you
Lawyers: for ye haue taken away the key of knowledge: ye entred not
in your selues, and them that were entring in, ye
hindred.<note> Matth. 23 13. , Or forbade</note></ab>
<ab n="53">And as he said
these things vnto them, the Scribes and the Pharisees began to vrge
him vehemently, and to prouoke him to speake of many
things:</ab>
<ab n="54">Laying wait for
him, and seeking to catch something out of his mouth, that they
might accuse him.</ab>



</div>