<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Christ reproueth the Pharises
blindnesse about the obseruation of the Sabbath, by Scripture,
reason, and miracle: 13 Chooseth twelue Apostles: 17 Healeth the
diseased: 20 Preacheth to his disciples before the people of
blessings, and curses: 27 How we must loue our enemies: 46 And
ioyne the obedience of good workes, to the hearing of the word:
least in the euill day of temptation, we fall like an house built
vpon the face of the earth, without any foundation.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe on the second Sabbath after the first, that he went thorow
the corne fields: and his disciples plucked the eares of corne, and
did eate, rubbing them in their hands.<note> Marke 12 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And certaine of
the Pharisees said vnto them, Why doe yee that which is not lawfull
to doe on the Sabbath dayes?</ab>
<ab n="3">And Iesus
answering them, said, Haue yee not read so much as this what Dauid
did, when himselfe was an hungred, and they which were with
him:</ab>
<ab n="4">How he went
into the house of God, and did take and eate the Shew bread, and
gaue also to them that were with him, which it is not lawful to
eate but for the Priests alone?</ab>
<ab n="5">And he said
vnto them, That the sonne of man is Lord also of the
Sabbath.</ab>
<ab n="6">And it came to
passe also on another Sabbath, that he entred into the Synagogue,
and taught: and there was a man whose right hand was
withered.<note> Mat. 12. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the Scribes
and Pharisees watched him, whether he would heale on the Sabbath
day: that they might find an accusation against him.</ab>
<ab n="8">But he knew
their thoughts, and said to the man which had the withered hand,
Rise vp, and stand foorth in the mids. And he arose, and stood
foorth.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then said Iesus
vnto them, I will aske you one thing, Is it lawfull on the Sabbath
dayes to doe good, or to doe euill? to saue life, or to destroy
it?</ab>
<ab n="10">And looking
round about vpon them all, he said vnto the man, Stretch foorth thy
hand. And he did so: and his hand was restored whole as the
other.</ab>

<fw>Who are blessed.</fw>
<ab n="11">And they were
filled with madnesse, and communed one with another what they might
doe to Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="12">And it came to
passe in those dayes, that hee went out into a mountaine to pray,
and continued all night in prayer to God.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And
when it was day, he called vnto him his disciples: and of them he
chose twelue; whom also hee named Apostles:<note> Mat.10. 1</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Simon, (whom
he also named Peter,) and Andrew his brother: Iames and Iohn,
Philip and Bartholomew,</ab>
<ab n="15">Matthew and
Thomas, Iames the sonne of Alpheus, and Simon, called
Zelotes,</ab>
<ab n="16">And Iudas the
brother of Iames, and Iudas Iscariot, which also was the
traitour.<note> Iude. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And hee
came downe with them, and stood in the plaine, and the company of
his disciples, and a great multitude of people, out of all Iudea
and Hierusalem, and from the Sea coast of Tyre and Sidon, which
came to heare him, and to be healed of their diseases,</ab>
<ab n="18">And they that
were vexed with vncleane spirits: and they were healed.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the whole
multitude sought to touch him: for there went vertue out of him,
and healed them all.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And hee
lifted vp his eyes on his disciples, and said, Blessed be yee
poore: for yours is the kingdome of God.<note> Mat.5.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Blessed are
yee that hunger now: for yee shall be filled. Blessed are yee that
weepe now, for yee shall laugh.</ab>
<ab n="22">Blessed are
yee when men shall hate you, and when they shall separate you from
their company, and shal reproach you, and cast out your name as
euill, for the Sonne of mans sake.</ab>
<ab n="23">Reioice yee in
that day, and leape for ioy: for behold, your reward is great in
heauen for in the like maner did their fathers vnto the
Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="24">But woe vnto
you that are rich: for yee haue receiued your
consolation.<note> Amos.6.1</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Woe vnto you
that are full: for yee shall hunger. Woe vnto you that laugh now:
for yee shall mourne and weepe.<note> Esai.65. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Woe vnto you
when all men shall speake well of you: for so did their fathers to
the false Prophets.</ab>

<fw>Rash iudgement.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ But I
say vnto you which heare, Loue your enemies, doe good to them which
hate you,<note> Matth 5. 44.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Blesse them
that curse you, &amp; pray for them which despitefully vse
you.</ab>
<ab n="29">And vnto him
that smiteth thee on the one cheeke, offer also the other: and him
that taketh away thy cloake, forbid not to take thy coat
also.<note> Matth. 5. 39. , 1.Cor.6. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Giue to euery
man that asketh of thee, and of him that taketh away thy goods,
aske them not againe.</ab>
<ab n="31">And as yee
would that men should doe to you, doe yee also to them
likewise.<note> Matth. 7. 12. tob.4. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For if yee
loue them which loue you, what thanke haue ye? for sinners also
loue those that loue them.<note> Matth. 5 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And if ye doe
good to them which doe good to you, What thanke haue ye? for
sinners also doe euen the same.</ab>
<ab n="34">And if ye lend
to them of whom ye hope to receiue, What thanke haue ye? for
sinners also lend to sinners, to receiue as much
againe.<note> Matth. 5. 42.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">But loue yee
your enemies, and doe good, and lend, hoping for nothing againe:
and your reward shall bee great, and ye shalbe the children of the
Highest: for hee is kinde vnto the vnthankfull, and to the
euill.</ab>
<ab n="36">Be ye
therefore mercifull, as your Father also is mercifull.</ab>
<ab n="37">Iudge not, and
ye shall not bee iudged: condemne not, and ye shall not be
condemned: forgiue, and ye shall be forgiuen.<note> Matt. 7. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Giue, and it
shall bee giuen vnto you, good measure, preassed downe, and shaken
together, and running ouer, shall men giue into your bosome: for
with the same measure that ye mete withall, it shall bee measured
to you againe.</ab>
<ab n="39">And hee spake
a parable vnto them, Can the blinde leade the blinde? Shall they
not both fall into the ditch?<note> Matth. 15. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">The disciple
is not aboue his master: but euery one that is perfect shalbe as
his master.<note> Matth. 10. 24. , Or, shalbe perfected as his master.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And why
beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brothers eye, but perceiuest
not the beame that is in thine owne eye?<note> Matth. 7. 3.</note></ab>

<fw>A good tree.</fw>
<ab n="42">Either how
canst thou say to thy brother, Brother, let mee pull out the mote
that is in thine eye: when thou thy selfe beholdest not the beame
that is in thine owne eye? Thou hypocrite, cast out first the beame
out of thine owne eye, and then shalt thou see clearly to pul out
the mote that is in thy brothers eye.</ab>
<ab n="43">For a good
tree bringeth not foorth corrupt fruit: neither doeth a corrupt
tree bring foorth good fruit.<note> Matth.7. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">For euery tree
is knowen by his owne fruit: for of thornes men doe not gather
figs, nor of a bramble bush gather they grapes.</ab>
<ab n="45">A good man out
of the good treasure of his heart, bringeth foorth that which is
good: and an euill man out of the euill treasure of his heart,
bringeth foorth that which is euill: For of the abundance of the
heart, his mouth speaketh.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ And why
call ye mee Lord, Lord, and doe not the things which I
say?<note> Matth.7. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Whosoeuer
commeth to me, and heareth my sayings, and doeth them, I will shew
you to whom he is like.</ab>
<ab n="48">He is like a
man which built an house, and digged deepe, and layd the foundation
on a rocke. And when the flood arose, the streame beat vehemently
vpon that house, and could not shake it: for it was founded vpon a
rocke.</ab>
<ab n="49">But he that
heareth, and doeth not, is like a man that without a foundation
built an house vpon the earth: against which the streame did beate
vehemently, and immediatly it fell, and the ruine of that house was
great.</ab>



</div>