<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CLuke_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-23-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Luke-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1 Iesus is accused before Pilate,
and sent to Herode. 8 Herode mocketh him. 12 Herode and Pilate are
made friends. 13 Barabbas is desired of the people, and is loosed
by Pilate, and Iesus is giuen to be crucified. 27 He telleth the
women that lament him, the destruction of Hierusalem: 34 Prayeth
for his enemies. 39 Two euill doers are crucified with him. 46 His
death. 50 His buriall.</head>


<fw>Barabbas released.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the whole
multitude of them arose, and led him vnto Pilate.</ab>
<ab n="2">And they began
to accuse him, saying, We found this fellow peruerting the nation,
and forbidding to giue tribute to Cesar, saying, that he himselfe
is Christ a king.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Pilate
asked him, saying, Art thou the king of the Iewes? And he answered
him, &amp; said, Thou sayest it.<note> Matth. 27 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then saide
Pilate to the chiefe Priests, and to the people, I finde no fault
in this man.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they were
the more fierce, saying, He stirreth vp the people, teaching
thorowout all Iurie, beginning from Galilee to this place.</ab>
<ab n="6">When Pilate
heard of Galilee, he asked whether the man were a Galilean.</ab>
<ab n="7">And assoone as
he knew that hee belonged vnto Herods iurisdiction, hee sent him to
Herode, who himselfe also was at Hierusalem at that time.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
when Herode saw Iesus, he was exceeding glad, for hee was desirous
to see him of a long season, because he had heard many things of
him, and hee hoped to haue seene some miracle done by him.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then he
questioned with him in many words, but he answered him
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the chiefe
Priests and Scribes stood, and vehemently accused him.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Herod with his
men of warre set him at naught, and mocked him, and arayed him in a
gorgeous robe, and sent him againe to Pilate.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the same
day Pilate and Herod were made friends together; for before, they
were at enmitie betweene themselues.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And Pilate,
when hee had called together the chiefe Priests, and the rulers,
and the people,<note> Matth.27 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Said vnto them, Ye
haue brought this man vnto me, as one that peruerteth the people,
and behold, I hauing examined him before you, haue found no fault
in this man, touching those things whereof ye accuse him.</ab>
<ab n="15">No, nor yet Herod:
for I sent you to him, and loe, nothing worthy of death is done
vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="16">I will therefore
chastise him, and release him.</ab>

<fw>Christ crucified.</fw>
<ab n="17">For of necessitie
hee must release one vnto them at the Feast.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they cried out
all at once, saying, Away with this man, and release vnto vs
Barabbas,</ab>
<ab n="19">Who for a certaine
sedition made in the citie, and for murder, was cast in
prison.</ab>
<ab n="20">Pilate therefore
willing to release Iesus, spake againe to them:</ab>
<ab n="21">But they cried,
saying, Crucifie him, crucifie him.</ab>
<ab n="22">And hee said vnto
them the third time, Why, what euill hath he done? I haue found no
cause of death in him, I will therefore chastise him, &amp; let him
goe.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they were
instant with loud voyces, requiring that he might be crucified: and
the voyces of them, and of the chiefe Priests preuailed.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Pilate gaue
sentence that it should be as they required.<note> Or, assented.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And he released
vnto them, him that for sedition and murder was cast into prison,
whom they had desired, but he deliuered Iesus to their
will.</ab>
<ab n="26">And as they led him
away, they laid hold vpon one Simon a Cyrenian, comming out of the
countrey, and on him they laid the crosse, that hee might beare it
after Iesus.<note> Matth.27. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And there
followed him a great company of people, and of women, which also
bewailed &amp; lamented him.</ab>
<ab n="28">But Iesus turning
vnto them, said, Daughters of Hierusalem, weepe not for me, but
weepe for your selues, and for your children.</ab>
<ab n="29">For beholde, the
dayes are comming, in the which they shall say, Blessed are the
barren, and the wombs that neuer bare, and the paps which neuer
gaue sucke.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then shall they
begin to say to the mountaines, Fall on vs, and to the hils, Couer
vs.<note> Isa.2.19. hos.10.8. reuel.6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For if they doe
these things in a green tree, what shalbe done in the
drie?<note> 1.Pet.4. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And there were also
two other malefactors led with him, to bee put to
death.<note> Matth.27 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And when they were
come to the place which is called Caluarie, there they crucified
him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand, and the other on
the left.<note> Or, the place of a skull.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Then said
Iesus, Father, forgiue them, for they know not what they doe: And
they parted his raiment, and cast lots.</ab>

<fw>Christs death, and
resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="35">And the people
stood beholding, &amp; the rulers also with them derided him,
saying, Hee saued others, let him saue himselfe, if he be Christ,
þe chosen of God.</ab>
<ab n="36">And the souldiers
also mocked him, comming to him, and offering him vineger,</ab>
<ab n="37">And saying, If thou
be the king of the Iewes, saue thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="38">And a
superscription also was written ouer him in letters of Greeke, and
Latin, &amp; Hebrew, THIS IS THE KING OF THE IEWES.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And one of
þe malefactors, which were hanged, railed on him,
saying, If thou be Christ, saue thy selfe and vs.</ab>
<ab n="40">But the other
answering, rebuked him, saying, Doest not thou feare God, seeing
thou art in the same condemnation?</ab>
<ab n="41">And we indeed
iustly; for we receiue the due reward of our deeds, but this man
hath done nothing amisse.</ab>
<ab n="42">And he said vnto
Iesus, Lord, remember me when thou commest into thy
kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="43">And Iesus said vnto
him, Uerily, I say vnto thee, to day shalt thou be with me in
Paradise.</ab>
<ab n="44">And it was about
the sixt houre, and there was a darkenesse ouer all the earth,
vntill the ninth houre.<note> Or, land.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And the Sunne was
darkened, and the vaile of the temple was rent in the mids.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ And when
Iesus had cried with a loud voice, he said, Father, into thy hands
I commend my spirit: And hauing said thus, he gaue vp the
ghost.<note> Psal.31.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Now when the
Centurion saw what was done, he glorified God, saying, Certainly
this was a righteous man.</ab>
<ab n="48">And all the people
that came together to that sight, beholding the things which were
done, smote their breasts, and returned.</ab>
<ab n="49">And all his
acquaintance, and the women that followed him from Galilee, stood a
farre off, beholding these things.</ab>
<ab n="50">¶ And behold,
there was a man named Ioseph, a counseller, and hee was a good man,
and a iust.<note> Mat.27. 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">(The same had not
consented to the counsell and deede of them) he was of Arimathea, a
city of the Iewes (who also himselfe waited for the kingdome of
God.)</ab>

<fw>Christs death, and
resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="52">This man went vnto
Pilate, and begged the body of Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="53">And he tooke it
downe, and wrapped it in linnen, and layd it in a Sepulchre that
was hewen in stone, wherein neuer man before was layd.</ab>
<ab n="54">And that day was
the Preparation, and the Sabbath drew on.</ab>
<ab n="55">And the women also
which came with him from Galilee, followed after, and beheld the
Sepulchre, and how his body was layd.</ab>
<ab n="56">And they returned,
and prepared spices and ointments, and rested the Sabbath day,
according to the commandement.</ab>



</div>