<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMalachi_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Malachi-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Malachi-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 He sharpely reprooueth the Priests
for neglecting their couenant. 11 and the people for idolatrie, 14
for adulterie, 17 and for infidelitie.</head>


<fw>The people, and Priests,
reproued.</fw>
<ab n="1">And now, O yee
Priests, this commaundement is for you.</ab>
<ab n="2">If ye will not
heare, and if yee will not lay it to heart, to giue glory vnto my
name, saith the Lord of hostes; I will euen send a curse vpon you,
and will curse your blessings: yea, I haue cursed them already,
because yee doe not lay it to heart.<note> Leuit.26. 14. deut.28 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Behold, I will
corrupt your seed, and spread doung vpon your faces, euen the doung
of your solemne feasts, and one shall take you away with
it.<note> Or, reproue. , Heb. scatter. , Or, it shall take you away to it.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And yee shall know
that I haue sent this commaundement vnto you, that my couenant
might be with Leui, saith the Lord of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="5">My couenant was
with him of life and peace, and I gaue them to him, for the feare,
wherewith he feared mee, and was afraid before my name.</ab>
<ab n="6">The law of truth
was in his mouth, and iniquitie was not found in his lips: he
walked with me in peace and equitie, and did turne many away from
iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the priests
lips should keepe knowledge, and they should seeke the law at his
mouth: for he is the messenger of the Lord of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="8">But yee are
departed out of the way: ye haue caused many to stumble at the law:
ye haue corrupted the couenant of Leui, saith the Lord of
hostes.<note> Or, fall in the law.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore haue I
also made you contemptible and base before al the people, according
as yee haue not kept my wayes, but haue bin partiall in
þ<note/> law.<note> Or, lifted vp the face against. Heb. accepted faces.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Haue we not all
one father? hath not one God created vs? Why doe we deale
treacherously euery man against his brother, by prophaning the
couenant of our fathers?<note> Eph.4.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Iudah hath
dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and
in Ierusalem: for Iudah hath prophaned the holinesse of the Lord
which he loued, and hath maried the daughter of a strange
God.<note> Or, ought to loue.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The Lord will cut
off the man that doth this: the Master and the scholler out of the
tabernacles of Iacob, and him that offereth an offring vnto the
Lord of hostes.<note> Or, him that waketh and him that answereth.</note></ab>

<fw>God witnesseth against sinners.</fw>
<ab n="13">And this haue yee
done againe, couering the Altar of the Lord with teares, with
weeping and with crying out, in so much that hee regardeth not the
offering any more, or receiueth it with good will at your
hand.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Yet ye
say, Wherefore? Because the Lord hath bene witnes betweene thee and
the wife of thy youth, against whome thou hast dealt treacherously:
yet is she thy companion, and the wife of thy couenant.</ab>
<ab n="15">And did not he
make one? yet had he the residue of the spirit: and wherefore one?
that hee might seeke a godly seed: therefore take heed to your
spirit, and let none deale treacherously against the wife of his
youth.<note> Or, excellencie. , Heb. a seed of God. , Or, vnfaithfully.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For the Lord the
God of Israel saith, that he hateth putting away: for one couereth
violence with his garment, saith the Lord of hosts, therfore take
heed to your spirit, that ye deale not treacherously.<note> Or, if hee hate her, put her away. , Heb. to put away.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Ye haue
wearied the Lord with your words: yet ye say, Wherein haue we
wearied him? when ye say, Euery one that doeth euill, is good in
the sight of the Lord, and he delighteth in them, or where is the
God of iudgement?</ab>



</div>