<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMalachi_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-14-14-Malachi.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Malachi-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Malachi complaineth of Israels
vnkindnesse. 6 Of their irreligiousnes, 12 and
profanenesse.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of the
word of þ<note/> Lord to Israel by Malachi.<note> Heb. by the hand of Malachi.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I haue loued you,
sayth the Lord: yet yee say, Wherein hast thou loued vs? was not
Esau Iacobs brother, sayth the Lord ? yet I loued
Iacob,<note> Rom.9.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And I hated Esau,
and layde his mountaines, and his heritage waste, for the dragons
of the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="4">Whereas Edom
sayth, Wee are impouerished, but we will returne and build the
desolate places; Thus sayth the Lord of hostes, They shal build,
but I will throw downe; and they shal call them, The border of
wickednesse, &amp; the people against whom the Lord hath
indignation for euer.</ab>
<ab n="5">And your eyes
shall see, and yee shall say; The Lord will be magnified from the
border of Israel.<note> Or, vpon. Heb. from vpon.</note></ab>

<fw>The people, and Priests,
reproued.</fw>
<ab n="6">¶ A sonne
honoureth his father, and a seruant his Master. If then I be a
father, where is mine honour? and if I be a Master, where is my
feare, saith the Lord of hostes, vnto you O priests, that despise
my name? and yee say, Wherein haue we despised thy name?</ab>
<ab n="7">Yee offer polluted
bread vpon mine altar; and yee say, Wherein haue we polluted thee?
In that yee say, The table of the Lord is contemptible.<note> Or, bring vnto &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And if hee offer
the blind for sacrifice, is it not euill? and if yee offer the lame
and sicke, is it not euill? offer it now vnto thy gouernour: will
he be pleased with thee, or accept thy person, saith the Lord of
hostes?<note> Heb. to sacrifice.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And now I pray
you, beseech God, that hee will be gracious vnto vs: this hath
beene by your meanes: will he regard your persons, saith the Lord
of hostes?<note> Heb. the face of God. , Heb. from your hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Who is there euen
among you that would shut the doores for nought? neither doe yee
kindle fire on mine altar for nought. I haue no pleasure in you,
saith the Lord of hostes, neither will I accept an offring at your
hand.<note> Isai.1.11. ier.6.20. amos.5.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For from the
rising of the Sunne, euen vnto the going downe of the same my name
shall be great among the Gentiles, and in euery place incense shall
be offered vnto my name, and a pure offring: for my name shall be
great among the heathen, saith the Lord of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ But yee
haue prophaned it, in that yee say; The table of the Lord is
polluted, and the fruite thereof, euen his meate, is
contemptible.</ab>
<ab n="13">Yee said also;
Behold what a wearinesse is it, and yee haue snuffed at it, saith
the Lord of hostes, and yee brought that which was torne, and the
lame, and the sicke: thus yee brought an offring: should I accept
this of your hand, saith the Lord ?<note> Or, whereas you might haue blowen it away.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But cursed be the
deceiuer, which hath in his flocke a male, and voweth and
sacrificeth vnto the Lord a corrupt thing: for I am a great King,
saith the Lord of hostes, and my name is dreadfull among the
heathen.<note> Heb. in whose flocke is.</note></ab>



</div>