<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMalachi_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Malachi-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Malachi-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Of the Messenger, Maiesty, &amp;
Grace of Christ. 7 Of the rebellion, 8 sacriledge, 13 and
infidelitie of the people. 16 The promise of blessing to them that
feare God.</head>

<ab n="1">Beholde, I will
send my messenger, and he shal prepare the way before mee: and the
Lord whom ye seeke, shall suddenly come to his Temple: euen
þ<note/> messenger of the Couenant, whom ye delight in:
behold, he shall come, saith the Lord of hosts.<note> Matt.11. 10. mat.1.2 luk.1.76. &amp; 7.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But who may abide
the day of his comming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for
he is like a refiners fire, and like fullers sope.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he shall sit
as a refiner and purifier of siluer: and he shall purifie the
sonnes of Leui, and purge them as gold &amp; siluer, that they may
offer vnto the Lord an offring in righteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then shall the
offerings of Iudah and Ierusalem bee pleasant vnto the Lord, as in
the dayes of old, and as in former yeeres.<note> Or, ancient.</note></ab>

<fw>God witnesseth against sinners.</fw>
<ab n="5">And I will come
neere to you to iudgement, and I will bee a swift witnesse against
the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against false
swearers, and against those that oppresse the hireling in his
wages, the widowe, and the fatherlesse, and that turne aside the
stranger from his right, and feare not me, saith the Lord of
hosts.<note> Or, defraud</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For I am the Lord,
I change not: therefore ye sonnes of Iacob are not
consumed.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Euen from
the dayes of your fathers yee are gone away from mine ordinances,
and haue not kept them: returne vnto me, and I will returne vnto
you, saith the Lord of hosts: But ye said, Wherein shall we
returne?<note> Zech. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Wil a man
rob God? yet ye haue robbed me. But ye say, Wherein haue we robbed
thee? In tithes &amp; offerings.</ab>
<ab n="9">Ye are cursed with
a curse: for ye haue robbed me, euen this whole nation.</ab>
<ab n="10">Bring ye all the
tithes into the store-house, that there may be meate in mine house,
&amp; proue me now herewith, saith the Lord of hostes, if I will
not open you the windowes of heauen, and powre you out a blessing,
that there shall not be roome enough to receiue it.<note> Gen.7.11 , Heb. emptie out.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I wil rebuke
the deuourer for your sakes: and he shal not destroy the fruits of
your ground, neither shal your vine cast her fruit before the time
in the field, saith the Lord of hosts.<note> Heb. corrupt.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And all nations
shall call you blessed: for ye shall be a delightsome land, saith
the Lord of hosts.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Your words
haue bin stout against me, saith the Lord, yet ye say, What haue we
spoken so much against thee?<note> Iob.1.14</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Ye haue said, It
is vaine to serue God: and what profit is it, that we haue kept his
ordinance, and that wee haue walked mournfully before the Lord of
hosts?<note> Heb. his obseruation. , Hebr in blacke.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And now we call
the proud happy: yea, they that worke wickednes are set vp, yea
they that tempt God, are euen deliuered.<note> Heb. are built. , Psal.95.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then they
that feared the Lord, spake often one to another, and the Lord
hearkened and heard it, &amp; a booke of remembrance was written
before him, for them that feared the Lord, &amp; that thought vpon
his name.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they shall be
mine, saith the Lord of hosts, in that day when I make vp my
iewels, and I wil spare them as a man spareth his owne sonne that
serueth him.<note> Or, speciall treasure.</note></ab>

<fw>The comming, and Office of
Eliiah.</fw>
<ab n="18">Then shall yee
returne and discerne betweene the righteous and the wicked,
betweene him that serueth God, and him that serueth him
not.</ab>



</div>