<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 Iesus brought bound, and accused
before Pilate. 15 Vpon the clamour of the common people, the
murderer Barabbas is loosed, and Iesus deliuered vp to be
crucified: 17 hee is crowned with thornes, 19 spit on, and mocked:
21 fainteth in bearing his crosse: 27 hangeth betweene two theeues,
29 suffreth the triumphing reproches of the Iewes: 39 but confessed
by the Centurion, to bee the Sonne of God: 43 and is honourably
buried by Ioseph.</head>

<ab n="1">And
straightway in the morning the chiefe Priests helde a consultation
with the Elders and Scribes, and the whole Councell, and bound
Iesus, and caried him away, and deliuered him to
Pilate.<note> Matth.27. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Pilate
asked him, Art thou the King of the Iewes? And hee answering, said
vnto him, Thou sayest it.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the chiefe
Priests accused him of many things: but hee answered
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Pilate
asked him againe, saying, Answerest thou nothing? behold how many
things they witnesse against thee.<note> Matth.27. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But Iesus yet
answered nothing, so that Pilate marueiled.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now at that
Feast he released vnto them one prisoner, whomsoeuer they
desired.</ab>
<ab n="7">And there was
one named Barabbas, which lay bound with them that had made
insurrection with him, who had committed murder in the
insurrection.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the
multitude crying alowd, began to desire him to doe as he had euer
done vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="9">But Pilate
answered them, saying, Will ye that I release vnto you the King of
the Iewes?</ab>
<ab n="10">(For hee knew that
the chiefe Priests had deliuered him for enuie.)</ab>
<ab n="11">But the chiefe
Priests mooued the people, that hee should rather release Barabbas
vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Pilate
answered, and said againe vnto them, What will yee then that I
shall do vnto him whom ye call the King of the Iewes?</ab>
<ab n="13">And they cried out
againe, Crucifie him.</ab>

<fw>Christ crucified.</fw>
<ab n="14">Then Pilate saide
vnto them, Why, what euill hath hee done? And they cried out the
more exceedingly, Crucifie him.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And so
Pilate, willing to content the people, released Barabbas vnto them,
and deliuered Iesus, when he had scourged him, to be
crucified.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the souldiers
led him away into the hall, called Pretorium, and they call
together the whole band.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they clothed
him with purple, and platted a crowne of thornes, and put it about
his head,</ab>
<ab n="18">And beganne to
salute him, Haile King of the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they smote him
on the head with a reed, and did spit vpon him, and bowing their
knees, worshipped him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when they had
mocked him, they tooke off the purple from him, and put his owne
clothes on him, and led him out to crucifie him.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they compell
one Simon a Cyrenian, who passed by, comming out of the country,
the father of Alexander and Rufus, to beare his Crosse.<note> Matth.27. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And they bring him
vnto the place Golgotha, which is, being interpreted, the place of
a skull.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they gaue him
to drinke, wine mingled with myrrhe: but he receiued it
not.</ab>
<ab n="24">And when they had
crucified him, they parted his garments, casting lots vpon them,
what euery man should take.</ab>
<ab n="25">And it was the
third houre, and they crucified him.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the
superscription of his accusation was written ouer, THE KING OF THE
IEWES.</ab>
<ab n="27">And with him they
crucifie two theeues, the one on his right hand, and the other on
his left.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the Scripture
was fulfilled, which sayeth, And hee was numbred with the
transgressours.<note> Esay 53. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And they that
passed by, railed on him, wagging their heads, and saying, Ah thou
that destroyest the Temple, and buildest it in three dayes,</ab>
<ab n="30">Saue thy selfe, and
come downe from the Crosse.</ab>
<ab n="31">Likewise also the
chiefe Priests mocking, said among themselues with the Scribes, He
saued others, himselfe he cannot saue.</ab>

<fw>Christs death, and
resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="32">Let Christ the King
of Israel descend now from the Crosse, that we may see and beleeue:
And they that were crucified with him, reuiled him.</ab>
<ab n="33">And when the sixth
houre was come, there was darkenesse ouer the whole land, vntill
the ninth houre.</ab>
<ab n="34">And at the ninth
houre, Iesus cryed with a loude voice, saying, Eloi, Eloi,
lamasabachthani? which is, being interpreted, My God, my God, why
hast thou forsaken me?<note> Mat.27. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And some of them
that stood by, when they heard it, said, Behold, he calleth
Elias.</ab>
<ab n="36">And one ranne, and
filled a spunge full of vineger, and put it on a reed, and gaue him
to drinke, saying, Let alone, let vs see whether Elias will come to
take him downe.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Iesus cryed
with a loude voice, and gaue vp the ghost.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the vaile of
the Temple was rent in twaine, from the top to the bottome.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And when the
Centurion which stood ouer against him, saw that hee so cryed out,
and gaue vp the ghost, hee said, Truely this man was the Sonne of
God.</ab>
<ab n="40">There were also
women looking on afarre off, among whom was Mary Magdalene, and
Mary the mother of Iames the lesse, and of Ioses, and
Salome:</ab>
<ab n="41">Who also when hee
was in Galile, followed him, and ministred vnto him, and many other
women which came vp with him vnto Hierusalem.<note> Luke 8. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">¶ And now when
the euen was come, (because it was the Preparation, that is, the
day before the Sabbath)<note> Mat.27. 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Ioseph of
Arimathea, an honourable counseller, which also waited for the
kingdome of God, came, and went in boldly vnto Pilate, and craued
the body of Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="44">And Pilate
marueiled if he were already dead, and calling vnto him the
Centurion, hee asked him whether hee had beene any while
dead.</ab>
<ab n="45">And when he knew it
of the Centurion, he gaue the body to Ioseph.</ab>
<ab n="46">And hee bought fine
linnen, and tooke him downe, and wrapped him in the linnen, and
laide him in a sepulchre, which was hewen out of a rocke, and
rolled a stone vnto the doore of the sepulchre.</ab>

<fw>Christs death, and
resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="47">And Mary Magdalene,
and Mary the mother of Ioses behelde where he was laide.</ab>



</div>