<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The serpent deceiueth Eue. 6 Mans
shamefull fall. 9 God arraigneth them. 14 The serpent is cursed. 15
The promised Seed. 16 The punishment of Mankind. 21 Their first
clothing. 22 Their casting out of Paradise.</head>


<fw>The fall of man.</fw>
<ab n="1">Now the serpent
was more subtill then any beast of the field, which the LORD God
had made, and he said vnto the woman, Yea, hath God said, Ye shall
not eat of euery tree of the garden?<note> Heb. Yea, because, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the woman said
vnto the serpent, Wee may eate of the fruite of the trees of the
garden:</ab>
<ab n="3">But of the fruit
of the tree, which is in the midst of the garden, God hath said, Ye
shal not eate of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye
die.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Serpent
said vnto the woman, Ye shall not surely die.<note> 2.Cor. 11 3. 1.tim. 2.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For God doeth
know, that in the day ye eate thereof, then your eyes shalbee
opened: and yee shall bee as Gods, knowing good and euill.</ab>
<ab n="6">And when the woman
saw, that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleasant to
the eyes, and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she tooke of
the fruit thereof, and did eate, and gaue also vnto her husband
with her, and hee did eate.<note> Heb. a desire. , Ecclus.25 26. 1.tim. 2.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the eyes of
them both were opened, &amp; they knew that they were naked, and
they sewed figge leaues together, and made themselues
aprons.<note> Or, things to gird about.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And they heard the
voyce of the LORD God, walking in the garden in the coole of the
day: and Adam and his wife hid themselues from the presence of the
LORD God, amongst the trees of the garden.<note> Heb. wind.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the LORD God
called vnto Adam, and said vnto him, Where art thou?</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said, I
heard thy voice in the garden: and I was afraid, because I was
naked, and I hid my selfe.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he said, Who
told thee, that thou wast naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree,
whereof I commanded thee, that thou shouldest not eate?</ab>
<ab n="12">And the man said,
The woman whom thou gauest to be with mee, shee gaue me of the
tree, and I did eate.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the LORD God
said vnto the woman, What is this that thou hast done? And the
woman said, The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eate.</ab>

<fw>The promised seed.</fw>
<ab n="14">And the LORD God
said vnto the Serpent, Because thou hast done this, thou art cursed
aboue all cattel, and aboue euery beast of the field: vpon thy
belly shalt thou goe, and dust shalt thou eate, all the dayes of
thy life.</ab>
<ab n="15">And I will put
enmitie betweene thee and the woman, and betweene thy seed and her
seed: it shal bruise thy head, and thou shalt bruise his
heele.</ab>
<ab n="16">Unto the woman he
said, I will greatly multiply thy sorowe and thy conception. In
sorow thou shalt bring forth children: and thy desire shall be to
thy husband, and hee shall rule ouer thee.<note> Or, subiect to thy husband. , 1.Corin. 14.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And vnto Adam he
said, Because thou hast hearkened vnto the voyce of thy wife, and
hast eaten of the tree, of which I commaunded thee, saying, Thou
shalt not eate of it: cursed is the ground for thy sake: in sorow
shalt thou eate of it all the dayes of thy life.</ab>
<ab n="18">Thornes also and
thistles shall it bring forth to thee: and thou shalt eate the
herbe of the field.<note> Heb. cause to bud.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">In the sweate of
thy face shalt thou eate bread, till thou returne vnto the ground:
for out of it wast thou taken, for dust thou art, and vnto dust
shalt thou returne.</ab>
<ab n="20">And Adam called
his wiues name Eue, because she was the mother of all
liuing.<note> Heb. Chanah.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Unto Adam also,
and to his wife, did the LORD God make coates of skinnes, and
cloathed them.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
LORD God said, Behold, the man is become as one of vs, to know good
&amp; euill. And now lest hee put foorth his hand, and take also of
the tree of life, and eate and liue for euer:</ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore the
LORD God sent him foorth from the garden of Eden, to till the
ground, from whence he was taken.</ab>
<ab n="24">So he droue out
the man: and he placed at the East of the garden of Eden,
Cherubims, and a flaming sword, which turned euery way, to keepe
the way of the tree of life.</ab>



</div>