<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-14-14b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 A conspiracie against Christ. 3
Precious ointment is powred on his head by a woman. 10 Iudas
selleth his master for money. 12 Christ himselfe foretelleth how he
shall be betrayed of one of his disciples: 22 after the Passeouer
prepared, &amp; eaten, instituteth his Supper: 26 declareth
aforehand the flight of all his disciples, and Peters deniall. 43
Iudas betrayeth him with a kisse. 46 Hee is apprehended in the
garden, 53 Falsly accused, and impiously condemned of the Iewes
counsell: 65 shamefully abused by them: 66 and thrise denied of
Peter.</head>

<ab n="1">After two
dayes was the feast of the Passeouer, and of vnleauened bread: and
the chiefe Priests, and the Scribes sought how they might take him
by craft, and put him to death.<note> Mat. 26.2</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But they said,
Not on the feast day, lest there be an vprore of the
people.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
being in Bethanie, in the house of Simon the leper, as he sate at
meat, there came a woman, hauing an Alabaster boxe of oyntment of
spikenard very precious, and shee brake the boxe, and powred it on
his head.<note> Mat.26.6 , Or, pure nard: or liquid nard.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And there were
some that had indignation within themselues, and said, Why was this
waste of the oyntment made?</ab>
<ab n="5">For it might
haue bene solde for more then three hundred pence, and haue bene
giuen to the poore: and they murmured against her.<note> See Matt. 18.28.</note></ab>

<fw>The Passeouer.</fw>
<ab n="6">And Iesus
said, Let her alone, why trouble you her? Shee hath wrought a good
worke on me.</ab>
<ab n="7">For ye haue
the poore with you alwayes, and whensoeuer ye will yee may doe them
good: but me ye haue not alwayes.</ab>
<ab n="8">She hath done
what she could: she is come aforehand to anoint my body to the
burying.</ab>
<ab n="9">Uerely I say
vnto you, Wheresoeuer this Gospel shalbe preached thorowout the
whole world, this also that she hath done, shall be spoken of for a
memoriall of her.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And Iudas
Iscariot, one of the twelue, went vnto the chiefe Priests, to
betray him vnto them.<note> Mat. 26. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And when they heard
it, they were glad, and promised to giue him money. And he sought
how he might conueniently betray him.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
first day of vnleauened bread, when they killed the Passeouer, his
disciples said vnto him, Where wilt thou that we goe, and prepare,
that thou mayest eate the Passeouer?<note> Mat.26. 17. , Or, sacrificed.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he sendeth
forth two of his disciples, and saith vnto them, Goe yee into the
citie, and there shall meet you a man bearing a pitcher of water:
follow him.</ab>
<ab n="14">And wheresoeuer he
shall goe in, say yee to the good man of the house, The Master
saith, Where is the guest chamber, where I shall eate the Passeouer
with my disciples?</ab>
<ab n="15">And he will shew
you a large vpper roome furnished, and prepared: there make ready
for vs.</ab>
<ab n="16">And his disciples
went forth, and came into the citie, and found as hee had said vnto
them: and they made readie the Passeouer.</ab>
<ab n="17">And in the euening
hee commeth with the twelue.</ab>
<ab n="18">And as they sate,
and did eat, Iesus said, Uerily I say vnto you, one of you which
eateth with me, shall betray mee.<note> Mat.26. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And they began to
be sorowfull, and to say vnto him, one by one, Is it I? And another
said, Is it I?</ab>
<ab n="20">And he answered,
and saide vnto them, It is one of the twelue, that dippeth with me
in the dish.</ab>

<fw>Christs last Supper.</fw>
<ab n="21">The sonne of man
indeed goeth, as it is written of him: but woe to that man by whom
the Sonne of man is betrayed: Good were it for that man, if he had
neuer bene borne.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And as they
did eate, Iesus tooke bread, and blessed, and brake it, and gaue to
them, and said, Take, eate: this is my body.<note> Mat.26. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And he tooke the
cup, and when he had giuen thanks, he gaue it to them: and they all
dranke of it.</ab>
<ab n="24">And he said vnto
them, This is my blood of the new Testament, which is shed for
many.</ab>
<ab n="25">Uerely I say vnto
you, I will drinke no more of the fruit of the Uine, vntill that
day that I drinke it new in the kingdome of God.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And when
they had sung an hymne, they went out into the mount of
Oliues.<note> Or, psalme</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And Iesus saith
vnto them, All ye shall be offended because of mee this night: for
it is written, I will smite the shepheard, and the sheepe shall be
scattered.<note> Mat.26. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">But after that I am
risen, I will goe before you into Galilee.</ab>
<ab n="29">But Peter said vnto
him, Although al shalbe offended, yet wil not I.<note> Mat.26. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And Iesus saith
vnto him, Uerily I say vnto thee, that this day, euen in this night
before the cocke crow twise, thou shalt denie me thrise.</ab>
<ab n="31">But he spake the
more vehemently, If I should die with thee, I will not denie thee
in any wise. Likewise also said they all.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they came to a
place which was named Gethsemani, and hee saith to his disciples,
Sit yee here, while I shall pray.<note> Matth.26. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And hee taketh with
him Peter, and Iames, and Iohn, and began to be sore amazed, and to
be very heauy,</ab>
<ab n="34">And saith vnto
them, My soule is exceeding sorowful vnto death: tarie ye here, and
watch.</ab>
<ab n="35">And he went forward
a litle, and fell on the ground, and prayed, that if it were
possible, the houre might passe from him.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he said, Abba,
father, all things are possible vnto thee, take away this cup from
me: Neuerthelesse, not that I will, but what thou wilt.</ab>
<ab n="37">And hee commeth,
and findeth them sleeping, and saith vnto Peter, Simon, sleepest
thou? Couldest not thou watch one houre?</ab>

<fw>Christ betrayed.</fw>
<ab n="38">Watch ye and pray,
lest yee enter into temptation: The spirit truly is ready, but the
flesh is weake.</ab>
<ab n="39">And againe he went
away, and prayed, and spake the same words.</ab>
<ab n="40">And when he
returned, he found them asleepe againe, (for their eies were
heauie) neither wist they what to answere him.</ab>
<ab n="41">And he commeth the
third time, and saith vnto them, Sleepe on now, and take your rest:
it is enough, the houre is come, behold, the Son of man is betrayed
into the hands of sinners.</ab>
<ab n="42">Rise vp, let vs
goe, Loe, he that betrayeth me, is at hand.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ And
immediately, while hee yet spake, commeth Iudas, one of the twelue,
and with him a great multitude with swords, and staues, from the
chiefe Priests, and the Scribes, &amp; the Elders.<note> Mat.26. 47.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And he that
betrayed him, had giuen them a token, saying, Whomsoeuer I shall
kisse, that same is he; take him, and lead him away safely.</ab>
<ab n="45">And assoone as he
was come, he goeth straightway to him, and sayeth, Master, Master,
and kissed him.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ And they
layed their hands on him, and tooke him.</ab>
<ab n="47">And one of them
that stood by, drew a sword, and smote a seruant of the high
Priest, and cut off his eare.</ab>
<ab n="48">And Iesus answered,
&amp; said vnto thē, Are ye come out as against a theefe, with
swords, &amp; with staues to take me?</ab>
<ab n="49">I was daily with
you in the Temple, teaching, and yee tooke me not; but the
Scriptures must be fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="50">And they all
forsooke him, &amp; fled.</ab>
<ab n="51">And there followed
him a certaine yong man, hauing a linnen cloth cast about his naked
body, and the yong men laid hold on him.</ab>
<ab n="52">And he left the
linnen cloth, and fled from them naked.</ab>
<ab n="53">¶ And they led
Iesus away to the high Priest, and with him were assembled all the
chiefe Priests, and the Elders, and the Scribes.<note> Mat.26. 57.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">And Peter followed
him a farre off, euen into the pallace of the high Priest: and he
sate with the seruants, and warmed himselfe at the fire.</ab>
<ab n="55">And the chiefe
Priests, and all the counsell sought for witnesse against Iesus, to
put him to death, &amp; found none.<note> Mat.26. 59.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">For many bare false
witnesse against him, but their witnesse agreed not
together.</ab>

<fw>Peters deniall.</fw>
<ab n="57">And there arose
certaine, and bare false witnesse against him, saying,</ab>
<ab n="58">We heard him say, I
will destroy this Temple that is made with hands, and within three
dayes I will build another made without hands.</ab>
<ab n="59">But neither so did
their witnesse agree together.</ab>
<ab n="60">And the high Priest
stood vp in the mids, and asked Iesus, saying, Answerest thou
nothing? What is it which these witnesse against thee?</ab>
<ab n="61">But he held his
peace, and answered nothing. Againe, the high Priest asked him, and
said vnto him, Art thou the Christ, the sonne of the
Blessed?</ab>
<ab n="62">And Iesus said, I
am: and yee shall see the sonne of man sitting on the right hand of
power, and comming in the clouds of heauen.<note> Mat.24. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">Then the high
Priest rent his clothes, and saith, What neede we any further
witnesses?</ab>
<ab n="64">Yee haue heard the
blasphemy: what thinke yee? And they all condemned him to be guilty
of death.</ab>
<ab n="65">And some beganne to
spit on him, and to couer his face, and to buffet him, and to say
vnto him, Prophecie: And the seruants did stricke him with the
palmes of their hands.</ab>
<ab n="66">¶ And as Peter
was beneath in the palace, there commeth one of the maides of the
high Priest.<note> Mat.26. 69.</note></ab>
<ab n="67">And when she saw
Peter warning himselfe, she looked vpon him, and said, And thou
also wast with Iesus of Nazareth.</ab>
<ab n="68">But hee denied,
saying, I know not, neither vnderstand I what thou sayest. And he
went out into the porch, and the cocke crew.</ab>
<ab n="69">And a maide saw him
againe, and beganne to say to them that stood by, This is one of
them.</ab>
<ab n="70">And he denied it
againe. And a little after, they that stood by said againe to
Peter, Surely thou art one of them: for thou art a Galilean, and
thy speach agreeth thereto.</ab>
<ab n="71">But he beganne to
curse and to sweare, saying, I know not this man of whom yee
speake.</ab>
<ab n="72">And the second time
the cocke crew: and Peter called to minde the word that Iesus said
vnto him, Before the cockecrow twise, thou shalt denie me thrise.
And when he thought thereon, he wept.<note> Mat.26. 75. , Or, he wept abundantly, or he began to wept.</note></ab>



</div>