<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Christ healeth the withered hand,
10 and many other infirmities: 11 Rebuketh the vncleane spirits: 13
Chooseth his twelue Apostles: 22 Conuinceth the blasphemie of
casting out deuils by Beelzebub: 31 and sheweth who are his
brother, sister and mother.</head>

<ab n="1">And he entred
againe into the Synagogue, and there was a man there which had a
withered hand:<note> Mat.12.9</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And they
watched him, whether hee would heale him on the Sabbath day, that
they might accuse him.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he saith
vnto the man which had the withered hand, Stand forth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee saith
vnto them, Is it lawfull to doe good on the Sabbath dayes, or to
doe euill? to saue life, or to kill? but they held their
peace.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when he had
looked round about on them with anger, being grieued for the
hardnesse of their hearts, He saith vnto the man, Stretch foorth
thine hand. And he stretched it out: and his hand was restored
whole as the other.<note> Or, blindnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the
Pharisees went forth, and straightway tooke counsel with the
Herodians against him, how they might destroy him.</ab>
<ab n="7">But Iesus
withdrew himselfe with his disciples to the Sea: and a great
multitude from Galilee followed him, and from Iudea,</ab>
<ab n="8">And from
Hierusalem, and from Idumea, and from beyond Iordane, and they
about Tyre &amp; Sydon, a great multitude, when they had heard what
great things he did, came vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="9">And he spake to
his disciples that a small ship should wait on him, because of the
multitude, lest they should throng him.</ab>
<ab n="10">For he had
healed many, insomuch that they preassed vpon him, for to touch
him, as many as had plagues.<note> Or, rushed</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And vncleane
spirits, when they saw him, fell downe before him, and cried,
saying, Thou art the Sonne of God.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he
straitly charged them, that they should not make him
knowen.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he goeth
vp into a mountaine, and calleth vnto him whom he would: and they
came vnto him.<note> Matt.10.1</note></ab>

<fw>Christs mother, &amp;c.</fw>
<ab n="14">And he
ordeined twelue, that they should be with him, and that hee might
send them foorth to preach:</ab>
<ab n="15">And to haue
power to heale sickenesses, and to cast out deuils.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Simon he
surnamed Peter.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Iames the
sonne of Zebedee, and Iohn the brother of Iames (and he surnamed
them Boanerges, which is, The sonnes of thunder.)</ab>
<ab n="18">And Andrew,
and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and Iames the
sonne of Alpheus, and Thaddeus, and Simon the Canaanite,</ab>
<ab n="19">And Iudas
Iscariot, which also betrayed him: and they went into an
house.<note> Or, home.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And the
multitude commeth together againe, so that they could not so much
as eate bread.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when his
friends heard of it, they went out to lay hold on him, for they
said, He is beside himselfe.<note> Or, kinsemen.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
Scribes which came downe from Hierusalem, said, He hath Beelzebub,
and by the prince of the deuils, casteth he out deuils.<note> Mat.9.34</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And he called
them vnto him, and said vnto them in parables, Howe can Satan cast
out Satan?</ab>
<ab n="24">And if a
kingdome be diuided against it selfe, that kingdome cannot
stand.</ab>
<ab n="25">And if a house
be diuided against it selfe, that house cannot stand.</ab>
<ab n="26">And if Satan
rise vp against himselfe, and be diuided, hee cannot stand, but
hath an end.</ab>
<ab n="27">No man can
enter into a strong mans house, and spoile his goods, except he
will first bind the strong man, and then he will spoile his
house.</ab>
<ab n="28">Uerely I say
vnto you, All sinnes shalbe forgiuen vnto the sonnes of men, and
blasphemies, wherewith soeuer they shall blaspheme:<note> Matt.12.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">But he that
shal blaspheme against the holy Ghost, hath neuer forgiuenesse, but
is in danger of eternall damnation.</ab>
<ab n="30">Because they
said, He hath an vncleane spirit.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ There
came then his brethren, and his mother, and standing without, sent
vnto him, calling him.<note> Mat.13.46.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And the
multitude sate about him and they said vnto him, Behold, thy mother
and thy brethren without seeke for thee.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he
answered them, saying, Who is my mother, or my brethren?</ab>

<fw>The parable of the seed.</fw>
<ab n="34">And he looked
round about on them which sate about him, and saide, Behold my
mother and my brethren.</ab>
<ab n="35">For whosoeuer
shall doe the will of God, the same is my brother, and my sister,
and mother.</ab>



</div>