<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 In a parable of the vineyard let
out to vnthankful husbandmen, Christ foretelleth the reprobation of
the Iewes, and the calling of the Gentiles: 13 Hee auoideth the
snare of the Pharisees and Herodians about paying tribute to Cesar:
18 conuinceth the errour of the Sadducees, who denied the
resurrection: 28 resolueth the Scribe who questioned of the first
commandement: 35 refuteth the opinion that the Scribes held of
Christ: 38 Bidding the people to beware of their ambition, and
hypocrisie: 41 and commendeth the poore widow for her two mites,
aboue all.</head>

<ab n="1">And hee began
to speake vnto them by parables. A certaine man planted a vineyard,
and set an hedge about it, and digged a place for the wine fat, and
built a towre, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into a farre
countrey.<note> Mat.21.33</note></ab>

<fw>The corner stone.</fw>
<ab n="2">And at the
season, he sent to the husbandmen a seruant, that he might receiue
from the husbandmen of the fruite of the vineyard.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they
caught him, and beat him, and sent him away emptie.</ab>
<ab n="4">And againe,
hee sent vnto them another seruant; and at him they cast stones,
and wounded him in the head, and sent him away shamefully
handled.</ab>
<ab n="5">And againe, he
sent another, and him they killed: and many others, beating some,
and killing some.</ab>
<ab n="6">Hauing yet
therefore one sonne his welbeloued, he sent him also last vnto
them, saying, They will reuerence my sonne.</ab>
<ab n="7">But those
husbandmen said amongst themselues, This is the heire, come, let vs
kill him, and the inheritance shall be ours.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they tooke
him, and killed him, and cast him out of the vineyard.</ab>
<ab n="9">What shall
therefore the Lord of the vineyard doe? He will come and destroy
the husbandmen, and will giue the vineyard vnto others.</ab>
<ab n="10">And haue ye not
read this Scripture? The stone which the builders reiected, is
become the head of the corner:<note> Psal.118. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">This was the Lords
doing, and it is maruellous in our eies.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they sought to
lay hold on him, but feared the people, for they knew that he had
spoken the parable against them: and they left him, and went their
way.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And they
send vnto him certaine of the Pharises, and of the Herodians, to
catch him in his words.<note> Matth.22 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And when they were
come, they say vnto him, Master, we know that thou art true, and
carest for no man: for thou regardest not the person of men, but
teachest the way of God in truth. Is it lawfull to giue tribute to
Cesar, or not?</ab>
<ab n="15">Shall we giue, or
shall we not giue? But he knowing their hypocrisie, said vnto them,
Why tempt yee mee? Bring me a penny that I may see it.<note> Valewing of our money seuen pence halfe penie, as Mat.18. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And they brought
it: and he saith vnto them, Whose is this image and superscription?
And they said vnto him, Cesars.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Iesus
answering, said vnto them, Render to Cesar the things that are
Cesars: and to God the things that are Gods. And they maruailed at
him.</ab>

<fw>The Resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="18">¶ Then come
vnto him the Sadducees, which say there is no resurrection, and
they asked him, saying,<note> Matth.22. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Master, Moses wrote
vnto vs, If a mans brother die, and leaue his wife behind him, and
leaue no children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise
vp seed vnto his brother.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now there were
seuen brethren: and the first tooke a wife, and dying left no
seede.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the second
tooke her, and died, neither left he any seed, and the third
likewise.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the seuen had
her, and left no seede: last of all the woman died also.</ab>
<ab n="23">In the resurrection
therefore, when they shall rise, whose wife shall she be of them?
for the seuen had her to wife.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Iesus
answering, said vnto them, Doe ye not therefore erre, because yee
know not the scriptures, neither the power of God?</ab>
<ab n="25">For when they shall
rise from the dead, they neither marry, nor are giuen in marriage:
but are as the Angels which are in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="26">And as touching the
dead, that they rise: haue ye not read in the booke of Moses, how
in the bush God spake vnto him, saying, I am the God of Abraham,
and the God of Isahac, and the God of Iacob?</ab>
<ab n="27">Hee is not the God
of the dead, but the God of the liuing: yee therefore doe greatly
erre.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And one of
the Scribes came, and hauing heard them reasoning together, and
perceiuing that he had answered them well, asked him which is the
first commandement of all.<note> Matth.22. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And Iesus answered
him, The first of al the commandements is, Heare, O Israel, the
Lord our God is one Lord:</ab>
<ab n="30">And thou shalt loue
the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soule, and
with all thy minde, and with all thy strength: This is the first
commandement.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the second is
like, namely this, Thou shalt loue thy neighbour as thy selfe:
there is none other commandement greater then these.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the Scribe said
vnto him, Well master, thou hast said the truth: for there is one
God, and there is none other but he.</ab>

<fw>Christ Dauids Lord.</fw>
<ab n="33">And to loue him
with all the heart, and with all the vnderstanding, and with all
the soule, and with all the strength, and to loue his neighbour as
himselfe, is more then all whole burnt offerings and
sacrifices.</ab>
<ab n="34">And when Iesus saw
that he answered discreetly, hee saide vnto him, Thou art not far
from the kingdome of God. And no man after that durst aske him any
question.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And Iesus
answered, and said, while hee taught in the Temple, How say the
Scribes that Christ is the sonne of Dauid?<note> Matth.22. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">For Dauid himselfe
said by the holy Ghost, The Lord said to my Lord, Sit thou on my
right hand, til I make thine enemies thy footstoole.</ab>
<ab n="37">Dauid therefore
himselfe calleth him Lord, and whence is hee then his sonne? And
the common people heard him gladly.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ And he said
vnto them in his doctrine, Beware of the Scribes, which loue to goe
in long clothing, and loue salutations in the market
places,<note> Matth.23. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And the chiefe
seates in the Synagogues, and the vppermost roomes at
feasts:</ab>
<ab n="40">Which deuoure
widowes houses, and for a pretence make long prayers: These shall
receiue greater damnation.<note> Matth.23. 14</note></ab>
<ab n="41">¶ And Iesus
sate ouer against the treasurie, and beheld how the people cast
money into the treasurie: and many that were rich, cast in
much.<note> Luke 21. 1. , A piece of brasse money, See Matth. 10. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And there came a
certaine poore widow, and she threw in two mites, which make a
farthing.<note> It is the seuenth part of one piece of that brasse money.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And he called vnto
him his disciples, and saith vnto them, Uerily I say vnto you, that
this poore widow hath cast more in, then all they which haue cast
into the treasurie.</ab>
<ab n="44">For all they did
cast in of their aboundance: but she of her want, did cast in all
that she had, euen all her liuing.</ab>



</div>