<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-6-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Christ is contemned of his
countreymen. 7 He giueth the twelue power ouer vncleane spirits. 14
Diuers opinions of Christ. 18 Iohn Baptist is beheaded, 29 and
buried. 30 The Apostles returne from preaching. 34 The miracle of
fiue loaues and two fishes. 45 Christ walketh on the Sea: 53 And
healeth all that touch him.</head>

<ab n="1">And hee went
out from thence, and came into his owne countrey, and his disciples
follow him.<note> Mat.13.54.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And when the
Sabbath day was come, he began to teach in the Synagogue: and many
hearing him, were astonished, saying, From whence hath this man
these things? And what wisedome is this which is giuen vnto him,
that euen such mightie workes are wrought by his hands?</ab>
<ab n="3">Is not this the
carpenter, the sonne of Mary, the brother of Iames and Ioses, and
of Iuda, and Simon? And are not his sisters heere with vs? And they
were offended at him.</ab>

<fw>Disciples sent out.</fw>
<ab n="4">But Iesus sayde
vnto them, A Prophet is not without honour, but in his owne
countrey, and among his owne kinne, and in his owne
house.<note> Iohn 4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And he could
there doe no mightie worke, saue that he laid his hands vpon a few
sicke folke, and healed them.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
marueiled because of their vnbeliefe. And he went round about the
villages, teaching.<note> Mat.9.35 luke 13.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And he
calleth vnto him the twelue, and began to send them foorth, by two
and two, and gaue them power ouer vncleane spirits,<note> Mat.10.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And commanded
them that they should take nothing for their iourney, saue a staffe
onely: no scrip, no bread, no money in their purse:<note> The word signifieth a piece of brasse money, in value somewhat lesse then a farthing, mat. 10.9. but here it is taken in generall for mony.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But be shod
with sandales: and not put on two coats.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said
vnto them, In what place soeuer yee enter into an house, there
abide til ye depart from that place.</ab>
<ab n="11">And whosoeuer
shall not receiue you, nor heare you, when yee depart thence, shake
off the dust vnder your feet, for a testimonie against them: Uerely
I say vnto you, it shalbe more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrha in
the day of iudgement, then for that citie.<note> Mat.10.14 , Act.13.51</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they went
out, and preached that men should repent.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they cast
out many deuils, and anointed with oyle many, that were sicke, and
healed them.<note> Iam.5.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And king Herod
heard of him (for his name was spread abroad:) and hee said that
Iohn the Baptist was risen from the dead, and therefore mightie
workes doe shew foorth themselues in him.<note> Mat.14.1</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Others said,
That it is Elias. And others said, That it is a Prophet, or as one
of the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="16">But when Herod
heard thereof, he said, It is Iohn, whome I beheaded, he is risen
from the dead.<note> Luk.3.19</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For Herod
himselfe had sent forth and laid hold vpon Iohn, and bound him in
prison for Herodias sake, his brother Philips wife, for hee had
maried her.</ab>
<ab n="18">For Iohn had
said vnto Herod, It is not lawfull for thee to haue thy brothers
wife.<note> Leuit.18.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Therfore
Herodias had a quarrel against him, &amp; would haue killed him,
but she could not.<note> Or, an inward grudge</note></ab>

<fw>Iohn beheaded.</fw>
<ab n="20">For Herod
feared Iohn, knowing that he was a iust man, and an holy, and
obserued him: and when he heard him, hee did many things, and heard
him gladly.<note> Or, kept him or saued him.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And when a
conuenient day was come, that Herod on his birth day made a supper
to his lords, high captaines, and chiefe estates of
Galilee:</ab>
<ab n="22">And when the
daughter of the said Herodias came in, and danced, and pleased
Herod, and them that sate with him, the king said vnto the
damosell, Aske of me whatsoeuer thou wilt, and I will giue it
thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">And he sware
vnto her, Whatsoeuer thou shalt aske of me, I will giue it thee,
vnto the halfe of my kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="24">And she went
forth, and said vnto her mother, What shall I aske? And she said,
The head of Iohn þe Baptist.</ab>
<ab n="25">And she came
in straightway with haste, vnto the king, and asked, saying, I will
that thou giue me by and by in a charger, the head of Iohn the
Baptist.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the king
was exceeding sory, yet for his othes sake, and for their sakes
which sate with him, hee would not reiect her.</ab>
<ab n="27">And immediatly
the king sent an executioner, and commaunded his head to be
brought, and he went, and beheaded him in the prison,<note> Or, one of his guard.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And brought
his head in a charger, and gaue it to the damosell, and the
damosell gaue it to her mother.</ab>
<ab n="29">And when his
disciples heard of it, they came and tooke vp his corpse, and laid
it in a tombe.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the
Apostles gathered themselues together vnto Iesus, and tolde him all
things, both what they had done, and what they had
taught.<note> Luk.9.10</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And he said
vnto them, Come yee your selues apart into a desert place, and rest
a while. For there were many comming and going, and they had no
leisure so much as to eate.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they
departed into a desert place by ship priuately.<note> Mat.14.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the people
saw them departing, and many knew him, and ranne afoote thither out
of all cities, and outwent them, and came together vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="34">And Iesus when
he came out, saw much people, and was moued with compassion toward
them, because they were as sheepe not hauing a shepherd: and hee
beganne to teach them many things.<note> Mat.6.39.</note></ab>

<fw>Miraculous feeding.</fw>
<ab n="35">And when the
day was now far spent, his Disciples came vnto him, and said, This
is a desert place, and now the time is farre passed.<note> Matth. 14.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Send them
away, that they may goe into the countrey round about, and into the
villages, and buy themselues bread: for they haue nothing to
eate.</ab>
<ab n="37">He answered
and said vnto them, Giue yee them to eate. And they say vnto him,
Shall we goe and buy two hundred penniworth of bread, and giue them
to eate?<note> The Rom. penie is seuen pence halfe penie as Mat.18.28</note></ab>
<ab n="38">He saith vnto
them, How many loaues haue yee? goe, and see. And when they knew,
they say, Fiue, and two fishes.</ab>
<ab n="39">And he
commanded them to make all sit downe by companies vpon the greene
grasse.</ab>
<ab n="40">And they sate
downe in rankes by hundreds, and by fifties.</ab>
<ab n="41">And when he
had taken the fiue loaues, and the two fishes, he looked vp to
heauen, and blessed, and brake the loaues, and gaue them to his
disciples to set before them; and the two fishes diuided he among
them all.</ab>
<ab n="42">And they did
all eate, and were filled.</ab>
<ab n="43">And they tooke
vp twelue baskets full of the fragments, and of the fishes.</ab>
<ab n="44">And they that
did eate of the loaues, were about fiue thousand men.</ab>
<ab n="45">And
straightway he constrained his disciples to get into the ship, and
to goe to the other side before vnto Bethsaida, while he sent away
the people.<note> Or, ouer against Bethsaida.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">And when hee
had sent them away, he departed into a mountaine to pray.</ab>
<ab n="47">And when Euen
was come, the ship was in the midst of the Sea, and he alone on the
land.<note> Matth.14.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And he saw
them toiling in rowing (for the wind was contrary vnto them:) and
about the fourth watch of the night, he commeth vnto them, walking
vpon the Sea, and would haue passed by them.</ab>
<ab n="49">But when they
saw him walking vpon the Sea, they supposed it had bene a spirit,
and cried out.</ab>
<ab n="50">(For they all
saw him, and were troubled) and immediately hee talked with them,
and saith vnto them, Be of good cheere, It is I, be not
afraid.</ab>

<fw>Mens traditions.</fw>
<ab n="51">And hee went
vp vnto them into the ship, and the wind ceased: and they were sore
amazed in themselues beyond measure, and wondered.</ab>
<ab n="52">For they
considered not the miracle of the loaues, for their heart was
hardened.</ab>
<ab n="53">And when they
had passed ouer, they came into the land of Genesareth, and drew to
the shore.<note> Matth.14.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">And when they
were come out of the ship, straightway they knew him,</ab>
<ab n="55">And ran
through that whole region round about, and beganne to carrie about
in beds, those that were sicke, where they heard he was.</ab>
<ab n="56">And
whithersouer he entred, into villages, or cities, or countrie, they
laide the sicke in the streetes, &amp; besought him that they might
touch if it were but the border of his garment: and as many as
touched him, were made whole.<note> Or, it.</note></ab>



</div>