<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-16-16-Luke.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 An Angel declareth the
resurrection of Christ to three women. 9 Christ himselfe appeareth
to Mary Magdalene: 12 to two going into the countrey: 14 then, to
the Apostles, 15 whom he sendeth foorth to preach the Gospel: 19
and ascendeth into heauen.</head>

<ab n="1">And when the
Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of Iames, and
Salome, had bought sweete spices, that they might come and anoint
him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And very early
in the morning, the first day of the week they came vnto the
sepulchre, at the rising of the sunne:<note> Luk. 24. 1 ioh. 20. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And they said
among themselues, who shall roll vs away the stone from the doore
of the sepulchre?</ab>
<ab n="4">(And when they
looked, they saw that the stone was rolled away) for it was very
great.</ab>
<ab n="5">And entring
into the sepulchre, they sawe a young man sitting on the right
side, clothed in a long white garment, and they were
affrighted.<note> Iohn 20. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And hee sayth
vnto them, Be not affrighted; ye seeke Iesus of Nazareth, which was
crucified: he is risen, hee is not here: behold the place where
they laide him.</ab>
<ab n="7">But goe your
way, tell his disciples, and Peter, that hee goeth before you into
Galile, there shall ye see him, as he said vnto you.<note> Mat.26. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And they went
out quickely, and fledde from the sepulchre, for they trembled, and
were amazed, neither sayd they any thing to any man, for they were
afraid.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Now
when Iesus was risen early, the first day of the weeke, he appeared
first to Mary Magdalene, out of whom he had cast seuen
deuils.<note> Iohn 20. 14. , Luke 8. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And she went and
told them that had beene with him, as they mourned and
wept.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they, when they
had heard that he was aliue, and had beene seene of her, beleeued
not.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ After that,
he appeared in another forme vnto two of them, as they walked, and
went into the countrey.<note> Luke 24. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And they went and
tolde it vnto the residue, neither beleeued they them.</ab>

<fw>Vnbeliefe reproued.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ Afterward he
appeared vnto the eleuen, as they sate at meat, and vpbraided them
with their vnbeliefe, and hardnesse of heart, because they beleeued
not them, which had seene him after he was risen.<note> Luk. 24. 36. iohn 20 19. , Or, together.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he said vnto
them, Goe yee into all the world, and preach the Gospel to euery
creature.<note> Mat.28. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">He that beleeueth
and is baptized, shalbe saued, but he that beleeueth not, shall be
damned.<note> Ioh.12.48</note></ab>

<fw>Christs ascension.</fw>
<ab n="17">And these signes
shal follow them that beleeue, In my Name shall they cast out
deuils, they shall speake with new tongues,<note> Act. 16. 18 , Acts 2.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">They shall take vp
serpents, and if they drinke any deadly thing, it shall not hurt
them, they shall lay hands on the sicke, and they shall
recouer.<note> Act. 28.5. , Act. 28.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">¶ So then
after the Lord had spoken vnto them, he was receiued vp into
heauen, and sate on the right hand of God.<note> Luk. 24. 51.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And they went
foorth, and preached euery where, the Lord working with them, and
confirming the worde with signes following. Amen.<note> Heb.2.4.</note></ab>



</div>