<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 Christ feedeth the people
miraculously: 10 refuseth to giue a signe to the Pharisees: 14
admonisheth his disciples to beware of the leuen of the Pharisees,
and of the leuen of Herode: 22 giueth a blinde man his sight: 27
acknowledgeth that hee is the Christ, who should suffer and rise
againe: 34 and exhorteth to patience in persecution for the
profession of the Gospel.</head>


<fw>The multitude fed.</fw>
<ab n="1">In those dayes
the multitude being very great, and hauing nothing to eat. Iesus
called his disciples vnto him, &amp; saith vnto them,<note> Mat.15.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I haue
compassion on the multitude, because they haue now bene with me
three daies, and haue nothing to eat:</ab>
<ab n="3">And if I send
them away fasting to their owne houses, they will faint by the way:
for diuers of them came from farre.</ab>
<ab n="4">And his
disciples answered him, From whence can a man satisfie these men
with bread here in the wildernes?</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee asked
them, How many loaues haue ye? And they said, Seuen.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he
commanded the people to sit downe on the ground: and he tooke the
seuen loaues, and gaue thanks, and brake, and gaue to his disciples
to set before them: and they did set them before the
people.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they had a
few small fishes: and he blessed, and commaunded to set them also
before them.</ab>
<ab n="8">So they did
eate, and were filled: and they tooke vp, of the broken meate that
was left, seuen baskets.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they that
had eaten were about foure thousand, and he sent them away.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
straightway he entred into a ship with his disciples, and came into
the parts of Dalmanutha.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the
Pharisees came foorth, and began to question with him, seeking of
him a signe from heauen, tempting him.<note> Mat.16.1</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And he sighed
deepely in his spirit, and saith, Why doeth this generation seeke
after a signe? Uerely I say vnto you, There shall no signe be giuen
vnto this generation.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he left
them, &amp; entring into the ship againe, departed to the other
side.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Now the
disciples had forgotten to take bread, neither had they in the ship
with them more then one loafe.<note> Mat.16.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And hee
charged them, saying, Take heed, beware of the leauen of the
Pharisees, and of the leauen of Herode.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they
reasoned among themselues, saying, It is, because we haue no
bread.<note> Mat.16.7.</note></ab>

<fw>Peters confession.</fw>
<ab n="17">And when Iesus
knew it, he saith vnto them, Why reason ye, because yee haue no
bread? Perceiue ye not yet, neither vnderstand? Haue yee your heart
yet hardened?</ab>
<ab n="18">Hauing eyes,
see ye not? and hauing eares heare ye not? And doe ye not
remember?</ab>
<ab n="19">When I brake
the fiue loaues among fiue thousand, how many baskets full of
fragments tooke yee vp? They say vnto him, Twelue.</ab>
<ab n="20">And when the
seuen among foure thousand: how many baskets full of fragments
tooke ye vp? And they said, Seuen.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he said
vnto them, How is it that ye doe not vnderstand?</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And he
commeth to Bethsaida, and they bring a blind man vnto him, and
besought him to touch him:</ab>
<ab n="23">And he tooke
the blind man by the hand, and led him out of the towne, and when
he had spit on his eyes, &amp; put his hands vpon him, he asked
him, if hee saw ought.</ab>
<ab n="24">And he looked
vp, and saide, I see men as trees, walking.</ab>
<ab n="25">After that hee
put his handes againe vpon his eies, and made him look vp: and he
was restored, and saw euery man clearely.</ab>
<ab n="26">And hee sent
him away to his house, saying, Neither goe into the towne, nor tell
it to any in the towne.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And
Iesus went out, and his disciples, into the townes of Cesarea
Philippi: and by the way he asked his disciples, saying vnto them,
Whom doe men say that I am?<note> Mat.16.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And they
answered, Iohn the Baptist: but some say, Elias: &amp; others, one
of the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="29">And hee saith
vnto them, But whom say yee that I am? And Peter answereth and
saith vnto him, Thou art the Christ.</ab>
<ab n="30">And he charged
them that they should tell no man of him.</ab>
<ab n="31">And hee
beganne to teach them, that the Sonne of man must suffer many
things, and be reiected of the Elders, and of the chiefe Priests,
&amp; Scribes, and be killed, &amp; after three dayes rise
againe.</ab>
<ab n="32">And he spake
that saying openly. And Peter tooke him, and beganne to rebuke
him.</ab>
<ab n="33">But when he
had turned about, and looked on his disciples, he rebuked Peter,
saying, Get thee behind me, Satan: for thou sauourest not the
things that be of God, but the things that be of men.</ab>

<fw>The transfiguration.</fw>
<ab n="34">¶ And
when he had called the people vnto him, with his disciples also, he
said vnto them, Whosoeuer will come after me, let him denie
himselfe, and take vp his crosse and follow mee.<note> Matt.10. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">For whosoeuer
will saue his life shall lose it, but whosoeuer shall lose his life
for my sake and the Gospels, the same shall saue it.</ab>
<ab n="36">For what shall
it profit a man, if he shall gaine the whole world, and lose his
owne soule?</ab>
<ab n="37">Or what shall
a man giue in exchange for his soule?</ab>
<ab n="38">Whosoeuer
therefore shall be ashamed of me, and of my words, in this
adulterous and sinfull generation, of him also shall the Sonne of
man bee ashamed, when he commeth in the glory of his Father, with
the holy Angels.<note> Mat.10. 33.</note></ab>



</div>