<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 The generations of Noah. 2 The
sonnes of Iaphet. 6 The sonnes of Ham. 8 Nimrod the first Monarch.
21 The sonnes of Shem.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are the
generations of the sonnes of Noah; Shem, Ham, and Iaphet: and vnto
them were sonnes borne after the Flood.</ab>
<ab n="2">The sonnes of
Iaphet: Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Iauan, &amp; Tubal, and
Meshech, &amp; Tiras.<note> 1.Chron. 1.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the sonnes of
Gomer: Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the sons of
Iauan: Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim.</ab>
<ab n="5">By these were the
Iles of the Gentiles diuided in their lands, euery one after his
tongue: after their families, in their nations.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
sonnes of Ham: Cush, and Mizraim, and Phut, and Canaan.<note> 1.Chron. 1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And the sonnes of
Cush, Seba, and Hauilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabtecha: and
the sonnes of Raamah: Sheba, and Dedan.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Cush begat
Nimrod: he began to be a mighty one in the earth.</ab>

<fw>The first Monarch.</fw>
<ab n="9">He was a mighty
hunter before the LORD: wherefore it is saide, Euen as Nimrod the
mightie hunter before the LORD.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
beginning of his kingdome was Babel, and Erech, and Accad, and
Calneh, in the land of Shinar.<note> Gr. Babylon.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Out of that land
went forth Asshur, and builded Nineueh, and the citie Rehoboth, and
Calah,<note> Or, he went out into Assyria. , Or, the streetes of the Citie.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And Resen
betweene Nineueh and Calah: the same is a great citie.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Mizraim
begat Ludim, and Anamim, and Lehabim, and Naphtuhim,</ab>
<ab n="14">And Pathrusim,
and Casluhim (out of whome came Philistiim) and Caphtorim.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And
Canaan begate Sidon his first borne, and Heth,<note> Heb. Tzidon.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And the
Iebusite, and the Emorite, and the Girgasite,</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Hiuite,
and the Arkite, and the Sinite,</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
Aruadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite: and afterward were
the families of the Canaanites spread abroad.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the border
of the Canaanites, was from Sidon, as thou commest to Gerar, vnto
Gaza, as thou goest vnto Sodoma and Gomorah, and Admah, &amp;
Zeboim, euen vnto Lasha.<note> Hebr. Azzah.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">These are the
sonnes of Ham, after their families, after their tongues, in their
countries, and in their nations.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Unto Shem
also the father of all the children of Eber, the brother of Iaphet
the elder, euen to him were children borne.</ab>
<ab n="22">The children of
Shem: Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and
Aram.<note> 1.Chron. 1.17. , Hebr. Arpachshad.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the children
of Aram: Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Mash.</ab>
<ab n="24">And Arphaxad
begate Salah, and Salah begate Eber.<note> Hebr. Shelah.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And vnto Eber
were borne two sonnes: the name of one was Peleg, for in his dayes
was the earth diuided, and his brothers name was
Ioktan.<note> 1.Chron. 1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And Ioktan
begate Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaueth, and Ierah,</ab>
<ab n="27">And Hadoram, and
Uzal, and Diklah,</ab>
<ab n="28">And Obal, and
Abimael, and Sheba,</ab>
<ab n="29">And Ophir, and
Hauilah, &amp; Iobab: all these were the sonnes of Ioktan.</ab>

<fw>Babel builded.</fw>
<ab n="30">And their
dwelling was from Mesha, as thou goest vnto Sephar, a mount of the
East.</ab>
<ab n="31">These are the
sonnes of Shem, after their families, after their tongues, in their
lands after their nations.</ab>
<ab n="32">These are the
families of the sonnes of Noah after their generations, in their
nations: and by these were the nations diuided in the earth after
the Flood.</ab>



</div>