<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>2 Iesus is transfigured. 11 Hee
instructeth his disciples, concerning the comming of Elias: 14
casteth forth a dumbe, and deafe spirit: 30 foretelleth his death
and resurrection: 33 exhorteth his disciples to humilitie: 38
bidding them, not to prohibite such as be not against thē, nor
to giue offence to any of the faithfull.</head>

<ab n="1">And hee said
vnto them, Uerely I say vnto you, that there be some of them that
stand here, which shal not taste of death, till they haue seene the
kingdome of God come with power.<note> Mat.16. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ And
after sixe dayes, Iesus taketh with him Peter, and Iames, and Iohn,
and leadeth them vp into an high mountaine apart by themselues: and
he was transfigured before them.<note> Mat.17.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And his raiment
became shining, exceeding white as snow: so as no Fuller on earth
can white them.</ab>
<ab n="4">And there
appeared vnto them Elias with Moses: and they were talking with
Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Peter
answered, and saide to Iesus, Master, it is good for vs to bee
here, and let vs make three Tabernacles; one for thee, and one for
Moses, and one for Elias.</ab>
<ab n="6">For he wist not
what to say, for they were sore afraid.</ab>
<ab n="7">And there was a
cloud that ouershadowed them: and a voyce came out of the cloud,
saying, This is my beloued Sonne: heare him.</ab>

<fw>Elias is come.</fw>
<ab n="8">And suddenly
when they had looked round about, they saw no man any more, saue
Iesus only with themselues.</ab>
<ab n="9">And as they
came downe from the mountaine, he charged them that they should
tell no man, what things they had seene, till the Sonne of man were
risen from the dead.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they kept
that saying with themselues, questioning one with another, what the
rising from the dead should meane.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And
they asked him, saying, Why say the Scribes that Elias must first
come?</ab>
<ab n="12">And he
answered, and told them, Elias verely commeth first, and restoreth
al things, and how it is written of the Sonne of man, that he must
suffer many things, and be set at nought.<note> Esai.53.23</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But I say vnto
you, that Elias is indeed come, and they haue done vnto him
whatsoeuer they listed, as it is written of him.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
when he came to his disciples, he saw a great multitude about them,
and the Scribes questioning with them.<note> Mat.17. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And
straightway all the people, when they beheld him, were greatly
amazed, &amp; running to him, saluted him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he asked
the Scribes, What question ye with them?<note> Or, among your selues.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And one of the
multitude answered, and said, Master, I haue broughe vnto thee my
son, which hath a dumbe spirit:</ab>
<ab n="18">And
wheresoeuer he taketh him, he teareth him, &amp; he fometh, and
gnasheth with his teeth, and pineth away: and I spake to thy
disciples, that they should cast him out, and they could
not.<note> Or, dasheth him.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">He answereth
him, and saith, O faithlesse generation, how long shall I be with
you, how long shall I suffer you? Bring him vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="20">And they
brought him vnto him: and when he saw him, straightway the spirit
tare him, and he fel on the ground, and wallowed, foming.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he asked
his father, Howe long is it agoe since this came vnto him? And he
said, Of a child.</ab>
<ab n="22">And oft times
it hath cast him into the fire, and into the waters to destroy him:
but if thou canst doe any thing, haue compassion on vs, and helpe
vs.</ab>
<ab n="23">Iesus said
vnto him, If thou canst beleeue, all things are possible to him
that beleeueth.</ab>

<fw>Prayer and fasting.</fw>
<ab n="24">And
straightway the father of the child cried out and said with teares,
Lord, I beleeue, helpe thou mine vnbeliefe.</ab>
<ab n="25">When Iesus saw
that the people came running together, he rebuked the foule spirit,
saying vnto him, Thou dumbe and deafe spirit, I charge thee come
out of him, and enter no more into him.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the spirit
cried, and rent him sore, and came out of him, and he was as one
dead, insomuch that many said, He is dead.</ab>
<ab n="27">But Iesus
tooke him by the hand, and lifted him vp, and he arose.</ab>
<ab n="28">And when he
was come into the house, his disciples asked him priuately, Why
could not we cast him out?</ab>
<ab n="29">And hee said
vnto them, This kind can come forth by nothing, but by prayer, and
fasting.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ And
they departed thence, and passed through Galilee, and he would not
þt any man should know it.<note> Mat.17. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For he taught
his disciples, and said vnto them, The sonne of man is deliuered
into the hands of men, and they shall kill him, and after that he
is killed, he shall rise the third day.</ab>
<ab n="32">But they
vnderstood not that saying, and were afraid to aske him.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And he
came to Capernaum; and being in the house, he asked them, What was
it that yee disputed among your selues by the way?<note> Mat.18.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But they held
their peace: For by the way they had disputed among themselues, who
should be the greatest.</ab>
<ab n="35">And he sate
downe, and called the twelue, and saith vnto them, If any man
desire to be first, the same shall be last of all, and seruant of
all.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he tooke a
child, and set him in the midst of them: &amp; when he had taken
him in his arms, he said vnto them,</ab>
<ab n="37">Whosoeuer
shall receiue one of such children in my Name, receiueth me: and
whosoeuer shall receiue me, receiueth not me, but him that sent
me.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ And
Iohn answered him, saying, Master, we saw one casting out deuils in
thy Name, and he followeth not vs, and we forbade him, because he
followeth not vs.<note> Luke 9. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">But Iesus
said, Forbid him not, for there is no man, which shall doe a
miracle in my Name, that can lightly speake euill of
me.<note> 1.Cor.12. 3.</note></ab>

<fw>Auoid offences.</fw>
<ab n="40">For he that is
not against vs, is on our part.</ab>
<ab n="41">For whosoeuer
shall giue you a cup of water to drinke in my Name, because yee
belong to Christ: Uerily I say vnto you, he shall not lose his
reward.<note> Mat.10. 42.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And whosoeuer
shall offend one of these litle ones that beleeue in me, it is
better for him, that a milstone were hanged about his necke, and he
were cast into the Sea.<note> Mat.18. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And if thy
hand offend thee, cut it off: It is better for thee to enter into
life maimed, then hauing two hands, to goe into hell, into the fire
that neuer shall be quenched:<note> Mat.5.29 and 18.8. , Or, cause thee to offend.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">Where their
worme dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.<note> Esai.66. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And if thy
foote offend thee, cut it off: it is better for thee to enter halt
into life, then hauing two feete, to be cast into hell, into the
fire that neuer shall be quenched:</ab>
<ab n="46">Where their
worme dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</ab>
<ab n="47">And if thine
eye offend thee, pluck it out: it is better for thee to enter into
the kingdom of God with one eye, then hauing two eyes, to be cast
into helfire:<note> Or, cause thee to offend.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Where their
worme dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</ab>
<ab n="49">For euery one
shall be salted with fire, and euery sacrifice shall be salted with
salt.<note> Leuit.2. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">Salt is good:
but if the salt haue lost his saltnesse, wherewith will you season
it? Haue salt in your selues, and haue peace one with
another.<note> Mat.5.13.</note></ab>



</div>