<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Christ foretelleth the destruction
of the Temple: 9 the persecutions for the Gospel: 10 that the
Gospel must bee preached to all nations: 14 that great calamities
shall happen to the Iewes: 24 and the maner of his comming to
Iudgement: 32 The houre whereof, beeing knowen to none, euery man
is to watch and pray, that we be not found vnprouided, when he
commeth to each one particularly by death.</head>


<fw>Hated for Christ.</fw>
<ab n="1">And as he went
out of the Temple, one of his disciples saith vnto him, Master, see
what maner of stones, and what buildings are here.<note> Matth.24. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Iesus
answering, said vnto him, Seest thou these great buildings? there
shall not be left one stone vpon an other, that shal not be throwen
downe.</ab>
<ab n="3">And as he sate
vpon the mount of Oliues, ouer against the Temple, Peter, and
Iames, and Iohn, and Andrew asked him priuately,</ab>
<ab n="4">Tell vs, when
shall these things be? And what shalbe the signe when all these
things shalbe fulfilled?<note> Matth.24. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Iesus
answering them, began to say, Take heed lest any man deceiue
you.</ab>
<ab n="6">For many shal
come in my Name, saying, I am Christ: and shall deceiue
many.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when yee
shall heare of warres, and rumors of warres, be yee not troubled:
For such things must needs be, but the end shall not be
yet.</ab>
<ab n="8">For nation
shall rise against nation, and kingdome against kingdome: and there
shalbe earthquakes in diuers places, and there shall be famines,
and troubles: these are the beginnings of sorrowes.<note> The word in the originall, importeth, the paines of a woman in trauaile.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ But
take heed to your selues: for they shall deliuer you vp to
councels, and in the Synagogues ye shall be beaten, and ye shalbe
brought before rulers and kings for my sake, for a testimony
against them.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the Gospel must
first be published among all nations.</ab>
<ab n="11">But when they shall
lead you, and deliuer you vp, take no thought before hand what ye
shall speake, neither doe yee premeditate: but whatsoeuer shall bee
giuen you in that houre, that speake yee: for it is not yee that
speake, but the holy Ghost.<note> Matth.10. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Now the brother
shall betray the brother to death, and the father the sonne: and
children shall rise vp against their parents, and shall cause them
to be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="13">And ye shall bee
hated of all men for my Names sake: but hee that shall endure vnto
the ende, the same shall be saued.</ab>

<fw>False Christs.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ But when ye
shall see the abomination of desolation spoken of by Daniel the
Prophet, standing where it ought not (let him that readeth
vnderstand) then let them that be in Iudea, flee to the
mountaines:<note> Matt.24. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And let him that is
on the house top, not goe downe into the house, neither enter
therin, to take any thing out of his house.</ab>
<ab n="16">And let him that is
in the field, not turne backe againe for to take vp his
garment.</ab>
<ab n="17">But woe to them
that are with child, and to them that giue suck in those
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="18">And pray ye that
your flight bee not in the winter.</ab>
<ab n="19">For in those dayes
shall be affliction, such as was not from the beginning of the
creation which God created, vnto this time, neither shall
be.</ab>
<ab n="20">And except that the
Lord had shortened those dayes, no flesh should be saued: but for
the elects sake whome he hath chosen, he hath shortned the
daies.</ab>
<ab n="21">And then, if any
man shall say to you, Loe, here is Christ, or loe, hee is there:
beleeue him not.<note> Matt.24. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For false Christs
and false prophets shall rise, and shall shewe signes and wonders,
to seduce, if it were possible, euen the elect.</ab>
<ab n="23">But take ye heed:
behold, I haue foretold you all things.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ But in those
dayes, after that tribulation, the Sunne shalbe darkned, and the
Moone shall not giue her light.<note> Matt.24. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And the Starres of
heauen shall fall, and the powers that are in heauen shall be
shaken.</ab>
<ab n="26">And then shal they
see the Sonne of man comming in the cloudes, with great power and
glory.</ab>
<ab n="27">And then shal he
send his Angels, and shall gather together his elect from the foure
winds, from the vttermost part of the earth, to the vttermost part
of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="28">Now learne a
parable of the fig tree. When her branch is yet tender, and putteth
forth leaues, ye know that summer is neere:</ab>
<ab n="29">So ye in like
maner, when ye shal see these things come to passe, knowe that it
is nigh, euen at the doores.</ab>
<ab n="30">Uerely I say vnto
you, that this generation shall not passe, till all these things be
done.</ab>

<fw>Watch and pray.</fw>
<ab n="31">Heauen and earth
shal passe away: but my words shall not passe away.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ But of that
day and that houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels which are in
heauen, neither the Son, but the Father.</ab>
<ab n="33">Take ye heed, watch
and pray: for ye know not when the time is.<note> Mat.24.42</note></ab>
<ab n="34">For the Sonne of
man is as a man taking a farre iourney, who left his house, and
gaue authority to his seruants, and to euery man his worke, and
commanded the porter to watch:</ab>
<ab n="35">Watch ye therefore
(for ye knowe not when the master of the house commeth, at Euen, or
at midnight, or at the cocke crowing, or in the morning.)</ab>
<ab n="36">Lest comming
suddenly, he finde you sleeping.</ab>
<ab n="37">And what I say vnto
you, I say vnto all, Watch.</ab>



</div>