<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-2-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Christ healeth one sicke of the
palsie, 14 calleth Matthew from the receit of Custome, 15 eateth
with Publicanes, and sinners, 18 excuseth his disciples for not
fasting, 23 and for plucking the eares of corne on the Sabbath
day.</head>


<fw>Sinnes forgiuen.</fw>
<ab n="1">And againe hee
entred into Capernaum after some dayes, and it was noysed that he
was in the house.<note> Matt. 9.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And straightway
many were gathered together, insomuch that there was no roome to
receiue them, no not so much as about the doore: and he preached
the word vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they come
vnto him, bringing one sicke of the palsie, which was borne of
foure.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when they
could not come nigh vnto him for preasse, they vncouered the roofe
where he was: and when they had broken it vp, they let downe the
bed wherin the sick of the palsie lay.</ab>
<ab n="5">When Iesus saw
their faith, hee said vnto the sicke of the palsie, Sonne, thy
sinnes be forgiuen thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">But there were
certaine of the Scribes sitting there, and reasoning in their
hearts,</ab>
<ab n="7">Why doeth this
man thus speake blasphemies? Who can forgiue sinnes but God
onely?<note> Iob 14.4. esay 43.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And immediatly,
when Iesus perceiued in his Spirit, that they so reasoned within
themselues, he said vnto them, Why reason ye these things in your
hearts?</ab>
<ab n="9">Whether is it
easier to say to the sicke of the palsie, Thy sinnes be forgiuen
thee: or to say, Arise, and take vp thy bed and walke?</ab>
<ab n="10">But that yee
may know that the Sonne of man hath power on earth to forgiue
sinnes, (Hee saith to the sicke of the palsie,)</ab>
<ab n="11">I say vnto
thee, Arise, &amp; take vp thy bed, &amp; goe thy way into thine
house.</ab>
<ab n="12">And immediatly
he arose, tooke vp the bed, and went foorth before them all,
insomuch that they were all amazed, and glorified God, saying, Wee
neuer saw it on this fashion.</ab>
<ab n="13">And he went
foorth againe by the sea side, and all the multitude resorted vnto
him, and he taught them.</ab>
<ab n="14">And as he
passed by, he saw Leui the son of Alpheus sitting at the receit of
Custome, and said vnto him, Follow me. And he arose, and followed
him.<note> Matt. 9.9. , Or, at the place where the Custome are receive,</note></ab>

<fw>When to fast.</fw>
<ab n="15">And it came to
passe, that as Iesus sate at meate in his house, many Publicanes
and sinners sate also together with Iesus and his disciples: for
there were many, &amp; they followed him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when the
Scribes and Pharisees saw him eate with Publicanes and sinners,
they said vnto his disciples, How is it that hee eateth and
drinketh with Publicanes and sinners?</ab>
<ab n="17">When Iesus
heard it, he saith vnto them, They that are whole, haue no need of
the Physition, but they that are sicke: I came not to call the
righteous, but sinners to repentance.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
disciples of Iohn, and of the Pharisees vsed to fast; and they
come, and say vnto him, Why doe the disciples of Iohn, and of the
Pharisees fast, but thy disciples fast not?<note> Matth. 9.14 luke 5.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Iesus said
vnto them, Can the children of the bride-chamber fast, while the
Bridegrome is with them? As long as they haue the Bridegrome with
them, they cannot fast.</ab>
<ab n="20">But the dayes
will come, when the Bridegrome shall bee taken away from them, and
then shall they fast in those dayes.</ab>
<ab n="21">No man also
soweth a piece of new cloth on an old garment: else the new piece
that filled it vp, taketh away from the old, &amp; the rent is made
worse.<note> Or, raw, or vnwrought.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And no man
putteth new wine into old bottles, else the new wine doeth burst
the bottles, and the wine is spilled, and the bottles will bee
marred: But new wine must bee put into new bottles.</ab>
<ab n="23">And it came to
passe, that he went thorow the corne fields on the Sabbath day,
&amp; his disciples began as they went, to plucke the eares of
corne.<note> Matt. 12.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the
Pharisees saide vnto him, Behold, why do they on the Sabbath day
that which is not lawfull?</ab>
<ab n="25">And he said
vnto them, Haue ye neuer read what Dauid did, when hee had need,
and was an hungred, he, and they that were with him?</ab>
<ab n="26">How hee went
into the house of God in the dayes of Abiathar the high Priest, and
did eate the Shew-bread, which is not lawfull to eate, but for the
Priests, and gaue also to them which were with him?</ab>
<ab n="27">And hee said
vnto them, The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the
Sabbath:</ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore the
Sonne of man is Lord also of the Sabbath.</ab>



</div>