<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-28-28-Mark.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The office of Iohn the Baptist. 9
Iesus is baptized, 12 tempted, 14 he preacheth: 16 calleth Peter,
Andrew, Iames and Iohn: 23 healeth one that had a deuill, 29 Peters
mother in law, 32 many diseased persons, 41 and cleanseth the
Leper.</head>

<ab n="1">The beginning
of the Gospel of Iesus Christ, the Sonne of God,</ab>
<ab n="2">As it is
written in the Prophets, Behold, I send my messenger before thy
face, which shall prepare thy way before thee.<note> Esa. 40.3. luke 3.4. iohn 1.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The voice of
one crying in the wildernesse, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make
his paths straight.<note> Matt. 3.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Iohn did
baptize in the wildernesse, and preach the baptisme of repentance,
for the remission of sinnes.<note> Or, vnto. , Matt. 3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And there went
out vnto him all the land of Iudea, and they of Ierusalem, and were
all baptized of him in the riuer of Iordane, cōfessing their
sinnes.<note> Mark. 16.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Iohn was
clothed with camels haire, and with a girdle of a skin about his
loines: and he did eat locusts and wilde honie,<note> Matt. 3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And preached,
saying, There commeth one mightier then I after me, the latchet of
whose shooes I am not worthy to stoupe downe, and vnloose.</ab>
<ab n="8">I indeed haue
baptized you with water: but hee shall baptize you with the holy
Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="9">And it came to
passe in those daies, that Iesus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and
was baptized of Iohn in Iordane.<note> Matth. 3.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And
straightway comming vp out of the water, hee saw the heauens
opened, and the Spirit like a doue descending vpon him.<note> Or, clouen, or rent.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And there came
a voice from heauen, saying, Thou art my beloued Sonne, in whom I
am well pleased.</ab>
<ab n="12">And
immediately the Spirit driueth him into the
wildernesse.<note> Matt. 4.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And he was
there in the wildernesse fourtie daies tempted of Satan, and was
with the wildbeasts, and the Angels ministred vnto him.</ab>

<fw>Simon called.</fw>
<ab n="14">Now after that
Iohn was put in prison, Iesus came into Galilee, preaching the
Gospell of the kingdome of God,<note> Matth.4.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And saying,
The time is fulfilled, and the kingdome of God is at hand: repent
ye, and beleeue the Gospell.</ab>
<ab n="16">Now as he
walked by the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon, and Andrew his brother,
casting a net into the Sea (for they were fishers.)<note> Matth.4.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Iesus said
vnto them, Come ye after me; and I will make you to become fishers
of men.</ab>
<ab n="18">And
straightway they forsooke their nets, and followed him.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when hee
had gone a little further thence, hee saw Iames the sonne of
Zebedee, and Iohn his brother, who also were in the ship mending
their nets.</ab>
<ab n="20">And
straightway he called them: and they left their father Zebedee in
the ship with the hired seruants, and went after him.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they went
into Capernaum, and straightway on the Sabbath day he entred into
the Synagogue, and taught.<note> Matth.4.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And they were
astonished at his doctrine: for hee taught them as one that had
authority, and not as the Scribes.<note> Matth.7.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And there was
in their Synagogue a man with an vncleane spirit, and he cried
out,<note> Luke 4.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Saying, Let vs
alone, what haue we to doe with thee, thou Iesus of Nazareth? Art
thou come to destroy vs? I know thee who thou art, the holy One of
God.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Iesus
rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace, and come out of him.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when the
vncleane spirit had torne him, and cried with a lowd voice, he came
out of him.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they were
all amased, insomuch that they questioned among themselues, saying,
What thing is this? What new doctrine is this? For with authoritie
commandeth he euen the vncleane spirits, and they doe obey
him.</ab>
<ab n="28">And immediatly
his fame spread abroad throughout al the region round about
Galilee.</ab>
<ab n="29">And forth
with, when they were come out of the Synagogue, they entered into
the house of Simon, and Andrew, with Iames and Iohn.<note> Matth.8.14.</note></ab>

<fw>A leper clensed.</fw>
<ab n="30">But Simons
wiues mother lay sicke of a feuer: and anone they tell him of
her.</ab>
<ab n="31">And he came
and tooke her by the hand, and lift her vp, and immediately the
feuer left her, and she ministred vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="32">And at euen,
when the Sunne did set, they brought vnto him all that were
diseased, and them that were possessed with diuels:</ab>
<ab n="33">And all the
citie was gathered together at the doore.</ab>
<ab n="34">And he healed
many that were sicke of diuers diseases, and cast out many deuils,
and suffered not the deuils to speake, because they knew
him.<note> Or, to say that they knew him.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And in the
morning, rising vp a great while before day, hee went out, and
departed into a solitarie place, and there prayed.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Simon, and
they that were with him, followed after him:</ab>
<ab n="37">And when they
had found him, they said vnto him, All men seek for thee.</ab>
<ab n="38">And he said
vnto them, Let vs goe into þe next townes, that I
may preach there also: for therefore came I foorth.</ab>
<ab n="39">And he
preached in their Synagogues throughout all Galilee, and cast out
deuils.</ab>
<ab n="40">And there came
a leper to him, beseeching him, and kneeling downe to him, and
saying vnto him, If thou wilt, thou canst make me
cleane.<note> Matth.8.2</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And Iesus
mooued with compassion, put foorth his hand, and touched him, and
saith vnto him, I will, be thou cleane.</ab>
<ab n="42">And assoone as
he had spoken, immediately the leprosie departed from him, and he
was cleansed.</ab>
<ab n="43">And he
straitly charged him, and forth with sent him away,</ab>
<ab n="44">And saith vnto
him, See thou say nothing to any man: but goe thy way, shew thy
selfe to the Priest, and offer for thy clensing those things which
Moses commanded, for a testimony vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="45">But he went
out, and beganne to publish it much, and to blase abroad the
matter: insomuch that Iesus could no more openly enter into the
citie, but was without in desert places: and they came to him from
euery quarter.<note> Luke 5.15.</note></ab>



</div>