<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMark_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Mark-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 Christ rideth with triumph into
Hierusalem: 12 curseth the fruitlesse leafie tree: 15 purgeth the
Temple: 20 exhorteth his disciples to stedfastnesse of faith, and
to forgiue their enemies: 27 and defendeth the lawfulnes of his
actions, by the witnesse of Iohn, who was a man sent of
God.</head>

<ab n="1">And when they
came nigh to Hierusalem, vnto Bethphage, and Bethanie, at the mount
of Oliues, hee sendeth foorth two of his disciples,<note> Matth.21. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And saith vnto
them, Goe your way into the village ouer against you, and assoone
as ye bee entred into it, yee shall finde a colt tied, whereon
neuer man sate, loose him, and bring him.</ab>
<ab n="3">And if any man
say vnto you, Why doe yee this? Say yee, that the Lord hath need of
him: and straightway he will send him hither.</ab>
<ab n="4">And they went
their way, and found the colt tied by the doore without, in a place
where two wayes met: and they loose him.</ab>
<ab n="5">And certaine
of them that stood there, said vnto them, What doe ye loosing the
colt?</ab>
<ab n="6">And they said
vnto them euen as Iesus had commanded: and they let them
goe.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they
brought the colt to Iesus, and cast their garments on him, and he
sate vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="8">And many
spread their garments in the way: and others cut downe branches of
the trees, and strawed them in the way.</ab>

<fw>A figtree cursed.</fw>
<ab n="9">And they that
went before, and they that followed, cryed, saying, Hosanna,
blessed is hee that commeth in the Name of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="10">Blessed be the
kingdome of our father Dauid, that commeth in the Name of the Lord,
Hosanna in the highest.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Iesus entred
into Hierusalem, and into the Temple, and when hee had looked round
about vpon all things, &amp; now the euentide was come, he went out
vnto Bethanie with the twelue.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And on the
morow when they were come from Bethanie, hee was hungry.</ab>
<ab n="13">And seeing a
figtree a farre off, hauing leaues, hee came, if haply hee might
find any thing thereon, &amp; when he came to it, hee found nothing
but leaues: for the time of figs was not yet.<note> Matt.21. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Iesus answered,
and said vnto it, No man eate fruite of thee hereafter for euer.
And his disciples heard it.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And they
come to Hierusalem, and Iesus went into the Temple, and beganne to
cast out them that sold and bought in the Temple, and ouerthrew the
tables of the money changers, and the seats of them that sold
doues,<note> Matt.21. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And would not
suffer that any man should carie any vessell thorow the
Temple.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he taught,
saying vnto them, Is it not written, My house shalbe called of all
nations the house of prayer? but ye haue made it a den of
theeues.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Scribes and
chiefe Priests heard it, and sought how they might destroy him: for
they feared him, because all the people was astonished at his
doctrine.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when Euen was
come, Hee went out of the citie.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And in the
morning, as they passed by, they saw the fig tree dried vp from the
roots.<note> Matt.21. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Peter calling
to remembrance saith vnto him, Master, behold, the fig tree which
thou cursedst, is withered away.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Iesus
answering, saith vnto them, Haue faith in God.<note> Or, haue the faith of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For verely I say
vnto you, that whosoeuer shall say vnto this mountaine, Bee thou
remoued, and bee thou cast into the sea, and shall not doubt in his
heart, but shall beleeue that those things which hee saith, shall
come to passe: he shal haue whatsoeuer he saith.</ab>

<fw>Of forgiuenesse.</fw>
<ab n="24">Therfore I say vnto
you, What things soeuer ye desire when ye pray, beleeue that ye
receiue them, and ye shall haue them.<note> Matt.7.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And when ye stand,
praying, forgiue, if ye haue ought against any: that your Father
also which is in heauen, may forgiue you your
trespasses.<note> Mat.6.14</note></ab>
<ab n="26">But if you doe not
forgiue, neither will your Father which is in heauen, forgiue your
trespasses.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And they
come againe to Hierusalem, and as he was walking in the Temple,
there come to him the chiefe Priests, and the Scribes, &amp; the
Elders,<note> Matt.21. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And say vnto him,
By what authoritie doest thou these things? and who gaue thee this
authority to doe these things?</ab>
<ab n="29">And Iesus answered,
and saide vnto them, I will also aske of you one question, and
answere me, and I will tell you by what authoritie I doe these
things.<note> Or, thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The baptisme of
Iohn, was it from heauen, or of men? Answere me.</ab>
<ab n="31">And they reasoned
with themselues, saying, If we shall say, From heauen, he will say,
Why then did ye not beleeue him?</ab>
<ab n="32">But if we shall
say, Of men, they feared the people: for all men counted Iohn, that
he was a Prophet indeed.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they answered
and said vnto Iesus, We cannot tell. And Iesus answering, saith
vnto them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I doe these
things.</ab>



</div>