<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>2 Christ clenseth the leper, 5
healeth the Centurions seruant, 14 Peters mother in lawe, 16 and
many other diseased: 18 Sheweth how he is to be followed: 23
stilleth the tempest on the Sea, 28 driueth the deuils out of two
men possessed, 31 and suffereth them to goe into the
swine.</head>

<ab n="1">When he was come
downe from the Mountaine, great multitudes folowed him.</ab>

<fw>The Centurion.</fw>
<ab n="2">And behold, there
came a leper, and worshipped him, saying, Lord, If thou wilt, thou
canst make me cleane.<note> Mar.1.40. luke 5.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Iesus put
forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will, bee thou cleane.
And immediately his leprosie was cleansed.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iesus saith
vnto him, See thou tell no man, but go thy way, shew thy selfe to
the priest, and offer the gift that Moses commanded, for a
testimonie vnto them.<note> Leui.14.4</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And when
Iesus was entred into Capernaum, there came vnto him a Centurion,
beseeching him,<note> Luke 7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And saying, Lord,
my seruant lieth at home sicke of the palsie, grieuously
tormented.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Iesus saith
vnto him, I will come, and heale him.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Centurion
answered, and said, Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldest come
vnder my roofe: but speake the word onely, and my seruant shalbe
healed.</ab>
<ab n="9">For I am a man
vnder authority, hauing souldiers vnder me: and I say to this man,
Goe, and he goeth: and to another, Come, and he commeth: and to my
seruant, Doe this, and he doth it.</ab>
<ab n="10">When Iesus heard
it, he marueiled, and said to them that followed, Uerely, I say
vnto you, I haue not found so great faith, no not in
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I say vnto
you, that many shall come from the East and West, and shal sit
downe with Abraham, and Isaac, &amp; Iacob, in the kingdome of
heauen:</ab>
<ab n="12">But the children
of the kingdome shall be cast out into outer darkenesse: there
shalbe weeping and gnashing of teeth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Iesus said
vnto the Centurion, Go thy way, and as thou hast beleeued, so be it
done vnto thee. And his seruant was healed in the self same
houre.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And when
Iesus was come into Peters house, hee saw his wiues mother laid,
and sicke of a feuer:<note> Mar.1.29 luke 4.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he touched
her hand, and the feuer left her: and she arose, and ministred vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ When the
Euen was come, they brought vnto him many that were possessed with
deuils: and hee cast out the spirits with his worde, and healed all
that were sicke,<note> Mar.1.32. luke 4.40.</note></ab>

<fw>Swine drowned.</fw>
<ab n="17">That it might be
fulfilled which which was spoken by Esaias the Prophet, saying,
Himselfe tooke our infirmities, and bare our
sicknesses.<note> Esai.53.4. 1.pet.2.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Now when
Iesus saw great multitudes about him, hee gaue commaundement to
depart vnto the other side.</ab>
<ab n="19">And a certaine
Scribe came, and said vnto him, Master, I will follow thee
whithersoeuer thou goest.<note> Luke 9.57.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Iesus saith
vnto him, The Foxes haue holes, and the birds of the ayre haue
nests: but the sonne of man hath not where to lay his head.</ab>
<ab n="21">And another of
his Disciples said vnto him, Lord, suffer me first to goe, and bury
my father.</ab>
<ab n="22">But Iesus said
vnto him, Follow me, &amp; let the dead, bury their dead.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And when
he was entred into a ship, his Disciples followed him.</ab>
<ab n="24">And behold, there
arose a great tempest in the Sea, insomuch that the ship was
couered with the waues: but he was asleepe.<note> Marke.4.37. luke 8.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And his Disciples
came to him, and awoke, saying, Lord, saue vs: we perish.</ab>
<ab n="26">And he saith vnto
them, Why are yee fearefull, O yee of litle faith? Then hee arose,
and rebuked the winds and the Sea, and there was a great
calme.</ab>
<ab n="27">But the men
marueiled, saying, What maner of man is this, that euen the winds
and the Sea obey him?</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ And when
hee was come to the other side, into the countrey of the
Gergesenes, there met him two possessed with deuils, comming out of
the tombes, exceeding fierce, so that no man might passe by that
way.<note> Marke 5.1. luk. 8.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And behold, they
cryed out, saying, What haue we to doe with thee, Iesus thou sonne
of God? Art thou come hither to torment vs befor þ<note/>
time?</ab>
<ab n="30">And there was a
good way off from them, an heard of many swine, feeding.</ab>
<ab n="31">So the deuils
besought him, saying, If thou cast vs out, suffer vs to goe away
into the herd of swine.</ab>
<ab n="32">And he said vnto
them, Goe. And when they were come out, they went into the herd of
swine: and behold, the whole herd of swine ranne violently downe a
steepe place into the Sea, and perished in the waters.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they that
kept them, fled, and went their waies into the citie, and told
euery thing, and what was befallen to the possessed of the
deuils.</ab>

<fw>Matthew called.</fw>
<ab n="34">And behold, the
whole citie came out to meete Iesus: and when they saw him, they
besought him that hee would depart out of their coasts.</ab>



</div>