<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 The transfiguration of Christ. 14
He healeth the lunatike, 22 foretelleth his owne passion, 24 and
payeth tribute.</head>

<ab n="1">And after sixe
dayes, Iesus taketh Peter, Iames, and Iohn his brother, and
bringeth them vp into an high mountaine apart,<note> Mark. 9.2. luke 9.28.</note></ab>

<fw>Elias is come.</fw>
<ab n="2">And was
transfigured before them, and his face did shine as the Sunne, and
his raiment was white as the light.</ab>
<ab n="3">And behold, there
appeared vnto them Moses, and Elias, talking with him.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then answered
Peter, and saide vnto Iesus, Lord, it is good for vs to be here: If
thou wilt, let vs make here three tabernacles: one for thee, and
one for Moses, and one for Elias.</ab>
<ab n="5">While he yet
spake, behold, a bright cloud ouershadowed them: and behold a voyce
out of the cloude, which saide, This is my beloued sonne, in whom I
am well pleased: heare ye him.<note> 2.Pet.1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And when the
disciples heard it, they fell on their face, and were sore
afraid.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Iesus came
and touched them, and said, Arise, and be not afraid.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when they had
lift vp their eyes, they saw no man, saue Iesus only.</ab>
<ab n="9">And as they came
downe from the mountaine, Iesus charged them, saying, Tell the
vision to no man, vntil the sonne of man bee risen againe from the
dead.</ab>
<ab n="10">And his
disciples asked him, saying, Why then say the Scribes that Elias
must first come?<note> Chap.11.14. mark.9.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Iesus
answered, and said vnto them, Elias truely shall first come, and
restore all things:</ab>
<ab n="12">But I say vnto
you, that Elias is come already, and they knew him not, but haue
done vnto him whatsoeuer they listed: Likewise shall also the Son
of man suffer of them.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then the
Disciples vnderstood that he spake vnto them of Iohn the
Baptist.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And when
they were come to the multitude, there came to him a certaine man,
kneeling downe to him, and saying,<note> Mar.9.17. luke 9.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Lord, haue
mercie on my sonne, for he is lunatike, and sore vexed: for oft
times he falleth into the fire, and oft into the water.</ab>
<ab n="16">And I brought
him to thy disciples, and they could not cure him.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then Iesus
answered, and said, O faithlesse and peruerse generation, how long
shall I bee with you? howe long shal I suffer you? bring him hither
to me.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Iesus
rebuked the deuill, and hee departed out of him: and the childe was
cured from that very houre.</ab>

<fw>Tribute paid.</fw>
<ab n="19">Then came the
Disciples to Iesus apart, and said, Why could not we cast him
out?</ab>
<ab n="20">And Iesus said
vnto them, Because of your vnbeliefe: for verily I say vnto you, If
yee haue faith as a graine of mustard seed, yee shall say vnto this
mountaine; Remoue hence to yonder place: and it shall remoue, and
nothing shall be vnpossible vnto you.<note> luke 17.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Howbeit, this
kind goeth not out, but by prayer and fasting.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And while
they abode in Galilee, Iesus said vnto them, The sonne of man shall
be betraied into the hands of men:<note> Mat. 20.17. mar. 9.31. luke 9.44.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And they shall
kill him, and the third day he shall be raised againe: And they
were exceeding sorie.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ And when
they were come to Capernaum, they that receiued tribute money, came
to Peter, and said, Doeth not your master pay tribute?<note> Called in the originall Dadrachma, being in valew fifteene pence.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Hee saith, Yes.
And when hee was come into the house, Iesus preuented him, saying,
What thinkest thou, Simon? of whom doe the kings of the earth take
custome or tribute? of their owne children, or of
strangers?</ab>
<ab n="26">Peter saith vnto
him, Of strangers. Iesus saith vnto him, Then are the children
free.</ab>
<ab n="27">Notwithstanding,
least we should offend them, goe thou to the Sea, and cast an
hooke, and take vp the fish that first commeth vp: and when thou
hast opened his mouth, thou shalt find a piece of money: that take,
and giue vnto them for me, and thee.<note> Or, a stater. It is halfe an ounce of silver, in valew two shillings sixe pence, after fiue shillings the ounce.</note></ab>



</div>