<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-27-27.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 Christ is deliuered bound to
Pilate. 3 Iudas hangeth himselfe. 19 Pilate admonished of his wise,
24 washeth his hands: 26 and looseth Barabbas. 29 Christ is crowned
with thornes, 34 crucified, 40 reuiled, 50 dieth, and is buried: 66
his Sepulchre is sealed, and watched.</head>

<ab n="1">When the morning
was come, all the chiefe Priests and Elders of the people, tooke
counsell against Iesus to put him to death.<note> Mark. 15.1. luke 22.66. ioh. 18.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And when they had
bound him, they led him away, and deliuered him to Pontius Pilate
the gouernour.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ Then
Iudas, which had betraied him, when he saw that hee was condemned,
repented himselfe, and brought againe the thirtie pieces of siluer
to the chiefe Priests and Elders,</ab>
<ab n="4">Saying, I haue
sinned, in that I haue betraied the innocent blood. And they said,
What is that to vs? see thou to that.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee cast
downe the pieces of siluer in the Temple, and departed, and went
and hanged himselfe.<note> Act. 1.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the chiefe
Priests tooke the siluer pieces, and said, It is not lawfull for to
put them into the treasurie, because it is the price of
blood.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they tooke
counsell, and bought with them the potters field, to burie
strangers in.</ab>
<ab n="8">Wherefore that
field was called, The field of blood vnto this day.<note> Acts. 1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">(Then was
fulfilled that which was spoken by Ieremie the Prophet, saying, And
they tooke the thirtie pieces of siluer, the price of him that was
valued, whom they of the children of Israel did value:<note> Zach. 11.12. , Or, whom they bought of the children of Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And gaue them
for the potters field, as the Lord appointed me.)</ab>

<fw>Barabbas released.</fw>
<ab n="11">And Iesus stood
before the gouernour, and the gouernour asked him, saying; Art thou
the King of the Iewes? And Iesus sayd vnto him, Thou
sayest.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when hee was
accused of the chiefe Priests and Elders, he answered
nothing.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then saith
Pilate vnto him, Hearest thou not how many things they witnesse
against thee?</ab>
<ab n="14">And he answered
him to neuer a word: insomuch that the Gouernour marueiled
greatly.</ab>
<ab n="15">Now at that
feast the Gouernor was woont to release vnto the people a prisoner,
whom they would.<note> Luke 23.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And they had
then a notable prisoner, called Barabbas.</ab>
<ab n="17">Therefore when
they were gathered together, Pilate said vnto them, Whom will ye
that I release vnto you? Barabbas, or Iesus, which is called
Christ?</ab>
<ab n="18">For hee knew
that for enuie they had deliuered him.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ When he
was set downe on the Iudgement seate, his wife sent vnto him,
saying, Haue thou nothing to doe with that iust man: for I haue
suffered many things this day in a dreame, because of him.</ab>
<ab n="20">But the chiefe
Priestes and Elders perswaded the multitude that they should aske
Barabbas, &amp; destroy Iesus.<note> Iohn 18.40. actes 3.14</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The Gouernour
answered, and said vnto them, Whether of the twaine will ye that I
release vnto you? They said, Barabbas.</ab>
<ab n="22">Pilate said vnto
them, What shall I doe then with Iesus, which is called Christ?
They all sayde vnto him, Let him be crucified.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the
Gouernour said, Why, what euil hath he done? But they cried out
þe more, saying, Let him be crucified.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ When
Pilate saw that he could preuaile nothing, but that rather a tumult
was made, hee tooke water, and washed his hands before the
multitude, saying, I am innocent of the blood of this iust person:
see yee to it.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then answered
all the people, and said, His blood be on vs, and on our
children.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Then
released hee Barabbas vnto them, and when he had scourged Iesus, he
deliuered him to be crucified.</ab>
<ab n="27">Then the
souldiers of the Gouernour tooke Iesus into the common hall, and
gathered vnto him the whole band of souldiers.<note> Ioh. 19.1. , Or, gouernours house.</note></ab>

<fw>Christ crucified.</fw>
<ab n="28">And they
stripped him, and put on him a scarlet robe.</ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And when
they had platted a crowne of thornes, they put it vpon his head,
and a reed in his right hand: and they bowed the knee before him,
and mocked him, saying, Haile king of the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="30">And they spit
vpon him, and tooke the reed, and smote him on the head.</ab>
<ab n="31">And after that
they had mocked him, they tooke the robe off from him, and put his
owne raiment on him, and led him away to crucifie him.</ab>
<ab n="32">And as they came
out, they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name: him they compelled
to beare his Crosse.<note> Marke 15.21. luke 23.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And when they
were come vnto a place called Golgotha, that is to say, a place of
a skull,<note> Iohn 19.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">¶ They gaue
him vineger to drinke, mingled with gall: and when hee had tasted
thereof, hee would not drinke.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they
crucified him, and parted his garments, casting lots: that it might
be fulfilled which was spoken by the Prophet, They parted my
garments among them, and vpon my vesture did they cast
lots.<note> Psal. 22.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And sitting
downe, they watched him there:</ab>
<ab n="37">And set vp ouer
his head, his accusation written, THIS IS IESVS THE KING OF THE
IEWES.</ab>
<ab n="38">Then were there
two theeues crucified with him: one on the right hand, and another
on the left.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ And they
that passed by, reuiled him, wagging their heads,</ab>
<ab n="40">And saying, Thou
that destroyest the Temple, &amp; buildest it in three dayes, saue
thy selfe: If thou be the Sonne of God, come downe from the
Crosse.</ab>
<ab n="41">Likewise also
the chiefe Priests mocking him, with the Scribes and Elders,
said,</ab>
<ab n="42">He saued others,
himselfe he cannot saue: If he be the King of Israel, let him now
come downe from the Crosse, and we will beleeue him.</ab>
<ab n="43">He trusted in
God, let him deliuer him now if hee will haue him: for he said, I
am the Sonne of God.<note> Psal. 22.8. wisd. 2.15, 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">The thieues also
which were crucified with him, cast þe same in his
teeth.</ab>
<ab n="45">Now from the
sixth houre there was darkenesse ouer all the land vnto the ninth
houre.</ab>

<fw>Christs death, and
resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="46">And about the
ninth houre, Iesus cried with a loud voyce, saying, Eli, Eli,
Lamasabachthani, that is to say, My God, my God, why hast thou
forsaken mee?<note> Psal. 22.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">Some of them
that stood there, when they heard that, said, This man calleth for
Elias.</ab>
<ab n="48">And straightway
one of them ran, and tooke a spunge, and filled it with vineger,
and put it on a reede, and gaue him to drinke.<note> Psa.69.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">The rest said,
Let bee, let vs see whether Elias will come to saue him.</ab>
<ab n="50">¶ Iesus,
when hee had cried againe with a loud voice, yeelded vp the
ghost.</ab>
<ab n="51">And behold, the
vaile of the Temple was rent in twaine, from the top to the
bottome, and the earth did quake, and the rocks rent.</ab>
<ab n="52">And the graues
were opened, and many bodies of Saints which slept, arose,</ab>
<ab n="53">And came out of
the graues after his resurrection, and went into the holy citie,
and appeared vnto many.</ab>
<ab n="54">Now when the
Centurion, and they that were with him, watching Iesus, saw the
earthquake, &amp; those things that were done, they feared greatly,
saying, Truely this was the Son of God.</ab>
<ab n="55">And many women
were there (beholding afarre off) which followed Iesus from
Galilee, ministring vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="56">Among which was
Mary Magdalene, &amp; Mary the mother of Iames and Ioses, and the
mother of Zebedees children.</ab>
<ab n="57">When the Euen
was come, there came a rich man of Arimathea, named Ioseph, who
also himselfe was Iesus disciple:<note> Mar.15.42. luk.23.50. ioh. 19.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">He went to
Pilate, and begged the body of Iesus: then Pilate commanded the
body to be deliuered.</ab>
<ab n="59">And when Ioseph
had taken the body, hee wrapped it in a cleane linnen
cloth,</ab>
<ab n="60">And laide it in
his owne newe tombe, which he had hewen out in the rocke: and he
rolled a great stone to the doore of the sepulchre, and
departed.</ab>
<ab n="61">And there was
Mary Magdalene, and the other Mary, sitting ouer against the
sepulchre.</ab>

<fw>Christs death, and
resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="62">¶ Now the
next day that followed the day of the preparation, the chiefe
Priests and Pharisees came together vnto Pilate,</ab>
<ab n="63">Saying, Sir, we
remember that that deceiuer said, while he was yet aliue, After
three daies I wil rise againe.</ab>
<ab n="64">Command therfore
that the sepulchre be made sure, vntill the third day, lest his
disciples come by night, &amp; steale him away, and say vnto the
people, He is risen from the dead: so the last errour shalbe worse
then the first.</ab>
<ab n="65">Pilate said vnto
them, Yee haue a watch, goe your way, make it as sure as you
can.</ab>
<ab n="66">So they went,
and made the sepulchre sure, sealing the stone, and setting a
watch.</ab>



</div>