<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>3 Christ reprooueth the Scribes, and
Pharisees, for transgressing Gods Commaundements through their owne
traditions: 11 teacheth how that which goeth into the mouth, doeth
not defile a man. 21 He healeth the daughter of the woman of
Canaan, 30 and other great multitudes: 32 and with seuen loaues and
a few little fishes feedeth foure thousand men, beside women and
children.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came to
Iesus Scribes and Pharisees, which were of Hierusalem,
saying,<note> Mark.7.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Why do thy
disciples transgresse the tradition of the Elders? for they wash
not their handes when they eat bread.</ab>
<ab n="3">But hee answered,
and said vnto them, Why doe you also transgresse the Commandement
of God by your tradition?</ab>
<ab n="4">For God
commaunded, saying, Honour thy father and mother: And hee that
curseth father or mother, let him die the death.<note> Exod. 20.12. deut.5.16. , Exod. 21.17. leui.20.9. pro.20.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But yee say,
Whosoeuer shall say to his father or his mother, It is a gift by
whatsoeuer thou mightest bee profited by me,<note> Mar.7.11, 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And honour not
his father or his mother, hee shall be free. Thus haue yee made the
Commaundement of God of none effect by your tradition.</ab>
<ab n="7">Yee hypocrites,
well did Esaias prophecie of you, saying,</ab>
<ab n="8">This people
draweth nigh vnto mee with their mouth, and honoureth mee with
their lips: but their heart is farre from me.<note> Esa.29.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But in vaine they
do worship me, teaching for doctrines, the commandements of
men.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And he
called the multitude, and said vnto them, Heare and
vnderstand.<note> Marke 7.14.</note></ab>

<fw>What defileth.</fw>
<ab n="11">Not that which
goeth into the mouth defileth a man: but that which commeth out of
the mouth, this defileth a man.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then came his
disciples, and said vnto him, Knowest thou that the Pharisees were
offended after they heard this saying?</ab>
<ab n="13">But he answered
and said, Euery plant which my heauenly father hath not planted,
shalbe rooted vp.<note> Ioh. 15.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Let them alone:
they be blinde leaders of the blinde. And if the blinde lead the
blinde, both shall fall into the ditch.<note> Luke 6.39.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Then answered
Peter, and said vnto him, Declare vnto vs this parable.<note> Mar.7.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Iesus said,
Are yee also yet without vnderstanding?</ab>
<ab n="17">Doe not yee yet
vnderstand, that whatsoeuer entreth in at the mouth, goeth into the
belly, and is cast out into the draught?</ab>
<ab n="18">But those things
which proceed out of the mouth, come forth from the heart, and they
defile the man.</ab>
<ab n="19">For out of the
heart proceed euill thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications,
thefts, false witnes, blasphemies.<note> Gen.6.5. and 8.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">These are the
things which defile a man: But to eate with vnwashen hands,
defileth not a man.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then
Iesus went thence, and departed into the coastes of Tyre and
Sidon.<note> Marke 7.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And behold, a
woman of Canaan came out of the same coasts, &amp; cried vnto him,
saying, Haue mercy on me, O Lord, thou sonne of Dauid, my daughter
is grieuously vexed with a deuill.</ab>
<ab n="23">But he answered
her not a word. And his disciples came, and besought him, saying,
Send her away, for she cryeth after vs.</ab>
<ab n="24">But he answered,
and said, I am not sent, but vnto the lost sheepe of the house of
Israel.<note> Chap.10.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Then came she,
and worshipped him, saying, Lord, helpe me.</ab>
<ab n="26">But he answered,
and said, It is not meete to take the childrens bread, and to cast
it to dogs.</ab>
<ab n="27">And she said,
Trueth Lord: yet the dogs eat of the crummes which fall from their
masters table.</ab>
<ab n="28">Then Iesus
answered, and said vnto her, O woman, great is thy faith: be it
vnto thee euen as thou wilt. And her daughter was made whole from
that very houre.</ab>

<fw>A multitude fed.</fw>
<ab n="29">And Iesus
departed frō thence, and came nigh vnto the sea of Galile, and
went vp into a mountaine, and sate downe there.<note> Marke 7.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And great
multitudes came vnto him, hauing with them those that were lame,
blinde, dumbe, maimed, and many others, and cast them downe at
Iesus feet, and he healed them:<note> Esay 35.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Insomuch that
the multitude wondred, when they saw the dumbe to speake, the
maimed to be whole, the lame to walke, and the blind to see: and
they glorified the God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ Then
Iesus called his disciples vnto him, and said, I haue compassion on
the multitude, because they continue with me now three dayes, and
haue nothing to eate: and I will not send them away fasting, lest
they faint in the way.<note> Mark.8.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And his
disciples say vnto him, Whence should we haue so much bread in the
wildernesse, as to fill so great a multitude?</ab>
<ab n="34">And Iesus saith
vnto them, How many loaues haue yee? And they said, Seuen, and a
few little fishes.</ab>
<ab n="35">And hee
commaunded the multitude to sit downe on the ground.</ab>
<ab n="36">And he tooke the
seuen loaues and the fishes, and gaue thankes, and brake them, and
gaue to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitude.</ab>
<ab n="37">And they did all
eate, and were filled: and they tooke vp of the broken meate that
was left, seuen baskets full.</ab>
<ab n="38">And they that
did eat, were foure thousand men, beside women and
children.</ab>
<ab n="39">And he sent away
the multitude, and tooke ship, and came into the coasts of
Magdala.</ab>



</div>