<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_28" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-28-28-Mark.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVIII.</head>
<head>1 Christs resurrection is declared
by an Angel, to the women. 9 He himselfe appeareth vnto them. 11
The high Priests giue the souldiers money to say that he was
stollen out of his sepulchre. 16 Christ appeareth to his disciples,
19 and sendeth them to baptize and teach all Nations.</head>

<ab n="1">In the ende of
the Sabbath, as it began to dawne towards the first day of the
weeke, came Mary Magdalene, and the other Mary, to see the
sepulchre.<note> Mar. 16.1 iohn 20.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And behold, there
was a great earthquake, for the Angel of the Lord descended from
heauen, and came and rolled backe the stone from the doore, and
sate vpon it.<note> Or, had bin</note></ab>
<ab n="3">His countenance
was like lightning, and his raiment white as snowe.</ab>
<ab n="4">And for feare of
him, the keepers did shake, and became as dead men.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Angel
answered, and said vnto the women, Feare not ye: for I know that ye
seeke Iesus, which was crucified.</ab>
<ab n="6">He is not here:
for he is risen, as hee said: Come, see the place where the Lord
lay.</ab>
<ab n="7">And goe quickly,
and tell his disciples that he is risen from the dead. And behold,
hee goeth before you into Galilee, there shall ye see him: loe, I
haue told you.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they departed
quickly from the sepulchre, with feare and great ioy, and did run
to bring his disciples word.</ab>

<fw>Iohn Baptist baptizeth Christ.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ And as
they went to tell his disciples, behold, Iesus met them, saying,
All haile. And they came, and held him by the feet, and worshipped
him.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then said Iesus
vnto them, Be not afraid: Goe tell my brethren that they goe into
Galilee, and there shall they see me.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Now when
they were going, behold, some of the watch came into the citie, and
shewed vnto the chiefe Priests all the things that were
done.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when they
were assembled with the Elders, and had taken counsell, they gaue
large money vnto the souldiers,</ab>
<ab n="13">Saying, Say ye,
His disciples came by night, and stole him away while we
slept.</ab>
<ab n="14">And if this come
to the gouernours eares, wee will perswade him, and secure
you.</ab>

<fw>Iohn Baptist baptizeth Christ.</fw>
<ab n="15">So they tooke
the money, and did as they were taught. And this saying is commonly
reported among the Iewes vntill this day.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then the
eleuen disciples went away into Galilee, into a mountaine where
Iesus had appointed them.</ab>
<ab n="17">And when they
saw him, they worshipped him: but some doubted.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Iesus came,
and spake vnto them, saying, All power is giuen vnto me in heauen
and in earth.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Goe ye
therefore, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the Name of the
Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghost:<note> Mala. 3.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Teaching them to
obserue all things, whatsoeuer I haue commanded you: and loe, I am
with you alway, euen vnto the end of the world. Amen.</ab>



</div>