<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>2 Christ healeth the sicke: 3
answereth the Pharisees concerning diuorcement: 10 sheweth when
mariage is necessary: 13 receiueth litle children: 16 instructeth
the yong man how to attaine eternall life, 20 and how to be
perfect: 23 telleth his disciples how hard it is for a rich man to
enter into the kingdom of God, 27 and promiseth reward to those
that forsake any thing, to follow him.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, that when Iesus had finished these sayings, he departed from
Galilee, and came into the coastes of Iudea, beyond
Iordane:<note> Mar.10.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And great
multitudes followed him, and he healed them there.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ The
Pharisees also came vnto him, tempting him, and saying vnto him, Is
it lawfull for a man to put away his wife for euery cause?</ab>
<ab n="4">And hee answered,
and said vnto them, Haue ye not read, that he which made them at
the beginning, made them male and female?<note> Gen.1.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And said, For
this cause shall a man leaue father and mother, and shall cleaue to
his wife: and they twaine shalbe one flesh.<note> Gen.2.24. ephe.5.31. , 1.Cor.6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Wherefore they
are no more twaine, but one flesh. What therefore God hath ioyned
together, let not man put asunder.</ab>
<ab n="7">They say vnto
him, Why did Moses then command to giue a writing of diuorcement,
and to put her away?<note> Deut.24.1.</note></ab>

<fw>Little children.</fw>
<ab n="8">Hee saith vnto
them, Moses, because of the hardnesse of your hearts, suffered you
to put away your wiues: but from the beginning it was not
so.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I say vnto
you, Whosoeuer shall put away his wife, except it be for
fornication, and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and
whoso marrieth her which is put away, doth commit
adultery.<note> Cha.5.32. mar. 10.11 luke 16.18. 1. cor. 7.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ His
disciples say vnto him, If the case of the man be so with his wife,
it is not good to marrie.</ab>
<ab n="11">But hee said
vnto them, All men cannot receiue this saying, saue they to whom it
is giuen.</ab>
<ab n="12">For there are
some Eunuches, which were so borne from their mothers wombe: and
there are some Eunuches, which were made Eunuches of men: and there
be Eunuches, which haue made themselues Eunuches for the kingdome
of heauens sake. He that is able to receiue it, let him receiue
it.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Then were
there brought vnto him little children, that he should put his
hands on them, and pray: and the disciples rebuked
them.<note> Mark. 10.13. luke 18.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But Iesus said,
Suffer little children, and forbid them not to come vnto me: for of
such is þ<note/> kingdome of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he laide his
hands on them, and departed thence.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And
behold, one came and said vnto him, Good master, what good thing
shall I do, that I may haue eternall life?<note> Marke 10.17. luke 18.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And he said vnto
him, Why callest thou me good? there is none good but one, that is
God: but if thou wilt enter into life, keep the
commandements.</ab>
<ab n="18">He saith vnto
him, Which? Iesus said, Thou shalt do no murder, Thou shalt not
commit adultery, Thou shalt not steale, Thou shalt not beare false
witnesse,<note> Exod. 10.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Honour thy
father and thy mother: and, Thou shalt loue thy neighbour as thy
selfe.</ab>
<ab n="20">The young man
saith vnto him, All these things haue I kept from my youth vp: what
lacke I yet?</ab>
<ab n="21">Iesus said vnto
him, If thou wilt be perfect, goe and sell that thou hast, and giue
to the poore, and thou shalt haue treasure in heauen: and come and
follow me.</ab>
<ab n="22">But when the
young man heard that saying, he went away sorrowfull: for he had
great possessions.</ab>

<fw>The first, last.</fw>
<ab n="23">¶ Then said
Iesus vnto his disciples, Uerely I say vnto you, that a rich man
shall hardly enter into the kingdome of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="24">And againe I say
vnto you, It is easier for a camel to goe thorow the eye of a
needle, then for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of
God.</ab>
<ab n="25">When his
disciples heard it, they were exceedingly amazed, saying, Who then
can be saued?</ab>
<ab n="26">But Iesus beheld
them, and said vnto them, With men this is vnpossible, but with God
al things are possible.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Then
answered Peter, and said vnto him, Behold, we haue forsaken all,
and followed thee, what shall we haue therefore?<note> Mark.10.28. luke 18.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And Iesus said
vnto them, Uerily I say vnto you, that ye which haue followed me,
in the regeneration when the Sonne of man shal sit in the throne of
his glory, ye also shal sit vpon twelue thrones, iudging the twelue
tribes of Israel.<note> Luke 22.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And euery one
that hath forsaken houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or
mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my Names sake, shall
receiue an hundred fold, and shall inherite euerlasting
life.</ab>
<ab n="30">But many that
are first, shall be last, and the last shall be first.<note> Chap.20.16. mark. 10.31. luk. 13.30.</note></ab>



</div>