<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Christ warneth his Disciples to be
humble and harmelesse: 7 To auoide offences, and not to despise the
little ones: 15 Teacheth howe we are to deale with our brethren,
when they offend vs: 21 And how oft to forgiue them: 23 Which hee
setteth forth by a parable of the King, that tooke account of his
seruants, 32 And punished him, who shewed no mercie to his
fellowe.</head>

<ab n="1">At the same time
came the Disciples vnto Iesus, saying, Who is the greatest in the
Kingdome of heauen?<note> Marke 9.23. luke 9.46.</note></ab>

<fw>Auoide offences.</fw>
<ab n="2">And Iesus called
a little child vnto him, and set him in the midst of them,</ab>
<ab n="3">And said, Uerily
I say vnto you, Except yee be conuerted, and become as little
children, yee shall not enter into the kingdome of
heauen.<note> Chap.19.14. 1.cor.14.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Whosoeuer
therefore shall humble himselfe as this little childe, the same is
greatest in the Kingdome of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="5">And who so shall
receiue one such little child in my name, receiueth me.</ab>
<ab n="6">But who so shall
offend one of these little ones which beleeue in me, it were better
for him that a milstone were hanged about his necke, and that hee
were drowned in the depth of the Sea.<note> Marke 9.42. luke 17.1,2.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Woe vnto
the world because of offences: for it must needs be that offences
come: but wo to that man by whom the offence commeth.</ab>
<ab n="8">Wherefore if thy
hand or thy foote offend thee, cut them off, and cast them from
thee: it is better for thee to enter into life halt or maimed,
rather then hauing two hands or two feete, to be cast into
euerlasting fire.<note> Chap.5.30. mar.9.45.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And if thine eie
offend thee, plucke it out, and cast it from thee: it is better for
thee to enter into life with one eie, rather then hauing two eies,
to be cast into hell fire.</ab>
<ab n="10">Take heed that
yee despise not one of these little ones: for I say vnto you, that
in heauen their Angels do alwaies behold the face of my father
which is in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="11">For the sonne of
man is come to saue that which was lost.<note> Luke 19.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">How thinke yee?
if a man haue an hundred sheepe, and one of them be gone astray,
doth he not leaue the ninetie and nine, and goeth into the
mountaines, and seeketh that which is gone astray?<note> Luke 15.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And if so be
that he find it, Uerily I say vnto you, hee reioyceth more of that
sheepe, then of the ninetie and nine which went not astray.</ab>
<ab n="14">Euen so, it is
not the will of your father which is in heauen, that one of these
little ones should perish.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Moreouer,
if thy brother shall trespasse against thee, goe and tell him his
fault betweene thee and him alone: if he shall heare thee, thou
hast gained thy brother.<note> Leuit. 19.17. luke 17.3.</note></ab>

<fw>Of forgiuenesse.</fw>
<ab n="16">But if he will
not heare thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in the
mouth of two or three witnesses, euery word may be
established.<note> Deut. 19.15. iohn 8.17. 2. cor. 13.1. hebr. 10.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And if hee shall
neglect to heare them, tell it vnto the Church: But if he neglect
to heare the Church, let him be vnto thee as an heathen man, and a
Publicane.<note> 1. Cor.5.9. 2. thes. 3.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Uerily I say
vnto you, Whatsoeuer ye shall binde on earth, shall bee bound in
heauen: and whatsoeuer yee shall loose on earth, shall bee loosed
in heauen.<note> Iohn 20.23. 1.cor. 5.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Againe I say
vnto you, that if two of you shall agree on earth as touching any
thing that they shall aske, it shall bee done for them of my father
which is in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="20">For where two or
three are gathered together in my Name, there am I in the midst of
them.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Then came
Peter to him, and said, Lord, how oft shall my brother sinne
against mee, and I forgiue him? till seuen times?<note> Luke 17.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Iesus saith vnto
him, I say not vnto thee, Untill seuen times: but, Untill seuentie
times seuen.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Therefore
is the kingdome of heauen likened vnto a certaine king, which would
take accompt of his seruants.</ab>
<ab n="24">And when hee had
begun to reckon, one was brought vnto him which ought him ten
thousand talents.<note> A talent is 750. ounces of siluer, which after fiue shillings the ounce, is 187.li.10.s.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But forasmuch as
hee had not to pay, his lord commanded him to bee sold, and his
wife, and children, and all that he had, and payment to be
made.</ab>
<ab n="26">The seruant
therfore fell downe, and worshipped him, saying, Lord, haue
patience with mee, and I will pay thee all.<note> Or, besought him.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Then the Lord of
that seruant was moued with compassion, and loosed him, and forgaue
him the debt.</ab>
<ab n="28">But the same
seruant went out, and found one of his fellow-seruants, which ought
him an hundred pence: and hee layd handes on him, and tooke him by
the throte, saying, Pay mee that thou owest.<note> The Romane penie is the eighth part of an ounce, which after 5. shillings the ounce is 7. d. ob.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And his fellow
seruant fell downe at his feete, and besought him, saying, Haue
patience with me, and I will pay thee all.</ab>
<ab n="30">And he would
not: but went and cast him into prison, till hee should pay the
debt.</ab>

<fw>Diuorcement.</fw>
<ab n="31">So when his
fellow-seruants saw what was done, they were very sorie, and came,
and told vnto their lord all that was done.</ab>
<ab n="32">Then his lord,
after that hee had called him, said vnto him, O thou wicked
seruant, I forgaue thee all that debt because thou desiredst
me:</ab>
<ab n="33">Shouldest not
thou also haue had compassion on thy fellow-seruant, euen as I had
pitie on thee?</ab>
<ab n="34">And his lord was
wroth, and deliuered him to the tormentors, till hee should pay all
that was due vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="35">So likewise
shall my heauenly Father doe also vnto you, if yee from your hearts
forgiue not euery one his brother their trespasses.</ab>



</div>