<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-21-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Christ rideth into Hierusalem vpon
an asse, 12 driueth the buyers and sellers out of the Temple, 17
curseth the fig-tree, 23 putteth to silence the Priests and Elders,
28 and rebuketh them by the similitude of the two sonnes, 35 and
the husbandmen, who slew such as were sent vnto them.</head>


<fw>House of prayer.</fw>
<ab n="1">And when they
drewe nigh vnto Hierusalem, and were come to Bethphage, vnto the
mount of Oliues, then sent Iesus two Disciples,<note> Marke 11.1. luke 19.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Saying vnto them,
Goe into the village ouer against you, and straightway yee shall
find an Asse tied, and a colt with her: loose them, and bring them
vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="3">And if any man
say ought vnto you, yee shall say, The Lord hath need of them, and
straightway hee will send them.</ab>
<ab n="4">All this was
done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the Prophet,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Tell yee the
daughter of Sion, Behold, thy king commeth vnto thee, meeke, and
sitting vpon an Asse, and a colt, the foale of an Asse.<note> Esai. 62.11. zach. 9.9. iohn 12.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the Disciples
went, and did as Iesus commanded them,<note> Marke 11.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And brought the
Asse, and the colt, and put on them their clothes, and they set him
thereon.</ab>
<ab n="8">And a very great
multitude spread their garments in the way, others cut downe
branches from the trees, and strawed them in the way.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the
multitudes that went before, and that followed, cried, saying,
Hosanna to the sonne of Dauid: Blessed is he that commeth in the
Name of the Lord, Hosanna in the highest.</ab>
<ab n="10">And when hee was
come into Hierusalem, all the citie was mooued, saying, Who is
this?<note> Marke 11.15. luke 19.45. iohn 2.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the
multitude said, This is Iesus the Prophet of Nazareth of
Galilee.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Iesus
went into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and
bought in the Temple, and ouerthrew the tables of the money
changers, and the seats of them that solde doues,</ab>
<ab n="13">And said vnto
them, It is written, My house shall be called the house of prayer,
but yee haue made it a denne of theeues.<note> Esai. 56.7. , Iere 7.11. mar. 11.17. luke. 19.46.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the blind
and the lame came to him in the Temple, &amp; he healed
them.</ab>
<ab n="15">And when the
chiefe Priests and Scribes saw the wonderfull things that he did,
&amp; the children crying in the temple, &amp; saying, Hosanna to
the sonne of Dauid, they were sore displeased,</ab>

<fw>A figtree cursed.</fw>
<ab n="16">And said vnto
him, Hearest thou what these say? And Iesus saith vnto them, Yea,
haue yee neuer read, Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings thou
hast perfected praise?<note> Psal. 8.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And he
left them, and went out of the citie into Bethany, and he lodged
there.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now in the
morning, as hee returned into the citie, he hungred.</ab>
<ab n="19">And when he saw
a figge tree in the way, hee came to it, and found nothing thereon
but leaues only, and said vnto it, Let no fruite growe on thee
hence forward for euer. And presently the figge tree withered
away.<note> Marke 11.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And when the
Disciples saw it, they marueiled, saying, How soone is the figge
tree withered away?</ab>
<ab n="21">Iesus answered,
and said vnto them, Uerily I say vnto you, if yee haue faith, and
doubt not, yee shall not onely doe this which is done to the figge
tree, but also, if ye shall say vnto this mountaine, Be thou
remoued, and be thou cast into the Sea, it shall be done.</ab>
<ab n="22">And all things
whatsoeuer yee shall aske in prayer, beleeuing, ye shall
receiue.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And when
he was come into the temple, the chiefe Priests and the Elders of
the people came vnto him as he was teaching, and said, By what
authoritie doest thou these things? and who gaue thee this
authoritie?<note> Marke 11.27. luke 20.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Iesus
answered, and said vnto them, I also will aske you one thing, which
if ye tell me, I in like wise will tell you by what authoritie I
doe these things.</ab>
<ab n="25">The baptisme of
Iohn, whence was it? from heauen, or of men? and they reasoned with
themselues saying, If we shall say, From heauen, hee will say vnto
vs, Why did ye not then beleeue him?</ab>
<ab n="26">But if we shall
say, Of men, we feare the people, for all hold Iohn as a
Prophet.<note> Chap. 14.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And they
answered Iesus, and said, We cannot tell. And he said vnto them,
Neither tell I you by what authoritie I doe these things.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ But what
thinke you? A certaine man had two sonnes, and he came to the
first, and said, Sonne, goe worke to day in my vineyard.</ab>
<ab n="29">He answered,
&amp; said, I will not: but afterward he repented, and
went.</ab>

<fw>Of the Vineyard.</fw>
<ab n="30">And hee came to
the second, and said likewise: and hee answered, and said, I goe
sir, and went not.</ab>
<ab n="31">Whether of them
twaine did the will of his father? They say vnto him, The first.
Iesus saith vnto them, Uerely I say vnto you, that the Publicanes
and the harlots go into the kingdome of God before you.</ab>
<ab n="32">For Iohn came
vnto you in the way of righteousnesse, and ye beleeued him not: but
the Publicanes and the harlots beleeued him. And ye when ye had
seene it, repented not afterward, that ye might beleeue
him.<note> Chap. 3.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Heare
another parable. There was a certaine house-holder, which planted a
Uineyard, and hedged it round about, and digged a wine-presse in
it, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into
a farre countrey.<note> Esa. 5.1. iere. 2.21. mark. 12.1. luke 20.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And when the
time of the fruite drew neere, he sent his seruants to the
husbandmen, that they might receiue the fruits of it.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the
husbandmen tooke his seruants, and beat one, and killed another,
and stoned another.</ab>
<ab n="36">Againe hee sent
other seruants, moe then the first, and they did vnto them
likewise.</ab>
<ab n="37">But last of all,
he sent vnto them his sonne, saying, They will reuerence my
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="38">But when the
husbandmen saw the sonne, they said among themselues, This is the
heire, come, let vs kill him, and let vs sease on his
inheritance.<note> Chap. 26.3. iohn. 11.53.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And they caught
him, and cast him out of the Uineyard, and slew him.</ab>
<ab n="40">When the Lord
therefore of the Uineyard commeth, what will he doe vnto those
husbandmen?</ab>
<ab n="41">They say vnto
him, He will miserably destroy those wicked men, and will let out
his Uineyard vnto other husbandmen, which shall render him the
fruits in their seasons.</ab>
<ab n="42">Iesus saith vnto
them, Did ye neuer reade in the Scriptures, The stone which the
builders reiected, the same is become the head of the corner? This
is the Lords doing, and it is marueilous in our eyes.<note> Psal. 118.22. acts. 4.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Therefore say I
vnto you, the kingdome of God shall be taken from you, and giuen to
a nation bringing forth the fruits thereof.</ab>

<fw>The marriage.</fw>
<ab n="44">And whosoeuer
shall fall on this stone, shalbe broken: but on whom soeuer it
shall fall, it will grinde him to powder.<note> Rom. 9.33. 1. pet. 2.7. esa. 8.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And when the
chiefe Priests and Pharisees had heard his parables, they perceiued
that he spake of them.</ab>
<ab n="46">But when they
sought to lay hands on him, they feared the multitude, because they
tooke him for a Prophet.</ab>



</div>