<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The genealogie of Christ from
Abraham to Ioseph. 18 Hee was conceiued by the holy Ghost, and
borne of the Virgin Mary when she was espoused to Ioseph. 19 The
Angel satisfieth the misdeeming thoughts of Ioseph, and
interpreteth the names of Christ.</head>

<ab n="1">The booke of the
generation of Iesus Christ, the sonne of Dauid, the sonne of
Abraham.<note> Luke 3. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Abraham begate
Isaac, and Isaac begate Iacob, and Iacob begate Iudas and his
brethren.<note> Gen. 21.3. , Gene. 25. 26. , Gen. 29. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Iudas begate
Phares and Zara of Thamar, and Phares begate Esrom, and Esrom
begate Aram.<note> Gen. 38. 27. , 1. Chro. 2. 5. ruth. 4. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Aram begate
Aminadab, and Aminadab begate Naasson, and Naasson begate
Salmon.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Salmon begat
Boos of Rachab, and Boos begate Obed of Ruth, and Obed begate
Iesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Iesse begate
Dauid the King, &amp; Dauid the King begat Solomon of her that had
bin the wife of Urias.<note> 1. Sam. 16. 1. and 17. 12. , 2. Sam. 12. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Solomon begat
Roboam, and Roboam begate Abia, and Abia begate Asa.<note> 1. Chro. 3. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Asa begate
Iosaphat, and Iosaphat begate Ioram, and Ioram begate
Ozias.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Ozias begat
Ioatham, and Ioatham begate Achas, and Achas begate
Ezekias.</ab>

<fw>The generation of Christ.</fw>
<ab n="10">And Ezekias
begate Manasses, and Manasses begate Amon, and Amon begate
Iosias.<note> 2. King. 20.21. 1. chro. 3. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Iosias begate
Iechonias and his brethren, about the time they were caried away to
Babylon.<note> Some read, Iosias begate Iakim, and Iakim begat Iechonias.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And after they
were brought to Babylon, Iechonias begat Salathiel, and Salathiel
begate Zorobabel.<note> 1. Chro. 3. 16,17.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Zorobabel
begat Abiud, and Abiud begat Eliakim, and Eliakim begate
Azor.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Azor begat
Sadoc, &amp; Sadoc begat Achim, and Achim begat Eliud.</ab>
<ab n="15">And Eliud begate
Eleazar, and Eleazar begate Matthan, and Matthan begate
Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Iacob begate
Ioseph the husband of Mary, of whom was borne Iesus, who is called
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="17">So all the
generations from Abraham to Dauid, are fourteene generations: and
from Dauid vntill the carying away into Babylon, are foureteene
generations: and from the carying away into Babylon vnto Christ,
are fourteene generations.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Now the
birth of Iesus Christ was on this wise: When as his mother Mary was
espoused to Ioseph (before they came together) shee was found with
childe of the holy Ghost.<note> Luke 1. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Then Ioseph her
husband being a iust man, and not willing to make her a publique
example, was minded to put her away priuily.</ab>
<ab n="20">But while hee
thought on these things, behold, the Angel of the Lord appeared
vnto him in a dreame, saying, Ioseph thou sonne of Dauid, feare not
to take vnto thee Mary thy wife: for that which is conceiued in
her, is of the holy Ghost.</ab>

<fw>The Wisemen.</fw>
<ab n="21">And she shall
bring forth a sonne, and thou shalt call his Name Iesus: for hee
shall saue his people from their sinnes.<note> Luke 1. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">(Now all this was
done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken of the Lord by
the Prophet, saying,</ab>
<ab n="23">Behold, a Uirgin
shall be with childe, and shall bring foorth a sonne, and they
shall call his name Emmanuel, which being interpreted, is, God with
vs.)<note> Esai. 7.14. , Or, his name shall be called.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Then Ioseph,
being raised from sleepe, did as the Angel of the Lord had bidden
him, &amp; tooke vnto him his wife:</ab>
<ab n="25">And knewe her
not, till shee had brought forth her first borne sonne, and he
called his name Iesus.</ab>



</div>