<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-22-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 The parable of the marriage of the
Kings sonne. 9 The vocation of the Gentiles. 12 The punishment of
him that wanted the wedding garment. 15 Tribute ought to be payed
to Cæsar. 23 Christ confuteth the Sadducees for the
Resurrection: 34 answereth the Lawyer, which is the first and great
Commandement: 41 and poseth the Pharisees about the
Messias.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iesus
answered, and spake vnto them againe by parables, and
said,<note> Luke 14.16. reuel. 19.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The Kingdome of
heauen is like vnto a certaine King, which made a marriage for his
sonne,</ab>
<ab n="3">And sent forth
his seruants to call them that were bidden to the wedding, and they
would not come.</ab>
<ab n="4">Againe, hee sent
foorth other seruants, saying, Tell them which are bidden, Beholde,
I haue prepared my dinner; my oxen, and my fatlings are killed, and
all things are ready: come vnto the marriage.</ab>
<ab n="5">But they made
light of it, and went their wayes, one to his farme, another to his
merchandize:</ab>
<ab n="6">And the remnant
tooke his seruants, and intreated them spitefully, and slew
them.</ab>
<ab n="7">But when the king
heard thereof, he was wroth, and hee sent foorth his armies, and
destroyed those murderers, and burnt vp their citie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then saith hee to
his seruants, The wedding is ready, but they which were bidden,
were not worthy.</ab>
<ab n="9">Goe yee therefore
into the high wayes, and as many as yee shall finde, bid to the
marriage.</ab>
<ab n="10">So those
seruants went out into the high wayes, and gathered together all as
many as they found, both bad and good, and the wedding was
furnished with ghests.</ab>

<fw>Of Cesars tribute.</fw>
<ab n="11">¶ And when
the King came in to see the guests, hee sawe there a man, which had
not on a wedding garment,</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee sayth
vnto him, Friend, how camest thou in hither, not hauing a wedding
garment? And hee was speechlesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then said the
king to the seruants, Binde him hand and foot, and take him away,
and cast him into outer darkenesse, there shall be weeping and
gnashing of teeth.</ab>
<ab n="14">For many are
called, but few are chosen.<note> Chap. 20.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Then went
the Pharises, and tooke counsell, how they might intangle him in
his talke.<note> Marke 12.13. luke 10.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And they sent
out vnto him their disciples, with the Herodians, saying, Master,
wee know that thou art true, and teachest the way of God in trueth,
neither carest thou for any man; for thou regardest not the person
of men.</ab>
<ab n="17">Tell vs
therefore, what thinkest thou? Is it lawfull to giue tribute vnto
Cesar, or not?</ab>
<ab n="18">But Iesus
perceiued their wickednesse, and said, Why tempt ye me, ye
hypocrites?</ab>
<ab n="19">Shew me the
tribute money. And they brought vnto him a peny.<note> In value seven pence halfe peny, chap. 20.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And he sayth
vnto them, Whose is this image and superscription?<note> Or, inscription.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">They say vnto
him, Cesars. Then sayth he vnto them, Render therefore vnto Cesar,
the things which are Cesars: and vnto God, the things that are
Gods.<note> Rom. 13.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">When they had
heard these wordes, they marueiled, and left him, and went their
way.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ The same
day came to him the Sadduces, which say that there is no
resurrection, and asked him,<note> Marke 12.18. luke 20.27. , Acts 23.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Saying, Master,
Moses said, If a man die, hauing no children, his brother shall
marrie his wife, and raise vp seed vnto his brother.<note> Deu. 25.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Now there were
with vs seuen brethren, and the first when he had maried a wife,
deceased, and hauing no issue, left his wife vnto his
brother.</ab>
<ab n="26">Likewise the
second also, and the third, vnto the seuenth.</ab>
<ab n="27">And last of al
the woman died also.</ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore, in
the resurrection, whose wife shall she be of the seuen? for they
all had her.</ab>

<fw>The resurrection.</fw>
<ab n="29">Iesus answered,
and said vnto them, Yee doe erre, not knowing the Scriptures, nor
the power of God.</ab>
<ab n="30">For in the
resurrection they neither marry, nor are giuen in marriage, but are
as the Angels of God in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="31">But as touching
the resurrection of the dead, haue ye not read that which was
spoken vnto you by God, saying,</ab>
<ab n="32">I am the God of
Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Iacob? God is not the
God of the dead, but of the liuing.<note> Exod.3.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And when the
multitude heard this, they were astonished at his doctrine.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ But when
the Pharises had heard that he had put the Sadduces to silence,
they were gathered together.<note> Marke 12.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Then one of
them, which was a Lawyer, asked him a question, tempting him, and
saying,</ab>
<ab n="36">Master, which is
the great Commandement in the Law?</ab>
<ab n="37">Iesus sayd vnto
him, Thou shalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with
all thy soule, and with all thy minde.<note> Deut.6.5. luke 10.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">This is the
first and great Commandement.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the second
is like vnto it, Thou shalt loue thy neighbour as thy
selfe.<note> Leuit. 19.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">On these two
Commandements hang all the Law and the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ While the
Pharises were gathered together, Iesus asked them,<note> Marke 12.35. luke 20.41.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">Saying, What
thinke yee of Christ? whose sonne is hee? They say vnto him, The
sonne of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="43">He saith vnto
them, How then doth Dauid in spirit call him Lord, saying,</ab>
<ab n="44">The Lord said
vnto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thine enemies
thy footstoole?<note> Psal.110.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">If Dauid then
call him Lord, how is he his sonne?</ab>
<ab n="46">And no man was
able to answere him a word, neither durst any man (from that day
foorth) aske him any moe questions.</ab>



</div>