<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>3 The parable of the Sower, and the
seed: 18 the exposition of it. 24 The parable of the tares, 31 of
the mustardseed, 33 of the leuen, 44 of the hidden treasure, 45 of
the pearle, 47 of the drawnet cast into the Sea, 53 And how Christ
is contemned of his own countrymen.</head>

<ab n="1">The same day went
Iesus out of the house, and sate by the sea side.<note> Mark.4.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And great
multitudes were gathered together vnto him, so that hee went into a
ship, and sate, and the whole multitude stood on the shore.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hee spake
many things vnto them in parables, saying, Behold, a sower went
foorth to sow.<note> Luke 8.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when he
sowed, some seedes fell by the wayes side, and the foules came, and
deuoured them vp.</ab>
<ab n="5">Some fell vpon
stony places, where they had not much earth: and foorth with they
sprung vp, because they had no deepenesse of earth.</ab>
<ab n="6">And when the
Sunne was vp, they were scorched: and because they had not root,
they withered away.</ab>
<ab n="7">And some fell
among thorns: and the thornes sprung vp, &amp; choked them.</ab>
<ab n="8">But other fell
into good ground, and brought foorth fruit, some an hundred folde,
some sixtie folde, some thirty folde.</ab>
<ab n="9">Who hath eares to
heare, let him heare.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the
disciples came, and sayd vnto him, Why speakest thou vnto them in
parables?</ab>
<ab n="11">He answered, and
said vnto them, Because it is giuen vnto you to know the mysteries
of the kingdome of heauen, but to them it is not giuen.</ab>
<ab n="12">For whosoeuer
hath, to him shall be giuen, and he shall haue more abundance: but
whosoeuer hath not, from him shall be taken away, euen that hee
hath.<note> Chap. 25.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore speake
I to then in parables: because they seeing, see not: and hearing,
they heare not, neither doe they vnderstand.</ab>
<ab n="14">And in them is
fulfilled the prophecie of Esaias, which saith, By hearing ye shall
heare, and shall not vnderstand: and seeing yee shall see, and
shall not perceiue.<note> Esai 6.9. mark.4.12. luke 8.10. ioh. 12.40. acts 28.26. rom. 11.8.</note></ab>

<fw>Parables of seed, and of tares.</fw>
<ab n="15">For this peoples
heart is waxed grosse, and their eares are dull of hearing, and
their eyes they haue closed, lest at any time they should see with
their eyes, and heare with their eares, and should vnderstand with
their heart, and should be conuerted, and I should heale
them.</ab>
<ab n="16">But blessed are
your eyes, for they see: and your eares, for they heare.</ab>
<ab n="17">For verely I say
vnto you, that many Prophets, and righteous men haue desired to see
those things which yee see, and haue not seene them: and to heare
those things which ye heare, and haue not heard them.<note> Luke 10.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Heare ye
therefore the parable of the sower.</ab>
<ab n="19">When any one
heareth the word of the kingdome, and vnderstandeth it not, then
commeth the wicked one, and catcheth away that which was sowen in
his heart: this is hee which receiued seede by the way
side.</ab>
<ab n="20">But he that
receiued the seed into stony places, the same is he that heareth
the word, &amp; anon with ioy receiueth it:</ab>
<ab n="21">Yet hath hee not
root in himselfe, but dureth for a while: for when tribulation or
persecution ariseth because of the word, by and by he is
offended.</ab>
<ab n="22">He also that
receiued seed among the thorns, is he that heareth the word, and
the care of this world, and the deceitfulnesse of riches choke the
word, and he becommeth vnfruitfull.</ab>
<ab n="23">But he that
receiued seed into the good ground, is hee that heareth the word,
and vnderstandeth it, which also beareth fruit, and bringeth
foorth, some an hundred fold, some sixtie, some thirty.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Another
parable put he forth vnto them, saying; The kingdome of heauen is
likened vnto a man which sowed good seed in his field:</ab>
<ab n="25">But while men
slept, his enemy came &amp; sowed tares among the wheat, and went
his way.</ab>
<ab n="26">But when the
blade was sprung vp, and brought forth fruit, then appeared the
tares also.</ab>
<ab n="27">So the seruants
of the housholder came, and said vnto him, Sir, didst not thou sow
good seede in thy field? from whence then hath it tares?</ab>
<ab n="28">He said vnto
them, An enemy hath done this. The seruants said vnto him, Wilt
thou then that we goe and gather them vp?</ab>

<fw>Mustard seed, tares, and hid
treasure.</fw>
<ab n="29">But he said,
Nay: lest while yee gather vp the tares, ye root vp also the wheat
with them.</ab>
<ab n="30">Let both grow
together vntil the haruest: and in the time of haruest, I will say
to the reapers, Gather ye together first the tares, and binde them
in bundels to burne them: but gather the wheat into my
barne.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Another
parable put he foorth vnto them, saying, The kingdome of heauen is
like to a graine of mustard seed, which a man tooke, and sowed in
his field.<note> Mar.4.30 luke 13.19</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Which indeed is
the least of al seeds: but when it is growen, it is the greatest
among herbes, and becommeth a tree: so that the birds of the aire
come and lodge in the branches thereof.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Another
parable spake he vnto them, The kingdome of heauen is like vnto
leauen, which a woman tooke, and hid in three measures of meale,
till the whole was leauened.<note> Luke 13.20. , The worde in the Greek is a measure conteining about a peck and an halfe, wanting litle more then a pinte.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">All these things
spake Iesus vnto the multitude in parables, and without a parable
spake hee not vnto them:<note> Marke 4.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">That it might
bee fulfilled which was spoken by the Prophet, saying, I will open
my mouth in parables, I wil vtter things which haue bin kept secret
from the foundation of the world.<note> Psal.78.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Then Iesus sent
the multitude away, and went into the house: and his disciples came
vnto him, saying, Declare vnto vs the parable of the tares of the
field.</ab>
<ab n="37">He answered, and
said vnto them, Hee that soweth the good seed, is the sonne of
man.</ab>
<ab n="38">The field is the
world. The good seed, are the children of the kingdome: but the
tares are the children of the wicked one.</ab>
<ab n="39">The enemie that
sowed them, is the deuill. The haruest, is the ende of the world.
And the reapers are the Angels.<note> Ioel.3.13. reue,14.15</note></ab>
<ab n="40">As therefore the
tares are gathered and burnt in the fire: so shall it be in the end
of this world.</ab>
<ab n="41">The Sonne of man
shall send forth his Angels, and they shall gather out of his
kingdome all things that offend, and them which doe
iniquitie:<note> Or, scandales.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And shall cast
them into a furnace of fire: there shall be wayling and gnashing of
teeth.</ab>

<fw>Mustard seed, tares, and hid
treasure.</fw>
<ab n="43">Then shall the
righteous shine foorth as the Sunne, in the kingdome of their
father. Who hath eares to heare, let him heare.<note> Dan.12.3</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ Againe,
the kingdome of heauen is like vnto treasure hid in a field: the
which when a man hath found, hee hideth, and for ioy thereof goeth
and selleth all that hee hath, and buyeth that field.</ab>
<ab n="45">¶ Againe,
the kingdome of heauen is like vnto a marchant man, seeking goodly
pearles:</ab>
<ab n="46">Who when hee had
found one pearle of great price, he went and solde all that he had,
and bought it.</ab>
<ab n="47">¶ Againe,
the kingdome of heauen is like vnto a net that was cast into the
sea, and gathered of euery kind,</ab>
<ab n="48">Which, when it
was full, they drew to shore, and sate downe, and gathered the good
into vessels, but cast the bad away.</ab>
<ab n="49">So shall it be
at the ende of the world: the Angels shal come forth, and seuer the
wicked from among the iust,</ab>
<ab n="50">And shal cast
them into the furnace of fire: there shall be wailing, and gnashing
of teeth.</ab>
<ab n="51">Iesus saith vnto
them, Haue ye vnderstood all these things? They say vnto him, Yea,
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="52">Then said he
vnto them, Therefore euery Scribe which is instructed vnto the
kingdom of heauen, is like vnto a man that is an housholder, which
bringeth foorth out of his treasure things new and old.</ab>
<ab n="53">¶ And it
came to passe, that when Iesus had finished these parables, hee
departed thence.</ab>
<ab n="54">And when hee was
come into his owne countrey, he taught them in their Synagogue,
insomuch that they were astonished, and said, Whence hath this man
this wisedome, and these mighty works?<note> Marke 6.1. luke.4.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">Is not this the
Carpenters sonne? Is not his mother called Marie? and his brethren,
Iames, and Ioses, and Simon, and Iudas?<note> Ioh.6.42.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">And his sisters,
are they not all with vs? whence then hath this man all these
things?</ab>
<ab n="57">And they were
offended in him. But Iesus said vnto them, A Prophet is not without
honour, saue in his owne countrey, and in his owne
house.<note> Mar.6.4. luke 4.24. iohn 4.44.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">And hee did not
many mighty workes there, because of their vnbeliefe.</ab>



</div>