<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The Pharises require a signe. 6
Iesus warneth his disciples of the leauen of the Pharises and
Sadduces. 13 The peoples opinion of Christ, 16 and Peters
confession of him. 21 Iesus foresheweth his death, 23 Reproouing
Peter for disswading him from it: 24 And admonisheth those that
will follow him, to beare the Crosse.</head>

<ab n="1">The Pharises
also, with the Sadduces, came, and tempting, desired him that hee
would shew them a signe from heauen.<note> Mar.8.11. luke 12.54.</note></ab>

<fw>Pharises leauen.</fw>
<ab n="2">He answered, and
said vnto them, When it is euening, yee say, It will bee faire
weather: for the skie is red.</ab>
<ab n="3">And in the
morning, It will be foule weather to day: for the skie is red and
lowring. O ye hypocrites, yee can discerne the face of the skie,
but can ye not discerne the signes of the times?</ab>
<ab n="4">A wicked and
adulterous generation seeketh after a signe, and there shall no
signe be giuen vnto it, but the signe of the Prophet Ionas. And hee
left them, and departed.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when his
disciples were come to the other side, they had forgotten to take
bread.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Then Iesus
said vnto them, Take heed and beware of the leauen of the Pharises,
and of the Sadduces.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they reasoned
among themselues, saying, It is because we haue taken no
bread.</ab>
<ab n="8">Which when Iesus
perceiued, he said vnto them, O ye of little faith, why reason ye
among your selues, because ye haue brought no bread?</ab>
<ab n="9">Doe ye not yet
vnderstand, neither remember the fiue loaues of the fiue thousand,
and how many baskets ye tooke vp?<note> Chap. 14.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Neither the
seuen loaues of the foure thousand, and how many baskets ye tooke
vp?<note> Chap. 15.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">How is it that
ye doe not vnderstand, that I spake it not to you concerning bread,
that ye should beware of the leauen of the Pharises, and of the
Sadduces?</ab>
<ab n="12">Then vnderstood
they how that he bade them not beware of the leauen of bread: but
of the doctrine of the Pharisees, and of the Sadduces.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ When
Iesus came into the coasts of Cesarea Philippi, he asked his
disciples, saying, Whom doe men say, that I, the sonne of man,
am?<note> Mar.8.27. luke 9.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And they said,
Some say that thou art Iohn the Baptist, some Elias, and others
Ieremias, or one of þ<note/> Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="15">He saith vnto
them, But whom say ye that I am?</ab>
<ab n="16">And Simon Peter
answered, and said, Thou art Christ the sonne of the liuing
God.<note> Ioh.6.69.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And Iesus
answered, and said vnto him, Blessed art thou Simon Bar Iona: for
flesh and blood hath not reueiled it vnto thee, but my Father which
is in heauen.</ab>

<fw>The keyes.</fw>
<ab n="18">And I say also
vnto thee, that thou art Peter, and vpon this rocke I will build my
Church: and the gates of hell shall not preuaile against
it.<note> Ioh.1.42.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And I will giue
vnto thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen: and whatsoeuer thou
shalt bind on earth, shall be bound in heauen: whatsoeuer thou
shalt loose on earth, shall be loosed in heauen.<note> Ioh.20.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then charged hee
his disciples that they should tel no man that he was Iesus the
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ From that
time foorth began Iesus to shew vnto his disciples, how that he
must goe vnto Hierusalem, and suffer many things of the Elders and
chiefe Priests &amp; Scribes, and be killed, and be raised againe
the third day.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then Peter tooke
him, and began to rebuke him, saying, Be it farre from thee Lord:
This shal not be vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">But he turned,
and said vnto Peter, Get thee behind mee, Satan, thou art an
offence vnto me: for thou sauourest not the things that be of God,
but those that be of men.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Then said
Iesus vnto his disciples, If any man will come after me, let him
denie himselfe, and take vp his crosse, and follow me.<note> Chap.10.38. mar.8.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For whosoeuer
will saue his life, shall lose it: and whosoeuer will lose his his
life for my sake, shall finde it.</ab>
<ab n="26">For what is a
man profited, if hee shal gaine the whole world, and lose his owne
soule? Or what shall a man giue in exchange for his soule?</ab>
<ab n="27">For the sonne of
man shall come in the glory of his father, with his Angels: and
then he shall reward euery man according to his works.<note> Psa.62.12 rom.2.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Uerely I say
vnto you, There be some standing here, which shall not taste of
death, till they see the Sonne of man comming in his
Kingdome.<note> Mar.9.1. luke 9.27.</note></ab>



</div>