<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-25-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 The parable of the tenne Virgins,
14 and of the talents. 31 Also the description of the last
Iudgement.</head>

<ab n="1">Then shall the
kingdome of heauen be likened vnto ten Uirgins, which tooke their
lamps, &amp; went forth to meet the bridegrome.</ab>
<ab n="2">And fiue of them
were wise, and fiue were foolish.</ab>
<ab n="3">They that were
foolish tooke their lampes, and tooke no oyle with them:</ab>
<ab n="4">But the wise
tooke oyle in their vessels with their lampes.</ab>
<ab n="5">While the
bridegrome taried, they all slumbred and slept.</ab>

<fw>Of the talents.</fw>
<ab n="6">And at midnight
there was a cry made, Behold, the bridegrome commeth, goe ye out to
meet him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then all those
virgins arose, and trimmed their lampes.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the foolish
said vnto the wise, Giue vs of your oyle, for our lampes are gone
out.<note> Or, going out,</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But the wise
answered, saying, Not so, lest there be not ynough for vs and you,
but goe ye rather to them that sell, and buy for your
selues.</ab>
<ab n="10">And while they
went to buy, the bridegrome came, and they that were ready, went in
with him to the marriage, and the doore was shut.</ab>
<ab n="11">Afterward came
also the other virgines, saying, Lord, Lord, open to vs.</ab>
<ab n="12">But he answered,
and said, Uerely I say vnto you, I know you not.</ab>
<ab n="13">Watch therefore,
for ye know neither the day, nor the houre, wherein the Sonne of
man commeth.<note> Chap. 24.42. marke 13.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ For the
kingdome of heauen is as a man trauailing into a farre countrey,
who called his owne seruants, and deliuered vnto them his
goods:<note> Luke 19.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And vnto one he
gaue fiue talents, to another two, and to another one, to euery man
according to his seuerall ability, &amp; straightway tooke his
iourney.<note> A talent is 187. pound 10. shillings, chap. 18.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Then hee that
had receiued the fiue talents, went and traded with the same, and
made them other fiue talents.</ab>
<ab n="17">And likewise he
that had receiued two, he also gained other two.</ab>
<ab n="18">But hee that had
receiued one, went and digged in the earth, and hid his lordes
money.</ab>
<ab n="19">After a long
time, the lord of those seruants commeth, and reckoneth with
them.</ab>
<ab n="20">And so hee that
had receiued fiue talents, came and brought other fiue talents,
saying, Lord, thou deliueredst vnto me fiue talents, behold, I haue
gained besides them, fiue talents moe.</ab>
<ab n="21">His lord said
vnto him, Well done, thou good and faithfull seruant, thou hast
been faithfull ouer a few things, I wil make thee ruler ouer many
things: enter thou into the ioy of thy lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">He also that had
receiued two talents, came and said, Lord, thou deliueredst vnto me
two talents: behold, I haue gained two other talents besides
them.</ab>

<fw>The last iudgment.</fw>
<ab n="23">His lord said
vnto him, Well done, good and faithfull seruant, thou hast beene
faithfull ouer a few things, I wil make thee ruler ouer many
things: enter thou into the ioy of thy lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">Then he which
had receiued the one talent, came &amp; said, Lord, I knew thee
that thou art an hard man, reaping where thou hast not sowen, &amp;
gathering where thou hast not strawed:</ab>
<ab n="25">And I was
afraid, and went and hidde thy talent in the earth: loe, there thou
hast that is thine.</ab>
<ab n="26">His lord
answered, and said vnto him, Thou wicked and slouthfull seruant,
thou knewest that I reape where I sowed not, and gather where I
haue not strawed:</ab>
<ab n="27">Thou oughtest
therefore to haue put my money to the exchangers, and then at my
comming I should haue receiued mine owne with vsurie.</ab>
<ab n="28">Take therefore
the talent from him, and giue it vnto him which hath ten
talents.</ab>
<ab n="29">For vnto euery
one that hath shall be giuen, and he shall haue abundance: but from
him that hath not, shal be taken away, euen that which he
hath.<note> Chap. 13.12. marke 4.25. luke 8.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And cast yee the
vnprofitable seruant into outer darkenesse, there shall be weeping
and gnashing of teeth.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ When the
Sonne of man shall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with
him, then shall hee sit vpon the throne of his glory:</ab>
<ab n="32">And before him
shall be gathered all nations, and he shall separate them one from
another, as a shepheard diuideth his sheepe from the goats.</ab>
<ab n="33">And he shall set
the sheepe on his right hand, but the goats on the left.</ab>
<ab n="34">Then shall the
King say vnto them on his right hand, Come ye blessed of my Father,
inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the
world.</ab>
<ab n="35">For I was an
hungred, and yee gaue me meate: I was thirstie, and ye gaue me
drinke: I was a stranger, and ye tooke me in:<note> Esai 58.7. ezec. 18.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Naked, and ye
clothed me: I was sicke, and yee visited me: I was in prison, and
ye came vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="37">Then shal the
righteous answere him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee an hungred,
and fedde thee? or thirstie, and gaue thee drinke?</ab>
<ab n="38">When saw wee
thee a stranger, and tooke thee in? or naked, and clothed
thee?</ab>

<fw>Last iudgement.</fw>
<ab n="39">Or when saw we
thee sicke, or in prison, and came vnto thee?</ab>
<ab n="40">And the King
shall answere, and say vnto them, Uerely I say vnto you, in as much
as ye haue done it vnto one of the least of these my brethren, ye
haue done it vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="41">Then shall he
say also vnto them on the left hand, Depart from me, ye cursed,
into euerlasting fire, prepared for the deuill and his
angels.<note> Psal. 6.8. chap. 7.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">For I was an
hungred, and yee gaue me no meat: I was thirstie, and ye gaue me no
drinke:</ab>
<ab n="43">I was a
stranger, and yee tooke me not in: naked, and ye clothed mee not:
sicke, and in prison, and yee visited me not.</ab>
<ab n="44">Then shall they
also answere him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee an hungred, or
athirst, or a stranger, or naked, or sicke, or in prison, and did
not minister vnto thee?</ab>
<ab n="45">Then shall he
answere them, saying, Uerely, I say vnto you, in as much as ye did
it not to one of the least of these, ye did it not to me.</ab>
<ab n="46">And these shall
goe away into euerlasting punishment: but the righteous into life
eternall.<note> Dan. 12.2 iohn 5.29.</note></ab>



</div>