<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The Wise men out of the East, are
directed to Christ by a Starre. 11 They worship him, and offer
their presents. 14 Ioseph fleeth into Egypt, with Iesus and his
mother. 16 Herod slayeth the children: 20 Himselfe dyeth. 23 Christ
is brought backe againe into Galilee to Nazareth.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when Iesus was
borne in Bethlehem of Iudea, in the dayes of Herod the king,
behold, there came Wise men from the East to
Hierusalem,<note> Luk.2.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Saying, Where is
he that is borne King of the Iewes? for we haue seene his Starre in
the East, and are come to worship him.</ab>
<ab n="3">When Herod the
king had heard these things, he was troubled, and all Hierusalem
with him.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when he had
gathered all the chiefe Priests and Scribes of the people together,
hee demanded of them where Christ should be borne.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they said vnto
him, In Bethlehem of Iudea: For thus it is written by the
Prophet;</ab>
<ab n="6">And thou Bethlehem
in the land of Iuda, art not the least among the Princes of Iuda:
for out of thee shall come a Gouernour, that shall rule my people
Israel.<note> Mic.5.2. iohn 7.41. , Or, feede.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then Herod, when
he had priuily called the Wise men, enquired of them diligently
what time the Starre appeared:</ab>

<fw>Herods crueltie.</fw>
<ab n="8">And he sent them
to Bethlehem, and said, Goe, and search diligently for the yong
child, and when ye haue found him, bring me word againe, that I may
come and worship him also.</ab>
<ab n="9">When they had
heard the King, they departed, and loe, the Starre which they saw
in the East, went before them, till it came and stood ouer where
the young childe was.</ab>
<ab n="10">When they saw the
Starre, they reioyced with exceeding great ioy.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And when
they were come into the house, they saw the yong child with Mary
his mother, and fell downe, and worshipped him: and when they had
opened their treasures, they presented vnto him gifts, gold, and
frankincense, and myrrhe.<note> Or, offered.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And being warned
of God in a dreame, that they should not returne to Herode, they
departed into their owne countrey another way.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when they
were departed, behold, the Angel of the Lord appeareth to Ioseph in
a dreame, saying, Arise and take the young childe, and his mother,
and flee into Egypt, and bee thou there vntill I bring thee word:
for Herode will seeke the young childe, to destroy him.</ab>
<ab n="14">When he arose, he
tooke the yong childe and his mother by night, and departed into
Egypt:</ab>
<ab n="15">And was there
vntill the death of Herode, that it might be fulfilled which was
spoken of the Lord by the Prophet, saying, Out of Egypt haue I
called my sonne.<note> Ose.11.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Then
Herode, when hee saw that hee was mocked of the Wise men, was
exceeding wroth, and sent foorth, and slewe all the children that
were in Bethlehem, and in all the coasts thereof, from two yeeres
olde and vnder, according to the time, which he had diligently
enquired of the Wise men.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then was
fulfilled that which was spoken by Ieremie the Prophet,
saying,<note> Ier.31.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">In Rama was there
a voice heard, lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning, Rachel
weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, because they
are not.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ But when
Herode was dead, behold, an Angel of the Lord appeareth in a dreame
to Ioseph in Egypt,</ab>
<ab n="20">Saying, Arise,
and take the yong childe and his mother, and goe into the land of
Israel: for they are dead which sought the yong childes
life.</ab>

<fw>Iohns preaching.</fw>
<ab n="21">And he arose, and
tooke the yong childe and his mother, and came into the land of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="22">But when he heard
that Archelaus did reigne in Iudea in the roome of his father
Herod, hee was afraid to goe thither: notwithstanding, beeing
warned of God in a dreame, he turned aside into the parts of
Galilee:</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee came and
dwelt in a city called Nazareth, that it might be fulfilled which
was spoken by the Prophets, He shalbe called a Nazarene.</ab>



</div>