<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-26-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-26-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 The rulers conspire against
Christ. 6 The woman anointeth his feet. 14 Iudas selleth him. 17
Christ eateth the Passeouer: 26 instituteth his holy Supper: 36
prayeth in the garden: 47 and being betrayed with a kisse, 57 is
caried to Caiaphas, 69 and denied of Peter.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when Iesus had finished al these sayings, hee said vnto his
disciples,</ab>
<ab n="2">Ye know that
after two dayes is the feast of the Passeouer, and the Sonne of man
is betrayed to be crucified.<note> Mar. 14.1 luke 22.1. iohn 13.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Then assembled
together the chiefe Priests, and the Scribes, and the Elders of the
people, vnto the palace of the high Priest, who was called
Caiaphas,<note> Ioh.11.47</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And consulted
that they might take Iesus by subtiltie, and kill him.</ab>
<ab n="5">But they said,
Not on the feast day, lest there bee an vproare among the
people.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Now when
Iesus was in Bethanie, in the house of Simon the leper,<note> Mar.14.3 iohn 11.1.</note></ab>

<fw>The Passeouer.</fw>
<ab n="7">There came vnto
him a woman, hauing an alabaster boxe of very precious ointment,
and powred it on his head, as he sate at meat.</ab>
<ab n="8">But when his
disciples saw it, they had indignation, saying, To what purpose is
this waste?</ab>
<ab n="9">For this ointment
might haue bin sold for much, and giuen to the poore.</ab>
<ab n="10">When Iesus
vnderstood it, he said vnto them, Why trouble ye the woman? for she
hath wrought a good worke vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="11">For ye haue the
poore alwayes with you, but me ye haue not alwayes.<note> Deu. 15.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For in that she
hath powred this ointment on my body, shee did it for my
buriall.</ab>
<ab n="13">Uerely I say
vnto you, Wheresoeuer this Gospel shall be preached in the whole
world, there shall also this, that this woman hath done, be told
for a memoriall of her.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Then one
of the twelue, called Iudas Iscariot, went vnto the chiefe
Priests,<note> Marke 14.10. luke 22.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And said vnto
them, What will ye giue me, and I will deliuer him vnto you? and
they couenanted with him for thirtie pieces of siluer.</ab>
<ab n="16">And from that
time he sought opportunitie to betray him.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Now the
first day of the feast of vnleauened bread, the disciples came to
Iesus, saying vnto him, Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to
eat the Passeouer?<note> Mar. 14.12. luke 22.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And he said, Goe
into the citie to such a man, and say vnto him, The Master saith,
My time is at hand, I will keepe the Passeouer at thy house with my
disciples.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
disciples did, as Iesus had appointed them, and they made ready the
Passeouer.</ab>
<ab n="20">Now when the
euen was come, he sate downe with the twelue.<note> Mark 14.18. luke 22.14. ioh. 13.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And as they did
eate, he said, Uerely I say vnto you, that one of you shal betray
me.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they were
exceeding sorowfull, and began euery one of them to say vnto him,
Lord, Is it I?</ab>
<ab n="23">And he answered
and said, Hee that dippeth his hand with mee in the dish, the same
shall betray me.<note> Psal. 41.9.</note></ab>

<fw>The last supper.</fw>
<ab n="24">The sonne of man
goeth as it is written of him: but woe vnto that man by whom the
sonne of man is betrayed: It had bin good for that man, if hee had
not bene borne.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then Iudas,
which betrayed him, answered, and said, Master, Is it I? He said
vnto him, Thou hast said.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And as
they were eating, Iesus took bread, and blessed it, and brake it,
and gaue it to the Disciples, and said, Take, eate, this is my
body.<note> 1. Cor. 11.24. , Many Greeke copies haue, gaue thanks.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And he tooke the
cup, and gaue thankes, and gaue it to them, saying, Drinke ye all
of it:</ab>
<ab n="28">For this is my
blood of the new Testament, which is shed for many for the
remission of sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="29">But I say vnto
you, I will not drinke henceforth of this fruite of the vine,
vntill that day when I drinke it new with you in my fathers
kingdom.</ab>
<ab n="30">And when they
had sung an hymne, they went out into the mount of
Oliues.<note> Or, psalme.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Then saith Iesus
vnto them, All ye shall be offended because of me this night, For
it is written, I will smite the Shepheard, and the sheepe of the
flocke shall be scattered abroad.<note> Marke 14.27. iohn. 16.32. , Zach. 13.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">But after I am
risen againe, I will goe before you into Galilee.<note> Mar. 14.2. and 16.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Peter answered,
and said vnto him, Though all men shall be offended because of
thee, yet will I neuer be offended.</ab>
<ab n="34">Iesus said vnto
him, Uerily I say vnto thee, that this might before the cocke crow,
thou shalt denie me thrise.<note> Iohn 13.38.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Peter said vnto
him, Though I should die with thee, yet will I not denie thee.
Likewise also said all the Disciples.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ Then
commeth Iesus with them vnto a place called Gethsemane, and saith
vnto the Disciples, Sit yee heere, while I goe and pray
yonder.<note> Marke 14.32. luke 22. 39.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And hee tooke
with him Peter, and the two sonnes of Zebedee, and beganne to be
sorrowful, and very heauie.</ab>
<ab n="38">Then saith he
vnto them, My soule is exceeding sorrowfull, euen vnto death: tary
ye heere, &amp; watch with me.</ab>
<ab n="39">And he went a
little further, and fell on his face, and prayed, saying, O my
father, if it be possible, let this cup passe from me:
neuerthelesse, not as I will, but as thou wilt.</ab>
<ab n="40">And he commeth
vnto the Disciples, and findeth them asleepe, and saith vnto Peter,
What, could ye not watch with me one houre?</ab>

<fw>Christ betrayed.</fw>
<ab n="41">Watch and pray,
that yee enter not into temptation: The spirit indeed is willing,
but the flesh is weake.</ab>
<ab n="42">He went away
again the second time, and prayed, saying, O my father, if this cup
may not passe away from me, except I drinke it, thy will be
done.</ab>
<ab n="43">And he came and
found them asleep againe: For their eies were heauie.</ab>
<ab n="44">And he left
them, and went away againe, and prayed the third time, saying the
same words.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then commeth he
to his Disciples, and saith vnto them, Sleepe on now, and take your
rest, behold, the houre is at hand, and the sonne of man is
betrayed into the hands of sinners.</ab>
<ab n="46">Rise, let vs be
going: behold, he is at hand that doeth betray me.</ab>
<ab n="47">¶ And while
yet spake, loe, Iudas one of the twelue came, and with him a great
multitude with swords and staues from the chiefe Priests and Elders
of the people.<note> Mar. 14.43. luke 22.47. iohn 18.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">Now he that
betrayed him, gaue them a signe, saying, Whomsoeuer I shall kisse,
that same is he, hold him fast.</ab>
<ab n="49">And forthwith
hee came to Iesus, and said, Haile master, and kissed him.</ab>
<ab n="50">And Iesus said
vnto him, Friend, Wherefore art thou come? Then came they, and laid
handes on Iesus, and tooke him.</ab>
<ab n="51">And behold, one
of them which were with Iesus, stretched out his hand, and drew his
sword, and stroke a seruant of the high Priests, and smote off his
eare.</ab>
<ab n="52">Then said Iesus
vnto him, Put vp againe thy sword into his place: for all they that
take the sword, shall perish with the sword.<note> Gen. 9.6. reuel. 13.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">Thinkest thou
that I cannot now pray to my father, and he shall presently giue me
more then twelue legions of Angels?</ab>
<ab n="54">But how then
shall the Scriptures be fulfilled, that thus it must
be?<note> Esai. 53.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">In that same
houre said Iesus to the multitudes, Are ye come out as against a
thiefe with swords and staues for to take mee? I sate daily with
you teaching in the Temple, and ye laide no hold on me.</ab>
<ab n="56">But all this was
done, that the Scriptures of the Prophets might be fulfilled. Then
all the Disciples forsooke him, and fled:<note> Lamen. 4.20.</note></ab>

<fw>Peters deniall, and repentance.</fw>
<ab n="57">¶ And they
that had laid hold on Iesus, led him away to Caiaphas the high
Priest, where the Scribes and the Elders were
assembled.<note> Mark. 14.53. luke 22.54. iohn 18.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">But Peter
followed him afarre off, vnto the high Priests palace, and went in,
and sate with the seruants to see the end.</ab>
<ab n="59">Now the chiefe
Priests and Elders, and all the councell, sought false witnesse
against Iesus to put him to death,</ab>
<ab n="60">But found none:
yea, though many false witnesses came, yet found they none. At the
last came two false witnesses,</ab>
<ab n="61">And said, This
fellow said, I am able to destroy the Temple of God, and to build
it in three dayes.<note> Iohn 2.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">And the high
Priest arose, and said vnto him, Answerest thou nothing? what is
it, which these witnesse against thee?</ab>
<ab n="63">But Iesus held
his peace. And the high Priest answered, and said vnto him, I
adiure thee by the liuing God, that thou tell vs, whether thou bee
the Christ the Sonne of God.</ab>
<ab n="64">Iesus saith vnto
him, Thou hast saide: Neuerthelesse I say vnto you, Hereafter shall
yee see the Sonne of man sitting on the right hand of power, and
coming in the clouds of heauen.<note> Chap. 16.27. 1. thess. 4.16. rom. 14.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="65">Then the high
Priest rent his clothes, saying, He hath spoken blasphemie: what
further need haue wee of witnesses? Behold, now ye haue heard his
blasphemie.</ab>
<ab n="66">What thinke ye?
They answered and said, He is guiltie of death.</ab>
<ab n="67">Then did they
spit in his face, and buffeted him, and others smote him with the
palmes of their hands,<note> Esay. 50.6. , Or, rods.</note></ab>
<ab n="68">Saying,
Prophecie vnto vs, thou Christ, who is he that smote thee?</ab>
<ab n="69">¶ Now Peter
sate without in the palace: and a damosell came vnto him, saying,
Thou also wast with Iesus of Galilee.<note> Mark. 14.66. luke 22.55. iohn 18.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="70">But hee denied
before them all, saying, I know not what thou saiest.</ab>
<ab n="71">And when he was
gone out into the porch, another maide saw him, and saide vnto them
that were there, This fellow was also with Iesus of
Nazareth.</ab>
<ab n="72">And againe hee
denied with an oath, I doe not know the man.</ab>

<fw>Peters deniall, and repentance.</fw>
<ab n="73">And after a
while came vnto him they that stood by, and saide to Peter, Surely
thou also art one of them, for thy speech bewrayeth thee.</ab>
<ab n="74">Then beganne hee
to curse and to sweare, saying, I know not the man. And immediatly
the cocke crew.</ab>
<ab n="75">And Peter
remembred the words of Iesus, which said vnto him, Before the cocke
crow, thou shalt denie mee thrice. And hee went out, and wept
bitterly.</ab>



</div>