<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Christ foretelleth the destruction
of the temple: 3 what, and how great calamities shall be before it:
29 the signes of his comming to iudgement. 36 And because that day
and houre is vnknowen, 42 we ought to watch like good seruants
expecting euery moment our masters comming.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iesus went
out, and departed from the temple, and his Disciples came to him,
for to shew him the buildings of the temple.<note> Mar.13.1. luke 21.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Iesus said
vnto them, See yee not all these things? Uerily I say vnto you,
there shall not be left heere one stone vpon another, that shall
not be throwen downe.<note> Luke 19.44.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And as he
sate vpon the mount of Oliues, the Disciples came vnto him
priuately, saying, Tell vs, when shall these things be? And what
shall be the signe of thy coming, and of the end of the
world?</ab>
<ab n="4">And Iesus
answered, and said vnto them, Take heed that no man deceiue
you.</ab>

<fw>Of persecution, and
afflictions.</fw>
<ab n="5">For many shall
come in my name, saying, I am Christ: and shall deceiue
many.</ab>
<ab n="6">And yee shall
heare of warres, and rumors of warres: See that yee be not
troubled: for all these things must come to passe, but the end is
not yet.</ab>
<ab n="7">For nation shall
rise against nation, and kingdome against kingdome, and there shall
be famines, and pestilences, and earthquakes in diuers
places.</ab>
<ab n="8">All these are the
beginning of sorrowes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then shall they
deliuer you vp to be afflicted, and shall kill you: and yee shall
bee hated of all nations for my names sake.<note> Chap.10.17. luke 21.12. iohn 16.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And then shall
many be offended, and shall betray one another, and shall hate one
another.</ab>
<ab n="11">And many false
Prophets shall rise, and shall deceiue many.</ab>
<ab n="12">And because
iniquitie shal abound, the loue of many shall waxe cold.</ab>
<ab n="13">But he that
shall endure vnto the end, the same shall be saued.</ab>
<ab n="14">And this Gospell
of the kingdome shall be preached in all the world, for a witnesse
vnto al nations, and then shall the end come.</ab>
<ab n="15">When yee
therefore shall see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by
Daniel the Prophet, stand in the holy place, (who so readeth, let
him vnderstand.)<note> Mar. 13.14. , Dan.9.27.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Then let them
which be in Iudea, flee into the mountaines.</ab>
<ab n="17">Let him which is
on the house top, not come downe, to take any thing out of his
house:</ab>
<ab n="18">Neither let him
which is in the field, returne backe to take his clothes.</ab>
<ab n="19">And woe vnto
them that are with child, and to them that giue sucke in those
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="20">But pray yee
that your flight bee not in the winter, neither on the Sabbath
day:</ab>
<ab n="21">For then shall
be great tribulation, such as was not since the beginning of the
world to this time, no, nor euer shall be.</ab>
<ab n="22">And except those
dayes should be shortned, there should no flesh be saued: but for
the elects sake, those dayes shall be shortned.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then if any man
shall say vnto you, Loe, heere is Christ, or there: beleeue it
not.<note> Mar.13.21. luke 17.23.</note></ab>

<fw>Of the end of the world.</fw>
<ab n="24">For there shall
arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shal shew great signes
and wonders: insomuch that (if it were possible,) they shall
deceiue the very elect.</ab>
<ab n="25">Behold, I haue
told you before.</ab>
<ab n="26">Wherefore, if
they shall say vnto you, Behold, he is in the desert, goe not
foorth: Behold, he is in the secret chambers, beleeue it
not.</ab>
<ab n="27">For as the
lightening commeth out of the East, and shineth euen vnto the West:
so shall also the coming of the Sonne of man be.</ab>
<ab n="28">For wheresoeuer
the carkeise is, there will the Eagles bee gathered
together.<note> Luke 17.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶
Immediately after the tribulation of those dayes, shall the Sunne
be darkned, and the Moone shall not giue her light, and the starres
shall fall from heauen, and the powers of the heauens shall be
shaken.<note> Marke 13.24. luke 21.25. esay 13.10. ioel 2.31. ezek. 32.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And then shall
appeare the signe of the Sonne of man in heauen: and then shall all
the Tribes of the earth mourne, and they shall see the Sonne of man
coming in the clouds of heauen, with power and great
glory.<note> Reuel.1.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And hee shall
send his Angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they shall
gather together his Elect from the foure windes, from one end of
heauen to the other.<note> 1. Cor. 15.52. 1.thes. 4.16. , Or, with a Trumpet and a great voice.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Now learne a
parable of the figtree: when his branch is yet tender, and putteth
foorth leaues, yee know that Summer is nigh:</ab>
<ab n="33">So likewise yee,
when ye shall see all these things, know that it is neere, euen at
the doores.</ab>
<ab n="34">Uerely I say
vnto you, this generation shall not passe, till all these things be
fulfilled.</ab>
<ab n="35">Heauen and earth
shall passe away, but my wordes shall not passe away.<note> Mark.13.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">¶ But of
that day and houre knoweth no man, no, not the Angels of heauen,
but my Father onely.</ab>
<ab n="37">But as the dayes
of Noe were, so shall also the comming of the Sonne of man
be.</ab>
<ab n="38">For as in the
dayes that were before the Flood, they were eating, and drinking,
marrying, and giuing in mariage, vntill the day that Noe entred
into the Arke,<note> Gene.7. luke 17.26.</note></ab>

<fw>Of the end of the world.</fw>
<ab n="39">And knew not
vntill the Flood came, and tooke them all away: so shall also the
comming of the Sonne of man be.</ab>
<ab n="40">Then shall two
be in the field, the one shalbe taken, and the other
left.<note> Luke 17.36.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">Two women shall
be grinding at the mill: the one shall be taken, and the other
left.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶ Watch
therfore, for ye know not what houre your Lord doth
come.<note> Mark 13.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">But know this,
that if the good man of the house had knowen in what watch the
thiefe would come, he would haue watched, and would not haue
suffered his house to be broken vp.<note> Luke 12.39. 1.thes. 5.2. reuel. 16.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">Therefore be yee
also ready: for in such an houre as you thinke not, the sonne of
man commeth.</ab>
<ab n="45">Who then is a
faithfull and wise seruant, whom his Lord hath made ruler ouer his
houshold, to giue them meat in due season?<note> Luke 12.42.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">Blessed is that
seruant, whome his Lord when he commeth, shall finde so
doing.</ab>
<ab n="47">Uerely I say
vnto you, that hee shal make him ruler ouer all his goods.</ab>
<ab n="48">But and if that
euill seruant shal say in his heart, My Lord delayeth his
comming,</ab>
<ab n="49">And shall begin
to smite his fellow seruants, and to eate and drinke with the
drunken:</ab>
<ab n="50">The Lord of that
seruant shall come in a day when hee looketh not for him, and in an
houre that hee is not ware of:</ab>
<ab n="51">And shall cut
him asunder, and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites: there
shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.<note> Or, cut him off.</note></ab>



</div>