<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-2-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Christ fasteth, and is tempted. 11
The Angels minister vnto him. 13 Hee dwelleth in Capernaum, 17
beginneth to preach, 18 calleth Peter, and Andrew, 21 Iames, and
Iohn: 23 and healeth all the diseased.</head>

<ab n="1">Then was Iesus led
vp of the Spirit into the wildernesse, to bee tempted of the
deuill.<note> Marke 1. 12. luke 4. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And when hee had
fasted forty dayes and forty nights, hee was afterward an
hungred.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when the
tempter came to him, hee said, If thou be the sonne of God, command
that these stones bee made bread.</ab>
<ab n="4">But he answered,
and said, It is written, Man shall not liue by bread alone, but by
euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.<note> Deut.8.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then the deuill
taketh him vp into the holy Citie, and setteth him on a pinacle of
the Temple,</ab>
<ab n="6">And saith vnto
him, If thou bee the Sonne of God, cast thy selfe downe: For it is
written, He shall giue his Angels charge concerning thee, &amp; in
their handes they shall beare thee vp, lest at any time thou dash
thy foote against a stone.<note> Psal.91. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>Christ tempted.</fw>
<ab n="7">Iesus said vnto
him, It is written againe, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy
God.<note> Deu.6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Againe the Deuill
taketh him vp into an exceeding high mountaine, and sheweth him all
the kingdomes of the world, and the glory of them:</ab>
<ab n="9">And saith vnto
him, All these things will I giue thee, if thou wilt fall downe and
worship me.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then saith Iesus
vnto him, Get thee hence, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt
worship the Lord thy God, and him onely shalt thou
serue.<note> Deu.6.13 and 10.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then the deuill
leaueth him, and behold, Angels came and ministred vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Now when
Iesus had heard that Iohn was cast into prison, he departed into
Galilee.<note> Mar.1.14. luke 4.14. iohn 4.43. , Or, deliuered vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And leauing
Nazareth, he came and dwelt in Capernaum, which is vpon the Sea
coast, in the borders of Zabulon and Nephthali:</ab>
<ab n="14">That it might be
fulfilled which was spoken by Esaias the Prophet, saying,</ab>
<ab n="15">The land of
Zabulon, and the land of Nephthali, by the way of the Sea beyond
Iordane, Galilee of the Gentiles:<note> Esai.9.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The people which
sate in darkenesse, saw great light: and to them which sate in the
region and shadow of death, light is sprung vp.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ From that
time Iesus began to preach, and to say, Repent, for the kingdome of
heauen is at hand.<note> Mar.1.14</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And Iesus
walking by the sea of Galilee, saw two brethren, Simon, called
Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the Sea (for they
were fishers)<note> Mar.1.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And he saith vnto
them, Follow mee: and I will make you fishers of men.</ab>
<ab n="20">And they
straightway left their nets, and followed him.</ab>
<ab n="21">And going on from
thence, hee sawe other two brethren, Iames the sonne of Zebedee,
and Iohn his brother, in a ship with Zebedee their father, mending
their nets: and he called them.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they
immediatly left the shippe and their father, and followed
him.</ab>

<fw>The blessed.</fw>
<ab n="23">¶ And Iesus
went about all Galilee, teaching in their Synagogues, and preaching
the Gospel of the kingdome, and healing all maner of sickenesse,
and all maner of disease among the people.</ab>
<ab n="24">And his fame went
thorowout all Syria: and they brought vnto him all sicke people
that were taken with diuerse diseases and torments, and those which
were possessed with deuils, and those which were lunaticke, and
those that had the palsie, and he healed them.</ab>
<ab n="25">And there
followed him great great multitudes of people, from Galilee, and
from Decapolis, and from Hierusalem, and from Iudea, and from
beyond Iordane.</ab>



</div>