<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-10-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>2 Iohn sendeth his disciples to
Christ. 7 Christs testimonie concerning Iohn. 18 The opinion of the
people, both concerning Iohn, and Christ. 20 Christ vpbraideth the
vnthankfulnesse, and vnrepentance of Chorazin, Bethsaida, and
Capernaum: 25 and praising his fathers wisedome in reueiling the
Gospel to the simple, 28 hee calleth to him all such as feele the
burden of their sinnes.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when Iesus had made an end of commaunding his twelue
Disciples, hee departed thence to teach and to preach in their
cities.</ab>
<ab n="2">Now when Iohn had
heard in the prison the workes of Christ, he sent two of his
disciples,<note> Luk. 7. 18</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And said vnto
him, Art thou hee that should come? Or doe wee looke for
another?</ab>
<ab n="4">Iesus answered
and saide vnto them, Go and shew Iohn againe those things which we
doe heare and see:</ab>
<ab n="5">The blind receiue
their sight, and the lame walke, the lepers are cleansed, and the
deafe heare, the dead are raised vp, and the poore haue the Gospel
preached to them.<note> Esai. 35. 6 , Esai. 61.1</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And blessed is
he, whoseouer shal not be offended in me.</ab>

<fw>Of Iohn Baptist.</fw>
<ab n="7">¶ And as
they departed, Iesus began to say vnto the multitudes concerning
Iohn, what went ye out into the wildernesse to see? a reede shaken
with the winde?</ab>
<ab n="8">But what went ye
out for to see? A man clothed in soft raiment? Behold, they that
weare soft cloathing, are in kings houses.</ab>
<ab n="9">But what went ye
out for to see? A Prophet? yea, I say vnto you, and more then a
Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="10">For this is he
of whom it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face,
which shall prepare thy way before thee.<note> Mala. 3. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Uerely I say
vnto you, Among them that are borne of women, there hath not risen
a greater then Iohn the Baptist: notwithstanding, hee that is least
in the kingdome of heauen, is greater then he.</ab>
<ab n="12">And from the
dayes of Iohn the Baptist, vntill now, the kingdome of heauen
suffereth violence, and the violent take it by force.<note> Luk. 16. 16. , Or, is gotten by force, and they that thrust men.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For all the
Prophets, and the Law prophecied vntill Iohn.</ab>
<ab n="14">And if ye wil
receiue it, this is Elias which was for to come.<note> Mala. 4. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hee that hath
eares to heare, let him heare.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ But
whereunto shall I liken this generation? It is like vnto children,
sitting in the markets, and calling vnto their
fellowes,<note> Luk. 7. 31</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And saying, we
haue piped vnto you, and ye haue not danced: wee haue mourned vnto
you, and ye haue not lamented.</ab>
<ab n="18">For Iohn came
neither eating nor drinking, and they say, he hath a
deuill.</ab>
<ab n="19">The sonne of man
came eating and drinking, and they say, Behold a man gluttonous,
and a wine bibber, a friend of publicanes and sinners: but wisedom
is iustified of her children.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Then
began he to vpbraid the cities wherein most of his mighty works
were done, because they repented not.<note> Luke 10. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Woe vnto thee
Chorazin, woe vnto thee Bethsaida: for if the mightie workes which
were done in you, had bene done in Tyre and Sidon, they would haue
repented long agoe in sackcloth and ashes.</ab>
<ab n="22">But I say vnto
you, It shall bee more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the day of
iudgement, then for you.</ab>

<fw>Christs yoke.</fw>
<ab n="23">And thou
Capernaum, which art exalted vnto heauen, shalt be brought downe to
hell: For if the mighty works which haue beene done in thee, had
bin done in Sodome, it would haue remained vntil this day.</ab>
<ab n="24">But I say vnto
you, that it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom, in
þ<note/> day of iudgment, then for thee.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ At that
time Iesus answered, and said, I thanke thee, O Father, Lord of
heauen and earth, because thou hast hid these things frō the
wise &amp; prudent, &amp; hast reueiled them vnto
babes.<note> Luke 10. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Euen so, Father,
for so it seemed good in thy sight.</ab>
<ab n="27">All things are
deliuered vnto me of my father: and no man knoweth the sonne but
the father: neither knoweth any man the father, saue the sonne, and
hee to whomsoeuer the sonne will reueile him.<note> Iohn 3. 35. , Iohn 6. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Come vnto
me all yee that labour, and are heauy laden, and I will giue you
rest.</ab>
<ab n="29">Take my yoke
vpon you, and learne of me, for I am meeke and lowly in heart: and
yee shall find rest vnto your soules.<note> Iere. 6. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">For my yoke is
easie, and my burden is light.<note> 1.Iohn 5. 3.</note></ab>



</div>