<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-5-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>Christ beginneth his Sermon in the
Mount: 3 declaring who are blessed, 13 who are the salt of the
earth, 14 the light of the world, the citie on an hill, 15 the
candle: 17 that he came to fulfill the Law: 21 what it is to kill,
27 to commit adulterie, 33 to sweare: 38 Exhorteth to suffer wrong,
44 to loue euen our enemies, 38 and to labour after
perfectnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">And seeing the
multitudes, he went vp into a mountaine: and when he was set, his
disciples came vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he opened his
mouth, and taught them, saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Blessed are the
poore in spirit: for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.<note> Luk.6.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Blessed are they
that mourne: for they shall be comforted.</ab>
<ab n="5">Blessed are the
meeke: for they shall inherit the earth.<note> Psa.37.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Blessed are they
which doe hunger and thirst after righteousnesse: for they shall be
filled.<note> Esa.65.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Blessed are the
mercifull: for they shall obtaine mercie.</ab>
<ab n="8">Blessed are the
pure in heart: for they shall see God.<note> Psal.24.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Blessed are the
peacemakers: for they shall bee called the children of God.</ab>
<ab n="10">Blessed are they
which are persecuted for righteousnesse sake: for theirs is the
kingdome of heauen.<note> 1.Pet.3.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Blessed are ye,
when men shall reuile you, and persecute you, and shal say all
manner of euill against you falsly for my sake.<note> 1.Pet.4. 14. , Gr. lying.</note></ab>

<fw>The Law is expounded.</fw>
<ab n="12">Reioyce, and be
exceeding glad: for great is your reward in heauen: For so
persecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Yee are
the salt of the earth: But if the salt haue lost his sauour,
wherewith shall it bee salted? It is thenceforth good for nothing,
but to be cast out, and to be troden vnder foote of
men.<note> Marke 9. 50 luke. 14 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Yee are the light
of the world. A citie that is set on an hill, cannot be
hid.</ab>
<ab n="15">Neither doe men
light a candle, and put it vnder a bushell: but on a candlesticke,
and it giueth light vnto all that are in the house.<note> The word in the originall signifieth a measure containing about a pint lesse then a pecke. , Marke 4. 21 luke 8. 16.and 11. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Let your light so
shine before men, that they may see your good workes, and glorifie
your father which is in heauen.<note> 1.Pet.2. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Thinke not
that I am come to destroy the lawe or the Prophets. I am not come
to destroy, but to fulfill.</ab>
<ab n="18">For verily I say
vnto you, Till heauen and earth passe, one iote or one title, shall
in no wise passe from the law, till all be fulfilled.<note> Luke 16. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Whosoeuer
therfore shall breake one of these least commaundements, and shall
teach men so, he shall be called the least in the kingdome of
heauen: but whosoeuer shall doe, and teach them, the same shall be
called great in the kingdome of heauen.<note> Iames 2. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For I say vnto
you, That except your righteousnesse shall exceede the
righteousnesse of the Scribes and Pharisees, yee shall in no case
enter into the kingdome of heauen.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ Yee haue
heard, that it was saide by them of old time, Thou shalt not kill:
and, Whosoeuer shall kill, shalbe in danger of the
iudgement.<note> Or, to them , Exod. 20. 13. deut.5. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But I say vnto
you, that whosoeuer is angry with his brother without a cause,
shall be in danger of the Iudgement: and whosoeuer shall say to his
brother, Racha, shal be in danger of the counsell: but whosoeuer
shall say, Thou foole, shalbe in danger of hell fire.</ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore if thou
bring thy gift to the altar, and there remembrest that thy brother
hath ought against thee:</ab>
<ab n="24">Leaue there thy
gift before the altar, and goe thy way, first be reconciled to thy
brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</ab>

<fw>The Law is expounded.</fw>
<ab n="25">Agree with thine
aduersarie quickly, whiles thou art in the way with him: least at
any time the aduersarie deliuer thee to the iudge, and the iudge
deliuer thee to the officer, and thou be cast into
prison.<note> Luke 12. 58.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Uerily I say vnto
thee, thou shalt by no meanes come out thence, till thou hast payd
the vttermost farthing.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Yee haue
heard that it was said by them of old time, Thou shalt not commit
adulterie.<note> Exod. 20. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">But I say vnto
you, That whosoeuer looketh on a woman to lust after her, hath
committed adulterie with her already in his heart.</ab>
<ab n="29">And if thy right
eie offend thee, plucke it out, and cast it from thee. For it is
profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not
that thy whole body should be cast into hell.<note> Chap. 18. 8. marke 9. 47. , Or, doe cause thee to offend.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">And if thy right
hand offend thee, cut it off, and cast it from thee. For it is
profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not
that thy whole body should be cast into hell.</ab>
<ab n="31">It hath beene
said, Whosoeuer shall put away his wife, let him giue her a writing
of diuorcement.<note> Deut.24. 1. luke 16. 18. 1.cor. 7.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">But I say vnto
you, that whosoeuer shall put away his wife, sauing for the cause
of fornication, causeth her to commit adultery: and whosoeuer shall
marie her that is diuorced, committeth adulterie.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Againe,
yee haue heard that it hath beene said by them of old time, Thou
shalt not forsweare thy selfe, but shalt performe vnto the Lord
thine othes.<note> Exod.20. 7. leuit. 19. 12. deut.5. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">But I say vnto
you, Sweare not at all, neither by heauen, for it is Gods
throne:</ab>
<ab n="35">Nor by the earth,
for it is his footstoole: neither by Hierusalem, for it is the
citie of the great king.</ab>
<ab n="36">Neither shalt
thou sweare by thy head, because thou canst not make one haire
white or blacke.</ab>
<ab n="37">But let your
communication bee Yea, yea: Nay, nay: For whatsoeuer is more then
these, commeth of euill.<note> Iam.5.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">¶ Yee haue
heard that it hath beene said, An eie for an eie, and a tooth for a
tooth.<note> Exod. 21. 24. leuit.24 20. deut.19 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">But I say vnto
you, that yee resist not euill: but whosoeuer shall smite thee on
thy right cheeke, turne to him the other also.<note> Luke 6. 29. rom.12. 17. 1.cor.6. 7.</note></ab>

<fw>Of loue, almes, prayer, and
fasting.</fw>
<ab n="40">And if any man
will sue thee at the law, and take away thy coate, let him haue thy
cloake also.</ab>
<ab n="41">And whosoeuer
shall compell thee to goe a mile, goe with him twaine.</ab>
<ab n="42">Giue to him that
asketh thee: and from him that would borrow of thee, turne not thou
away.<note> Deut. 15.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">¶ Yee haue
heard, that it hath beene said, Thou shalt loue thy neighbour, and
hate thine enemie:<note> Leuit.19.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">But I say vnto
you, Loue your enemies, blesse them that curse you, doe good to
them that hate you, and pray for them which despitefully vse you,
and persecute you:<note> Luke 6.27. , Luke 23.34. acts 7.60.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">That yee may be
the children of your father which is in heauen: for he maketh his
sunne to rise on the euill and on the good, and sendeth raine on
the iust, and on the vniust.</ab>
<ab n="46">For if yee loue
them which loue you, what reward haue yee? Doe not euen the
Publicanes the same?<note> Luke 6.32.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And if yee salute
your brethren only, what do you more then others? Doe not euen the
Publicanes so?</ab>
<ab n="48">Be yee therefore
perfect, euen as your father, which is in heauen, is
perfect.</ab>



</div>