<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Christ continueth his Sermon in
the Mount, speaking of almes, 5 prayer, 14 forgiuing our brethren,
16 fasting, 19 where our treasure is to be layed vp, 24 of seruing
God, and Mammon, 25 Exhorteth not to bee carefull for worldly
things: 33 but to seeke Gods kingdome.</head>

<ab n="1">Take heed that yee
doe not your almes before men, to bee seene of them: otherwise yee
haue no reward of your father which is in heauen.<note> Or, with.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Therefore, when
thou doest thine almes, doe not sound a trumpet before thee, as the
hypocrites doe, in the Synagogues, and in the streetes, that they
may haue glory of men. Uerily, I say vnto you, they haue their
reward.<note> Rom. 12.8 , Or, cause not a trumpet to be sounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But when thou
doest almes, let not thy left hand know, what thy right
doeth:</ab>
<ab n="4">That thine almes
may be in secret: And thy father which seeth in secret, himselfe
shall reward thee openly.</ab>

<fw>Of loue, almes, prayer, and
fasting.</fw>
<ab n="5">¶ And when
thou prayest, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites are: for they
loue to pray standing in the Synagogues, and in the corners of the
streets, that they may be seene of men. Uerily I say vnto you, they
haue their reward.</ab>
<ab n="6">But thou when thou
prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut thy doore,
pray to thy father which is in secret, and thy father which seeth
in secret, shall reward thee openly.</ab>
<ab n="7">But when yee pray,
vse not vaine repetitions, as the heathen doe. For they thinke that
they shall be heard for their much speaking.<note> Ecclus.7.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Be not yee
therefore like vnto them: For your father knoweth what things yee
haue neede of, before yee aske him.</ab>
<ab n="9">After this maner
therefore pray yee: Our father which art in heauen, hallowed be thy
name.<note> Luke 11.2</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thy kingdome
come. Thy will be done, in earth, as it is in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="11">Giue vs this day
our daily bread.</ab>
<ab n="12">And forgiue vs
our debts, as we forgiue our debters.</ab>
<ab n="13">And lead vs not
into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill: For thine is the
kingdome, and the power, and the glory, for euer, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="14">For, if yee
forgiue men their trespasses, your heauenly father will also
forgiue you.<note> Marke 11.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But, if yee
forgiue not men their trespasses, neither will your father forgiue
your trespasses.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ Moreouer,
when yee fast, be not as the Hypocrites, of a sad countenance: for
they disfigure their faces, that they may appeare vnto men to fast:
Uerily I say vnto you, they haue their reward.</ab>
<ab n="17">But thou, when
thou fastest, anoint thine head, and wash thy face:</ab>
<ab n="18">That thou appeare
not vnto men to fast, but vnto thy father which is in secret: and
thy father which seeth in secret, shall reward thee openly.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ Lay not vp
for your selues treasures vpon earth, where moth and rust doth
corrupt, and where theeues breake thorow, and steale.</ab>
<ab n="20">But lay vp for
your selues treasures in heauen, where neither moth nor rust doth
corrupt, &amp; where theeues doe not breake thorow, nor
steale.<note> Luke 12.33. 1.tim.6 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For where your
treasure is, there will your heart be also.</ab>

<fw>Take no thought.</fw>
<ab n="22">The light of the
body is the eye: If therefore thine eye be single, thy whole body
shalbe full of light.<note> Luke 11.34.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But if thine eye
be euill, thy whole body shall be full of darknesse. If therfore
the light that is in thee be darkenesse, how great is that
darkenesse?</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ No man can
serue two masters: for either he will hate the one and loue the
other, or else hee will holde to the one, and despise the other. Ye
cannot serue God and Mammon.<note> Luke 16.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Therfore I say
vnto you, Take no thought for your life, what yee shall eate, or
what ye shall drinke, nor yet for your body, what yee shall put on:
Is not the life more then meate? and the body then
raiment?<note> Luke 12.22. psal.55.22. 1.pet.5.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Behold the foules
of the aire: for they sow not, neither do they reape, nor gather
into barnes, yet your heauenly father feedeth them. Are yee not
much better then they?</ab>
<ab n="27">Which of you by
taking thought, can adde one cubite vnto his stature?</ab>
<ab n="28">And why take ye
thought for raiment? Consider the lillies of the field, how they
grow: they toile not, neither doe they spinne.</ab>
<ab n="29">And yet I say
vnto you, that euen Solomon in all his glory, was not arayed like
one of these.</ab>
<ab n="30">Wherefore, if God
so clothe the grasse of the field, which to day is, and to morrow
is cast into the ouen: shall he not much more clothe you, O yee of
little faith?</ab>
<ab n="31">Therefore take no
thought, saying, What shall we eate? or, what shall we drinke? or
wherewithall shall wee be clothed?</ab>
<ab n="32">(For after all
these things doe the Gentiles seeke:) for your heauenly father
knoweth that ye haue neede of all these things.</ab>
<ab n="33">But seeke ye
first the kingdome of God, and his righteousnesse, and all these
things shalbe added vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="34">Take therefore no
thought for the morrow: for the morrow shall take thought for the
things of it selfe: sufficient vnto the day is the euill
thereof.</ab>



</div>