<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMatthew_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Matthew-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Herods opinion of Christ. 3
Wherefore Iohn Baptist was beheaded. 13 Iesus departeth into a
desert place: 15 Where hee feedeth fiue thousand men with fiue
loaues, and two fishes: 22 he walketh on the Sea to his Disciples:
34 and landing at Gennezaret, healeth the sicke by the touch of the
hemme of his garment.</head>

<ab n="1">At that time
Herod the Tetrarch heard of the fame of Iesus,<note> Marke 6.14. luke 9.7</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And said vnto his
seruants, This is Iohn the Baptist, hee is risen from the dead, and
therfore mighty workes doe shew foorth themselues in
him.<note> Or, are wrought by him.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ For Herode
had layd hold on Iohn, and bound him, and put him in prison for
Herodias sake, his brother Philips wife.<note> Luke 3.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For Iohn said
vnto him, It is not lawfull for thee to haue her.<note> Leuit. 18.16. and 20.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And when he would
haue put him to death, hee feared the multitude, because they
counted him as a Prophet.<note> Chap.21.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But when Herods
birth day was kept, the daughter of Herodias daunced before them,
and pleased Herode.</ab>
<ab n="7">Whereupon he
promised with an oath, to giue her whatsoeuer she would
aske.</ab>
<ab n="8">And she, being
before instructed of her mother, said, Giue me heere Iohn Baptists
head in a charger.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the king was
sorie: neuerthelesse for the othes sake, and them which sate with
him at meate, he commanded it to be giuen her:</ab>
<ab n="10">And he sent, and
beheaded Iohn in the prison.</ab>
<ab n="11">And his head was
brought in a charger, and giuen to the Damsell: and she brought it
to her mother.</ab>
<ab n="12">And his
Disciples came, and took vp the body, and buried it, and went and
told Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ When
Iesus heard of it, he departed thence by ship, into a desert place
apart: and when the people had heard thereof, they followed him on
foote, out of the cities.<note> Marke 6.32. luke 9.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And Iesus went
forth, and saw a great multitude, and was mooued with compassion
toward them, and he healed their sicke.</ab>

<fw>The Sea calmed.</fw>
<ab n="15">¶ And when
it was euening, his Disciples came to him, saying, This is a desert
place, and the time is now past; send the multitude away, that they
may goe into the villages, and buy themselues victuals.<note> Iohn 6.5. marke 6.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But Iesus said
vnto them, They neede not depart; giue yee them to eate.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they say
vnto him, We haue heere but fiue loaues, and two fishes.</ab>
<ab n="18">He said, Bring
them hither to me.</ab>
<ab n="19">And hee
commanded the multitude to sit downe on the grasse, &amp; tooke the
fiue loaues, and the two fishes, and looking vp to heauen, hee
blessed, and brake, and gaue the loaues to his Disciples, and the
Disciples to the multitude.</ab>
<ab n="20">And they did all
eat, &amp; were filled: and they tooke vp of the fragments that
remained twelue baskets full.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they that
had eaten, were about fiue thousand men, beside women and
children.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And
straightway Iesus constrained his Disciples to get into a ship, and
to goe before him vnto the other side, while he sent the multitudes
away.</ab>
<ab n="23">And when he had
sent the multitudes away, he went vp into a mountaine apart to
pray: and when the euening was come, he was there
alone:<note> Marke 6.46. , Iohn 6.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But the ship was
now in the midst of the Sea, tossed with waues: for the wind was
contrary.</ab>
<ab n="25">And in the
fourth watch of the night, Iesus went vnto them, walking on the
Sea.</ab>
<ab n="26">And when the
Disciples saw him walking on the Sea, they were troubled, saying,
It is a spirit: and they cried out for feare.</ab>
<ab n="27">But straightway
Iesus spake vnto them, saying, Be of good cheere: it is I, be not
afraid.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Peter
answered him, and said, Lord, if it be thou, bid me come vnto thee
on the water.</ab>
<ab n="29">And he said,
Come. And when Peter was come downe out of the ship, he walked on
the water, to go to Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="30">But when he saw
the wind boysterous, he was afraid: and beginning to sinke, he
cried, saying, Lord saue me.<note> Or, strong.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And immediately
Iesus stretched foorth his hand, and caught him, and said vnto him,
O thou of little faith, wherefore didst thou doubt?</ab>
<ab n="32">And when they
were come into the ship, the wind ceased.</ab>

<fw>Mens traditions.</fw>
<ab n="33">Then they that
were in the ship, came and worshipped him, saying, Of a trueth thou
art the sonne of God.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ And when
they were gone ouer, they came into þ<note/> land of
Genesaret.<note> Marke 6.53.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And when the men
of that place had knowledge of him, they sent out into all that
countrey round about, and brought vnto him al that were
diseased,</ab>
<ab n="36">And besought
him, that they might onely touch the hemme of his garment; and as
many as touched, were made perfectly whole.</ab>



</div>