<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Jonah-Chapter-4-4-Micah.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Micah sheweth the wrath of God
against Iacob, for idolatry. 10 Hee exhorteth to
mourning.</head>

<ab n="1">The word of
the Lord that came to Micah the Morasthite in the dayes of Iotham,
Ahaz, and Hezekiah Kings of Iudah, which hee saw concerning Samaria
and Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="2">Heare all ye
people, hearken O earth, and all that therein is, and let the Lord
God be witnesse against you, the Lord from his holy
temple.<note> Heb. heare yee people all of them. , Deut. 32. 1. isai. 1. 2. , Heb. the fulnesse therof.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For behold,
the Lord commeth forth out of his place, and will come downe and
tread vpon the high places of the earth.<note> Isai. 26. 21 psal. 115. 3. , Deut. 32. 13. and 33. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the
mountaines shall be molten vnder him, and the valleis shall be
cleft: as waxe before the fire, and as the waters that are powred
downe a steepe place.<note> Psal. 97. 5. , Heb. a descent.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For the
transgression of Iacob is all this, and for the sinnes of the house
of Israel: What is the transgression of Iacob? Is it not Samaria?
and what are the high places of Iudah? are they not
Ierusalem?</ab>
<ab n="6">Therfore I
will make Samaria as an heape of the field, and as plantings of a
vineyard; and I will powre downe the stones therof into the valley,
and I will discouer the foundations thereof.</ab>
<ab n="7">And all the
grauen images thereof shall be beaten to pieces, and all the hires
thereof shall be burnt with the fire, and all the idoles therof
will I lay desolate: for she gathered it of the hire of an harlot,
and they shall returne to the hire of an harlot.</ab>
<ab n="8">Therfore I wil
waile and houle, I will goe stript and naked: I will make a wailing
like the dragons, and mourning as the owles.<note> Heb. daughters of the owle.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For her wound
is incurable, for it is come vnto Iudah: he is come vnto the gate
of my people, euen to Ierusalem.<note> Or, she is grieuously sicke of her wounds.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Declare yee
it not at Gath, weepe yee not at all: In the house of Aphrah rowle
thy selfe in the dust.<note> 2. Sam. 1. 20. , That is, dust. , Ier.6.26.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Passe yee away thou
inhabitant of Saphir, hauing thy shame naked; the inhabitant of
Zaanan came not forth in the mourning of Beth-ezel, he shall
receiue of you his standing.<note> Heb. inhabitresse. , Or, thou that dwellest fairely. , Isai.47.30. , Or, the countrey of flockes. , Or, a place neere.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For the inhabitant
of Maroth waited carefully for good, but euill came downe from the
Lord vnto the gate of Ierusalem.<note> Or, was grieued.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">O thou inhabitant
of Lachish, bind the charet to the swift beast: she is the
beginning of the sinne to the daughter of Zion: for the
transgressions of Israel were found in thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Therfore shalt thou
giue presents to Moresheth-Gath: the houses of Achzib shalbe a lie
to þe kings of Israel.<note> Or for. , That is, a lie.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Yet wil I bring an
heire vnto thee, O inhabitant of Mareshah: he shall come vnto
Adullam, the glory of Israel<note> Or, the glory of Israel shall come &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Make thee bald, and
polle thee for thy delicate children, enlarge thy baldnesse as the
Eagle, for they are gone into captiuitie from thee.<note> Isai.22.12</note></ab>



</div>