<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 The Church complaining of her
small number, 3 and the generall corruption, 5 putteth her
confidence, not in man but in God. 8 She triumpheh ouer her
enemies. 14 God comforteth her by promises, 16 by confusion of the
enemies, 18 and by his mercies.</head>


<fw>Perillous times.</fw>
<ab n="1">Woe is mee,
for I am as when they haue gathered the summer fruits, as the grape
gleanings of the vintage: there is no cluster to eate: my soule
desired the first ripe fruit.<note> Heb. the gatherings of summer.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The good man
is perished out of the earth, and there is none vpright among men:
they all lie in waite for blood: they hunt euery man his brother
with a net.<note> Psal.12. 3. isai.57.1. , Or, godly, or mercifull.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ That
they may doe euill with both hands earnestly, the prince asketh,
and the iudge asketh for a reward: and the great man, he vttereth
his mischieuous desire: so they wrap it vp.<note> Heb. the mischiefe of the soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The best of
them is as a brier: the most vpright is sharper then a thorne
hedge: the day of thy watchmen, and thy visitation commeth; now
shall be their perplexitie.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Trust
yee not in a friend, put ye not confidence in a guide: keepe the
doores of thy mouth from her that lyeth in thy bosome.</ab>
<ab n="6">For the sonne
dishonoureth the father: the daughter riseth vp against her mother:
the daughter in law against her mother in law; a mans enemies are
the men of his owne house.<note> Matth.10. 21, 35, 36. luc.24.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore I
will looke vnto you the Lord: I will waite for the God of my
saluation: my God will heare me.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ Reioyce
not against mee, O mine enemie: When I fall, I shall arise; when I
sit in darknes, the Lord shall be a light vnto me.</ab>
<ab n="9">I will beare
the indignation of the Lord, because I haue sinned against him,
vntill he plead my cause, and execute iudgement for me: he will
bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his
righteousnesse.</ab>

<fw>Gods mercie.</fw>
<ab n="10">Then she that is
mine enemie shall see it, and shame shall couer her which said vnto
mee; Where is the Lord thy God? mine eyes shall behold her: now
shall she bee troden downe, as the myre of the streets.<note> Or, and thou wilt see her that is mine enemie and couer her with shame. , Psal.79. 10. and 115 2. ioel.2.17 , Heb. she shall be for a treading downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">In the day that thy
walles are to be built, in that day shall the decree bee farre
remoued.<note> Amos 9. 11. &amp;c:</note></ab>
<ab n="12">In that day also he
shal come euen to thee from Assyria, and from the fortified cities,
and from the fortresse euen to the riuer, and from Sea to Sea, and
from mountaine to mountaine;<note> Or, euen to.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Notwithstanding the
land shall be desolate because of them that dwell therein, for the
fruite of their doings.<note> Or, after that it hath beene.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Feede thy
people with thy rod, the flocke of thine heritage, which dwell
solitarily in the wood, in the midst of Carmel: let them feede in
Bashan and Gilead, as in the dayes of old.<note> Or, rule.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">According to the
dayes of thy comming out of the land of Egypt will I shew vnto him
meruailous things.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ The nations
shall see, and be confounded at all their might: they shall lay
their hand vpon their mouth: their eares shall be deafe.</ab>
<ab n="17">They shall licke
the dust like a serpent, they shall moue out of their holes like
wormes of the earth: they shall be afraid of the Lord our God, and
shall feare because of thee.<note> Psal.72. 9. , Or, creeping things.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Who is a God like
vnto thee, that pardoneth iniquitie, and passeth by the
transgression of the remnant of his heritage? hee retaineth not his
anger for euer, because he delighteth in mercy.<note> Exod. 34. 6, 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">He wil turne
againe, he will haue compassion vpon vs: he will subdue our
iniquities, and thou wilt cast all their sinnes into the depths of
the Sea.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou wilt performe
the trueth to Iacob, and the mercy to Abraham, which thou hast
sworne vnto our fathers from the dayes of old.</ab>



</div>