<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Gods controuersie for vnkindnesse,
6 for ignorance, 10 for iniustice, 16 and for
idolatry.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare yee now
what the Lord saith, Arise, contend thou before the mountaines, and
let the hilles heare thy voice.<note> Or, with. , Isai.1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Heare yee, O
mountaines, the Lords controuersie, and ye strong foundations of
the earth: for the Lord hath a controuersie with his people, and he
will pleade with Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">O my people,
what haue I done vnto thee, and wherein haue I wearied thee?
testifie against me.</ab>
<ab n="4">For I brought
thee vp out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the
house of seruants, and I sent before thee Moses, Aaron and
Miriam.<note> Exod. 12. 51. and 14.30.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods controuersie with his
people.</fw>
<ab n="5">O my people,
remember now what Balak king of Moab consulted, and what Balaam the
sonne of Beor answered him from Shittim vnto Gilgal, that yee may
know the righteousnesse of the Lord.<note> Num.22. 5. and 23.7. , Num. 25. , Iosh. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶
Wherewith shall I come before the Lord, and bow my selfe before the
high God? shall I come before him with burnt offerings, with calues
of a yeere olde?<note> Heb. sonnes of a yeere.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Will the Lord
be pleased with thousands of rammes, or with tenne thousands of
riuers of oyle? shall I giue my first borne for my transgression,
the fruit of my body for the sinne of my soule?<note> Heb. belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Hee hath
shewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doeth the Lord require
of thee, but to do iustly, and to loue mercy, and to walke humbly
with thy God?<note> Deut. 10. 12. , Heb. humble thyselfe to walke.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The Lords
voice cryeth vnto the citie, and the man of wisedome shall see thy
Name: heare ye the rodde, and who hath appointed it.<note> Or, thy name shall see that which is.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Are there
yet the treasures of wickednesse in the house of the wicked, and
the scant measure that is abominable.<note> Or, is there yet vnto euery man an house of the wicked? &amp;c. , Heb. measure of leannesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Shall I count them
pure with the wicked balances, and with the bag of deceitfull
weights?<note> Or, shall I be pure with, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For the rich men
thereof are full of violence, and the inhabitants thereof haue
spoken lies, and their tongue is deceitfull in their mouth.</ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore also will
I make thee sicke in smiting thee, in making thee desolate, because
of thy sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="14">Thou shalt eate,
but not be satisfied, and thy casting downe shall be in the midst
of thee, and thou shalt take holde, but shalt not deliuer: &amp;
that which thou deliuerest, will I giue vp to the sword.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou shalt sow, but
thou shalt not reape: thou shalt tread the oliues, but thou shalt
not anoint thee with oile; &amp; sweet wine, but shalt not drinke
wine.<note> Deut. 28. 38. hagg. 1.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ For the
statutes of Omri are kept, and all the workes of the house of Ahab,
and ye walke in their counsels, that I should make thee a
desolation, and the inhabitants thereof an hissing: therefore yee
shall beare the reproch of my people.<note> Or, he doth much keepe the &amp;c. , 1.Kin. 16. 25, 26. , 1. Kin. 16. 30, &amp;c. , Or, astonishment.</note></ab>



</div>