<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Against oppression. 4 A
lamentation. 7 A reproofe of iniustice and idolatrie. 12 A promise
of restoring Iacob.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to them
that deuise iniquitie, and worke euill vpon their beds: when the
morning is light, they practise it, because it is in the power of
their hand.</ab>

<fw>Iudahs plagues.</fw>
<ab n="2">And they couet
fields and take them by violence: and houses, and take them away:
so they oppresse a man and his house, euen a man and his
heritage.<note> Isa. 5. 8. , Or, defraude.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore thus
saith the Lord, Behold, against this familie doe I deuise an euill,
from which ye shall not remoue your necks, neither shall ye goe
haughtily: for this time is euill.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ In that
day shall one take vp a parable against you, and lament with a
dolefull lamentation, and say, We be vtterly spoiled: hee hath
changed the portion of my people: how hath he remoued it from me?
turning away hee hath diuided our fields.<note> Heb. with a lamentation of lamentations. , Or, instead of restoring.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Therefore thou
shalt haue none that shall cast a cord by lot in the Congregation
of the Lord.<note> Deut. 32. 8,9.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Prophecie ye
not, say they, to them that prophecie: they shall not prophecie to
them, that they shall not take shame.<note> Or, prophecie not, as they prophecie. , Heb. drop, &amp;c. , Isa. 30. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ O thou
that art named the house of Iacob, is the Spirit of the Lord
straitned? are these his dongs? doe not my words do good to him
that walketh vprightly?<note> Or, shortened. , Hebr. vp right.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Euen of late,
my people is risen vp as an enemie: ye pull off the robe with the
garment, frō them that passe by securely, as men auerse from
warre.<note> Heb. yesterday. , Heb. ouer against a garment.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The women of
my people haue ye cast out from their pleasant houses, from their
children haue ye taken away my glory for euer.<note> Or, wiues.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Arise ye and
depart, for this is not your rest: because it is polluted, it shall
destroy you euen with a sore destruction.</ab>
<ab n="11">If a man walking in
the spirit and falshood, doe lie, saying, I will prophecie vnto
thee of wine and of strong drinke, he shall euen bee the prophet of
this people.<note> Or, walke with the winde, and lie falsly.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ I will
surely assemble, O Iacob, all of thee: I will surely gather the
remnant of Israel, I will put them together as the sheepe of
Bozrah, as the flocke in the midst of their fold: they shall make
great noise by reason of the multitude of men.</ab>
<ab n="13">The breaker is come
vp before them: they haue broken vp and haue passed through the
gate, and are gone out by it, and their king shal passe before
them, &amp; the Lord on the head of them.</ab>



</div>