<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The Glory, 3 Peace, 8 Kingdome, 11
and Victorie of the Church.</head>

<ab n="1">But in the
last dayes it shal come to passe, that the mountaine of the house
of the Lord shall be established in the top of the mountaines, and
it shalbe exalted aboue the hilles, and people shall flow vnto
it.<note> Isai.2.2. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And many
nations shall come, and say; Come, and let vs goe vp to the
mountaine of the Lord, and to the house of the God of Iacob, and he
will teach vs of his wayes, and wee will walke in his pathes: for
the Law shall goe foorth of Zion, and the word of the Lord from
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And he
shall iudge among many people, and rebuke strong nations afarre
off, and they shall beate their swords into plowshares, and their
speares into pruning hookes: nation shall not lift vp a sword
against nation, neither shall they learne warre any
more.<note> Isa.2.4. ioel 3.10. , Or, sythes.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But they shall
sit euery man vnder his Uine, and vnder his figgetree, and none
shal make them afraid: for the mouth of the Lord of hostes hath
spoken it.</ab>
<ab n="5">For all people
will walke euery one in the name of his god, and we will walke in
the Name of the Lord our God for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="6">In that day,
saith the Lord, will I assemble her that halteth, and I will gather
her that is driuen out, and her that I haue afflicted.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I will
make her that halted, a remnant; and her that was cast farre off, a
strong nation; and the Lord shall reigne ouer them, in Mount Zion
from hencefoorth, euen for euer.<note> Zeph. 3. 19. , Dan. 7.14. luke 1.33.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And
thou, O towre of the flock, the strong hold of the daughter of
Zion, vnto thee shall it come, euen the first dominion, the
kingdome shall come to the daughter of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="9">Now why doest
thou cry out alowd? is there no king in thee? is thy counseller
perished? for pangs haue taken thee, as a woman in trauell.</ab>

<fw>The glory of the Church.</fw>
<ab n="10">Bee in paine and
labour to bring forth, O daughter of Zion, like a woman in trauell:
for now shalt thou goe foorth out of the citie, and thou shalt dwel
in the field, and thou shalt go euen to Babylon: there shalt thou
be deliuered: there the Lord shall redeeme thee from the hand of
thine enemies.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ Now also
many nations are gathered against thee, that say, Let her be
defiled, &amp; let our eye look vpon Zion.</ab>
<ab n="12">But they know not
the thoughts of the Lord, neither vnderstand they his counsell: for
hee shall gather them as the sheaues into the floore.</ab>
<ab n="13">Arise and thresh, O
daughter of Zion: for I will make thine horne yron, &amp; I will
make thy hooues brasse, and thou shalt beat in pieces many people:
and I will consecrate their gaine vnto the Lord, and their
substance vnto the Lord of the whole earth.</ab>



</div>