<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The crueltie of the Princes. 5 The
falshood of the Prophets. 8 The security of them both.</head>


<fw>Pleasing prophets.</fw>
<ab n="1">And I said,
Heare, I pray you, O heads of Iacob, and ye princes of the house of
Israel: is it not for you to know iudgement?</ab>
<ab n="2">Who hate the
good and loue the euill, who plucke off their skinne from off them,
and their flesh from off their bones.</ab>
<ab n="3">Who also eate
the flesh of my people, and flay their skinne from off them, and
they breake their bones, and chop them in pieces, as for the pot,
and as flesh within the cauldron.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then shall
they cry vnto the Lord, but he will not heare them: he will euen
hide his face from them at that time, as they haue behaued
themselues ill in their doings.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Thus
saith the Lord concerning the Prophets that make my people erre,
that bite with their teeth and crie; Peace: and he that putteth not
into their mouths, they euen prepare warre against him:<note> Chap.2.11</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore
night shall be vnto you, that yee shall not haue a vision, and it
shall be darke vnto you, that yee shall not diuine, and the Sunne
shall goe downe ouer the Prophets, and the day shall be darke ouer
them.<note> Hebr. from a vision. , Heb. from diuining.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then shall the
seers be ashamed, and the diuiners confounded: yea, they shall all
couer their lips; for there is no answere of God.<note> Heb. vpper lippe.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But
truely I am full of power by the spirit of the Lord, and of
iudgment and of might, to declare vnto Iacob his transgression, and
to Israel his sinne.</ab>
<ab n="9">Heare this, I
pray you, yee heads of the house of Iacob, and princes of the house
of Israel, that abhorre iudgement and peruert all equitie.</ab>
<ab n="10">They build vp Zion
with blood, and Ierusalem with iniquitie.<note> Ezek. 22. 27. zeph.3. 3. , Heb. bloods.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The heads thereof
iudge for reward, and the priests thereof teach for hyre, and the
Prophets thereof diuine for money: yet will they leane vpon the
Lord, and say; Is not the Lord among vs? none euill can come vpon
vs.<note> Heb. saying.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore shall
Zion for your sake be plowed as a field, and Ierusalem shal become
heapes, and the mountaine of the house, as the high places of the
forrest.<note> Ier.26.18</note></ab>



</div>