<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMicah_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Micah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The birth of Christ. 4 His
Kingdome. 8 His conquest.</head>

<ab n="1">Now gather thy
selfe in troupes, O daughter of troupes: he hath laid siege against
vs: they shal smite the Iudge of Israel with a rod vpon the
cheeke.</ab>
<ab n="2">But thou
Beth-leem Ephratah, though thou bee little among the thousands of
Iudah, yet out of thee shall he come foorth vnto mee, that is to be
ruler in Israel: whose goings foorth haue bene from of old, from
euerlasting.<note> Matth. 2. 6. ioh.7.42. , Hebr. the dayes of eternitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore will
hee giue them vp, vntill the time that shee which trauaileth, hath
brought forth: then the remnant of his brethren shall returne vnto
the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And he
shall stand and feed in the strength of the Lord, in the Maiestie
of the Name of the Lord his God, and they shall abide: for now
shall he be great vnto the ends of the earth.<note> Or, rule.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And this man
shall bee the peace when the Assyrian shall come into our land: and
when hee shall tread in our palaces, then shall we raise against
him seuen Shepheards, and eight principall men.<note> Heb. princes of men.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And they shall
waste the land of Assyria with the sword, and the land of Nimrod in
the entrances thereof: thus shall hee deliuer vs from the Assyrian,
when he commeth into our land, and when hee treadeth within our
borders.<note> Hebr. eate vp. , Or, with her owne naked swords.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods controuersie with his
people.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the
remnant of Iacob shall be in the midst of many people, as a dew
from the Lord, as the showres vpon the grasse that tarieth not for
man, nor waiteth for the sonnes of men.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the
remnant of Iacob shal be among the Gentiles in the middest of many
people, as a Lyon among the beasts of the forrest, as a yong Lyon
among the flockes of sheepe: who if he goe through, both treadeth
downe, and teareth in pieces, and none can deliuer.<note> Or, goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thine hand
shall be lift vp vpon thine aduersaries, and all thine enemies
shalbe cut off.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it shall come
to passe in that day, sayth the Lord, that I will cut off thy
horses out of the midst of thee, and I will destroy thy
charets.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I will cut off
the cities of thy land, and throw downe all thy strong
holdes.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I will cut off
witchcrafts out of thine hand, and thou shalt haue no more
Southsayers.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thy grauen images
also will I cut off, and thy standing images out of the midst of
thee: &amp; thou shalt no more worship the worke of thine
hands.<note> Or, statues.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I will plucke
vp thy groues out of the middest of thee: so will I destroy thy
cities.<note> Or, enemies.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And I will execute
vengeance in anger, and furie vpon the heathen, such as they haue
not heard.</ab>



</div>