<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNahum_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nahum-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nahum-Chapter-3-3-Habakkuk.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>The miserable ruine of
Nineueh.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to the
bloody City, it is all full of lyes and robberie, the pray
departeth not.<note> Heb. Citie of bloods. , Eze.24.9. hab.2.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The noise of a
whip, and the noise of the rattling of the wheeles, and of the
praunsing horses, and of the iumping charets.</ab>
<ab n="3">The horseman
lifteth vp both the bright sword, &amp; the glittering speare, and
there is a multitude of slaine, and a great number of carkeises:
and there is none ende of their corpses: they stumble vpon their
corpses,<note> Heb. the flame of the sword and the lightning of the speare.</note></ab>

<fw>The destruction of Nineueh.</fw>
<ab n="4">Because of the
multitude of the whoredomes of the wel-fauoured harlot, the
mistresse of witchcrafts, that selleth nations through her
whoredomes, and families through her witchcrafts.</ab>
<ab n="5">Behold, I am
against thee, saith the Lord of hostes, and I will discouer thy
skirtes vpon thy face, and I will shew the nations thy nakednesse,
and the kingdomes thy shame.<note> Esa.47.3. ezek.16. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I will
cast abominable filth vpon thee, and make thee vile, and will set
thee as a gazing stocke.</ab>
<ab n="7">And it shall
come to passe, that all they that looke vpon thee, shall flee from
thee, and say; Nineueh is layde waste, who will bemoane her? whence
shall I seeke comforters for thee?</ab>
<ab n="8">Art thou
better then populous No, that was scituate among the riuers that
had the waters round about it, whose rampart was the sea, and her
wall was from the sea?<note> Or, nourishing. Hebr. No Amon.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Ethiopia and
Egypt were her strength, and it was infinit, Put and Lubim were thy
helpers.<note> Heb. in thy helpe.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yet was she caried
away, she went into captiuitie: her yong children also were dashed
in pieces at the top of all the streetes: and they cast lots for
her honourable men, and all her great men were bound in
chaines.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thou also shalt be
drunken: thou shalt bee hid, thou also shalt seeke strength because
of the enemie.<note> Iere.25. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">All thy strong
holds shall be like fig trees with the first ripe figs: if they bee
shaken, they shall euen fall into the mouth of the eater.</ab>
<ab n="13">Beholde, thy people
in the midst of thee are women: the gates of thy land shall be set
wide open vnto thine enemies, the fire shall deuoure thy
barres.</ab>
<ab n="14">Draw thee waters
for the siege: fortifie thy strong holdes, goe into clay, and tread
the morter: make strong the bricke-kill.</ab>
<ab n="15">There shall the
fire deuoure thee: the sword shall cut thee off: it shall eate thee
vp like the cankerworme: make thy selfe many as the cankerworme,
make thy selfe many as the locusts.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thou hast
multiplied thy merchants aboue the starres of heauen; the
cankerworme spoileth &amp; flieth away.<note> Or, spreadeth himselfe.</note></ab>

<fw>The iniquitie of the land.</fw>
<ab n="17">The crowned are as
the locusts, and thy captains as the great grashoppers which campe
in the hedges in the cold day: but when the Sunne ariseth, they
flee away, and their place is not knowen where they are.</ab>

<fw>The iniquitie of the land.</fw>
<ab n="18">Thy shepheards
slumber, O king of Assyria: thy nobles shall dwell in the dust: thy
people is scattered vpon the mountaines, &amp; no man gathereth
them.<note> Or, valiant ones.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">There is no healing
of thy bruise: thy wound is grieuous: all that heare the bruit of
thee, shall clap the hands ouer thee; for vpon whom hath not thy
wickednesse passed continually?<note> Heb. wrinkling.</note></ab>



</div>