<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNahum_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nahum-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>The Maiestie of God, in goodnesse to
his people, and seueritie against his enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">The burden of
Nineueh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.</ab>
<ab n="2">God is ielous,
and the Lord reuengeth: the Lord reuengeth, and is furious, the
Lord wil take vengeance on his aduersaries, and he reserueth wrath
for his enemies.<note> Or, the Lord is a ielous God, and a reuenger, &amp;c. , Exo.20.5 , Heb. that hath fury.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The Lord is
slow to anger, and great in power, and will not at all acquit the
wicked: the Lord hath his way in the whirlewind, and in the storme,
and the clouds are the dust of his feete.<note> Exo.34.7</note></ab>
<ab n="4">He rebuketh
the sea, and maketh it drie, and drieth vp all the riuers: Bashan
languisheth, and Carmel, and the floure of Lebanon
languisheth.</ab>
<ab n="5">The mountaines
quake at him, and the hilles melt, and the earth is burnt at his
presence, yea the world and all that dwell therein.</ab>
<ab n="6">Who can stand
before his indignation? and who can abide in the fiercenesse of his
anger? his furie is powred out like fire, and the rocks are throwen
downe by him.<note> Heb. stand vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The Lord is
good, a strong hold in the day of trouble, &amp; he knoweth them
that trust in him.<note> Or, strength</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But with an
ouer-running flood he will make an vtter ende of the place thereof,
and darkenesse shall pursue his enemies.</ab>
<ab n="9">What doe ye
imagine against the Lord ? he will make an vtter ende: affliction
shall not rise vp the second time.</ab>
<ab n="10">For while they be
folden together as thornes, and while they are drunken as
drunkards, they shall be deuoured as stubble fully drie.</ab>

<fw>The burden of Nineueh.</fw>
<ab n="11">There is one come
out of thee, that imagineth euill against the Lord: a wicked
counseller.<note> Hebr. a counseller of Belial.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thus saith the
Lord, Though they be quiet, and likewise many, yet thus shall they
be cut downe, when he shall passe through: though I haue afflicted
thee, I will afflict thee no more.<note> Or, if they would haue bin at peace, so should they haue beene many, and so should they haue bene shorne, &amp; he should haue passed away. , Heb. shorne</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For now will I
breake his yoke from off thee, and will burst thy bonds in
sunder.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the Lord hath
giuen a commandement concerning thee, that no more of thy name be
sowen: out of the house of thy gods will I cut off the grauen
image, and the molten image, I wil make thy graue, for thou art
vile.</ab>
<ab n="15">Behold vpon the
mountaines the feete of him that bringeth good tidings, that
publisheth peace. O Iudah keepe thy solemne feasts, performe thy
vowes: for the wicked shall no more passe through thee, he is
vtterly cut off.<note> Isa.52.7 rom.10.15. , Heb. feast. , Heb. Belial.</note></ab>



</div>