<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNahum_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nahum-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nahum-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>The fearefull and victorious armies
of God, against Nineueh.</head>

<ab n="1">He that
dasheth in pieces is come up before thy face: keep the munition,
watch the way: make thy loines strong: fortifie thy power
mightily.<note> Or, the disperser or hammer.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For the Lord
hath turned away the excellencie of Iacob, as the excellencie of
Israel: for the emptiers haue emptied them out, and marred their
vine branches.<note> Isa.10.12. , Or, the pride of Iacob and the pride of Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The shield of
his mightie men is made red, the valiant men are in scarlet: the
charets shall bee with flaming torches in the day of his
preparation, and the firre trees shall bee terribly
shaken.<note> Or, died scarlet. , Heb. fierie torches.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The charets
shall rage in the streets, they shall iustle one against another in
the broad wayes: they shall seeme like torches, they shall runne
like the lightnings.<note> Heb. their show.</note></ab>

<fw>The destruction of Nineueh.</fw>
<ab n="5">Hee shall
recount his worthies: they shall stumble in their walke: they shall
make haste to the wal thereof, and the defence shall bee
prepared.<note> Or, gallants , Hebr. couering or couerer.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The gates of
the riuers shall bee opened, and the palace shall bee
dissolued.<note> Or, molten.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Huzzab
shall be led away captiue, she shall be brought vp, and her maids
shall leade her as with the voyce of doues, tabring vpon their
breasts.<note> Or, That which was established, or, there was a stand made. , Or, discouered.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But Nineueh is
of olde like a poole of water: yet they shall flee away. Stand,
stand shall they cry: but none shal looke backe.<note> Or, from the dayes that she hath bene. , Or, cause them to turn.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Take ye the
spoyle of siluer, take the spoile of golde: for there is none end
of the store, and glory out of all the pleasant
furniture.<note> Or, And their infinite store, &amp;c. , Heb. vessels of desire..</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Shee is emptie, and
voide, and waste, and the heart melteth, and the knees smite
together, and much paine is in all loynes, and the faces of them
all gather blacknesse.<note> Isai.13. 7, 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Where is the
dwelling of the Lions, and the feeding place of the yong Lions?
where the Lion, euen the olde Lion walked, and the Lions whelpe,
and none made them afraid.</ab>
<ab n="12">The Lion did teare
in pieces enough for his whelpes, and strangled for his Lionesses,
and filled his holes with pray, and his dens with rauine.</ab>
<ab n="13">Behold, I am
against thee, saith the Lord of hosts, and I will burne her charets
in the smoke, and the sword shall deuoure thy yong Lions, and I wil
cut off thy pray from the earth, and the voice of thy messengers
shall no more be heard.</ab>



</div>