<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 The Priests, 8 and the Leuites
which came vp with Zerubbabel. 10 The succession of hie Priests. 22
Certaine chiefe Leuites. 27 The solemnitie of the dedication of the
walls. 44 The offices of Priests and Leuites appointed in the
Temple.</head>

<ab n="1">Now these are
the Priests and the Leuits that went vp with Zerubbabel the sonne
of Shealtiel, and Ieshua: Seraiah, Ieremiah, Ezra,<note> Ezra 2.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Amariah,
Malluch, Hattush,<note> Or, Melicu, ver.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Shecaniah,
Rehum, Merimoth,<note> Or, Sebaniah, ver, 14. , Or, Harim, ver.15. , Or, Meraloth, ver.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Iddo, Ginnetho,
Abiiah,<note> Or, Ginnethon, ver. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Miamin, Madish,
Bilgah,<note> Or, Miniamin, ver. 17. , Or, Moadiah, ver.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Shemaiah, &amp;
Ioiarib, Iedaiah,</ab>
<ab n="7">Sallu, Amok,
Hilkiah, Iedaiah: these were the chiefe of the Priests, and of
their brethren in the dayes of Ieshua.<note> Or, Sallai, ver.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Moreouer the
Leuites: Ieshua, Binnui, Kadmiel, Sherebiah, Iudah, and Mattaniah,
which was ouer the thankesgiuing, he and his brethren.<note> That is, the Psalmes of thankesgiuing.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Also Bakbukiah,
and Unni; their brethren, were ouer against them in the
watches.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
Ieshua begate Ioiakim, Ioiakim also begate Eliashib, and Eliashib
begate Ioiada,</ab>
<ab n="11">And Ioiada
begate Ionathan, and Ionathan begate Iaddua.</ab>

<fw>The wall is dedicated.</fw>
<ab n="12">And in the
dayes of Ioiakim, were Priests the chiefe of the fathers: of
Seraiah, Meraiah: of Ieremiah, Hananiah:</ab>
<ab n="13">Of Ezra,
Meshullam: of Amariah, Iehohanan:</ab>
<ab n="14">Of Melicu,
Ionathan: of Shebaniah, Ioseph:</ab>
<ab n="15">Of Harim, Adna:
of Meraioth, Helkai:</ab>
<ab n="16">Of Iodo,
Zechariah: of Ginnethon, Meshullam:</ab>
<ab n="17">Of Abijah,
Zichri: of Miniamin, of Moadiah, Piltai:</ab>
<ab n="18">Of Bilgah,
Shammua: of Shemaiah, Iehonathan:</ab>
<ab n="19">And of Ioiarib,
Mattenai: of Iedaiah, Uzzi:</ab>
<ab n="20">Of Sallai,
Kallai: of Amok, Eber:</ab>
<ab n="21">Of Hilkiah,
Hashabiah: of Iedaiah, Nethanael.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ The
Leuites in the dayes of Eliashib, Ioiada, and Iohanan, and Iaddua,
were recorded chiefe of the fathers: also the Priests, to the
reigne of Darius the Persian.</ab>
<ab n="23">The sonnes of
Leui, the chiefe of the fathers, were written in the booke of the
Chronicles, euen vntill the dayes of Iohanan the sonne of
Eliashib.<note> 1.Chro.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the chiefe
of the Leuites: Hashabiah, Sherebiah, and Ieshua the sonne of
Kadmiel, with their brethren ouer against them, to praise and to
giue thankes, according to the commandement of Dauid the man of
God, ward ouer against ward.</ab>
<ab n="25">Mattaniah, and
Bakbukiah, Obadiah, Meshullam, Talmon, Akkub, were porters keeping
the ward, at the thresholds of the gates.<note> Or, treasuries, or assemblies.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">These were in
the dayes of Ioiakim, the sonne of Ieshua, the sonne of Iozadak,
and in the dayes of Nehemiah the gouernour, and of Ezra the Priest,
the Scribe.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And at
the dedication of the wall of Ierusalem, they sought the Leuites
out of all their places, to bring them to Ierusalem, to keepe the
dedication with gladnesse, both with thankesgiuings and with
singing, with cymbals, psalteries, and with harpes.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the sonnes
of the Singers gathered themselues together, both out of the plaine
countrey round about Ierusalem, and from the villages of
Netophathi.</ab>

<fw>The wall is dedicated.</fw>
<ab n="29">Also from the
house of Gilgal, and out of the fields of Geba, and Azmaueth: for
the Singers had builded them villages round about
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the Priests
and the Leuites purified themselues, and purified the people, and
the gates, and the wall.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then I brought
vp the princes of Iudah vpon the wall, and appointed two great
companies of them that gaue thankes, whereof one went on the right
hand vpon the wall toward the dounggate:</ab>
<ab n="32">And after them
went Hoshaiah, and halfe of the Princes of Iudah,</ab>
<ab n="33">And Azariah,
Ezra, and Meshullam,</ab>
<ab n="34">Iudah, and
Beniamin, and Shemaiah, and Ieremiah,</ab>
<ab n="35">And certaine of
the Priests sonnes with trumpets: namely, Zechariah the sonne of
Ionathan, the sonne of Shemaiah, the sonne of Mattaniah, the sonne
of Michaiah, the sonne of Zaccur, the sonne of Asaph:</ab>
<ab n="36">And his
brethren, Shemaiah, and Asarael, Milalai, Gilalai, Maai, Nethanael,
and Iudah, Hanani, with the musicall instruments of Dauid the man
of God; and Ezra the Scribe before them.</ab>
<ab n="37">And at the
fountaine-gate, which was ouer against them, they went vp by the
staires of the citie of Dauid, at the going vp of the wall, aboue
the house of Dauid, euen vnto the water-gate, Eastward.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the other
company of them that gaue thankes, went ouer against them, and I
after them, and the halfe of the people vpon the wall, from beyond
the towre of the fornaces, euen vnto the broad wall,</ab>
<ab n="39">And from aboue
the gate of Ephraim, and aboue the olde gate, and aboue the
fish-gate, and the towre of Hananeel, and the towre of Meah, euen
vnto the sheepegate; and they stood still in the prison
gate.</ab>
<ab n="40">So stood the
two companies of them that gaue thankes in the house of God, and I,
and the halfe of the rulers with me:</ab>
<ab n="41">And the
Priests: Eliakim, Maaseiah, Miniamin, Michaiah, Elioenai,
Zachariah, and Hananiah with trumpets:</ab>

<fw>The Law read.</fw>
<ab n="42">And Maaseiah,
and Shemaiah, and Eleazar, and Uzzi, and Iehohanan, and Malchiiah,
and Elam, and Ezer. And the Singers sang loud, with Iezrahiah their
ouerseer.<note> Heb. made their voice to be heard.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">Also that day
they offered great sacrifices, and reioyced; for God had made them
reioyce with great ioy: the wiues also and the children reioyced:
so that the ioy of Ierusalem was heard euen afarre off.</ab>
<ab n="44">¶ And at
that time were some appointed ouer the chambers for the treasures,
for the offerings, for the first fruits, and for the tithes, to
gather into them out of the fields of the cities the portions of
the law for the priests and Leuites: for Iudah reioyced for the
Priests, &amp; for the Leuites that waited.<note> That is, appointed by the law. , Hebr. for the ioy of Iudah. , Heb. that stood.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And both the
singers and the porters kept the ward of their God, and the ward of
the purification, according to the commandement of Dauid, and of
Solomon his sonne.<note> 1.Chron. 24. and 25. chap.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">For in the
dayes of Dauid and Asaph of old, there were chiefe of the singers,
and songs of praise and thanksgiuing vnto God.<note> 1.Chron. 25.1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">And all Israel
in the dayes of Zerubbabel, and in the dayes of Nehemiah, gaue the
portions of the singers, and the porters, euery day his portion,
and they sanctified holy things vnto the Leuites, and the Leuites
sanctified them vnto the children of Aaron.<note> That is, set apart. , Num. 18. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>