<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The religious maner of reading and
hearing the Law. 9 They comfort the people. 13 The forwardnesse of
them to heare and be instructed. 16 They keepe the feast of
Tabernacles.</head>

<ab n="1">And all the
people gathered themselues together, as one man, into the street
that was before the water gate, and they spake vnto Ezra the
scribe, to bring the booke of the Law of Moses, which the Lord had
commanded to Israel.<note> Ezra 3.1. and 7.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Ezra the
priest brought the Law before the Congregation, both of men and
women, and all that could heare with vnderstanding, vpon the first
day of the seuenth moneth.<note> Heb. that vnderstood in hearing.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And hee read
therein before the street that was before the water gate, from the
morning vntill midday, before the men and the women, and those that
could vnderstand: And the eares of all the people were attentiue
vnto the booke of the law.<note> Heb. from the light.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Ezra the
scribe, stood vpon a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the
purpose, and beside him stood Mattithiah, and Shema, and Anaiah,
and Urijah, and Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand: and on
his left hand, Pedaiah, and Mishael, and Malchiah, and Hashum, and
Hashbadana, Zechariah, and Meshullam.<note> Heb. towre of wood.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Ezra opened
the booke in the sight of all the people (for hee was aboue al the
people) and when he opened it, all the people stood vp:<note> Hebr. eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Ezra blessed
the Lord the great God: and al the people answered, Amen, Amen,
with lifting vp their hands: and they bowed their heads, and
worshipped the Lord, with their faces to the ground.</ab>
<ab n="7">Also Ieshua and
Bani, and Sherebiah, Iamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodijah, Maaseiah,
Kelita, Azariah, Iozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Leuites, caused
the people to vnderstand the law: and the people stood in their
place.</ab>
<ab n="8">So they read in
the booke, in the Law of God distinctly, and gaue the sense, and
caused them to vnderstand the reading.</ab>

<fw>They make boothes.</fw>
<ab n="9">¶ And
Nehemiah, which is the Tirshatha, and Ezra the Priest the Scribe,
and the Leuites that taught the people, said vnto all the people,
This day is holy vnto the Lord your God, mourne not, nor weepe: for
all the people wept, when they heard the words of the
Law.<note> Or, the gouernour.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Then hee sayd
vnto them, Goe your way, eat the fat, &amp; drinke the sweet, and
send portions vnto them, for whom nothing is prepared: for this day
is holy vnto our Lord: neither be ye sory, for the ioy of the Lord
is your strength.</ab>
<ab n="11">So the Leuites
stilled all the people, saying, Holde your peace, for the day is
holy, neither be ye grieued.</ab>
<ab n="12">And all the
people went their way to eate, and to drinke, and to send portions,
and to make great mirth, because they had vnderstood the wordes
that were declared vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And on
the second day were gathered together the chiefe of the fathers of
all the people, the Priestes and the Leuites, vnto Ezra the Scribe,
euen to vnderstand the wordes of the Law.<note> Or, that they might instruct in the words of the Law.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And they found
written in the Law whith the Lord had commanded by Moses, that the
children of Israel should dwell in boothes, in the feast of the
seuenth moneth:<note> Heb. by the hand of. , Leuit. 23. 34. deut. 16.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And that they
should publish and proclaime in all their cities, and in Ierusalem,
saying, Goe foorth vnto the mount, and fetch Oliue branches, and
Pine branches, and Myrtle branches, and Palme branches, and
branches of thicke trees, to make boothes, as it is
written.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ So the
people went foorth, and brought them, and made themselues boothes,
euery one vpon the roofe of his house, and in their courts, and in
the courts of the house of God, and in the streete of the
water-gate, and in the streete of the gate of Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="17">And all the
congregation of them that were come againe out of the captiuitie,
made boothes, and sate vnder the boothes: for since the dayes of
Ieshua the sonne of Nun, vnto that day, had not the children of
Israel done so: and there was very great gladnesse.</ab>
<ab n="18">Also day by day
from the first day vnto the last day, he read in the booke of the
Law of God: and they kept the feast seuen dayes, and on the eight
day was a solemne assembly according vnto the maner.<note> Heb. are straint.</note></ab>



</div>