<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Nehemiah committeth the charge of
Ierusalem to Hanani and Hananiah. 5 A register of the genealogie of
them which came at the first out of Babylon, 9 of the people. 39 of
the Priests. 43 of the Leuites. 46 of the Nethinims. 57 of Solomons
seruants. 63 and of the Priests which could not find their
pedegree. 66 The whole number of them, with their substance. 70
Their oblations.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe when the wall was built, and I had set vp the doores; and the
porters, and the singers, and the Leuites were appointed,</ab>
<ab n="2">That I gaue my
brother Hanani, and Hananiah the ruler of the palace, charge ouer
Ierusalem (for hee was a faithfull man, and feared God aboue
many.)</ab>
<ab n="3">And I said vnto
them, Let not the gates of Ierusalem be opened, vntill the Sunne
bee hot; and while they stand by, let them shut the doores, and
barre them. And appoint watches of the inhabitants of Ierusalem,
euery one in his wateh, and euery one to bee ouer against his
house.</ab>
<ab n="4">Now the city was
large and great, but the people were few therein, and the houses
were not builded.<note> Hebr. broad in spaces.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And my God
put into mine heart, to gather together the nobles, and the rulers,
&amp; the people, that they might be reckoned by genealogie. And I
found a register of the genealogie of them which came vp at the
first, and found written therein;</ab>
<ab n="6">These are the
children of the prouince, that went vp out of the captiuitie, of
those that had beene caried away whom Nebuchadnezzar the King of
Babylon had caried away, and came againe to Ierusalem and to Iudah,
euery one vnto his citie:<note> Ezra. 2.1. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Who came with
Zerubbabel, Ieshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai,
Bilshan, Mispereth, Biguai, Nahum, Baanah. The number, I say, of
the men of the people of Israel, was this:<note> Or, Seraiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The children of
Parosh, two thousand, an hundred, seuentie and two.</ab>
<ab n="9">The children of
Shephatiah, three hundred, seuentie and two.</ab>
<ab n="10">The children of
Arah, sixe hundred, fiftie and two.</ab>

<fw>Who returned from Babylon to
Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="11">The children of
Pahath-Moab, of the children of Ieshua, and Ioab, two thousand, and
eight hundred, and eighteene.</ab>
<ab n="12">The children of
Elam, a thousand, two hundred, fiftie and foure.</ab>
<ab n="13">The children of
Zattu, eight hundred fourtie and fiue.</ab>
<ab n="14">The children of
Zaccai, seuen hundred and threescore.</ab>
<ab n="15">The children of
Binnui, sixe hundred, fourty and eight.<note> Or, Bani.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The children of
Bebai, sixe hundred, twentie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="17">The children of
Azgad, two thousand, three hundred, twentie and two.</ab>
<ab n="18">The children of
Adonikam, sixe hundred, threescore and seuen.</ab>
<ab n="19">The children of
Biguai, two thousand, threescore and seuen.</ab>
<ab n="20">The children of
Adin, sixe hundred, fiftie and fiue.</ab>
<ab n="21">The children of
Ater of Hezekiah, ninetie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="22">The children of
Hashum, three hundred, twentie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="23">The children of
Bezai, three hundred twentie and foure.</ab>
<ab n="24">The children of
Hariph, an hundred and twelue.<note> Or, Iora.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The children of
Gibeon, ninetie and fiue.<note> Or, Gibbar.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The men of
Bethlehem, and Netophah, an hundred, fourescore and eight.</ab>
<ab n="27">The men of
Anathoth, an hundred, twentie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="28">The men of
Bethazmaueth, fourtie and two.<note> Or, Azmaueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The men of
Kiriath-iearim, Chephirah and Beeroth, seuen hundred fourtie and
three.<note> Or, Kiriath-arim.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The men of Ramah
and Geba, sixe hundred, twentie and one.</ab>
<ab n="31">The men of
Michmash, an hundred and twenty and two.</ab>
<ab n="32">The men of
Bethel and Ai, an hundred, twentie and three.</ab>
<ab n="33">The men of the
other Nebo, fiftie and two.</ab>
<ab n="34">The children of
the other Elam, a thousand, two hundred, fiftie &amp;
foure.<note> See ver.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">The children of
Harim, three hundred and twentie.</ab>
<ab n="36">The children of
Iericho, three hundred, fourtie and fiue.</ab>
<ab n="37">The children of
Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seuen hundred, twentie and one.</ab>

<fw>Who returned from Babylon to
Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="38">The children of
Senaa, three thousand, nine hundred, and thirty.</ab>
<ab n="39">¶ The
Priests. The children of Iedaia, of the house of Ieshua, nine
hundred, seuentie and three.<note> 1.Chro. 24.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">The children of
Immer, a thousand, fifty and two.</ab>
<ab n="41">The children of
Pashur, a thousand, two hundred, fourtie and seuen.</ab>
<ab n="42">The children of
Harim, a thousand, and seuenteene.</ab>
<ab n="43">¶ The
Leuites. The children of Ieshua, of Kadmiel, and of the children of
Hodeuah, seuentie and foure.<note> Or, Hodauiah, Ezra 2.4. Or, Iudah, Ezra. 3.9</note></ab>
<ab n="44">¶ The
singers. The children of Asaph, an hundred, fourtie and
eight.</ab>
<ab n="45">¶ The
porters. The children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the
children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita,
the children of Shobai, an hundred, thirtie and eight.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ The
Nethinims. The children of Ziha, the children of Hashupha, the
children of Tabaoth,</ab>
<ab n="47">The children of
Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon,</ab>
<ab n="48">The children of
Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Shalmai,</ab>
<ab n="49">The children of
Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar,</ab>
<ab n="50">The children of
Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda,</ab>
<ab n="51">The children of
Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Phaseah,</ab>
<ab n="52">The children of
Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephishesim,</ab>
<ab n="53">The children of
Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur,</ab>
<ab n="54">The children of
Baslith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha,</ab>
<ab n="55">The children of
Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Tamiah,</ab>
<ab n="56">The children of
Neziah, the children of Hatipha.</ab>
<ab n="57">¶ The
children of Solomons seruants: The children of Sotai, the children
of Sophereth, the children of Perida,</ab>
<ab n="58">The children of
Iaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel,</ab>
<ab n="59">The children of
Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth
Zebaim, the children of Amon,<note> Or, Ami.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">All the
Nethinims, and the children of Solomons seruants, were three
hundred ninetie and two.</ab>

<fw>Gifts to the worke.</fw>
<ab n="61">And these were
they which went vp also from Tel-Melah, Tel-Haresha, Cherub, Addon,
and Immer: but they could not shewe their fathers house, nor their
seede, whether they were of Israel.<note> Ezra. 2. 43. , Or, pedegree.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">The children of
Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, sixe
hundred fourtie and two.</ab>
<ab n="63">¶ And of
the priests: the children of Habaiah, the children of Koz, the
children of Barzillai, which tooke one of the daughters of
Barzillai the Gileadite to wife, and was called after their
name.</ab>
<ab n="64">These sought
their register, among those that were reckoned by genealogie, but
it was not found: therfore were they, as polluted, put from the
priesthood.</ab>
<ab n="65">And the
Tirshatha said vnto them, that they should not eate of the most
holy things, till there stood vp a priest with Urim and
Thummim.<note> Or, the gouernour.</note></ab>
<ab n="66">¶ The whole
congregation together, was fourtie and two thousand, three hundred
and threescore:</ab>
<ab n="67">Beside their man
seruants, and their maid seruants, of whome there were seuen
thousand, three hundred, thirtie and seuen: and they had two
hundred fourtie and fiue singing men and singing women.</ab>
<ab n="68">Their horses,
seuen hundred, thirtie and sixe: their mules, two hundred fourtie
and fiue:</ab>
<ab n="69">Their camels,
foure hundred thirtie and fiue: sixe thousand, seuen hundred and
twentie asses.</ab>
<ab n="70">¶ And some
of the chiefe of the fathers, gaue vnto the worke: The Tirshatha
gaue to the treasure, a thousand drammes of gold, fiftie basons,
fiue hundred and thirtie priests garments.<note> Hebr. part.</note></ab>
<ab n="71">And some of the
chiefe of the fathers gaue to the treasure of the worke twentie
thousand drammes of golde, and two thousand and two hundred pound
of siluer.</ab>
<ab n="72">And that which
the rest of the people gaue, was twentie thousand drammes of gold,
and two thousand pound of siluer, and threescore and seuen priests
garments.</ab>
<ab n="73">So the priests,
and the Leuites, and the porters, and the singers, and some of the
people, and the Nethinims, and all Israel, dwelt in their cities:
And when the seuenth moneth came, the children of Israel were in
their cities.</ab>



</div>