<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-13-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Vpon the reading of the Law,
separation is made from the mixed multitude. 4 Nehemiah at his
returne, causeth the chambers to bee cleansed. 10 He reformeth the
offices in the house of God. 15 The violation of the Sabbath, 23
&amp; the mariages with strange wiues.</head>

<ab n="1">On that day they
read in the booke of Moses in the audience of the people, and
therein was found written, that the Ammonite and the Moabite should
not come into the Congregation of God for euer,<note> Heb. there was read. , Num. 22. 5. deut.23.3 , Heb. eares</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Because they met
not the children of Israel with bread, and with water, but hired
Balaam against them, that he should curse them: howbeit our God
turned the curse into a blessing.<note> Num. 22. 5. iosh.24.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now it came to
passe when they had heard the law, that they separated from Israel
all the mixed multitude.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And
before this Eliashib the priest hauing the ouersight of the chamber
of the house of our God, was allied vnto Tobiah:<note> Heb. being set ouer.</note></ab>

<fw>Abuses reformed.</fw>
<ab n="5">And hee had
prepared for him a great chamber, where aforetime they laid the
meat offrings, the frankincense and the vessels, and the tithes of
the corne, the new wine, and the oile, which was commanded to be
giuen to the Leuites, and the singers, and the porters, and the
offerings of the priests.<note> Hebr. the commandement of the Leuites.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But in all this
time was not I at Ierusalem: for in the two and thirtieth yeere of
Artaxerxes king of Babylon, came I vnto the king, and after
certaine dayes, obtained I leaue of the King:<note> Heb. at the end of daies. , Or, I earnestly requested.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And I came to
Ierusalem, and vnderstood of the euil that Eliashib did for Tobiah,
in preparing him a chamber in the courts of the house of
God.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it grieued
me sore, therefore I cast foorth all the houshold stuffe of Tobiah
out of the chamber:</ab>
<ab n="9">Then I
commanded, and they cleansed the chambers, and thither brought I
againe the vessels of the house of God, with the meate offering,
and the frankincense.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And I
perceiued that the portions of the Leuites had not beene giuen
them: for the Leuites and the singers that did the worke, were fled
euery one to his field.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then contended
I with the rulers, and said, Why is the house of God forsaken? And
I gathered them together, and set them in their place.<note> Heb. standing.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then brought
all Iudah the tithe of the corne, and the new wine, and the oyle,
vnto the treasuries.<note> Or, store-houses.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And I made
treasurers ouer the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the
scribe, and of the Leuites, Pedaiah: and next to them was Hanan the
sonne of Zaccur, the sonne of Mattaniah: for they were counted
faithfull, and their office was to distribute vnto their
brethren.<note> Hebr. at their hand. , Heb. it was vpon them.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Remember me, O
my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds, that I
haue done for the house of my God, and for the offices
thereof.<note> Verse 22. , Heb. kindnesses. , Or, obseruations.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ In those
dayes sawe I in Iudah, some treading wine presses on the Sabbath,
and bringing in sheaues, and lading asses, as also wine, grapes,
and figs, and all maner of burdens, which they brought into
Ierusalem on the Sabbath day: and I testified against them in the
day wherein they solde victuals.</ab>

<fw>Abuse of the Sabbath, reformed.</fw>
<ab n="16">There dwelt men
of Tyre also therein, which brought fish and all maner of ware, and
solde on the Sabbath vnto the children of Iudah, and in
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then I
contended with the Nobles of Iudah, and sayd vnto them, What euill
thing is this that ye doe, and profane the Sabbath day?</ab>
<ab n="18">Did not your
fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this euill vpon vs, and
vpon this citie? yet ye bring more wrath vpon Israel, by profaning
the Sabbath.</ab>
<ab n="19">And it came to
passe, that when the gates of Ierusalem beganne to be darke before
the Sabbath, I commanded that the gates should be shut, and charged
that they should not be opened till after the Sabbath: and some of
my seruants set I at the gates, that there should no burden be
brought in on the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="20">So the
merchants, and sellers of all kinde of ware, lodged without
Ierusalem once or twice.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then I
testified against them, and said vnto them, Why lodge yee about the
wall? If ye doe so againe, I will lay hands on you. From that time
forth came they no more on the Sabbath.<note> Heb. before the wall.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And I commanded
the Leuites, that they should cleanse themselues, and that they
should come and keepe the gates, to sanctifie the Sabbath day:
Remember me, O my God, concerning this also, and spare me,
according to the greatnesse of thy mercie.<note> Or, multitude.</note></ab>

<fw>Abuse of the Sabbath, reformed.</fw>
<ab n="23">¶ In those
dayes also sawe I Iewes that had maried wiues of Ashdod, of Ammon,
and of Moab:<note> Heb. had made to dwell with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And their
children spake halfe in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speake
in the Iewes language, but according to the language of ech
people.<note> Heb. they discerned not to speake. , Heb. of people and people.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And I contended
with them, and cursed them, and smote certeine of them, and pluckt
off their haire, and made them sweare by God, saying, Yee shall not
giue your daughters vnto their sonnes, nor take their daughters
vnto your sonnes, or for your selues.<note> Or, reuiled them.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Did not Solomon
king of Israel sinne by these things? yet among many nations was
there no king like him, who was beloued of his God, and God made
him king ouer all Israel: neuerthelesse, euen him did outlandish
women cause to sinne.<note> 1.King.11 1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Shall wee then
hearken vnto you, to doe all this great euill, to transgresse
against our God, in marrying strange wiues?</ab>
<ab n="28">And one of the
sonnes of Ioiada, the sonne of Eliashib the high Priest, was sonne
in law to Sanballat the Horonite: therfore I chased him from
me.</ab>
<ab n="29">Remember them,
O my God, because they haue defiled the Priesthood, and the
couenant of the Priesthood, and of the Leuites.<note> Heb. for the defilings.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Thus cleansed I
them from all strangers, and appointed the wards of the Priests and
the Leuites, euery one in his businesse:</ab>
<ab n="31">And for the
wood-offering, at times appointed, and for the first fruits.
Remember me, O my God, for good.</ab>



</div>