<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Sanballat practiseth by craft, by
rumours, by hired prophecies, to terrifie Nehemiah. 15 The worke is
finished to the terrour of the enemies. 17 Secret intelligence
passeth betweene the enemies, and the nobles of Iudah.</head>

<ab n="1">Now it came to
passe when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and Geshem the Arabian, and the
rest of our enemies heard, that I had builded the wall, and that
there was no breach left therein: (though at that time I had not
set vp the doores vpon the gates,)</ab>
<ab n="2">That Sanballat,
and Geshem sent vnto me, saying, Come, let vs meet together in some
one of the villages in the plaine of Ono: But they thought to doe
me mischiefe.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I sent
messengers vnto them, saying, I am doing a great worke, so that I
can not come down: why should the worke cease, whilest I leaue it,
and come downe to you?</ab>
<ab n="4">Yet they sent
vnto me foure times, after this sort; and I answered them after the
same maner.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then sent
Sanballat his seruant vnto me, in like manner, the fifth time, with
an open letter in his hand:</ab>
<ab n="6">Wherein was
written; It is reported among the heathen, and Gashmu sayth it,
that thou and the Iewes thinke to rebell: for which cause thou
buildest the wall, that thou mayest be their King, according to
these words.<note> Or, Geshem, ver. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And thou hast
also appointed Prophets to preach of thee at Ierusalem, saying,
There is a King in Iudah. And now shall it be reported to the king,
according to these wordes. Come now therefore, and let vs take
counsell together.</ab>

<fw>Tobiahs letters.</fw>
<ab n="8">Then I sent vnto
him, saying, There are no such things done as thou sayest, but thou
feignest them out of thine owne heart.</ab>
<ab n="9">For they all made
vs afraid, saying, Their handes shall be weakened from the worke
that it bee not done. Now therefore, O God, strengthen my
hands.</ab>
<ab n="10">Afterward I came
vnto the house of Shemaiah the sonne of Delaiah, the sonne of
Mehetabel, who was shut vp, and he said, Let vs meet together in
the house of God, within the Temple, and let vs shut the doores of
the Temple; for they will come to slay thee, yea in the night wil
they come to slay thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I said,
Should such a man as I, flee? and who is there, that being as I am,
would goe into the Temple to saue his life? I will not goe
in.</ab>
<ab n="12">And loe, I
perceiued that God had not sent him, but that he pronounced this
prophecie against mee: for Tobiah, and Sanballat had hired
him.</ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore was
hee hired, that I should be afraid, and doe so, and sinne, and that
they might haue matter for an euill report, that they might reproch
mee.</ab>
<ab n="14">My God, thinke
thou vpon Tobiah, and Sanballat, according to these their workes,
and on the prophetesse Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that
would haue put me in feare.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ So the
wall was finished, in the twentie and fifth day of the moneth Elul,
in fiftie and two dayes.</ab>
<ab n="16">And it came to
passe that when all our enemies heard thereof, and all the heathen,
that were about vs, saw these things, they were much cast downe in
their owne eyes: for they perceiued that this worke was wrought of
our God.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Moreouer,
in those dayes the nobles of Iudah sent many letters vnto Tobiah,
and the letters of Tobiah came vnto them.<note> Hebr. multiplied letters passing to Tobiah.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For there were
many in Iudah sworne vnto him: because hee was the sonne in law of
Shechaniah the sonne of Arah, and his sonne Iohanan had taken the
daughter of Meshullam, the sonne of Berechiah.</ab>
<ab n="19">Also they
reported his good deeds before me, and vttered my wordes to him:
and Tobiah sent letters to put me in feare.<note> Or, matters.</note></ab>




</div>