<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The Iewes complaine of their debt,
morgage, and bondage. 6 Nehemiah rebuketh the vsurers, and causeth
them to make a couenant of restitution. 14 Hee forbeareth his owne
allowance, and keepeth hospitalitie.</head>

<ab n="1">And there was a
great crie of the people, and of their wiues, against their
brethren the Iewes.</ab>
<ab n="2">For there were
that said, We, our sonnes, and our daughters are many: therefore
wee take vp corne for them, that we may eat, and liue.</ab>
<ab n="3">Some also there
were that saide, We haue morgaged our landes, vineyards and houses,
that we might buy corne, because of the dearth.</ab>
<ab n="4">There were also
that said, Wee haue borrowed money for the kings tribute, and that
vpon our lands and vineyards.</ab>
<ab n="5">Yet now our flesh
is as the flesh of our brethren, our children as their children:
and loe, wee bring into bondage our sonnes and our daughters, to
bee seruants, and some of our daughters are brought vnto bondage
already, neither is it in our power to redeeme them: for other men
haue our lands and vineyards.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And I was
very angry, when I heard their crie, and these words.</ab>

<fw>Vsurie reformed.</fw>
<ab n="7">Then I consulted
with my selfe, and I rebuked the Nobles, and the rulers, and said
vnto them, You exact vsurie, euery one of his brother. And I set a
great assembly against them:<note> Heb. my heart consulted in me.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I said vnto
them, We, after our abilitie, haue redeemed our brethren the Iewes,
which were sold vnto the heathen; and will you euen sell your
brethren? or shall they be sold vnto vs? Then held they their
peace, and found nothing to answere.<note> Leuit 25. 48.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Also I said, It
is not good that yee doe: ought yee not to walke in the feare of
our God, because of the reproch of the heathen our enemies?</ab>
<ab n="10">I likewise, and
my brethren, and my seruants, might exact of them money and corne:
I pray you let vs leaue off this vsurie.</ab>
<ab n="11">Restore, I pray
you, to them, euen this day, their lands, their vineyards, their
oliue-yards, and their houses, also the hundreth part of the money,
and of the corne, the wine, and the oyle, that ye exact of
them.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then said they,
Wee will restore them, and will require nothing of them; so will we
doe, as thou sayest. Then I called the Priests, and tooke an oath
of them, that they should doe according to this promise.</ab>
<ab n="13">Also I shooke my
lap, and said, So God shake out euery man from his house, and from
his labour, that performeth not this promise, euen thus be he
shaken out, and emptied. And all the Congregation said, Amen, and
praised the Lord. And the people did according to this
promise.<note> Heb. empty or void.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Moreouer,
from the time that I was appointed to be their gouernor in the land
of Iudah, from the twentieth yeere euen vnto the two and thirtieth
yere of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelue yeres, I and my
brethren, haue not eaten the bread of the gouernour:</ab>
<ab n="15">But the former
gouernours that had bene before me, were chargeable vnto the
people, and had taken of them bread, and wine, beside fourtie
shekels of siluer, yea euen their seruants bare rule ouer the
people: but so did not I, because of the feare of God.</ab>
<ab n="16">Yea also I
continued in the worke of this wall, neither bought wee any land:
and all my seruants were gathered thither vnto the worke.</ab>

<fw>Sanballats letters.</fw>
<ab n="17">Moreouer, there
were at my table, an hundred and fiftie of the Iewes and rulers,
besides those that came vnto vs from among the heathen that are
about vs.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now that which
was prepared for me daily, was one oxe, and sixe choice sheepe;
also foules were prepared for mee, and once in ten dayes, store of
all sorts of wine: yet for all this required not I the bread of the
gouernour, because the bondage was heauy vpon this people.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thinke vpon mee,
my God, for good, according to all that I haue done for this
people.<note> Chap.13. 22.</note></ab>



</div>