<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ezra-Chapter-10-10-Nehemiah.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Nehemiah, vnderstanding by Hanani,
the misery of Ierusalem, mourneth, fasteth and prayeth. 5 His
prayer.</head>

<ab n="1">The words of
Nehemiah the sonne of Hachaliah. And it came to passe in the moneth
Chisleu, in the twentieth yeere, as I was in Shushan the
palace;</ab>
<ab n="2">That Hanani, one
of my brethren came, he and certaine men of Iudah, and I asked them
concerning the Iewes that had escaped, which were left of the
captiuitie, and concerning Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they said
vnto me, The remnant that are left of the captiuitie there in the
prouince, are in great affliction and reproch: the wall of
Ierusalem also is broken downe, and the gates thereof are burnt
with fire.<note> 2.King.25. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And it
came to passe when I heard these words, that I sate downe and wept,
and mourned certaine dayes, and fasted, and prayed before the God
of heauen,</ab>

<fw>Nehemiahs prayer:</fw>
<ab n="5">And said, I
beseech thee, O Lord God of heauen, the great and terrible God,
that keepeth couenant and mercie for them that loue him, and
obserue his commandements:<note> Dan.9.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Let thine eare
now be attentiue, and thine eyes open, that thou mayest heare the
prayer of thy seruant, which I pray before thee now, day and night,
for the children of Israel thy seruants, and confesse the sinnes of
the children of Israel, which wee haue sinned against thee: both I,
and my fathers house haue sinned.</ab>
<ab n="7">We haue dealt
very corruptly against thee, and haue not kept the commandements,
nor the statutes, nor the iudgements, which thou commandedst thy
seruant Moses.</ab>
<ab n="8">Remember, I
beseech thee, the word that thou commandedst thy seruant Moses,
saying, If yee transgresse, I will scatter you abroad among the
nations:<note> Deut.4. 5. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But if ye turne
vnto me, and keepe my commandements, and doe them: though there
were of you cast out vnto the vttermost part of the heauen, yet
will I gather them from thence, and will bring them vnto the place
that I haue chosen, to set my Name there.<note> Deut. 30. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Now these are
thy seruants, and thy people, whom thou hast redeemed by thy great
power, and by thy strong hand.</ab>
<ab n="11">O Lord, I
beseech thee, let now thine eare be attentiue to the prayer of thy
seruant, and to the prayer of thy seruants, who desire to feare thy
name: and prosper, I pray thee, thy seruant this day, and grant him
mercie in the sight of this man. For I was the kings
cup-bearer.</ab>



</div>