<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNehemiah_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Nehemiah-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The names and order of them that
builded the wall.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Eliashib the
hie priest, rose vp with his brethren the Priests, and they built
the sheepe-gate, they sanctified it, &amp; set vp the doores of it,
euen vnto the towre of Meah they sanctified it, vnto the towre of
Hananeel.<note> Iere.3. 38.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And next vnto him
builded the men of Iericho: and next to them builded Zaccur the
sonne of Imri.<note> Hebr. at his hand.</note></ab>

<fw>The building of the walles.</fw>
<ab n="3">But the fish-gate
did the sonnes of Hassenaah build, who also laide the beames
thereof, and set vp the doores thereof, the locks thereof, and the
barres thereof.</ab>
<ab n="4">And next vnto
them repaired Merimoth the son of Uriah, the sonne of Koz: and next
vnto them repaired Meshullam the sonne of Berechiah, the sonne of
Meshezabeel: and next vnto them repaired Zadok the sonne of
Baana.</ab>
<ab n="5">And uext vnto
them, the Tekoites repaired; but their nobles put not their neckes
to the worke of their Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">Moreouer the olde
gate repaired Iehoiada the sonne of Paseah, and Meshullam the sonne
of Besodaiah; they laid the beames thereof, and set vp the doores
thereof, and the lockes thereof, and the barres thereof.</ab>
<ab n="7">And next vnto
them repaired Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Iadon the Meronothite,
the men of Gibeon, and of Mizpah, vnto the throne of the gouernour
on this side the Riuer.</ab>
<ab n="8">Next vnto him
repaired Uzziel the sonne of Harhaiah, of the goldsmiths: next vnto
him also repaired Hananiah, the sonne of one of the Apothecaries,
and they fortified Ierusalem vnto the broad wall.<note> Or, left Ierusalem vnto the broad wall.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And next vnto
them repaired Rephaiah the sonne of Hur, the ruler of the halfe
part of Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="10">And next vnto
them repaired Iedaiah the sonne of Harumaph, euen ouer against his
house: and next vnto him repaired Hattush the sonne of
Hashabniah.</ab>
<ab n="11">Malchiiah the
sonne of Harim, and Hashub the son of Pahath Moab, repaired the
other piece, &amp; the towre of the furnaces.<note> Hebr. second measure.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And next vnto
him repaired Shallum the sonne of Halloesh the ruler of the halfe
part of Ierusalem, hee, and his daughters.</ab>
<ab n="13">The valley-gate
repaired Hanun, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they built it, and
set vp the doores thereof, the lockes thereof, and the bars
thereof, and a thousand cubits on the wall, vnto the
doung-gate.</ab>
<ab n="14">But the
doung-gate repaired Malchiah the sonne of Rechab, the ruler of part
of Beth-haccerem: hee built it, and set vp the doores thereof, the
lockes thereof, and the barres thereof.</ab>

<fw>The building of the walles.</fw>
<ab n="15">But the gate of
the fountaine repaired Shallum the sonne of Col-hozeh, the ruler of
part of Mizpah: hee built it, and couered it, and set vp the doores
thereof, the lockes thereof, and the barres thereof, and the wall
of the poole of Siloah by the kings garden, and vnto the staires
that goe downe from the citie of Dauid.<note> Iohn 9.7</note></ab>
<ab n="16">After him
repaired Nehemiah the sonne of Azbuk, the ruler of the halfe part
of Beth-zur, vnto the place ouer against the sepulchres of Dauid,
and to the poole that was made, and vnto the house of the
mightie.<note> 2.King. 20.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">After him
repaired the Leuites, Rehum the sonne of Bani: next vnto him
repaired Hashabiah the ruler of the halfe part of Keilah in his
part.</ab>
<ab n="18">After him
repaired their brethren, Bauai, the sonne of Henadad the ruler of
the halfe part of Keilah.</ab>
<ab n="19">And next to him
repaired Ezer the sonne of Ieshua, the ruler of Mizpah, another
piece, ouer against the going vp to the armorie, at the turning of
the wall.</ab>
<ab n="20">After him Baruch
the sonne of Zabbai, earnestly repaired the other piece, from the
turning of the wall vnto the doore of the house of Eliashib the
high Priest.<note> Or, Zaccai.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">After him
repaired Merimoth the sonne of Uriiah, the sonne of Koz, another
piece, from the doore of the house of Eliashib, euen to the end of
the house of Eliashib.</ab>
<ab n="22">And after him
repaired the Priests, the men of the plaine.</ab>
<ab n="23">After him
repaired Beniamin, and Hashub, ouer against their house: after him
repaired Azariah the sonne of Maaseiah, the sonne of Ananiah, by
his house.</ab>
<ab n="24">After him
repaired Binnui the sonne of Henadad, another piece from the house
of Azariah, vnto the turning of the wall, euen vnto the
corner.</ab>
<ab n="25">Palal the sonne
of Uzai, ouer against the turning of the wall, and the tower which
lyeth out, from the kings hie house, that was by the court of the
prison: after him, Pedaiah the sonne of Parosh.<note> Iere. 32. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Moreouer the
Nethinims dwelt in Ophel, vnto the place ouer against the water
gate, toward the East, and the tower that lieth out.<note> 2.Chron. 27.3. , Or, the tower</note></ab>
<ab n="27">After them the
Tekoites repaired another piece, ouer against the great tower that
lieth out, euen vnto the wall of Ophel.</ab>

<fw>The building of the walles.</fw>
<ab n="28">From aboue the
horsegate repaired the Priests, euery one ouer against his
house.</ab>
<ab n="29">After them
repaired Zadok the sonne of Immer, ouer against his house: after
him repaired also Shemaiah, the son of Shechaniah, the keeper of
the East-gate.</ab>
<ab n="30">After him
repaired Hananiah the sonne of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth sonne
of Zalaph, another piece: after him repaired Meshullam, the sonne
of Berechiah ouer against his chamber.</ab>
<ab n="31">After him
repaired Malchiah, the goldsmiths sonne, vnto the place of the
Nethinims, and of the merchants, ouer against the gate Miphkad, and
to the going vp of the corner.<note> Or, corner chamber.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And betweene the
going vp of the corner vnto the sheepe-gate, repaired the
gold-smithes and the merchants.</ab>



</div>