<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 How the lampes are to be lighted.
5 The consecration of the Leuites. 23 The age and time of their
seruice.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto Aaron,
and say vnto him, When thou lightest the lampes, the seuen lampes
shall giue light, ouer against the candlesticke.<note> Exod.25. 37.and 40. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Aaron did so;
he lighted the lampes therof, ouer against the candlestick, as the
Lord comanded Moses.<note> Exod. 25. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And this worke of
the candlestick was of beaten gold, vnto the shaft thereof, vnto
the flowres thereof was beaten worke: according vnto the paterne
which the Lord had shewed Moses, so he made the
candlesticke.<note> Exod.25. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="6">Take the Leuites
from among the children of Israel, and cleanse them.</ab>
<ab n="7">And thus shalt
thou doe vnto them, to cleanse them: sprinkle water of purifying
vpon them, and let them shaue all their flesh, and let them wash
their clothes, and so make themselues cleane.<note> Hebr, let them cause a rasor to passe ouer, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Then let them take
a yong bullocke with his meat offering, euen fine flowre mingled
with oyle, and an other yong bullock shalt thou take for a sinne
offering.</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou shalt
bring the Leuites before the Tabernacle of the Congregation; and
thou shalt gather the whole assembly of the children of Israel
together.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
bring the Leuites before the Lord, and the children of Israel shall
put their hands vpon the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Aaron shall
offer the Leuites before the Lord for an offring of the children of
Israel, that they may execute the seruice of the Lord.<note> Heb. waue. , Heb. waue offering. , Hebr. they may be to execute, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the Leuites
shall lay their hands vpon the heads of the bullocks: and thou
shalt offer the one for a sinne offering, and the other for a burnt
offering vnto the Lord, to make an atonement for the
Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="13">And thou shalt
set the Leuites before Aaron, and before his sonnes, and offer them
for an offering vnto the Lord.</ab>

<fw>The cleansing the Leuites.</fw>
<ab n="14">Thus shalt thou
separate the Leuites from among the children of Israel: and the
Leuites shalbe mine.<note> Chap.3. 45.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And after that,
shall the Leuites goe in; to doe the seruice of the Tabernacle of
the Congregation: and thou shalt clense them, and offer them for an
offering.</ab>
<ab n="16">For they are
wholly giuen vnto me, from among the children of Israel: in stead
of such as open euery wombe, euen in stead of the first borne of
all the children of Israel, haue I taken them vnto me.<note> Chap.3. 13. exod. 13.2. luke 2.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For all the first
borne of the children of Israel, are mine, both man and beast: on
the day that I smote euery first borne in the land of Egypt, I
sanctified them for my selfe.</ab>
<ab n="18">And I haue taken
the Leuites for all the first borne of the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I haue giuen
the Leuites as a gift to Aaron, and to his sonnes, from among the
children of Israel, to do the seruice of the children of Israel, in
the Tabernacle of the Congregation, and to make an atonement for
the children of Israel: that there bee no plague among the children
of Israel, when the children of Israel come nigh vnto the
Sanctuarie.<note> Heb. giuen.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Moses and
Aaron, and all the Congregation of the children of Israel did to
the Leuites according vnto all that the Lord commanded Moses,
concerning the Leuites, so did the children of Israel vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the Leuites
were purified, and they washed their clothes: and Aaron offered
them as an offering before the Lord, and Aaron made an atonement
for them to cleanse them.</ab>
<ab n="22">And after that,
went the Leuites in, to do their seruice in the Tabernacle of the
Congregation before Aaron and and before his sonnes: as the Lord
had commanded Moses concerning the Leuites, so did they vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="24">This is it that
belongeth vnto the Leuites: from twentie and fiue yeeres old, and
vpward, they shall goe in to waite vpon the seruice of the
Tabernacle of the Congregation.<note> Heb. to warre the warfare of &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And from the age
of fiftie yeeres they shall cease waiting vpon the seruice thereof,
and shall serue no more:<note> Hebr. returne from the warfare of the seruice</note></ab>

<fw>The Passeouer.</fw>
<ab n="26">But shall
minister with their brethren in the Tabernacle of the Congregation,
to keepe the charge, and shall doe no seruice: thus shalt thou doe
vnto the Leuites, touching their charge.</ab>



</div>