<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 Eight and fourtie Cities for the
Leuites with their suburbs, and measure thereof. 6 Sixe of them are
to be cities of refuge. 9 The lawes of murder. 31 No satisfaction
for murder.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses in the plaines of Moab by Iordane, neere Iericho,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Command the
children of Israel, that they giue vnto the Leuites of the
inheritance of their possession, cities to dwell in: and yee shall
giue also vnto the Leuites suburbs for the cities round about
them.<note> Iosh.21. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And the cities
shall they haue to dwell in, and the suburbs of them shall be for
their cattell, and for their goods, and for all their
beasts.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the suburbs
of the cities, which yee shall giue vnto the Leuites, shall reach
from the wall of the citie, and outward, a thousand cubites round
about.</ab>

<fw>Cities of refuge.</fw>
<ab n="5">And ye shall
measure from without the city on the Eastside two thousand cubites,
and on the Southside two thousand cubites, and on the Westside two
thousand cubites, &amp; on the Northside two thousand cubites: and
the citie shall be in the midst; this shalbe to them the suburbs of
the cities.</ab>
<ab n="6">And among the
cities which yee shal giue vnto the Leuites, there shalbe sixe
cities for refuge, which ye shall appoint for the manslayer, that
hee may flee thither: And to them ye shall adde fourty and two
cities.<note> Deut.4. 41. iosh.20. 2. and 21.3. , Hebr. aboue them ye shall giue.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So all the cities
which ye shall giue to the Leuites, shall be fourty and eight
cities: them shall yee giue with their suburbs.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the cities
which ye shal giue, shalbe of the possession of the children of
Israel: from them that haue many ye shall giue many; but from them
that haue few, ye shall giue few. Euery one shal giue of his cities
vnto the Leuites, according to his inheritance which he
inheriteth.<note> Hebr. they inherite.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="10">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When ye bee come ouer
Iordane, into the land of Canaan:<note> Deut.19. 2. iosh.20. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Then ye shall
appoint you cities, to be cities of refuge for you; that the slayer
may flee thither which killeth any person at vnawares.<note> Hebr. by error.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they shall
be vnto you cities for refuge from the auenger, that the man-slayer
die not, vntill he stand before the Congregation in
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="13">And of these
cities which ye shall giue, sixe cities shall ye haue for
refuge.</ab>
<ab n="14">Yee shall giue
three cities on this side Iordane, and three cities shall yee giue
in the land of Canaan, which shall be cities of refuge.</ab>
<ab n="15">These sixe
cities shall be a refuge, both for the children of Israel, and for
the stranger, and for the soiourner among them: that euery one that
killeth any person vnawares, may flee thither.</ab>
<ab n="16">And if he smite
him with an instrument of Iron, (so that he die,) hee is a
murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to death.<note> Exod.21. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And if he smite
him with throwing a stone, (wherewith hee may die) and he die, he
is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to
death.<note> Hebr. with a stone of the hand.</note></ab>

<fw>Lawes for shedding of blood.</fw>
<ab n="18">Or if he smite
him with an handweapon of wood, (wherewith he may die) and he die,
hee is a murderer: the murderer shall surely be put to
death.</ab>
<ab n="19">The reuenger of
blood himselfe shall slay the murtherer: when he meeteth him, he
shall slay him.</ab>
<ab n="20">But if he thrust
him of hatred, or hurle at him by laying of waite that he
die,<note> Deut. 19. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Or in enmitie
smite him with his hand, that he die: hee that smote him shall
surely be put to death, for hee is a murderer: the reuenger of
blood shall slay the murderer, when hee meeteth him.</ab>
<ab n="22">But if hee
thrust him suddenly without enmitie, or haue cast vpon him any
thing without laying of wait,<note> Exod. 21. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Or with any
stone wherewith a man may die, seeing him not, and cast it vpon
him, that he die, and was not his enemie, neither sought his
harme:</ab>
<ab n="24">Then the
Congregation shall iudge betweene the slayer, and the reuenger of
blood, according to these iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the
Congregation shall deliuer the slayer out of the hand of the
reuenger of blood, and the Congregation shal restore him to the
city of his refuge, whither he was fled: and he shall abide in it
vnto the death of the high Priest, which was annoynted with the
holy oyle.</ab>
<ab n="26">But if the
slayer shall at any time come without the border of the citie of
his refuge, whither he was fled:</ab>
<ab n="27">And the reuenger
of blood finde him without the borders of the citie of his refuge,
and the reuenger of blood kill the slayer, he shall not be guiltie
of blood:<note> Hebr. no blood shalbe to him.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Because he
should haue remained in the citie of his refuge, vntill the death
of the high Priest: but after the death of the hie Priest, the
slayer shal returne into the land of his possession.</ab>
<ab n="29">So these things
shall be for a statute of iudgment vnto you, thorowout your
generations in al your dwellings.</ab>
<ab n="30">Who so killeth
any person, the murderer shall be put to death, by the mouth of
witnesses: but one witnesse shall not testifie against any person,
to cause him to die.<note> Deut.17. 6.and 19. 15. matt.18 16. 2.cor. 13.1. Heb.10.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Moreouer, yee
shall take no satisfaction for the life of a murderer, which is
guiltie of death, but he shalbe surely put to death.<note> Heb. faulty to die.</note></ab>

<fw>Lawes for shedding of blood.</fw>
<ab n="32">And yee shall
take no satisfaction for him that is fled to the citie of his
refuge, that hee should come againe to dwell in the land, vntil the
death of the Priest.</ab>
<ab n="33">So ye shall not
pollute the lande wherein ye are: for blood, it defileth the land:
and the land cannot bee cleansed of the blood that is shed therein,
but by the blood of him that shed it.<note> Heb. there can be no expiation for the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Defile not
therefore the lande which yee shall inhabite, wherein I dwell: for
I the Lord dwell among the children of Israel.</ab>



</div>