<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>1 The children of Israel come to
Zin, where Miriam dieth. 2 They murmure for want of water. 7 Moses
smiting the rocke bringeth forth water at Meribah. 14 Moses at
Kadesh desireth passage thorow Edom, which is denied him. 22 At
Mount Hor Aaron resigneth his place to Eleazar, and
dieth.</head>

<ab n="1">Then came the
children of Israel, euen the whole Congregation, into the desert of
Zin, in the first moneth: and the people abode in Kadesh, and
Miriam died there, and was buried there.</ab>
<ab n="2">And there was no
water for the Congregation: and they gathered themselues together
against Moses and against Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the people
chode with Moses, and spake, saying, Would God that we had died
when our brethren died before the Lord.<note> Chap.11. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And why haue yee
brought vp the Congregation of the Lord into this wildernesse, that
we and our cattell should die there?<note> Exod. 17. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And wherefore
haue ye made vs to come vp out of Egypt, to bring vs in vnto this
euil place? it is no place of seed, or of figges, or vines, or of
pomegranates, neither is there any water to drinke.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses and
Aaron went from the presence of the assembly, vnto the doore of the
Tabernacle of the congregation, and they fell vpon their faces: and
the glory of the Lord appeared vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>The rocke smitten.</fw>
<ab n="8">Take the rodde,
and gather thou the assembly together, thou and Aaron thy brother,
and speake yee vnto the rocke before their eyes, and it shall giue
foorth his water, and thou shalt bring foorth to them, water out of
the rocke: so thou shalt giue the Congregation, and their beasts
drinke.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Moses tooke
the rod from before the Lord, as he commanded him.</ab>
<ab n="10">And Moses and
Aaron gathered the Congregation together before the rocke, and hee
said vnto them, Heare now, ye rebels; must we fetch you water out
of this rocke?</ab>
<ab n="11">And Moses lift
vp his hand, and with his rod he smote the rocke twice: and the
water came out abundantly, and the Congregation dranke, and their
beasts also.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses and Aaron, Because ye beleeue me not, to
sanctifie me in the eyes of the children of Israel, therefore ye
shall not bring this Congregation into the land which I haue giuen
them.</ab>
<ab n="13">This is the
water of Meribah, because the children of Israel stroue with the
Lord; and he was sanctified in them.<note> Psal. 106. 32. &amp;c. , That is, strife.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And Moses
sent messengers from Kadesh, vnto the King of Edom; Thus saith thy
brother Israel, Thou knowest all the trauaile that hath befallen
vs:<note> Hebr. found vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">How our fathers
went downe into Egypt, and we haue dwelt in Egypt a long time: and
the Egyptians vexed vs, and our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="16">And when wee
cryed vnto the Lord, he heard our voyce, and sent an Angel, and
hath brought vs foorth out of Egypt: and behold, wee are in Kadesh,
a citie in the vttermost of thy border.</ab>
<ab n="17">Let vs passe, I
pray thee, thorow thy countrey: we will not passe thorow the
fields, or thorow the Uineyards, neither will we drinke of the
water of the wells: wee will goe by the Kings high-way, we wil not
turne to the right hand nor to the left, vntill wee haue passed thy
borders.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Edom said
vnto him, Thou shalt not passe by me, lest I come out against thee
with the sword.</ab>

<fw>Aaron dieth.</fw>
<ab n="19">And the children
of Israel said vnto him, We will goe by the high-way: and if I and
my cattell drinke of thy water, then I will pay for it: I will
onely (without doing any thing else) go thorow on my feet.</ab>
<ab n="20">And he said,
Thou shalt not goe thorow. And Edom came out against him with much
people, and with a strong hand.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thus Edom
refused to giue Israel passage thorow his border: wherefore Israel
turned away from him.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
children of Israel, euen the whole Congregation, iourneyed from
Kadesh, and came vnto mount Hor.<note> Chap.33. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses and Aaron in mount Hor, by the coast of the land
of Edom, saying;</ab>
<ab n="24">Aaron shall bee
gathered vnto his people: for hee shall not enter into the land
which I haue giuen vnto the children of Israel, because yee
rebelled against my word at the water of Meribah.<note> Hebr. mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Take Aaron, and
Eleazar his sonne, and bring them vp vnto mount Hor.<note> Chap.33. 38. deut. 32.50.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And strippe
Aaron of his garments, and put them vpon Eleazar his sonne, and
Aaron shall be gathered vnto his people, and shall die
there.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Moses did as
the Lord commaunded: and they went vp into mount Hor, in the sight
of all the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Moses
stripped Aaron of his garments, and put them vpon Eleazar his
sonne, and Aaron died there in the top of the mount: and Moses and
Eleazar came downe from the mount.<note> Deut.10. 6.and 32. 50.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And when all the
Congregation saw that Aaron was dead, they mourned for Aaron thirty
dayes, euen all the house of Israel.</ab>



</div>