<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-33-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 Two and fourtie iourneyes of the
Israelites. 50 The Canaanites are to be destroyed.</head>

<ab n="1">These are the
iourneyes of the children of Israel, which went foorth out of the
land of Egypt, with their armies, vnder the hand of Moses and
Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Moses wrote
their goings out according to their iourneyes, by the commandement
of the Lord: and these are their iourneyes according to their
goings out.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they departed
from Rameses in the first moneth, on the fifteenth day of the first
moneth: on the morrow after the Passeouer, the children of Israel
went out with an high hand in the sight of all the
Egyptians.<note> Exod.12. 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">(For the
Egyptians buried all their first borne, which the Lord had smitten
among them: vpon their gods also the Lord executed
iudgements.)</ab>
<ab n="5">And the children
of Israel remoued from Rameses, and pitched in Succoth.</ab>

<fw>The remouings of the
Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="6">And they departed
from Succoth, and pitched in Etham, which is in the edge of the
wildernesse.<note> Exod. 13. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And they remoued
from Etham, and turned againe vnto Pihahiroth, which is before
Baal-zephon: and they pitched before Migdol.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they departed
from before Pihahiroth, and passed thorow the midst of the sea,
into the wildernes, and went three dayes iourney in the wildernesse
of Etham, and pitched in Marah.<note> Exod. 15. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And they remoued
from Marah, and came vnto Elim, and in Elim were twelue fountaines
of water, and three score and ten palme trees, and they pitched
there.<note> Exod. 15. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And they
remooued from Elim, and encamped by the red sea.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they
remooued from the red sea, and encamped in the wildernesse of
Sin.<note> Exod. 16. 1</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they tooke
their iourney out of the wildernesse of Sin, and encamped in
Dophkah.</ab>
<ab n="13">And they
departed from Dophkah, and encamped in Alush.</ab>
<ab n="14">And they remoued
from Alush, and encamped at Rephidim, where was no water for the
people to drinke.<note> Exod 17. 1</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And they
departed from Rephidim, and pitched in the wildernesse of
Sinai.<note> Exod 19. 1</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And they remoued
from the desert of Sinai, and pitched at Kibroth
Hattaauah.<note> Chap. 11. 34. , That is, The graues of lust.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And they
departed from Kibroth Hattaauah, and encamped at
Hazeroth.<note> Chap. 11. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And they
departed from Hazeroth, and pitched in Rithmah.</ab>
<ab n="19">And they
departed from Rithmah, and pitched at Rimmon Parez.</ab>
<ab n="20">And they
departed from Rimmon Parez, and pitched in Libnah.</ab>
<ab n="21">And they remoued
from Libnah, and pitched at Rissah.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they
iourneyed from Rissah, and pitched in Kehelathah.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they went
from Kehelathah, and pitched in mount Shapher.</ab>
<ab n="24">And they remoued
from mount Shapher, and encamped in Haradah.</ab>
<ab n="25">And they
remooued from Haradah, and pitched in Makheloth.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they
remooued from Makheloth, and encamped at Tahath.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they
departed from Tahath, and pitched at Tarah.</ab>

<fw>The remouings of the
Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="28">And they remoued
from Tarah, and pitched in Mithcah.</ab>
<ab n="29">And they went
from Mithcah, and pitched in Hashmonah.</ab>
<ab n="30">And they
departed from Hashmonah, and encamped at Moseroth.<note> Deu. 10. 6</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And they
departed from Moseroth, and pitched in Bene-Iaakan.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they
remooued from Bene-Iaakan, &amp; encamped at Horhagidgad.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they went
from Horhagidgad, and pitched in Iotbathah.</ab>
<ab n="34">And they
remooued from Iotbathah, and encamped at Ebronah.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they
departed from Ebronah, and encamped at Ezion-gaber.</ab>
<ab n="36">And they remoued
from Ezion-gaber, and pitched in the wildernes of Zin, which is
Kadesh.<note> Chap. 20. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And they
remooued from Kadesh, and pitched in mount Hor, in the edge of the
land of Edom.<note> Chap. 20. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">And Aaron the
Priest went vp into mount Hor, at the commandement of the Lord, and
died there in the fourtieth yeere, after the children of Israel
were come out of the lande of Egypt, in the first day of the fift
moneth.<note> Chap. 20. 25. deut. 32.50.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And Aaron was an
hundred and twentie and three yeeres old, when hee died in mount
Hor.</ab>
<ab n="40">And King Arad
the Canaanite (which dwelt in the South, in the land of Canaan)
heard of the comming of the children of Israel.<note> Chap. 21. 1, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And they
departed from mount Hor, and pitched in Zalmonah.<note> Cha. 21.4</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And they
departed from Zalmonah, and pitched in Punon.</ab>
<ab n="43">And they
departed from Punon, and pitched in Oboth.</ab>
<ab n="44">And they
departed from Oboth, and pitched in Iie-Abarim, in the border of
Moab.<note> Or, heapes of Abarim.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">And they
departed from Iim, and pitched in Dibon Gad.</ab>
<ab n="46">And they remoued
from Dibon Gad, and encamped in Almon-Diblathaim.</ab>
<ab n="47">And they
remooued from Almon-Diblathaim, and pitched in the mountaines of
Abarim, before Nebo.</ab>
<ab n="48">And they
departed from the mountaines of Abarim, and pitched in the plaines
of Moab, by Iordan neere Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="49">And they pitched
by Iordane from Beth-Iesimoth, euen vnto Abel Shittim, in the
plaines of Moab.<note> Or, the plaines of Shittim. , Chap. 25. 1.</note></ab>

<fw>The borders of Canaan.</fw>
<ab n="50">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, in the plaines of Moab by Iordane, neere
Iericho, saying,</ab>
<ab n="51">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When ye are passed ouer
Iordane into the land of Canaan;<note> Deut. 7.2. iosh. 11.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">Then ye shall
driue out all the inhabitants of the land from before you, and
destroy all their pictures, and destroy all their molten images,
and quite plucke downe all their high places.</ab>
<ab n="53">And ye shall
dispossesse the inhabitants of the land, and dwell therein: for I
haue giuen you the land to possesse it.</ab>
<ab n="54">And ye shall
diuide the land by lot, for an inheritance among your families, and
to the moe ye shall giue the more inheritance, and to the fewer yee
shall giue the lesse inheritance: euery mans inheritance shall bee
in the place where his lot falleth, according to the tribes of your
fathers, ye shall inherite.<note> Chap. 26. 53. , Hebr. multiply his inheritance. , Hebr. diminish his inheritance.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">But if ye will
not driue out the inhabitants of the land from before you, then it
shall come to passe that those which ye let remaine of them, shall
be prickes in your eyes, and thornes in your sides, and shal vexe
you in the land wherein ye dwell.<note> Iosh. 23. 13. iudg. 2. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">Moreouer, it
shall come to passe, that I shall do vnto you, as I thought to doe
vnto them.</ab>



</div>