<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 The names of the men who were sent
to search the land. 17 Their instructions. 21 Their actes. 26 Their
relation.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Send thou men,
that they may search the lande of Canaan, which I giue vnto the
children of Israel: of euery tribe of their fathers shal ye send a
man, euery one a ruler among them.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Moses by the
commaundement of the Lord, sent them from the wildernes of Paran:
all those men were heads of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">And these were
their names. Of the tribe of Reuben, Shammua the sonne of
Zaccur.</ab>
<ab n="5">Of the tribe of
Simeon, Shaphat the sonne of Hori.</ab>
<ab n="6">Of the tribe of
Iudah, Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh.</ab>
<ab n="7">Of the tribe of
Issachar, Igal the sonne of Ioseph.</ab>
<ab n="8">Of the tribe of
Ephraim, Oshea the sonne of Nun.</ab>
<ab n="9">Of the tribe of
Beniamin, Palti the sonne of Raphu.</ab>
<ab n="10">Of the tribe of
Zebulun, Gaddiel the sonne of Sodi.</ab>
<ab n="11">Of the tribe of
Ioseph, namely of the tribe of Manasseh, Gaddi the sonne of
Susi.</ab>
<ab n="12">Of the tribe of
Dan, Ammiel the sonne of Gemalli.</ab>
<ab n="13">Of the tribe of
Asher, Sethur the sonne of Michael.</ab>
<ab n="14">Of the tribe of
Naphtali, Nahbi the sonne of Uophsi.</ab>
<ab n="15">Of the tribe of
Gad, Geuel the sonne of Machi.</ab>
<ab n="16">These are the
names of the men which Moses sent to spie out the land: and Moses
called Oshea the sonne of Nun, Iehoshua.</ab>

<fw>Spies are sent to search the
land.</fw>
<ab n="17">¶ And Moses
sent them to spie out the land of Canaan, and said vnto them, Get
you by this way Southward, and goe vp into the mountaine:</ab>
<ab n="18">And see the
lande what it is, and the people that dwelleth therein, whether
they bee strong or weake, fewe or many:</ab>
<ab n="19">And what the
lande is that they dwell in, whether it be good or bad, and what
cities they bee that they dwell in, whether in tents, or in strong
holds:</ab>
<ab n="20">And what the
land is, whether it be fat or leane, whether there be wood therein,
or not. And be ye of good courage, and bring of the fruit of the
land: (Now the time was the time of the first ripe grapes)</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ So they
went vp, and searched the land, from the wildernesse of Zin, vnto
Rehob, as men come to Hamath.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they
ascended by the South, and came vnto Hebron: where Ahiman, Sheshai,
and Talmai, the children of Anak were: Now Hebron was built seuen
yeeres before Zoan in Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they came
vnto the brooke of Eshcol, and cut downe from thence a branch with
one cluster of grapes, and they bare it betweene two vpon a staffe,
and they brought of the pomegranates and of the figs.<note> Deut.1. 24. , Or, valley</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The place was
called the brooke Eshcol, because of the cluster of grapes which
the children of Israel cut downe from thence.<note> Or, valley. , i. a cluster of grapes.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And they
returned from searching of the land after fourty dayes.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And they
went and came to Moses, and to Aaron, and to all the Congregation
of the children of Israel vnto the wildernesse of Paran, to Kadesh,
and brought backe word vnto them, and vnto all the Congregation,
and shewed them the fruit of the land.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they told
him, and said, We came vnto the land whither thou sentest vs, &amp;
surely it floweth with milke and honie; and this is the fruit of
it.<note> Exod. 33. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Neuerthelesse,
the people bee strong that dwell in the land, and the cities are
walled and very great: and moreouer, we saw the children of Anak
there.</ab>

<fw>Murmuring.</fw>
<ab n="29">The Amalekites
dwell in the land of the South: and the Hittites, and the
Iebusites, and the Amorites dwell in the mountaines: and the
Canaanites dwell by the sea, and by the coast of Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Caleb
stilled the people before Moses, and said, Let vs goe vp at once,
and possesse it, for we are well able to ouercome it.</ab>
<ab n="31">But the men that
went vp with him, said, Wee be not able to goe vp against the
people, for they are stronger then we.</ab>
<ab n="32">And they brought
vp an euill report of the land which they had searched, vnto the
children of Israel, saying, The land through which we haue gone, to
search it, is a land that eateth vp the inhabitants thereof, and
all the people that we saw in it, are men of a great
stature.<note> Heb. men of statures.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And there we saw
the giants, the sonnes of Anak, which come of the giants: and wee
were in our owne sight as grashoppers, and so wee were in their
sight.</ab>




</div>