<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-16-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>1 The rebellion of Korah, Dathan and
Abiram, 23 Moses separateth the people from the rebels tents, 31
The earth swalloweth vp Korah, and a fire consumeth others. 36 The
censers are reserued to holy vse. 41 Foureteene thousand and seuen
hundred are slaine by a plague for murmuring against Moses and
Aaron. 46 Aaron by incense stayeth the plague.</head>

<ab n="1">Now Korah the
sonne of Izhar, the sonne of Kohath, the sonne of Leui, and Dathan,
and Abiram the sonnes of Eliab, and On the sonne of Peleth, sonnes
of Reuben, tooke men.<note> Chap.27. 3. ecclus. 45.21. iud. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And they rose vp
before Moses, with certaine of the children of Israel, two hundred
and fiftie Princes of the assembly, famous in the Congregation, men
of renowne.<note> Chap.26. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And they gathered
themselues together against Moses, and against Aaron, and said vnto
them, Ye take too much vpon you, seeing all the Congregation are
holy euery one of them, and the Lord is among them: wherfore then
lift you vp your selues aboue the Congregation of the Lord
?<note> Hebr. It is much for you.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when Moses
heard it, he fell vpon his face.</ab>
<ab n="5">And hee spake
vnto Korah, and vnto all his company, saying, Euen to morrow the
Lord will shew who are his, and who is holy, and will cause him to
come neere vnto him: euen him whom he hath chosen, will he cause to
come neere vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="6">This doe: take
you censers, Korah, and all his company:</ab>
<ab n="7">And put fire
therein, and put incense in them, before the Lord to morrow; And it
shall be, that the man whom the Lord doeth choose, hee shall be
holy: yee take too much vpon you, ye sonnes of Leui.</ab>
<ab n="8">And Moses saide
vnto Korah, Heare, I pray you, ye sonnes of Leui.</ab>

<fw>He, Dathan &amp;c. are swallowed
vp.</fw>
<ab n="9">Seemeth it but a
small thing vnto you, that the God of Israel hath separated you
from the Congregation of Israel, to bring you neere to himselfe, to
doe the seruice of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to stand before
the Congregation to minister vnto them?</ab>
<ab n="10">And he hath
brought thee neere to him, and all thy brethren the sonnes of Leui
with thee: and seeke ye the Priesthood also?</ab>
<ab n="11">For which cause
both thou, and all thy company are gathered together against the
Lord: and what is Aaron, that ye murmure against him?</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And Moses
sent to call Dathan and Abiram the sonnes of Eliab: which said, We
will not come vp.</ab>
<ab n="13">Is it a small
thing that thou hast brought vs vp out of a land that floweth with
milke and hony, to kill vs in the wildernesse, except thou make thy
selfe altogether a prince ouer vs?</ab>
<ab n="14">Moreouer, thou
hast not brought vs into a land that floweth with milke and hony,
or giuen vs inheritance of fields and vineyards: wilt thou put out
the eyes of these men? we will not come vp.<note> Heb. boare out.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Moses was
very wroth, and said vnto the Lord, Respect not thou their
offering: I haue not taken one asse from them, neither haue I hurt
one of them.<note> Gen. 4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And Moses said
vnto Korah, Be thou and all thy company before the Lord, thou, and
they, and Aaron to morrow.</ab>
<ab n="17">And take euery
man his censer, and put incense in them, and bring yee before the
Lord euery man his censer, two hundred and fiftie censers, thou
also and Aaron, each of you his censer.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they tooke
euery man his censer, and put fire in them, and laide incense
thereon, and stood in the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation with Moses and Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Korah
gathered all the Congregation against them, vnto the doore of the
Tabernacle of the Congregation: and the glory of the Lord appeared
vnto all the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="21">Separate your
selues from among this Congregation, that I may consume them in a
moment.</ab>
<ab n="22">And they fell
vpon their faces, and said, O God, the God of the spirits of all
flesh, shal one man sinne, and wilt thou be wroth with all the
Congregation?</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>He, Dathan &amp;c. are swallowed
vp.</fw>
<ab n="24">Speake vnto the
Congregation, saying, Get you vp from about the tabernacle of
Korah, Dathan, and Abiram.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Moses rose
vp, and went vnto Dathan and Abiram: and the Elders of Israel
followed him.</ab>
<ab n="26">And hee spake
vnto the Congregation, saying, Depart, I pray you, from the tents
of these wicked men, and touch nothing of theirs, lest ye be
consumed in all their sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="27">So they gate vp
from the tabernacle of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, on euery side:
and Dathan and Abiram came out, and stood in the doore of their
tents, and their wiues, &amp; their sonnes, and their little
children.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Moses said,
Hereby ye shall know that the Lord hath sent me to doe all these
workes: for I haue not done them of mine owne mind.</ab>
<ab n="29">If these men die
the common death of all men, or if they be visited after the
visitation of all men, then the Lord hath not sent me:<note> Hebr. as euery man dieth.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">But if the Lord
make a new thing, and the earth open her mouth, and swallow them
vp, with all that appertaine vnto them, and they go downe quicke
into the pit: then ye shall vnderstand that these men haue prouoked
the Lord.<note> Hebr. create a creature.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">¶ And it
came to passe as he had made an ende of speaking all these words,
that the ground claue asunder that was vnder them:<note> Chap. 27. 3. deut. 11. 6. psal.106. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And the earth
opened her mouth, and swallowed them vp, and their houses, and all
the men that appertained vnto Korah, and all their goods.</ab>
<ab n="33">They, and all
that appertained to them, went downe aliue into the pit, and the
earth closed vpon them: and they perished from among the
Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="34">And all Israel
that were round about them, fled at the crie of them: for they
said, Lest the earth swallow vs vp also.</ab>
<ab n="35">And there came
out a fire from the Lord, and consumed the two hundred and fiftie
men that offered incense.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>The plague stayed.</fw>
<ab n="37">Speake vnto
Eleazar the sonne of Aaron the Priest, that he take vp the censers
out of the burning, and scatter thou the fire yonder, for they are
hallowed.</ab>
<ab n="38">The censers of
these sinners against their owne soules, let them make them broad
plates for a couering of the Altar: for they offered them before
the Lord, therefore they are hallowed, and they shall be a signe
vnto the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="39">And Eleazar the
Priest tooke the brasen censers, wherewith they that were burnt had
offered, and they were made broad plates for a couering of the
Altar:</ab>
<ab n="40">To bee a
memoriall vnto the children of Israel, that no stranger, which is
not of the seed of Aaron, come neere to offer incense before the
Lord, that he be not as Korah, and as his company, as the Lord said
to him by the hand of Moses.</ab>
<ab n="41">¶ But on
the morrow, all the Congregation of the children of Israel murmured
against Moses and against Aaron, saying, Ye haue killed the people
of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="42">And it came to
passe when the Congregation was gathered against Moses and against
Aaron, that they looked toward the Tabernacle of the Congregation:
and behold, the cloud couered it, and the glory of the Lord
appeared.</ab>
<ab n="43">And Moses and
Aaron came before the Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="44">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="45">Get you vp from
among this Congregation, that I may consume them, as in a moment:
and they fell vpon their faces.</ab>
<ab n="46">¶ And Moses
said vnto Aaron, Take a censer, and put fire therein from off the
Altar, and put on incense, and goe quickly vnto the Congregation,
and make an atonement for them: for there is wrath gone out from
the Lord; the plague is begun.</ab>
<ab n="47">And Aaron tooke
as Moses commanded, and ranne into the midst of the Congregation:
and behold, the plague was begun among the people, and he put on
incense, and made an atonement for the people.</ab>
<ab n="48">And he stood
betweene the dead and the liuing, and the plague was
stayed.</ab>

<fw>Aarons rodde.</fw>
<ab n="49">Now they that
died in the plague, were foureteene thousand and seuen hundred,
beside them that died about the matter of Korah.</ab>
<ab n="50">And Aaron
returned vnto Moses, vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation; and the plague was stayed.</ab>



</div>