<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 The people murmure at the newes. 6
Ioshua and Caleb labour to stil them. 11 God threatneth them. 13
Moses perswadeth God and obtaineth pardon. 26 The murmurers are
depriued of entring into the land. 36 The men who raised the euill
report, die by a plague. 40 The people that would inuade the land
against the wil of God, are smitten.</head>

<ab n="1">And all the
Congregation lifted vp their voyce and cried; and the people wept
that night.</ab>
<ab n="2">And all the
children of Israel murmured against Moses, and against Aaron: and
the whole Congregation said vnto them, Would God that we had died
in the land of Egypt, or would God we had died in this
wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="3">And wherefore
hath the Lord brought vs vnto this land, to fall by the sword, that
our wiues, and our children should be a pray? Were it not better
for vs to returne into Egypt?</ab>
<ab n="4">And they saide
one to another, Let vs make a captaine, and let vs returne into
Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then Moses and
Aaron fell on their faces before all the assembly of the
Congregation of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Ioshua
the sonne of Nun, and Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh, which were of
them that searched the land, rent their clothes.</ab>

<fw>Moses prayeth.</fw>
<ab n="7">And they spake
vnto all the company of the children of Israel, saying. The land
which wee passed thorow to search it, is an exceeding good
land.</ab>
<ab n="8">If the Lord
delight in vs, then he will bring vs into this land, and giue it
vs, a land which floweth with milke and hony.</ab>
<ab n="9">Onely rebell not
yee against the Lord, neither feare yee the people of the land, for
they are bread for vs: their defence is departed from them, and the
Lord is with vs: feare them not.<note> Hebr. shadow.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But all the
Congregation bade stone them with stones: and the glory of the Lord
appeared in the Tabernacle of the Congregation, before all the
children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
Lord said vnto Moses, How long will this people provoke me? and how
long will it bee, yer they beleeue me, for all the signes which I
haue shewed among them?</ab>
<ab n="12">I will smite
them with the pestilence, and disinherite them, and will make of
thee a greater nation, and mightier then they.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And Moses
said vnto the Lord, Then the Egyptians shall heare it, (for thou
broughtest vp this people in thy might from among
them:)<note> Exod. 32. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And they will
tell it to the inhabitants of this land: for they haue heard that
thou Lord art among this people, that thou Lord art seene face to
face, and that thy cloud standeth ouer them, and that thou goest
before them, by day time in a pillar of a cloud, and in a pillar of
fire by night.<note> Exod. 13. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ Now if
thou shalt kill all this people, as one man, then the nations which
haue heard the fame of thee, will speake, saying,</ab>
<ab n="16">Because the Lord
was not able to bring this people into the lande which he sware
vnto them, therefore he hath slaine them in the
wildernesse.<note> Deut.9. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And now, I
beseech thee, let the power of my Lord be great, according as thou
hast spoken, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord is long
suffering, and of great mercie, forgiuing iniquitie and
transgression, and by no meanes clearing the guiltie, visiting the
iniquity of the fathers vpon the chldren, vnto the third and fourth
generation.<note> Exod. 34. 6. psal. 103. 8. , Exod.20. 5.and 34.7.</note></ab>

<fw>Infidelitie is threatened.</fw>
<ab n="19">Pardon, I
beseech thee, the iniquitie of this people, according vnto the
greatnesse of thy mercie, and as thou hast forgiuen this people,
from Egypt, euen vntill now.<note> Or, hitherto.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord
said, I haue pardoned, according to thy word.</ab>
<ab n="21">But as truly as
I liue, all the earth shalbe filled with the glory of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="22">Because all
those men which haue seene my glory, and my miracles which I did in
Egypt, and in the wildernesse, and haue tempted mee now these ten
times, and haue not hearkened to my voice,</ab>
<ab n="23">Surely they
shall not see the land which I sware vnto their fathers, neither
shall any of them that prouoked me, see it.<note> Hebr. if they see the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But my seruant
Caleb, because hee had another spirit with him, (and hath followed
mee fully) him will I bring into the land, whereinto he went, and
his seed shall possesse it.<note> Iosh.14.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">(Now the
Amalekites, and the Canaanites dwelt in the valley) to morrow turne
you and get you into the wildernesse, by the way of the Red
sea.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="27">How long shall I
beare with this euil congregation which murmure against mee? I haue
heard the murmurings of the children of Israel, which they murmure
against mee.</ab>
<ab n="28">Say vnto them,
As truly as I liue, saith the Lord, as ye haue spoken in mine
eares, so will I doe to you:<note> Chap.26. 65. and 32. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Your carcases
shall fall in this wildernesse, and all that were numbred of you,
according to your whole number from twentie yeeres old and vpward,
which haue murmured against mee,<note> Deut.1. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Doubtlesse ye
shall not come into the land concerning which I sware to make you
dwell therein, saue Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh, and Ioshua the
sonne of Nun.<note> Heb. lifted vp my hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">But your little
ones, which yee said should be a pray, them will I bring in, and
they shall know the land which ye haue despised.</ab>
<ab n="32">But as for you,
your carkases, they shall fall in this wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="33">And your
children shall wander in the wildernes forty yeres, and beare your
whoredomes, vntill your carkases be wasted in the
wildernesse.<note> Or feed.</note></ab>

<fw>Infidelitie is threatened.</fw>
<ab n="34">After the number
of the dayes in which ye searched the land, euen fortie dayes (each
day for a yeere) shall yee beare your iniquities, euen forty
yeeres, and yee shall know my breach of promise.<note> Ezech.4. 6. psal.95. 19. , Or, altering of my purpose.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">I the Lord haue
said, I will surely doe it vnto all this euill Congregation, that
are gathered together against mee: in this wildernesse they shalbe
consumed, &amp; there they shall die.</ab>
<ab n="36">And the men
which Moses sent to search the land, who returned, and made all the
Congregation to murmure against him, by bringing vp a slander vpon
the land,</ab>
<ab n="37">Euen those men
that did bring vp the euill report vpon the land, died by the
plague, before the Lord.<note> 1.Cor.10. 10. Hebr.3. 10. iud.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">But Ioshua the
sonne of Nun, and Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh, which were of the
men that went to search the land, liued still.</ab>
<ab n="39">And Moses told
these sayings vnto all the children of Israel, and the people
mourned greatly.</ab>
<ab n="40">¶ And they
rose vp early in the morning, and gate them vp into the top of the
mountaine, saying, Loe, we be here, and will goe vp vnto the place
which the Lord hath promised: for we haue sinned.<note> Deut.1. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">And Moses said,
Wherefore now doe you transgresse the commaundement of the Lord ?
but it shall not prosper.</ab>
<ab n="42">Goe not vp, for
the Lord is not among you, that ye be not smitten before your
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="43">For the
Amalekites, and the Canaanites are there before you, and yee shall
fall by the sword, because yee are turned away from the Lord;
therefore the Lord will not bee with you.</ab>
<ab n="44">But they
presumed to go vp vnto the hill top: neuertheles the Arke of the
Couenant of the Lord, and Moses departed not out of the
campe.</ab>
<ab n="45">Then the
Amalekites came downe, and the Canaanites which dwelt in that hill,
and smote them, and discomfited them, euen vnto Hormah.<note> Deut.1. 44.</note></ab>



</div>