<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Balaks first message for Balaam is
refused. 15 His second message obtaineth him. 22 An Angel would
haue slaine him, if his asse had not saued him. 36 Balak
intertaineth him.</head>

<ab n="1">And the children
of Israel set forward, and pitched in the plaines of Moab, on this
side Iordane by Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="2">¶ And Balak
the sonne of Zippor, saw all that Israel had done to the
Amorites.</ab>
<ab n="3">And Moab was sore
afraid of the people, because they were many, and Moab was
distressed, because of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Moab said
vnto the elders of Midian; Now shall this company licke vp all that
are round about vs, as the oxe licketh vp the grasse of the field.
And Balak the sonne of Zippor, was King of the Moabites at that
time.</ab>

<fw>Balak sendeth for Balaam.</fw>
<ab n="5">He sent
messengers therefore vnto Balaam the sonne of Beor, to Pethor,
which is by the riuer of the land of the children of his people, to
call him, saying, Behold, there is a people come out from Egypt:
beholde, they couer the face of the earth, and they abide ouer
against me.<note> Iosh.24. 9. , Hebr. eye.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Come now
therefore, I pray thee, curse mee this people, for they are too
mightie for me: peraduenture I shall preuaile, that we may smite
them, and that I may driue them out of the land: for I wot that he
whom thou blessest, is blessed, and hee whom thou cursest, is
cursed.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the elders of
Moab, and the elders of Midian departed, with the rewards of
diuination in their hand; and they came vnto Balaam, and spake vnto
him the words of Balak.</ab>
<ab n="8">And hee said vnto
them, Lodge here this night, and I will bring you word againe as
the Lord shal speake vnto mee: and the Princes of Moab abode with
Balaam.</ab>
<ab n="9">And God came vnto
Balaam, and said, What men are these with thee?</ab>
<ab n="10">And Balaam said
vnto God, Balak the sonne of Zippor, King of Moab, hath sent vnto
me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="11">Behold, there is
a people come out of Egypt, which couereth the face of the earth:
Come now, curse me them; peraduenture I shalbe able to ouercome
them, and driue them out.<note> Hebr. I shall preuaile in fighting against him.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And God saide
vnto Balaam; Thou shalt not goe with them, thou shalt not curse the
people: for they are blessed.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Balaam rose
vp in the morning, and said vnto the Princes of Balak, Get you into
your land: for the Lord refuseth to giue mee leaue to goe with
you.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the Princes
of Moab rose vp, and they went vnto Balak, and said, Balaam
refuseth to come with vs.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And Balak
sent yet againe Princes, moe, and more honourable then
they.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they came to
Balaam, and said to him, Thus saith Balak the son of Zippor; Let
nothing, I pray thee, hinder thee from comming vnto me:<note> Hebr. Be not thou letted from &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For I wil
promote thee vnto very great honour, and I will do whatsoeuer thou
saiest vnto me: Come therefore, I pray thee, curse me this
people.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Balaam
answered and said vnto the seruants of Balak, If Balak would giue
me his house full of siluer and gold, I cannot goe beyond the word
of the Lord my God, to doe lesse or more.<note> Chap.24. 13.</note></ab>

<fw>The asse speaketh.</fw>
<ab n="19">Now therefore, I
pray you, tarie yee also here this night, that I may know what the
Lord will say vnto me more.</ab>
<ab n="20">And God came
vnto Balaam at night, and said vnto him, If the men come to call
thee, rise vp, and goe with them: but yet the word which I shall
say vnto thee, that shalt thou doe.</ab>
<ab n="21">And Balaam rose
vp in the morning, and sadled his asse, and went with the princes
of Moab.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And Gods
anger was kindled, because he went: and the Angel of the Lord stood
in the way for an aduersarie against him: Now he was riding vpon
his asse, and his two seruants were with him.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the Asse
sawe the Angel of the Lord standing in the way, and his sword
drawen in his hand: and the asse turned aside out of the way, and
went into the field: and Balaam smote the asse, to turne her into
the way.<note> 2.Pet.2. 16. iude 11</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But the Angel of
the Lord stood in a path of the vineyards, a wall being on this
side, &amp; a wall on that side.</ab>
<ab n="25">And when the
asse saw the Angel of the Lord, she thrust her selfe vnto the wall,
and crusht Balaams foote against the wall: and hee smote her
againe.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the Angel of
the Lord went further, and stood in a narrowe place, where was no
way to turne, either to the right hand, or to the left.</ab>
<ab n="27">And when the
asse sawe the Angel of the Lord, shee fell downe vnder Balaam, and
Balaams anger was kindled, and hee smote the asse with a
staffe.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the Lord
opened the mouth of the asse, and shee saide vnto Balaam, What haue
I done vnto thee, that thou hast smitten mee these three
times?</ab>
<ab n="29">And Balaam said
vnto the asse, Because thou hast mocked mee: I would there were a
sword in mine hand, for now would I kill thee.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the asse
said vnto Balaam, Am not I thine asse, vpon which thou hast ridden
euer since I was thine, vnto this day? was I euer wont to do so
vnto thee? And he said, Nay.<note> Hebr. who hast ridden vpon me. , Or, euer since thou wast, &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Balak and Balaam.</fw>
<ab n="31">Then the Lord
opened the eyes of Balaam, and hee saw the Angel of the Lord
standing in the way, and his sword drawen in his hand: and hee
bowed downe his head, and fell flat on his face.<note> Bowed himselfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">And the Angel of
the Lord said vnto him, Wherefore hast thou smitten thine asse
these three times? Behold, I went out to withstand thee, because
thy way is peruerse before me.<note> Hebr. to be an aduersarie vnto thee</note></ab>
<ab n="33">And the asse saw
me, and turned from me these three times: vnlesse shee had turned
from me, surely now also I had slaine thee, and saued her
aliue.</ab>
<ab n="34">And Balaam said
vnto the Angel of the Lord, I haue sinned: for I knew not that thou
stoodest in the way against mee: Now therefore if it displease
thee, I will get mee backe againe.<note> Heb. be euill in thine eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And the Angel of
the Lord said vnto Balaam, Goe with the men: but onely the word
that I shall speake vnto thee, that thou shalt speake: So Balaam
went with the princes of Balak.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ And when
Balak heard that Balaam was come, hee went out to meete him, vnto a
citie of Moab, which is in the border of Arnon, which is in the
vtmost coast.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Balak said
vnto Balaam, Did I not earnestly send vnto thee to call thee?
wherefore camest thou not vnto me? Am I not able indeed to promote
thee to honour?</ab>
<ab n="38">And Balaam saide
vnto Balak, Loe, I am come vnto thee: haue I now any power at all
to say any thing? the worde that God putteth in my mouth, that
shall I speake.</ab>
<ab n="39">And Balaam went
with Balak, and they came vnto Kiriath-Huzoth.<note> Or, a citie of streets.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">And Balak
offered oxen, and sheepe, and sent to Balaam, and to the princes
that were with him.</ab>
<ab n="41">And it came to
passe on the morrow, that Balak tooke Balaam, and brought him vp
into the high places of Baal, that thence hee might see the vtmost
part of the people.</ab>



</div>