<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-25-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-26-26.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-26-26b.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 The summe of all Israel is taken
in the plaines of Moab. 52 The law of diuiding among them the
inheritance of the land. 57 The families and number of the Leuites.
63 None were left of them which were numbred at Sinai, but Caleb
and Ioshua.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe after the plague, that the Lord spake vnto Moses, and vnto
Eleazar the sonne of Aaron the Priest, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Take the summe of
all the Congregation of the children of Israel, from twenty yeeres
old and vpward, throughout their fathers house, all that are able
to goe to warre in Israel.<note> Chap.1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Moses &amp;
Eleazar the Priest spake with them in the plaines of Moab by
Iordane neere Iericho, saying,</ab>
<ab n="4">Take the summe of
the people from twenty yeeres old and vpward, as the Lord commanded
Moses, and the children of Israel which went foorth out of the land
of Egypt.<note> Chap.1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Reuben the
eldest sonne of Israel: the children of Reuben, Hanoch, of whom
commeth the family of the Hanochites: of Pallu the family of the
Palluites:<note> Gene.46. 8. exod.6. 14. 1.chro. 5, 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Of Hesron the
family of the Hesronites: of Carmi the family of the
Carmites.</ab>
<ab n="7">These are the
families of the Reubenites: and they that were numbred of them,
were fourtie and three thousand, and seuen hundred and
thirtie.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the sonnes of
Pallu, Eliab.</ab>

<fw>Israel is numbred by their
tribes.</fw>
<ab n="9">And the sonnes of
Eliab, Nemuel, and Dathan, and Abiram: this is that Dathan &amp;
Abiram, which were famous in the Congregation, who stroue against
Moses and against Aaron in the companie of Korah, when they stroue
against the Lord:<note> Chap. 16. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the earth
opened her mouth, and swallowed them vp together with Korah when
that companie died, what time the fire deuoured two hundred and
fiftie men: and they became a signe.</ab>
<ab n="11">Notwithstanding,
the children of Korah died not.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ The
sonnes of Simeon, after their families: Of Nemuel, the family of
the Nemuelites: Of Iamin, the familie of the Iaminites: Of Iachin,
the familie of the Iachinites:</ab>
<ab n="13">Of Zerah, the
familie of the Zarhites: Of Shaul, the familie of the
Shaulites.</ab>
<ab n="14">These are the
families of the Simeonites, twentie and two thousand, and two
hundred.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ The
children of Gad after their families: Of Zephon, the familie of the
Zephonites: of Haggi the familie of the Haggites: of Shuni the
familie of the Shunites.</ab>
<ab n="16">Of Ozni, the
familie of the Oznites: Of Eri the familie of the Erites.</ab>
<ab n="17">Of Arod the
familie of the Arodites: of Areli the familie of the
Arelites.</ab>
<ab n="18">These are the
families of the children of Gad, according to those that were
numbred of them, fourtie thousand and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="19">¶ The
sonnes of Iudah, were Er and Onan: and Er and Onan died in the land
of Canaan.<note> Gen.38.2 &amp;c.and 46. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And the sonnes
of Iudah after their families were: Of Shelah the familie of the
Shelanites: Of Pharez the familie of the Pharzites: Of Zerah the
familie of the Zarhites.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the sonnes
of Pharez were: Of Hesron the familie of the Hesronites: Of Hamul
the familie of the Hamulites.</ab>
<ab n="22">These are the
families of Iudah according to those that were numbred of them,
threescore and sixteene thousand and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Of the
sonnes of Issachar after their families: Of Tola the familie of the
Tolaites: of Pua the familie of the Punites.</ab>

<fw>Israel is numbred by their
tribes.</fw>
<ab n="24">Of Iashub the
familie of the Iashubites: of Shimron the familie of the
Shimronites.</ab>
<ab n="25">These are the
families of Issachar according to those that were numbred of them,
threescore and foure thousand, and three hundred.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Of the
sonnes of Zebulun after their families, of Sered the familie of the
Sardites: Of Elon the familie of the Elonites: of Iahleel the
familie of the Iahleelites.</ab>
<ab n="27">These are the
families of the Zebulunites, according to those that were numbred
of them, threescore thousand and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ The
sonnes of Ioseph after their families, were Manasseh and
Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="29">Of the sonnes of
Manasseh: Of Machir the familie of the Machirites: and Machir
begate Gilead: Of Gilead come the familie of the
Gileadites.<note> Iosh.17.1</note></ab>
<ab n="30">These are the
sonnes of Gilead: Of Ieezer the family of the Ieezerites: Of Helek
the familie of the Helekites.</ab>
<ab n="31">And of Asriel
the family of the Asrielites: and of Shechem the familie of the
Shechemites.</ab>
<ab n="32">And of Shemida
the familie of the Shemidaites: and of Hepher the familie of the
Hepherites.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And
Zelophehad the sonne of Hepher had no sonnes, but daughters: and
the names of the daughters of Zelophehad, were Mahlah, and Noah,
Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah.<note> Chap.27. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">These are the
families of Manasseh, and those that were numbred of them, fiftie
and two thousand and seuen hundred.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ These are
the sonnes of Ephraim, after their families: Of Shuthelah the
familie of the Shuthalhites: Of Becher the familie of the
Bachrites: Of Tahan the familie of the Tahanites.</ab>
<ab n="36">And these are
the sonnes of Shuthelah: Of Eran the familie of the
Eranites.</ab>
<ab n="37">These are the
families of the sonnes of Ephraim, according to those that were
numbred of them, thirtie and two thousand, and fiue hundred. These
are the sonnes of Ioseph after their families.</ab>

<fw>Israel is numbred by their
tribes.</fw>
<ab n="38">¶ The
sonnes of Beniamin after their families: Of Bela the familie of the
Belaites: Of Ashbel the familie of the Ashbelites: Of Ahiram the
family of the Ahiramites:</ab>
<ab n="39">Of Shupham the
family of the Shuphamites: Of Hupham the family of the
Huphamites.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the sonnes
of Bela were Ard and Naaman: of Ard, the family of the Ardites: and
of Naaman the family of the Naamites.</ab>
<ab n="41">These are the
sonnes of Beniamin after their families; and they that were numbred
of them, were fourty and fiue thousand, and sixe hundred.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶ These are
the sonnes of Dan after their families: Of Shuham the family of the
Shuhamites. These are the families of Dan, after their
families.</ab>
<ab n="43">All the families
of the Shuhamites, according to those that were numbred of them,
were three score and foure thousand, and foure hundred.</ab>
<ab n="44">¶ Of the
children of Asher after their families: Of Iimna the family of the
Iimnites: Of Iesui the family of the Iesuites: Of Beriah the family
of the Beriites.</ab>
<ab n="45">Of the sonnes of
Beriah; of Heber the family of the Heberites: of Malchiel, the
family of the Malchielites.</ab>
<ab n="46">And the name of
the daughter of Asher, was Sarah.</ab>
<ab n="47">These are the
families of the sonnes of Asher, according to those that were
numbred of them; who were fiftie and three thousand, and foure
hundred.</ab>
<ab n="48">Of the sonnes of
Naphtali, after their families, of Iahzeel the family of the
Iahzeelites: Of Guni, the family of the Gunites:</ab>
<ab n="49">Of Iezer, the
family of the Iezerites: Of Shillem the family of the
Shillemites.</ab>
<ab n="50">These are the
families of Naphtali, according to their families: and they that
were numbred of them, were fourty and fiue thousand, and foure
hundred.</ab>
<ab n="51">These were the
numbred of the children of Israel, sixe hundred thousand, and a
thousand, seuen hundred and thirtie.</ab>
<ab n="52">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="53">Unto these the
land shall be diuided for an inheritance, according to the number
of names.</ab>

<fw>Israel is numbred by their
tribes.</fw>
<ab n="54">To many thou
shalt giue the more inheritance, and to few thou shalt giue the
lesse inheritance: to euery one shall his inheritance be giuen,
according to those that were numbred of him.<note> Chap.33. 54. , Hebr. multiply his inheritance. , Hebr. diminish his inheritance.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">Notwithstanding
the land shall bee diuided by lot: according to the names of the
tribes of their fathers, they shall inherite.<note> Chap.33. 54. iosh.11, 23. and 14. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="56">According to the
lot shall the possession thereof be diuided betweene many and
few.</ab>
<ab n="57">¶ And these
are they that were numbred of the Leuites, after their families: Of
Gershon, the family of the Gershonites: Of Kohath the family of the
Kohathites: Of Merari the family of the Merarites.<note> Exod.6. 16, 17, 18, 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">These are the
families of the Leuites: the family of the Libnites, the family of
the Hebronites, the family of the Mahlites, the family of the
Mushites, the family of the Korathites: and Kohath begate
Amram.</ab>
<ab n="59">And the name of
Amrams wife was Iochebed the daughter of Leui, whom her mother bare
to Leui in Egypt: And shee bare vnto Amram, Aaron and Moses, and
Miriam their sister.<note> Exod.2.2. and 6.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="60">And vnto Aaron
was borne Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar.</ab>
<ab n="61">And Nadab and
Abihu died, when they offered strange fire before the
Lord.<note> Leuit. 10. 2.chap.3.4. 1. chro.24. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">And those that
were numbred of them, were twenty and three thousand, all males
from a moneth old and vpward: for they were not numbred among the
children of Israel, because there was no inheritance giuen them
among the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="63">¶ These are
they that were numbred by Moses and Eleazar the Priest, who numbred
the children of Israel in the plaines of Moab, by Iordane neere
Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="64">But among these
there was not a man of them, whom Moses and Aaron the Priest
numbred, when they numbred the children of Israel in the
wildernesse of Sinai.</ab>
<ab n="65">For the Lord had
said of them, They shall surely die in the wildernesse: and there
was not left a man of them, saue Caleb the sonne of Iephunneh, and
Ioshua the sonne of Nun.<note> Chap. 14. 28. 1.corin. 10 5.6.</note></ab>



</div>