<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Leviticus-Chapter-27-27-Numbers.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 God commaundeth Moses to number
the people. 5 The Princes of the Tribes. 17 The number of euery
Tribe. 47 The Leuites are exempted for the Seruice of the
Lord.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses in the wildernesse of Sinai, in the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, on the first day of the second moneth, in the second
yeere, after they were come out of the land of Egypt,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Take yee the summe
of all the Congregation of the children of Israel, after their
families, by the house of their fathers, with the number of their
names, euery male by their polle:<note> Exod. 30. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">From twentie
yeeres old and vpward, all that are able to goe foorth to warre in
Israel: thou and Aaron shall number them by their armies.</ab>
<ab n="4">And with you there
shalbe a man of euery Tribe: euery one head of the house of his
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And these
are the names of the men that shall stand with you: of the tribe of
Reuben, Elizur the sonne of Shedeur.</ab>
<ab n="6">Of Simeon:
Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai.</ab>
<ab n="7">Of Iudah: Nahshon,
the sonne of Amminadab.</ab>
<ab n="8">Of Issachar:
Nethaneel, the sonne of Zuar.</ab>

<fw>Men of warre are numbred.</fw>
<ab n="9">Of Zebulun: Eliab
the sonne of Helon.</ab>
<ab n="10">Of the children
of Ioseph: of Ephraim, Elishama the sonne of Ammihud: of Manasseh,
Gamaliel the sonne of Pedahzur.</ab>
<ab n="11">Of Beniamin:
Abidan, the sonne of Gideoni.</ab>
<ab n="12">Of Dan: Ahiezer,
the sonne of Ammishaddai.</ab>
<ab n="13">Of Asher: Pagiel
the sonne of Ocran.</ab>
<ab n="14">Of Gad: Eliasaph,
the sonne of Deuel.</ab>
<ab n="15">Of Naphthali:
Ahira the sonne of Enan.</ab>
<ab n="16">These were the
renowned of the Congregation, Princes of the tribes of their
fathers, heads of thousands in Israel.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And Moses
and Aaron tooke these men, which are expressed by their
names.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they
assembled all the Congregation together on the first day of the
second moneth, and they declared their pedegrees after their
families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of
the names, from twenty yeres old and vpward by their polle.</ab>
<ab n="19">As the Lord
commaunded Moses, so he numbred them in the wildernesse of
Sinai.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the children
of Reuben Israels eldest sonne, by their generations after their
families, by the house of their fathers, according to the number of
the names, by their polle, euery male from twenty yeeres old and
vpward, all that were able to go forth to warre:</ab>
<ab n="21">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Reuben, were fourty and sixe
thousand and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ Of the
children of Simeon by their generations, after their families, by
the house of their fathers, those that were numbred of them,
according to the number of the names, by their polles, euery male
from twenty yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe foorth
to warre:</ab>
<ab n="23">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Simeon, were fiftie and nine
thousand, and three hundred.</ab>

<fw>Men of warre are numbred.</fw>
<ab n="24">¶ Of the
children of Gad by their generations, after their families by the
house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from
twenty yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe foorth to
warre:</ab>
<ab n="25">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Gad, were fourty and fiue
thousand, sixe hundred and fiftie.</ab>
<ab n="26">¶ Of the
children of Iudah by their generations, after their families by the
house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from
twenty yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe foorth to
warre:</ab>
<ab n="27">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Iudah, were threescore and
fourteene thousand, and sixe hundred.</ab>
<ab n="28">¶ Of the
children of Issachar, by their generations, after their families by
the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names,
from twenty yeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe foorth
to warre:</ab>
<ab n="29">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Issachar, were fiftie and
foure thousand, and foure hundred.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Of the
children of Zebulun, by their generations, after their families, by
the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names,
from twenty yeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe foorth
to warre:</ab>
<ab n="31">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Zebulun, were fiftie and
seuen thousand and foure hundred.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ Of the
children of Ioseph; namely of the children of Ephraim, by their
generations, after their families, by the house of their fathers,
according to the number of the names, from twenty yeres old and
vpward, all that were able to goe foorth to warre:</ab>
<ab n="33">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Ephraim, were fourty thousand
and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="34">¶ Of the
children of Manasseh by their generations, after their families, by
the house of their fathers according to the number of the names,
from twenty yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to go forth
to warre:</ab>
<ab n="35">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Manasseh, were thirty and two
thousand, and two hundred.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites office and charge.</fw>
<ab n="36">¶ Of the
children of Beniamin, by their generations, after their families,
by the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names
from twenty yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe foorth
to warre:</ab>
<ab n="37">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Beniamin, were thirtie and
fiue thousand, and foure hundred.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ Of the
children of Dan, by their generations, after their families, by the
house of their fathers, according to the number of the names, from
twentie yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe forth to
warre:</ab>
<ab n="39">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Dan, were threescore and two
thousand, and seuen hundred.</ab>
<ab n="40">¶ Of the
children of Asher, by their generations, after their families, by
the house of their fathers, according to the number of the names,
from twentie yeres old and vpward, all that were able to goe forth
to warre:</ab>
<ab n="41">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Asher, were fourtie and one
thousand, and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶ Of the
children of Naphtali, throughout their generations, after their
families by the house of their fathers, according to the number of
the names, from twentie yeeres olde and vpward, all that were able
to goe forth to warre:</ab>
<ab n="43">Those that were
numbred of them, euen of the tribe of Naphtali, were fiftie and
three thousand, and foure hundred.</ab>
<ab n="44">These are those
that were numbred, which Moses and Aaron numbred, and the Princes
of Israel, being twelue men: each one was for the house of his
fathers.</ab>
<ab n="45">So were all those
that were numbred of the children of Israel, by the house of their
fathers, from twenty yeeres old and vpward, all that were able to
goe forth to warre in Israel:</ab>
<ab n="46">Euen all they,
that were numbred, were sixe hundred thousand, and three thousand,
and fiue hundred and fiftie.</ab>
<ab n="47">¶ But the
Leuites after the tribe of their fathers, were not numbred among
them.</ab>
<ab n="48">For the Lord had
spoken vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>The Leuites office and charge.</fw>
<ab n="49">Onely thou shalt
not number the tribe of Leui, neither take the summe of them among
the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="50">But thou shalt
appoint the Leuites ouer the Tabernacle of Testimonie, and ouer all
the vessels thereof, and ouer all things that belong to it: they
shall beare the Tabernacle, and all the vessels thereof, and they
shall minister vnto it, and shall encampe round about the
Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="51">And when the
Tabernacle setteth forward, the Leuites shall take it downe: and
when the Tabernacle is to be pitched, the Leuites shall set it vp:
and the stranger that commeth nigh, shall be put to death.</ab>
<ab n="52">And the children
of Israel shall pitch their tents euery man by his own campe, and
euery man by his owne standerd, throughout their hostes.</ab>
<ab n="53">But the Leuites
shall pitch round about the Tabernacle of Testimonie, that there be
no wrath vpon the Congregation of the children of Israel: and the
Leuites shall keepe the charge of the Tabernacle of
Testimonie.</ab>
<ab n="54">And the children
of Israel did according to all that the Lord commanded Moses, so
did they.</ab>



</div>