<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 God rebuketh the sedition of
Miriam and Aaron. 10 Miriams leprosie is healed at the prayer of
Moses. 14 God commandeth her to be shut out of the
hoste.</head>


<fw>Miriam leprous.</fw>
<ab n="1">And Miriam and
Aaron spake against Moses, because of the Ethiophian woman, whom
hee had married: for he had married an Ethiopian woman.<note> Or, Cushite. , Hebr. taken.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And they said,
Hath the Lord indeed spoken onely by Moses? Hath hee not spoken
also by vs? And the Lord heard it.</ab>
<ab n="3">(Now the man
Moses was very meeke, aboue all the men which were vpon the face of
the earth.)<note> Ecclu.45. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord
spake suddenly vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, and vnto Miriam, Come
out ye three vnto the Tabernacle of the Congregation: and they
three came out.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Lord came
downe in the pillar of the cloude, and stood in the doore of the
Tabernacle, and called Aaron and Miriam: and they both came
foorth.</ab>
<ab n="6">And hee saide,
Heare now my words: If there be a Prophet among you, I the Lord
will make my selfe knowen vnto him in a vision, and will speake
vnto him in a dreame:</ab>
<ab n="7">My seruant Moses
is not so, who is faithfull in all mine house.<note> Hebr.3.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">With him will I
speake mouth to mouth euen apparantly, and not in darke speeches,
and the similitude of the Lord shall hee behold: wherefore then
were yee not afraid to speake against my seruant Moses?<note> Exod.33. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the anger of
the Lord was kindled against them, and he departed.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the cloud
departed from off the Tabernacle, and behold, Miriam became
leprous, white as snow: and Aaron looked vpon Miriam, and behold,
she was leprous.</ab>
<ab n="11">And Aaron said
vnto Moses, Alas my lord, I beseech thee, lay not the sinne vpon
vs, wherein we haue done foolishly, and wherein we haue
sinned:</ab>
<ab n="12">Let her not bee
as one dead, of whom the flesh is halfe consumed, when he commeth
out of his mothers wombe.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Moses cryed
vnto the Lord, saying, Heale her now, O God, I beseech
thee.</ab>

<fw>Spies are sent to search the
land.</fw>
<ab n="14">¶ And the
Lord said vnto Moses, If her father had but spit in her face,
should she not bee ashamed seuen dayes? let her be shut out from
the campe seuen dayes, and after that let her be receiued in
againe.<note> Leuit. 13. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Miriam was
shut out from the campe seuen dayes: and the people iourneied not,
til Miriam was brought in againe.</ab>
<ab n="16">And afterward
the people remoued from Hazeroth, and pitched in the wildernesse of
Paran.</ab>



</div>