<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-3-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-3-3b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The sonnes of Aaron. 5 The Leuites
are giuen to the Priests for the seruice of the Tabernacle, 11 in
stead of the first borne. 14 The Leuites are numbred by their
families. 21 The families, number and charge of the Gershonites, 27
Of the Kohathites, 33 Of the Merarites. 38 The place &amp; charge
of Moses &amp; Aaron. 40 The first borne are freed by the Leuites.
44 The ouerplus are redeemed.</head>

<ab n="1">These also are the
generations of Aaron and Moses, in the day that the Lord spake with
Moses in Mount Sinai.</ab>
<ab n="2">And these are the
names of the sonnes of Aaron: Nadab the first borne, and Abihu,
Eleazar and Ithamar.<note> Exod.6. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">These are the
names of the sonnes of Aaron the Priests, which were anointed, whom
he consecrated to minister in the Priests office.<note> Heb. whose hand he filled</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Nadab and
Abihu died before the Lord, when they offered strange fire before
the Lord in the wildernesse of Sinai, and they had no children: and
Eleazar and Ithamar ministred in the Priests office in the sight of
Aaron their father.<note> Leuit.10. 1.chap. 26. 61. 1.chro. 24.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="6">Bring the tribe of
Leui neere, and present them before Aaron the Priest, that they may
minister vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they shall
keepe his charge, and the charge of the whole Congregation before
the Tabernacle of the Congregation, to doe the seruice of the
Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they shall
keepe all the instruments of the Tabernacle of the Congregation,
and the charge of the children of Israel, to doe the seruice of the
Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="9">And thou shalt
giue the Leuites vnto Aaron and to his sonnes: they are wholly
giuen vnto him out of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
appoint Aaron and his sonnes, and they shall waite on their priests
office: and the stranger that commeth nigh, shall bee put to
death.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>The Leuites are numbred.</fw>
<ab n="12">And I, behold, I
haue taken the Leuites from among the children of Israel, in stead
of all the first borne that openeth the matrice among the children
of Israel: therefore the Leuites shall be mine,</ab>
<ab n="13">Because all the
first borne are mine: for on the day that I smote all the first
borne in the land of Egypt, I halowed vnto mee all the first borne
in Israel, both man, and beast, mine they shall be: I am the
Lord.<note> Exod.13. 1 leuit.27. 26.chap. 8. 16. luke.2. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, in the wildernesse of Sinai, saying,</ab>
<ab n="15">Number the
children of Leui, after the house of their fathers, by their
families: euery male from a moneth old and vpward shalt thou number
them.</ab>
<ab n="16">And Moses numbred
them according to the word of the Lord, as he was
commanded.<note> Gene 46. 11. exod 6. 16.chap.26 57. 1. chro. 6.11. , Hebr. mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And these were
the sonnes of Leui, by their names: Gershon, and Kohath, and
Merari.</ab>
<ab n="18">And these are the
names of the sonnes of Gershon, by their families: Libni, and
Shimei.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the sonnes of
Kohath by their families: Amram, and Izehar, Hebron and
Uzziel.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the sonnes of
Merari by their families: Mahli, and Mushi: these are the families
of the Leuites, according to the house of their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="21">Of Gershon was
the familie of the Libnites, and the familie of the Shimites: these
are the families of the Gershonites.</ab>
<ab n="22">Those that were
numbred of them, according to the number of all the males, from a
moneth old and vpward, euen those that were numbred of them, were
seuen thousand and fiue hundred.</ab>
<ab n="23">The families of
the Gershonites shal pitch behind the Tabernacle Westward.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the chiefe of
the house of the father of the Gershonites, shall be Eliasaph the
sonne of Lael.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the charge of
the sonnes of Gershon, in the Tabernacle of the Congregation, shall
be the Tabernacle, and the tent, the couering thereof, and the
hanging for the doore of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation:</ab>

<fw>The Leuites seuerall charges.</fw>
<ab n="26">And the hangings
of the Court, and the curtaine for the doore of the court, which is
by the Tabernacle, and by the Altar round about, and the cords of
it, for all the seruice therof.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And of
Kohath was the familie of the Amramites, and the familie of the
Izeharites, and the familie of the Hebronites, and the familie of
the Uzzielites: these are the families of the Kohathites.</ab>
<ab n="28">In the number of
all the males, from a moneth olde and vpward, were eight thousand,
and sixe hundred, keeping the charge of the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="29">The families of
the sonnes of Kohath, shall pitch on the side of the Tabernacle
Southward.</ab>
<ab n="30">And the chiefe of
the house of the father of the families of the Kohathites shalbe
Elizaphan the sonne of Uzziel.</ab>
<ab n="31">And their charge
shall be the Arke, and the Table, and the Candlesticke, and the
altars, and the vessels of the Sanctuarie, wherewith they minister,
and the hanging, and all the seruice thereof.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Eleazar the
sonne of Aaron the Priest, shall be chiefe ouer the chiefe of the
Leuites, and haue the ouersight of them that keepe the charge of
the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ Of Merari
was the family of the Mahlites, and the family of the Mushites:
these are the families of Merari.</ab>
<ab n="34">And those that
were numbred of them, according to the number of all the males from
a moneth old &amp; vpward, were sixe thousand and two
hundred.</ab>
<ab n="35">And the chiefe of
the house of the father of the families of Merari, was Zuriel the
sonne of Abihail: these shall pitch on the side of the Tabernacle
Northwards.</ab>
<ab n="36">And vnder the
custody and charge of the sonnes of Merari, shall bee the boards of
the Tabernacle, and the barres thereof, and the pillars thereof,
and the sockets thereof, &amp; all the vessels thereof, and all
that serueth thereto:<note> Heb. the office of the charge.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">And the pillars
of the Court round about, and their sockets, and their pinnes, and
their cords.</ab>
<ab n="38">¶ But those
that encampe before the Tabernacle toward the East, euen before the
Tabernacle of the Congregation Eastward, shall be Moses and Aaron,
and his sonnes, keeping the charge of the Sanctuary, for the charge
of the children of Israel: and the stranger that commeth nigh,
shall be put to death.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites seuerall charges.</fw>
<ab n="39">All that were
numbred of the Leuites, which Moses and Aaron numbred at the
commaundement of the Lord, throughout their families, all the males
from a moneth old and vpward, were twenty and two thousand.</ab>
<ab n="40">¶ And the
Lord said vnto Moses, Number all the first borne of the males of
the children of Israel, from a moneth old and vpward, and take the
number of their names.</ab>
<ab n="41">And thou shalt
take the Leuites for me, (I am the Lord ) in stead of all the first
borne among the children of Israel, and the cattell of the Leuites,
in stead of all the firstlings among the cattell of the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="42">And Moses numbred
as the Lord commanded him, all the first borne among the children
of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="43">And all the first
borne males, by the number of names, from a moneth old &amp;
vpward, of those that were numbred of them, were twenty and two
thousand, two hundred, and threescore and thirteene.</ab>
<ab n="44">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="45">Take the Leuites
in stead of all the first borne among the children of Israel, and
the cattell of the Leuites in stead of their cattell, and the
Leuites shalbe mine: I am the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="46">And for those
that are to be redeemed of the two hundred and threescore and
thirteene, of the first borne of the children of Israel, which are
more then the Leuites;</ab>
<ab n="47">Thou shalt euen
take fiue shekels a piece, by the polle, after the shekel of the
Sanctuary shalt thou take them; the shekel is twenty
gerahs.<note> Exod.30 13. leuit. 27.25. chap. 18. 16. ezek. 45.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">And thou shalt
giue the money, wherewith the odde number of them is to be
redeemed, vnto Aaron and to his sonnes.</ab>
<ab n="49">And Moses tooke
the redemption money, of them that were ouer and aboue them that
were redeemed by the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="50">Of the first
borne of the children of Israel tooke he the money; a thousand,
three hundred, and threescore and fiue shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuary.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites seuerall charges.</fw>
<ab n="51">And Moses gaue
the money of them that were redeemed, vnto Aaron and to his sonnes,
according to the word of the Lord, as the Lord commanded
Moses.</ab>



</div>