<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-35-36.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-36-36-Deuteronomy.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 The inconuenience of the
inheritance of daughters, 5 is remedied by marying in their owne
tribes, 7 lest the inheritance should be remoued from the tribe. 10
The daughters of Zelophehad marrie their fathers brothers
sonnes.</head>

<ab n="1">And the chiefe
fathers of the families of the children of Gilead, the sonne of
Machir, the sonne of Manasseh, of the families of the sonnes of
Ioseph, came neere, and spake before Moses, and before the Princes
the chiefe fathers of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="2">And they said,
The Lord commanded my lord to giue the lande for an inheritance by
lot to the children of Israel: and my lord was commanded by the
Lord, to giue the inheritance of Zelophehad our brother, vnto his
daughters.<note> Chap.27. 1. iosh.17.3</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And if they bee
married to any of the sonnes of the other tribes of the children of
Israel, then shall their inheritance be taken from the inheritance
of our fathers, and shall bee put to the inheritance of the tribe,
whereinto they are receiued: so shal it be taken from the lot of
our inheritance.<note> Heb. vnto whom they shall be.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And when the
Iubile of the children of Israel shall be, then shall their
inheritance be put vnto the inheritance of the tribe, whereunto
they are receiued: So shal their inheritance be taken away from the
inheritance of the tribe of our fathers.</ab>
<ab n="5">And Moses
commanded the children of Israel, according to the worde of the
Lord, saying, The tribe of the sonnes of Ioseph hath said
well.</ab>

<fw>Lawes for inheritances.</fw>
<ab n="6">This is the thing
which the Lord doeth command concerning the daughters of
Zelophehad, saying, Let them marry to whom they thinke best: onely
to the family of the tribe of their father shall they
marry.<note> Hebr. be wiues. , Tob. 1. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So shall not the
inheritance of the children of Israel remooue from tribe to tribe:
for euery one of the children of Israel shall keepe himselfe to the
inheritance of the tribe of his fathers.<note> Hebr. cleaue to the &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And euery
daughter that possesseth an inheritance, in any tribe of the
children of Israel, shall be wife vnto one of the family of the
tribe of her father, that the children of Israel may enioy euery
man the inheritance of his fathers.</ab>

<fw>Lawes for inheritances.</fw>
<ab n="9">Neither shall the
inheritance remoue from one tribe to another tribe: but euery one
of the tribes of the children of Israel, shall keepe himselfe to
his owne inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="10">Euen as the Lord
commanded Moses, so did the daughters of Zelophehad.</ab>
<ab n="11">For Mahlah,
Tirzah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Noah the daughters of
Zelophehad, were married vnto their fathers brothers
sonnes.<note> Chap.27. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And they were
married into the families of the sonnes of Manasseh, the sonne of
Ioseph, and their inheritance remained in the tribe of the family
of their father.<note> Hebr. to some that were of the families.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">These are the
commandements and the iudgements which the Lord commanded by the
hand of Moses, vnto the children of Israel in the plaines of Moab,
by Iordane, neere Iericho.</ab>



</div>