<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-31-31.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 The Midianites are spoyled, and
Balaam slaine. 13 Moses is wroth with the officers, for sauing the
women aliue. 19 How the souldiers with their captiues and spoile,
are to be purified. 25 The proportion whereby the pray is to be
diuided. 48 The voluntary oblation vnto the Treasury of the
Lord.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Auenge the
children of Israel of the Midianites: afterward shalt thou be
gathered vnto thy people.<note> Chap. 25. 17. , Chap. 27. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Moses spake
vnto the people, saying, Arme some of your selues vnto the warre,
and let them goe against the Midianites, and auenge the Lord of
Midian.</ab>
<ab n="4">Of euery tribe a
thousand, throughout all the tribes of Israel, shall ye send to the
warre.<note> Hebr. a thousand of a tribe, a thousand of a tribe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">So there were
deliuered out of the thousands of Israel, a thousand of euery
tribe, twelue thousand armed for warre.</ab>

<fw>Balaam slaine.</fw>
<ab n="6">And Moses sent
them to the warre, a thousand of euery tribe, them and Phinehas the
sonne of Eleazar the Priest, to the warre, with the holy
instruments, and the trumpets to blow, in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they warred
against the Midianites, as the Lord commanded Moses, and they slew
all the males.</ab>
<ab n="8">And they slew the
Kings of Midian, beside the rest of them that were slaine; namely
Eui, and Rekem, and Zur, and Hur, and Reba, fiue Kings of Midian;
Balaam also the sonne of Beor they slew with the sword.<note> Iosh. 13. 21,</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the children
of Israel tooke all the women of Midian captiues, and their little
ones, and tooke the spoile of all their cattell, and all their
flocks, and all their goods.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they burnt
all their cities wherein they dwelt, and all their goodly castles
with fire:</ab>
<ab n="11">And they tooke
all the spoile, and all the pray, both of men and of
beasts.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they brought
the captiues, and the pray, and the spoile vnto Moses and Eleazar
the Priest, and vnto the Congregation of the children of Israel,
vnto the campe at the plaines of Moab, which are by Iordan neere
Iericho.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And Moses
and Eleazar the Priest, and all the Princes of the Congregation
went foorth to meete them without the campe.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Moses was
wroth with the officers of the hoste, with the captaines ouer
thousands, and captaines ouer hundreds, which came from the
battel.<note> Hebr. hoste of warre.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Moses said
vnto them, Haue ye saued all the women aliue?</ab>
<ab n="16">Behold, these
caused the children of Israel, through the counsell of Balaam, to
commit trespasse against the Lord in the matter of Peor, and there
was a plague among the Congregation of the Lord.<note> Chap. 25. 2. , 2.Pet. 2. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Now therefore
kill euery male among the little ones, and kill euery woman that
hath knowen man, by lying with him.<note> Iudg. 21. 11. , Hebr. a male.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">But all the
women children that haue not knowen a man by lying with him, keepe
aliue for your selues.</ab>

<fw>The diuiding of the pray.</fw>
<ab n="19">And doe yee
abide without the campe seuen dayes: whosoeuer hath killed any
person, and whosoeuer hath touched any slaine, purifie both your
selues, and your captiues, on the third day, and on the seuenth
day.<note> Chap. 19. 11. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And purifie all
your raiment, and all that is made of skinnes, and all worke of
goates haire, and all things made of wood.<note> Hebr. instrument or vessell of skinnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And
Eleazar the Priest said vnto the men of warre which went to the
battell, This is the ordinance of the law which the Lord commaunded
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="22">Onely the gold,
and the siluer, the brasse, the yron, the tinne, and the
lead,</ab>
<ab n="23">Euery thing that
may abide the fire, yee shall make it goe through the fire, and it
shall be cleane: neuerthelesse, it shall be purified with the water
of separation: and all that abideth not the fire, yee shall make
goe through the water.</ab>
<ab n="24">And ye shall
wash your clothes on the seuenth day, and ye shalbe cleane, and
afterward yee shall come into the campe.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="26">Take the summe
of the pray, that was taken, both of man and of beast, thou and
Eleazar the Priest, and the chiefe fathers of the
Congregation:<note> Hebr. of the captiuity</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And diuide the
pray into two parts, betweene them that tooke the warre vpon them,
who went out to battell, and betweene all the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="28">And leuie a
tribute vnto the Lord of the men of warre which went out to
battell: one soule of fiue hundred, both of the persons, and of the
beeues, and of the asses, and of the sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="29">Take it of their
halfe, and giue it vnto Eleazar the Priest, for an heaue offering
of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="30">And of the
children of Israels halfe, thou shalt take one portion of fiftie,
of the persons, of the beeues, of the asses, and of the flockes, of
all maner of beasts, and giue them vnto the Leuites, which keepe
the charge of the Tabernacle of the Lord.<note> Or, goats.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And Moses and
Eleazar the Priest did as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="32">And the bootie
being the rest of the pray which the men of war had caught, was six
hundred thousand, and seuenty thousand, and fiue thousand
sheepe,</ab>
<ab n="33">And threescore
and twelue thousand beeues,</ab>

<fw>The diuiding of the pray.</fw>
<ab n="34">And threescore
and one thousand asses:</ab>
<ab n="35">And thirtie and
two thousand persons in all, of women that had not knowen man by
lying with him.</ab>
<ab n="36">And the halfe
which was the portion of them that went out to warre, was in number
three hundred thousand, and seuen and thirtie thousand, and fiue
hundred sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the Lords
tribute of the sheepe was sixe hundred and threescore and
fifteene.</ab>
<ab n="38">And the beeues
were thirtie and sixe thousand, of which the Lords tribute was
threescore and twelue.</ab>
<ab n="39">And the asses
were thirtie thousand and fiue hundred, of which the Lords tribute
was threescore and one.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the persons
were sixteene thousand, of which the Lords tribute was thirtie and
two persons.</ab>
<ab n="41">And Moses gaue
the tribute which was the Lords heaue offering, vnto Eleazar the
Priest, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="42">And of the
children of Israels halfe, which Moses diuided from the men that
warred:</ab>
<ab n="43">(Now the halfe
that perteined vnto the Congregation, was three hundred thousand,
and thirtie thousand, and seuen thousand, and fiue hundred
sheepe:</ab>
<ab n="44">And thirtie and
sixe thousand beeues:</ab>
<ab n="45">And thirtie
thousand asses, and fiue hundred:</ab>
<ab n="46">And sixteene
thousand persons)</ab>
<ab n="47">Euen of the
children of Israels halfe, Moses tooke one portion of fiftie, both
of man and of beast, and gaue them vnto the Leuites, which kept the
charge of the Tabernacle of the Lord, as the Lord commanded
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="48">¶ And the
officers which were ouer thousands of the hoste, the captaines of
thousands, and captaines of hundreds came neere vnto Moses.</ab>
<ab n="49">And they said
vnto Moses, Thy seruants haue taken the summe of the men of warre
which are vnder our charge, and there lacketh not one man of
vs.<note> Heb. hand.</note></ab>

<fw>The request of Reuben and Gad.</fw>
<ab n="50">Wee haue
therefore brought an oblation for the Lord, what euerie man hath
gotten, of iewels of golde chaines, and bracelets, rings,
earerings, and tablets, to make an atonement for our soules before
the Lord.<note> Hebr. found.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And Moses and
Eleazar the Priest tooke the gold of them: euen all wrought
iewels.</ab>
<ab n="52">And all the gold
of the offring that they offered vp to the Lord, of the captaines
of thousands, and of the captaines of hundreds, was sixteene
thousand, seuen hundred and fiftie shekels.<note> Heb. heaue offering.</note></ab>
<ab n="53">(For the men of
warre had taken spoile, euery man for himselfe.)</ab>
<ab n="54">And Moses and
Eleazar the Priest tooke the gold of the captaines, of thousands,
and of hundreds, and brought it into the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, for a memoriall for the children of Israel before the
Lord.</ab>



</div>