<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The vncleane are remoued out of
the campe. 5 Restitution is to be made in trespasses. 11 The triall
of Iealousie.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Commaund the
children of Israel, that they put out of the campe euery leper, and
euery one that hath an issue, and whosoeuer is defiled by the
dead:<note> Leuit.13. 3. , Leuit.15. 2. , Leuit.21, 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Both male and
female shal ye put out, without the campe shall yee put them, that
they defile not their campes in the middest whereof I
dwell.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the children
of Israel did so, and put them out, without the campe: as the Lord
spake vnto Moses, so did the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="6">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, When a man or woman shall commit any sinne that
men commit, to doe a trespasse against the Lord, and that person be
guiltie;<note> Leuit.6. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then they shall
confesse their sinne, which they haue done: and hee shall
recompense his trespasse, with the principall thereof, and adde
vnto it the fifth part thereof, and giue it vnto him against whom
he hath trespassed.<note> Leui.6.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But if the man
haue no kinsman to recompense the trespasse vnto, let the trespasse
be recompensed vnto the Lord, euen to the Priest: beside the ramme
of the atonement, whereby an atonement shall be made for
him.</ab>

<fw>Of iealousie.</fw>
<ab n="9">And euery offering
of all the holy things of the children of Israel, which they bring
vnto the Priest, shall be his.<note> Or, heaue offering.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And euery mans
halowed things shall be his: whatsoeuer any man giueth the Priest,
it shall be his.<note> Leuit. 10. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="12">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, If any mans wife goe aside,
and commit a trespasse against him;</ab>
<ab n="13">And a man lye
with her carnally, and it be hid from the eyes of her husband, and
be kept close, and she be defiled, and there be no witnesse against
her, neither she be taken with the maner;</ab>
<ab n="14">And the spirit of
ielousie come vpon him, and he be ielous of his wife, and shee be
defiled: or if the spirit of ielousie come vpon him, and hee be
ielous of his wife, and she be not defiled:</ab>
<ab n="15">Then shall the
man bring his wife vnto the Priest, and he shall bring her offering
for her, the tenth part of an Ephah of barley meale: hee shall
powre no oyle vpon it, nor put frankincense thereon; for it is an
offering of ielousie, an offering of memoriall, bringing iniquitie
to remembrance:</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Priest
shall bring her neere, and set her before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the Priest
shall take holy water in an earthen vessell, and of the dust that
is in the floore of the Tabernacle the Priest shall take, and put
it into the water:</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Priest
shall set the woman before the Lord, and vncouer the womans head,
and put the offering of memoriall in her hands, which is the
Ielousie offering: and the Priest shall haue in his hand the bitter
water that causeth the curse.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the Priest
shall charge her by an othe, and say vnto the woman, If no man haue
lyen with thee, and if thou hast not gone aside to vncleannesse
with another in stead of thy husband, be thou free from this bitter
water that causeth the curse.<note> Or, being in the power of thy husband. Hebr. vnder thy husband.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But if thou hast
gone aside to another in stead of thy husband, and if thou be
defiled, and some man hath lien with thee beside thine
husband:</ab>

<fw>The law of ielousie.</fw>
<ab n="21">Then the Priest
shall charge the woman with an othe of cursing, and the Priest
shall say vnto the woman, The Lord make thee a curse, and an othe
among thy people, when the Lord doth make thy thigh to rot, and thy
belly to swell.<note> Hebr. fall.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And this water
that causeth the curse, shall go into thy bowels, to make thy belly
to swell, and thy thigh to rot: and the woman shall say, Amen,
Amen.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the Priest
shall write these curses in a booke, and hee shall blot them out
with the bitter water:</ab>
<ab n="24">And he shall
cause the woman to drinke the bitter water, that causeth the curse:
and the water that causeth the curse shall enter into her, and
become bitter.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then the Priest
shall take the ielousie offering out of the womans hand, and shall
waue the offering before the Lord, and offer it vpon the
Altar.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the Priest
shal take an handfull of the offering, euen the memoriall thereof,
and burne it vpon the Altar, and afterward shall cause the woman to
drinke the water.</ab>
<ab n="27">And when he hath
made her to drinke the water, then it shall come to passe, that if
shee be defiled, and haue done trespasse against her husband, that
the water that causeth the curse, shall enter into her, and become
bitter, and her belly shall swell, and her thigh shal rot: and the
woman shalbe a curse among her people.</ab>
<ab n="28">And if the woman
be not defiled, but be cleane, then she shall be free, and shall
conceiue seed.</ab>
<ab n="29">This is the law
of ielousies, when a wife goeth aside to another in stead of her
husband, and is defiled:</ab>
<ab n="30">Or when the
spirit of ielousie commeth vpon him, and hee be ielous ouer his
wife, and shall set the woman before the Lord, and the Priest shal
execute vpon her all this law.</ab>
<ab n="31">Then shall the
man bee guiltlesse from iniquitie, and this woman shall beare her
iniquitie.</ab>



</div>