<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_23" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-23-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIII.</head>
<head>1. 13. 28 Balaks sacrifice. 7. 18
Balaams parable.</head>

<ab n="1">And Balaam saide
vnto Balak, Build me here seuen Altars, and prepare mee here seuen
oxen, and seuen rammes.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Balak did as
Balaam had spoken, and Balak &amp; Balaam offered on euery altar a
bullocke and a ramme.</ab>

<fw>Balaam blesseth the Israelites, and
prophesieth.</fw>
<ab n="3">And Balaam said
vnto Balak, Stand by thy burnt offring, and I wil goe: peraduenture
the Lord will come to meete mee; and whatsoeuer he sheweth me, I
will tell thee. And he went to an high place.<note> Or, he went solitary.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And God met
Balaam, and he said vnto him, I haue prepared seuen altars, and I
haue offered vpon euery altar a bullocke and a ramme.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Lord put
a word in Balaams mouth, and said, Returne vnto Balak, &amp; thus
thou shalt speake.</ab>
<ab n="6">And he returned
vnto him, and loe, he stood by his burnt sacrifice, hee, and all
the Princes of Moab.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he tooke vp
his parable, and said, Balak the King of Moab hath brought mee from
Aram, out of the mountaines of the East, saying, Come, curse me
Iacob, and come, defie Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">How shall I
curse, whom God hath not cursed? or how shall I defie, whom the
Lord hath not defied?</ab>
<ab n="9">For from the top
of the rockes I see him, and from the hilles I behold him: loe, the
people shall dwell alone, and shall not bee reckoned among the
nations.</ab>
<ab n="10">Who can count
the dust of Iacob, and the number of the fourth part of Israel? Let
mee die the death of the righteous, &amp; let my last end be like
his.<note> Hebr. my soule, or my life.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Balak saide
vnto Balaam, What hast thou done vnto me? I tooke thee to curse
mine enemies, and behold, thou hast blessed them
altogether.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he answered,
and said, Must I not take heede to speake that which the Lord hath
put in my mouth?</ab>
<ab n="13">And Balak said
vnto him, Come, I pray thee, with me, vnto another place, from
whence thou mayest see them: thou shalt see but the vtmost part of
them, and shalt not see them all: and curse me them from
thence.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And hee
brought him into the fielde of Zophim, to the toppe of Pisgah, and
built seuen altars, and offered a bullocke and a ramme on euery
altar.<note> Or, the hill.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he said vnto
Balak, Stand here by thy burnt offering, while I meete the Lord
yonder.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Lord met
Balaam, and put a word in his mouth, and saide, Goe againe vnto
Balak, and say thus.<note> Chap.22. 35.</note></ab>

<fw>Balaam blesseth the Israelites, and
prophesieth.</fw>
<ab n="17">And when hee
came to him, behold, he stood by his burnt offring, and the Princes
of Moab with him. And Balak said vnto him, What hath the Lord
spoken?</ab>
<ab n="18">And he tooke vp
his parable, and said, Rise vp Balak, &amp; heare; hearken vnto me,
thou sonne of Zippor:</ab>
<ab n="19">God is not a man
that he should lie, neither the sonne of man, that hee should
repent: hath he said, and shall he not doe it? or, hath hee spoken,
and shall he not make it good?</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, I haue
receiued commandement to blesse: and hee hath blessed, and I cannot
reuerse it.</ab>
<ab n="21">Hee hath not
beheld iniquitie in Iacob, neither hath he seene peruersenesse in
Israel: the Lord his God is with him, and the shoute of a King is
among them.</ab>
<ab n="22">God brought them
out of Egypt; he hath as it were the strength of an
Unicorne.<note> Num.24. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Surely there is
no inchantment against Iacob, neither is there any diuination
against Israel: according to this time it shalbe said of Iacob, and
of Israel, What hath God wrought!<note> Or, in.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Beholde, the
people shall rise vp as a great Lion, and lift vp himselfe as a
yong Lion: hee shall not lie downe vntill he eate of the pray, and
drinke the blood of the slaine.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ And Balak
said vnto Balaam, Neither curse them at all, nor blesse them at
all.</ab>
<ab n="26">But Balaam
answered, and said vnto Balak, Told not I thee, saying, All that
the Lord speaketh, that I must doe?</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ And Balak
saide vnto Balaam, Come, I pray thee, I will bring thee vnto
another place, peraduenture it will please God, that thou mayest
curse me them from thence.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Balak
brought Balaam vnto the top of Peor, that looketh toward
Ieshimon.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Balaam saide
vnto Balak, Build mee here seuen altars, and prepare me here seuen
bullocks, and seuen rammes.</ab>
<ab n="30">And Balak did as
Balaam had said, and offred a bullocke and a ramme on euery
altar.</ab>



</div>