<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 The borders of the land. 16 The
names of the men which shall diuide the land.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Command the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When ye come into the land
of Canaan, (this is the land that shall fall vnto you for an
inheritance, euen the land of Canaan, with the coasts
thereof.)</ab>
<ab n="3">Then your South
quarter shall be from the wildernesse of Zin, along by the coast of
Edom, and your South border shall be the outmost coast of the salt
Sea Eastward.<note> Iosh. 15.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And your border
shal turne from the South to the ascent of Akrabbim, and passe on
to Zin: and the going foorth thereof shall be from the South to
Kadesh-Barnea, and shall goe on to Hazar-Addar, and passe on to
Azmon.</ab>

<fw>The borders of Canaan.</fw>
<ab n="5">And the border
shall fetch a comcompasse from Azmon vnto the riuer of Egypt, and
the goings out of it shall be at the sea.</ab>
<ab n="6">And as for the
Westerne border, you shall euen haue the great sea for a border:
this shall be your West border.</ab>
<ab n="7">And this shall be
your North border: from the great sea, you shall point out for you,
mount Hor.</ab>
<ab n="8">From mount Hor,
ye shall point out your border vnto the entrance of Hamath: and the
goings foorth of the border shall be to Zedad.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
border shall goe on to Ziphron, and the goings out of it shall bee
at Hazar Enan: this shall be your North border.</ab>
<ab n="10">And ye shall
point out your East border, from Hazar Enan to Shepham.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the coast
shall goe downe from Shepham to Riblah, on the East side of Ain:
and the border shall descend and shall reach vnto the side of the
sea of Chinnereth Eastward.<note> Hebr. shoulder.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And the border
shall goe downe to Iordane, and the goings out of it shall be at
the salt sea: this shall be your land with the coastes thereof
round about.</ab>
<ab n="13">And Moses
commanded the children of Israel, saying, This is the land which ye
shall inherite by lot, which the Lord commanded to giue vnto the
nine tribes, and to the halfe tribe.</ab>
<ab n="14">For the tribe of
the children of Reuben, according to the house of their fathers,
and the tribe of the children of Gad, according to the house of
their fathers, haue receiued their inheritance, and halfe the tribe
of Manasseh haue receiued their inheritance.<note> Chap. 32. 33. iosh. 14. 2, 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The two tribes,
and the halfe tribe haue receiued their inheritance on this side
Iordane neere Iericho, Eastward, toward the Sunne rising.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="17">These are the
names of the men which shall diuide the land vnto you: Eleazar the
Priest, and Ioshua the sonne of Nun.<note> Iosh. 19. 51.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And yee shall
take one Prince of euery tribe, to diuide the land by
inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the names of
the men are these: Of the tribe of Iudah, Caleb the sonne of
Iephunneh.</ab>

<fw>The Leuites cities.</fw>
<ab n="20">And of the tribe
of the children of Simeon, Shemuel the sonne of Ammihud.</ab>
<ab n="21">Of the tribe of
Beniamin, Elidad the sonne of Chislon.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the Prince
of the tribe of the children of Dan, Bukki the sonne of
Iogli.</ab>
<ab n="23">The Prince of
the children of Ioseph: for the tribe of the children of Manasseh,
Hanniel the sonne of Ephod.</ab>
<ab n="24">And the Prince
of the tribe of the children of Ephraim, Kemuel the sonne of
Shiphtan.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the Prince
of the tribe of the children of Zebulun, Elizaphan the sonne of
Parnach.</ab>
<ab n="26">And the Prince
of the tribe of the children of Issachar, Paltiel the sonne of
Azzan.</ab>
<ab n="27">And the Prince
of the tribe of the children of Asher, Ahihud the sonne of
Shelomi.</ab>
<ab n="28">And the Prince
of the tribe of the children of Naphtali, Pedahel the sonne of
Ammihud.</ab>
<ab n="29">These are they
whom the Lord commaunded to diuide the inheritance vnto the
children of Israel in the land of Canaan.</ab>



</div>