<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The Passeouer is commanded againe.
6 A second Passeouer allowed for them that were vncleane or absent.
15 The cloude guideth the remouings &amp; incampings of the
Israelites.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses in the wildernesse of Sinai, in the first moneth of the
second yeere; after they were come out of the land of Egypt,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Let the children
of Israel also keepe the Passeouer, at his appointed
season.<note> Exod. 12. 1. &amp;c. leuit. 23.5. chap. 28.16. deut. 16.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">In the fourteenth
day of this moneth at euen, ye shall keepe it in his appointed
season: according to all the rites of it, and according to all the
ceremonies thereof shall ye keepe it.<note> Hebr. betweene the two euenings.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Moses spake
vnto the children of Israel that they should keepe the
Passeouer.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they kept the
Passeouer on the fourteenth day of the first moneth at Euen, in the
wildernesse of Sinai: according to all that the Lord commanded
Moses, so did the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And there
were certaine men who were defiled by the dead body of a man, that
they could not keepe the Passeouer on that day: and they came
before Moses, and before Aaron on that day.</ab>
<ab n="7">And those men said
vnto him, We are defiled by the dead body of a man: wherefore are
we kept backe, that wee may not offer an offring of the Lord in his
appointed season among the children of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="8">And Moses saide
vnto them, Stand still, and I will heare what the Lord wil command
concerning you.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="10">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, saying, If any man of you, or of your
posteritie shall be vncleane by reason of a dead body, or bee in a
iourney afarre off, yet he shall keepe the Passeouer vnto the
Lord.</ab>

<fw>Cloud and fire.</fw>
<ab n="11">The fourteenth
day of the second moneth at Euen they shall keepe it, and eat it
with vnleauened bread and bitter herbes.</ab>
<ab n="12">They shall leaue
none of it vnto the morning, nor breake any bone of it: according
to all the ordinances of the Passeouer they shall keepe
it.<note> Exod. 12. 46. ioh. 19. 36.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But the man that
is cleane, and is not in a iourney, and forbeareth to keep the
Passeouer, euen the same soule shall be cut off from his people,
because hee brought not the offering of the Lord in his appointed
season: that man shall beare his sinne.</ab>
<ab n="14">And if a stranger
shall soiourne among you, and will keepe the Passeouer vnto the
Lord; according to the ordinance of the Passeouer, and according to
the maner thereof, so shall he doe: ye shall haue one ordinance,
both for the stranger, and for him that was borne in the
land.<note> Exod.12. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And on the
day that the Tabernacle was reared vp, the cloud couered the
Tabernacle, namely the Tent of the Testimony: and at Euen there was
vpon the Tabernacle, as it were the appearance of fire, vntill the
morning.<note> Exod. 40. 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">So it was always:
the cloud couered it by day, and the appearance of fire by
night.</ab>
<ab n="17">And when the
cloud was taken vp from the Tabernacle, then after that, the
children of Israel iourneyed, and in the place where the cloud
abode, there the children of Israel pitched their tents.</ab>
<ab n="18">At the
commandement of the Lord the children of Israel iourneied, and at
the commandement of the Lord they pitched: as long as the cloud
abode vpon the Tabernacle, they rested in the tents.<note> 1.Corin. 10.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And when the
cloud taried long vpon the Tabernacle many daies, then the children
of Israel kept the charge of the Lord, and iourneyed
not.<note> Hebr. prolonged.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And so it was
when the cloude was a few daies vpon the Tabernacle, according to
the commandement of the Lord, they abode in their tents, and
according to the commandement of the Lord, they iourneyed.</ab>

<fw>Siluer trumpets.</fw>
<ab n="21">And so it was
when the cloude abode from Euen vnto the morning, and that the
cloude was taken vp in the morning, then they iourneyed: whether it
was by day or by night that the cloude was taken vp, they
iourneyed.<note> Hebr. was.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Or whether it
were two dayes, or a moneth, or a yeere that the cloude taried vpon
the Tabernacle, remayning thereon, the children of Israel abode in
their tents, and iourneyed not: but when it was taken vp, they
iourneyed.<note> Exod.40. 36.37.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">At the
commandement of the Lord they rested in the tents, and at the
commaundement of the Lord they iourneyed: they kept the charge of
the Lord, at the commandement of the Lord by the hand of
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>