<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-24-24.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<head>1 Balaam leauing diuinations,
prophesieth the happinesse of Israel. 10 Balak in anger dismisseth
him. 15 He prophesieth of the starre of Iacob, and the destruction
of some nations.</head>


<fw>Balaam blesseth the Israelites, and prophesieth.
The Starre of Iacob.</fw>
<ab n="1">And when Balaam
sawe that it pleased the Lord to blesse Israel, hee went not, as at
other times to seeke for inchantments, but hee set his face toward
the wildernesse.<note> Chap.23. 3.15. , Heb. to the meeting of inchantments.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And Balaam lift
vp his eyes, and he saw Israel abiding in his tents, according to
their Tribes: and the Spirit of God came vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he tooke vp
his parable, and said, Balaam the sonne of Beor hath said, and the
man whose eyes are open hath said:<note> Chap. 23. 7, 18. , Heb. who had his eyes shut, but now open.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Hee hath said,
which heard the words of God, which saw the vision of the
Almightie, falling into a trance, but hauing his eyes open:</ab>
<ab n="5">How goodly are
thy tents, O Iacob, and thy Tabernacles, O Israel!</ab>
<ab n="6">As the valleyes
are they spread forth, as gardens by the riuer side, as the trees
of Lign-Aloes which the Lord hath planted, and as Cedar trees
beside the waters.</ab>
<ab n="7">He shall powre
the water out of his buckets, and his seed shall be in many waters,
and his King shall be higher then Agag, and his Kingdome shall be
exalted.</ab>
<ab n="8">God brought him
forth out of Egypt, he hath as it were the strength of an Unicorne:
he shall eate vp the nations his enemies, and shall breake their
bones, and pierce them thorow with his arrowes.<note> Chap.23. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Hee couched, he
lay downe as a Lyon, and as a great Lyon: who shal stirre him vp?
Blessed is hee that blesseth thee, and cursed is hee that curseth
thee.<note> Gen.49. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And
Balaks anger was kindled against Balaam, and hee smote his hands
together: and Balak said vnto Balaam, I called thee to curse mine
enemies, and behold, thou hast altogether blessed them these three
times.</ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore now,
flee thou to thy place: I thought to promote thee vnto great
honour, but loe, the Lord hath kept thee backe from honour.</ab>
<ab n="12">And Balaam said
vnto Balak, Spake I not also to thy messengers which thou sentest
vnto me, saying,</ab>

<fw>The Starre of Iacob.</fw>
<ab n="13">If Balak would
give mee his house full of siluer and gold, I cannot goe beyond the
commandement of the Lord, to doe either good or bad of mine owne
mind? But what the Lord saith, that will I speake.</ab>
<ab n="14">And now beholde,
I goe vnto my people: come therefore, and I will aduertise thee,
what this people shall doe to thy people in the latter
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And hee
tooke vp his parable, and said, Balaam the sonne of Beor hath said,
and the man whose eyes are open, hath said:</ab>
<ab n="16">He hath said
which heard the words of God, and knewe the knowledge of the most
High, which sawe the vision of the Almightie, falling into a
trance, but hauing his eyes open.</ab>
<ab n="17">I shall see him,
but not now: I shall behold him, but not nigh: There shall come a
starre out of Iacob, and a Scepter shall rise out of Israel, and
shall smite the corners of Moab, and destroy all the children of
Sheth.<note> Or, smite through the Princes of Moab.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Edom shall
bee a possession, Seir also shall be a possession for his enemies,
and Israel shall doe valiantly.</ab>
<ab n="19">Out of Iacob
shall come he that shall haue dominion, and shall destroy him that
remaineth of the citie.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And when
he looked on Amalek, he tooke vp his parable, and sayd, Amalek was
the first of the nations, but his latter end shall bee, that hee
perish for euer.<note> The first of the nations that warred against Israel, Exod. 17. , Or, shalbe euen to destruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And hee looked
on the Kenites, and tooke vp his parable, and saide, Strong is thy
dwelling place, and thou puttest thy nest in a rocke:</ab>
<ab n="22">Neuerthelesse,
the Kenite shall be wasted, vntil Asshur shal carie thee away
captiue.<note> Heb. Kain , Or, how long shall it be ere Ashur carry thee away captiue.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And he tooke vp
his parable, and said, Alas! who shall liue when God doeth
this?</ab>
<ab n="24">And shippes
shall come from the coast of Chittim, and shal afflict Asshur, and
shall afflict Eber, and hee also shall perish for euer.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Balaam rose
vp, and went and returned to his place: and Balak also went his
way.</ab>



</div>