<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The Law of the Nazarites. 22 The
forme of blessing the people.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>

<fw>The law of the Nazarites.</fw>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When either man or woman
shall separate themselues to vow a vow of a Nazarite, to separate
themselues vnto the Lord:<note> Or, make themselues Nazarites.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Hee shall separate
himselfe from wine, and strong drinke, and shal drinke no vineger
of wine, or vineger of strong drinke, neither shal he drinke any
liquor of grapes, nor eate moist grapes, or dried.</ab>
<ab n="4">All the dayes of
his separation shall he eat nothing that is made of the vine tree,
from the kernels euen to the huske.<note> Or, Nazariteship. , Heb. Vine of the wine.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">All the dayes of
the vow of his separation, there shall no rasour come vpon his
head: vntill the dayes bee fulfilled in the which hee separateth
himselfe vnto the Lord, he shall be holy, and shall let the lockes
of the haire of his head grow.<note> Iudg.13. 5.1. sam.1. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">All the dayes that
he separateth himselfe vnto the Lord, hee shall come at no dead
body.</ab>
<ab n="7">Hee shall not make
himselfe vncleane for his father, or for his mother, for his
brother, or for his sister, when they die: because the consecration
of his God is vpon his head.<note> Hebr. separation.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">All the dayes of
his separation he is holy vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="9">And if any man die
very suddenly by him, and he hath defiled the head of his
consecration, then he shall shaue his head in the day of his
cleansing, on the seuenth day shall he shaue it.</ab>
<ab n="10">And on the eight
day he shal bring two turtles or two yong pigeons to the Priest, to
the doore of the Tabernacle of the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Priest
shall offer the one for a sinne offering, and the other for a burnt
offering, and make an atonement for him, for that hee sinned by the
dead, and shall hallow his head that same day.</ab>
<ab n="12">And hee shall
consecrate vnto the Lord the dayes of his separation, and shall
bring a lambe of the first yeere for a trespasse offering: but the
dayes that were before shall be lost, because his separation was
defiled.<note> Hebr. fall.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ And this
is the Lawe of the Nazarite: when the dayes of his separation are
fulfilled, he shall be brought vnto the doore of the Tabernacle of
the Congregation.</ab>

<fw>The law of the Nazarites.</fw>
<ab n="14">And he shall
offer his offring vnto the Lord, one hee lambe of the first yeere
without blemish, for a burnt offering, and one ewe lambe of the
first yeere without blemish, for a sinne offering, and one lambe
without blemish for peace offerings,</ab>
<ab n="15">And a basket of
vnleauened bread, cakes of fine flowre mingled with oyle, and
wafers of vnleauened bread anointed with oyle, and their meate
offering, and their drinke offerings.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the Priest
shall bring them before the Lord, and shall offer his sinne
offering, and his burnt offering.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he shall
offer the ramme for a sacrifice of peace offerings vnto the Lord,
with the basket of vnleauened bread: the Priest shall offer also
his meate offering, and his drinke offering.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the Nazarite
shal shaue the head of his separation, at the doore of the
Tabernacle of the Congregation, and shall take the haire of the
head of his separation, and put it in the fire which is vnder the
sacrifice of the peace offerings.<note> Acts 21. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the Priest
shall take the sodden shoulder of the ramme, and one vnleauened
cake out of the basket, and one vnleauened wafer, and shall put
them vpon the hands of the Nazarite, after the haire of his
separation is shauen.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Priest
shall waue them for a waue offring before the Lord: this is holy
for the Priest, with the waue breast, and heaue shoulder: and after
that, the Nazarite may drinke wine.<note> Exod. 29. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">This is the Law
of the Nazarite, who hath vowed, and of his offering vnto the Lord
for his separation, besides that, that his hand shall get:
according to the vow which he vowed, so he must do after the law of
his separation.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="23">Speake vnto
Aaron, and vnto his sonnes, saying, On this wise ye shall blesse
the children of Israel, saying vnto them:</ab>
<ab n="24">The Lord blesse
thee, and keepe thee:</ab>
<ab n="25">The Lord make his
face shine vpon thee, and be gracious vnto thee:</ab>
<ab n="26">The Lord lift vp
his countenance vpon thee, and giue thee peace.</ab>
<ab n="27">And they shall
put my Name vpon the children of Israel, and I will blesse
them.</ab>



</div>