<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-21-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Israel with some losse destroy the
Canaanites at Hormah. 4 The people murmuring are plagued with fiery
serpents. 7 They repenting are healed by a brasen serpent. 10
Sundry iourneyes of the Israelites. 21 Sihon is ouercome, 33 and
Og.</head>

<ab n="1">And when king
Arad the Canaanite, which dwelt in the South, heard tell that
Israel came by the way of the spies, then hee fought against
Israel, and tooke some of them prisoners.<note> Chap. 33. 40.</note></ab>

<fw>Fierie serpents.</fw>
<ab n="2">And Israel vowed
a vow vnto the Lord, and said, If thou wilt in deed deliuer this
people into my hand, then I wil vtterly destroy their
cities.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the Lord
hearkened to the voyce of Israel, and deliuered vp the Canaanites:
and they vtterly destroyed them, and their cities, and hee called
the name of the place Hormah.<note> That is, vtter destruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And they
iourneyed from mount Hor, by the way of the red sea, to compasse
the land of Edom: and the soule of the people was much discouraged
because of the way.<note> Or, grieued. Hebr. shortened.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the people
spake against God and against Moses, Wherefore haue ye brought vs
vp out of Egypt, to die in the wildernesse? for there is no bread,
neither is there any water, and our soule loatheth this light
bread.<note> Chap. 11.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the Lord sent
fierie serpents among the people, and they bit the people, and much
people of Israel died.<note> Wisd.16. 1, 5. 1.cor. 10.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Therefore
the people came to Moses, and said, We haue sinned: for wee haue
spoken against the Lord, and against thee: pray vnto the Lord that
hee take away the serpents from vs: and Moses prayed for the
people.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, Make thee a fierie serpent, and set it vpon a pole: and
it shall come to passe, that euery one that is bitten, when hee
looketh vpon it, shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Moses made a
serpent of brasse, and put it vpon a pole, and it came to passe,
that if a serpent had bitten any man, when hee beheld the serpent
of brasse, he liued.<note> 2.King.18 4 ioh.3.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
children of Israel set forward, and pitched in Oboth.<note> Chap. 33 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And they
iourneyed from Oboth, and pitched at Iie-Abarim, in the wildernes
which is before Moab, toward the Sunne rising.<note> Or, heapes of Abarim.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ From
thence they remooued, and pitched in the valley of Zared.</ab>
<ab n="13">From thence they
remooued, and pitched on the other side of Arnon, which is in the
wildernesse that commeth out of the coasts of the Amorites: for
Arnon is the border of Moab, betweene Moab and the
Amorites.</ab>
<ab n="14">Wherefore it is
said in the booke of the warres of the Lord, what he did in the Red
sea, and in the brookes of Arnon,<note> Or, Vaheb in Suphah.</note></ab>

<fw>Sihon smitten.</fw>
<ab n="15">And at the
streame of the brookes that goeth downe to the dwelling of Ar,
&amp; lieth vpon the border of Moab.<note> Heb. leaneth.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And from thence
they went to Beer: that is the well whereof the Lord spake vnto
Moses, Gather the people together, and I will giue them
water.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ Then
Israel sang this song, Spring vp O well, Sing ye vnto
it:<note> Heb. ascend , Or, answere.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The Princes
digged the well, the nobles of the people digged it, by the
direction of the Law-giuer, with their staues. And from the
wildernesse they went to Mattanah:</ab>
<ab n="19">And from
Mattanah, to Nahaliel, and from Nahaliel to Bamoth:</ab>
<ab n="20">And from Bamoth
in the valley, that is in the countrey of Moab, to the toppe of
Pisgah, which looketh toward Ieshimon.<note> Heb. field. , Or, hill. , Or, the wildernesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And
Israel sent messengers vnto Sihon king of the Amorites,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="22">Let me passe
thorow thy land, we will not turne into the fields, or into the
vineyards, we will not drinke of the waters of the well: but we
will goe along by the kings high way, vntill wee be past thy
borders.<note> Deut.2. 27. iudges 11.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And Sihon would
not suffer Israel to passe thorow his border: but Sihon gathered
all his people together, and went out against Israel into the
wildernes: and he came to Iahaz, and fought against
Israel.<note> Deut. 29.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Israel smote
him with the edge of the sword, and possessed his land from Arnon
vnto Iabok, euen vnto the children of Ammon: for the border of the
children of Ammon was strong.<note> Iosh.12.2 psal.135. 11. amos 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Israel tooke
all these cities: and Israel dwelt in all the cities of the
Amorites, in Heshbon, and in all the villages thereof.<note> Hebr. daughters.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For Heshbon was
the citie of Sihon the King of the Amorites, who had fought against
the former King of Moab, and taken all his land out of his hand,
euen vnto Arnon.</ab>
<ab n="27">Wherefore they
that speake in prouerbes, say, Come into Heshbon: let the citie of
Sihon bee built and prepared.</ab>
<ab n="28">For there is a
fire gone out of Heshbon, a flame from the citie of Sihon: it hath
consumed Ar of Moab, and the lordes of the high places of
Arnon.</ab>

<fw>Og slaine. Balak sendeth for
Balaam.</fw>
<ab n="29">Woe to thee,
Moab, thou art vndone, O people of Chemosh: he hath giuen his
sonnes that escaped, and his daughters, into captiuitie vnto Sihon
King of the Amorites.<note> 1.King.11 7, 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">We haue shot at
them; Heshbon is perished euen vnto Dibon, and we haue layde them
waste euen vnto Nophah, which reacheth vnto Medeba.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Thus
Israel dwelt in the land of the Amorites.</ab>
<ab n="32">And Moses sent
to spy out Iaazer, and they tooke the villages thereof, and droue
out the Amorites that were there.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And they
turned and went vp by the way of Bashan: and Og the King of Bashan
went out against them, he, and all his people, to the battell at
Edrei.<note> Deut.3.1. and 29.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And the Lord
said vnto Moses, Feare him not: for I haue deliuered him into thy
hand, and all his people, and his land, and thou shalt doe to him
as thou didst vnto Sihon King of the Amorites, which dwelt at
Heshbon.<note> Psal. 135. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">So they smote
him &amp; his sonnes, and all his people, vntill there was none
left him aliue, and they possessed his land.</ab>



</div>