<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Aarons rod among all the rods of
the Tribes onely flourisheth. 10 It is left for a monument against
the rebels.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and take of euery one of them a rod, according
to the house of their fathers, of all their princes, according to
the house of their fathers, twelue rods: write thou euery mans name
vpon his rodde.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thou shalt
write Aarons name vpon the rod of Leui: for one rod shall be for
the head of the house of their fathers.</ab>
<ab n="4">And thou shalt
lay them vp in the Tabernacle of the Congregation, before the
Testimony, where I will meet with you.<note> Exod.25. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And it shall come
to passe, that the mans rod whom I shall choose, shall blossome:
and I will make to cease from mee the murmurings of the children of
Israel, whereby they murmure against you.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Moses
spake vnto the children of Israel, and euery one of their Princes
gaue him a rod a piece, for each Prince one, according to their
fathers houses, euen twelue rods: and the rod of Aaron was among
their rods.<note> Hebr. a rod for one Prince, a rod for one Prince.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Moses layd vp
the rods before the Lord, in the Tabernacle of Witnesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">And it came to
passe that on the morrow Moses went into the Tabernacle of
Witnesse, and behold, the rod of Aaron for the house of Leui was
budded, and brought forth buds, and bloomed blossomes, and yeelded
almonds.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Moses brought
out all the rods from before the Lord, vnto all the children of
Israel: and they looked, and tooke euery man his rod.</ab>

<fw>The Priests charge, and
portion.</fw>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
Lord said vnto Moses, Bring Aarons rod againe before the Testimony,
to be kept for a token against the rebels, and thou shalt quite
take away their murmurings from me, that they die not.<note> Hebr.9.4. , Hebr. children of rebellion.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And Moses did
so: as the Lord commanded him, so did he.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the children
of Israel spake vnto Moses, saying, Behold, wee die, we perish, we
all perish.</ab>
<ab n="13">Whosoeuer
commeth any thing neere vnto the Tabernacle of the Lord, shall die:
Shall wee be consumed with dying?</ab>



</div>