<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-15-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 The law of the meat offering and
the drinke offring. 13.29 The stranger is vnder the same law. 17
The law of the first of the dough for a heaue offering. 22 The
sacrifice for sinne of ignorance. 30 The punishment of presumption.
32. Hee that violated the Sabbath, is stoned. 37 The law of
fringes.</head>


<fw>Offerings.</fw>
<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When ye be come into the
land of your habitations, which I giue vnto you,<note> Leuit. 23. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And will make an
offering by fire vnto the Lord, a burnt offering or a sacrifice in
performing a vow, or in a free will offering, or in your solemne
feasts, to make a sweet sauour vnto the Lord, of the herd or of the
flocke:<note> Leuit. 22. 21. , Heb. separating. , Exod. 29. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then shall he
that offereth his offering vnto the Lord, bring a meat offring of a
tenth deale of flowre, mingled with the fourth part of an Hyn of
oyle.<note> Leuit.2.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the fourth
part of an Hyn of wine for a drinke offring shalt thou prepare,
with the burnt offering or sacrifice for one lambe.</ab>
<ab n="6">Or for a ramme,
thou shalt prepare for a meate offering two tenth deales of flowre
mingled with the third part of an Hyn of oyle.</ab>
<ab n="7">And for a drinke
offering, thou shalt offer the third part of an Hyn of wine, for a
sweete sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when thou
preparest a bullocke for a burnt offering, or for a sacrifice in
performing a vow, or peace offerings vnto the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="9">Then shall hee
bring with a bullocke a meate offering of three tenth deales of
flowre, mingled with halfe an Hyn of oyle.</ab>
<ab n="10">And thou shalt
bring for a drinke offering halfe an Hyn of wine, for an offering
made by fire of a sweet sauour vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thus shall it be
done for one bullocke, or for one ramme, or for a lambe, or a
kidde.</ab>
<ab n="12">According to the
number that yee shall prepare, so shall yee doe to euery one,
according to their number.</ab>
<ab n="13">All that are
borne of the countrey shall doe these things after this maner, in
offering an offering made by fire of a sweet sauour, vnto the
Lord.</ab>

<fw>Offerings.</fw>
<ab n="14">And if a
stranger soiourne with you, or whosoeuer bee among you in your
generations, and will offer an offering made by fire of a sweete
sauour vnto the Lord: as ye doe, so hee shall doe.</ab>
<ab n="15">One ordinance
shall be both for you of the Congregation, and also for the
stranger that soiourneth with you, an ordinance for euer in your
generations: as ye are, so shall the stranger bee, before the
Lord.<note> Exod. 12. 49. chap.9. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">One law, and one
maner shall be for you, and for the stranger that soiourneth with
you.</ab>
<ab n="17">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="18">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and say vnto them, When ye come into the land
whither I bring you,</ab>
<ab n="19">Then it shall be
that when ye eate of the bread of the land, yee shall offer vp an
heaue offring vnto the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="20">Ye shall offer
vp a cake of the first of your dough, for an heaue offring: as ye
doe the heaue offering of the threshing floore, so shall ye heaue
it.</ab>
<ab n="21">Of the first of
your dough ye shal giue vnto the Lord, an heaue offering in your
generations.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And if
yee haue erred, and not obserued all these Commaundements which the
Lord hath spoken vnto Moses,</ab>
<ab n="23">Euen all that
the Lord hath commanded you, by the hand of Moses from the day that
the Lord commanded Moses, and henceforward among your
generations:</ab>
<ab n="24">Then it shalbe,
if ought be committed by ignorance without the knowledge of the
Congregation, that all the Congregation shall offer one yong
bullocke for a burnt offering, for a sweet sauour vnto the Lord,
with his meate offering, and his drinke offering, according to the
manner, and one kid of the goats for a sinne offering.<note> Hebr. from the eyes. , Or, ordinance.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And the Priest
shall make an atonement for all the Congregation of the children of
Israel, and it shal be forgiuen them, for it is ignorance: and they
shall bring their offring, a sacrifice made by fire vnto the Lord,
and their sinne offering before the Lord, for their
ignorance.</ab>
<ab n="26">And it shall bee
forgiuen all the Congregation of the children of Israel, and the
stranger that soiourneth among them, seeing all the people were in
ignorance.</ab>

<fw>Sabbath broken.</fw>
<ab n="27">¶ And if
any soule sinne through ignorance, then hee shall bring a shee goat
of the first yeere for a sinne offring.<note> Leuit.4. 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And the Priest
shall make an atonement for the soule that sinneth ignorantly, when
he sinneth by ignorance before the Lord, to make an atonement for
him, &amp; it shalbe forgiuen him.</ab>
<ab n="29">You shall haue
one law for him that sinneth through ignorance, both for him that
is borne amongst the children of Israel, and for the stranger that
soiourneth among them.<note> Hebr. doeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ But the
soule that doeth ought presumptuously, whether he be borne in the
land, or a stranger, the same reprocheth the Lord: and that soule
shall be cut off from among his people.<note> Hebr. with an high hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Because he hath
despised the word of the Lord, and hath broken his commandement,
that soule shall vtterly be cut off: his iniquitie shall be vpon
him.</ab>
<ab n="32">¶ And while
the children of Israel were in the wildernes, they found a man that
gathered stickes vpon the Sabbath day.</ab>
<ab n="33">And they that
found him gathering sticks, brought him vnto Moses and Aaron, and
vnto all the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="34">And they put him
in ward, because it was not declared what should be done to
him.<note> Leuit. 24. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And the Lord
said vnto Moses, The man shall bee surely put to death: all the
Congregation shall stone him with stones without the campe.</ab>
<ab n="36">And all the
Cogregation brought him without the campe, and stoned him with
stones, and he died, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>
<ab n="37">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="38">Speake vnto the
children of Israel, and bidde them that they make them fringes in
the borders of their garments, throughout their generations, and
that they put vpon the fringe of the borders a ribband of
blew.<note> Deut.22. 12. matth. 23.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And it shall bee
vnto you for a fringe, that ye may looke vpon it, and remember all
the commandements of the Lord, and doe them: and that ye seeke not
after your owne heart, and your owne eyes, after which ye vse to
goe a whoring:</ab>
<ab n="40">That ye may
remember, and doe all my commandements, and be holy vnto your
God.</ab>

<fw>Korahs rebellion.</fw>
<ab n="41">I am the Lord
your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt, to bee your
God: I am the Lord your God.</ab>



</div>