<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-29-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-30-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 Vowes are not to be broken. 3 The
exception of a maids vow, 6 Of a wiues, 9 Of a widowes, or her that
is diuorced.</head>

<ab n="1">And Moses spake
vnto the heads of the tribes, concerning the children of Israel,
saying, This is the thing which the Lord hath commanded.</ab>
<ab n="2">If a man vowe a
vow vnto the Lord, or sweare an othe to bind his soule with a bond:
he shall not breake his word, hee shall doe according to all that
proceedeth out of his mouth.<note> Hebr. profane.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">If a woman also
vow a vow vnto the Lord, and binde her selfe by a bond, being in
her fathers house in her youth;</ab>
<ab n="4">And her father
heare her vow, and her bond wherewith shee hath bound her soule,
and her father shall holde his peace at her: then all her vowes
shall stand, and euery bond wherewith shee hath bound her soule,
shall stand.</ab>
<ab n="5">But if her father
disallow her in the day that he heareth; not any of her vowes or of
her bonds, wherewith she hath bound her soule, shall stand: and the
Lord shall forgiue her, because her father disallowed her.</ab>
<ab n="6">And if she had at
all an husband when she vowed, or vttered ought out of her lips,
wherewith shee bound her soule,<note> Hebr. her vowes were vpon her.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And her husband
heard it, and held his peace at her in the day that hee heard it:
then her vowes shall stand, and her bonds wherewith shee bound her
soule, shall stand.</ab>
<ab n="8">But if her
husband disallowe her on the day that he heard it, then he shall
make her vowe which she vowed, and that which she vttered with her
lippes wherewith shee bound her soule, of none effect, and the Lord
shall forgiue her.</ab>
<ab n="9">But euery vow of
a widow, and of her that is diuorced, wherewith they haue bound
their soules, shall stand against her.</ab>
<ab n="10">And if she vowed
in her husbands house, or bound her soule by a bond with an
oath;</ab>

<fw>Of Vowes.</fw>
<ab n="11">And her husband
heard it, and held his peace at her, and disallowed her not: then
all her vowes shall stand, and euery bond wherewith shee bound her
soule, shall stand.</ab>
<ab n="12">But if her
husband hath vtterly made them voyd on the day hee heard them: then
whatsoeuer proceeded out of her lips concerning her vowes, or
concerning the bond of her soule, shall not stand: her husband hath
made them voyd, and the Lord shal forgiue her.</ab>
<ab n="13">Euery vow, and
euery binding othe to afflict the soule, her husband may establish
it, or her husband may make it voyd.</ab>
<ab n="14">But if her
husband altogether hold his peace at her, from day to day, then he
establisheth all her vowes, or all her bonds which are vpon her:
hee confirmeth them, because hee held his peace at her, in the day
that hee heard them.</ab>
<ab n="15">But if hee shall
any wayes make them voyd after that he hath heard them, then he
shall beare her iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="16">These are the
statutes which the Lord commanded Moses betweene a man and his
wife, betweene the father and his daughter, being yet in her youth,
in her fathers house.</ab>



</div>