<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_27" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-27-28.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVII.</head>
<head>1 The daughters of Zelophehad sue
for an inheritance. 6 The law of inheritances. 12 Moses beeing told
of his death, sueth for a successour. 18 Ioshua is appointed to
succeed him.</head>


<fw>Zelophehad.</fw>
<ab n="1">Then came the
daughters of Zelophehad, the sonne of Hepher, the sonne of Gilead,
the sonne of Machir, the sonne of Manasseh, of the families of
Manasseh, the sonne of Ioseph; and these are the names of his
daughters: Mahlah, Noah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and
Tirzah.<note> Chap. 26. 33. iosh. 17.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And they stood
before Moses, and before Eleazar the Priest, and before the
Princes, and all the Congregation, by the doore of the Tabernacle
of the Congregation, saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Our father died
in the wildernesse, and he was not in the company of them that
gathered themselues together against the Lord in the company of
Korah: but died in his owne sinne, and had no sonnes.<note> Chap. 14. 35.and 26. 64, 65.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Why should the
name of our father be done away from among his family, because he
hath no sonne? Giue vnto vs therefore a possession among the
brethren of our father.<note> Hebr. diminished.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Moses brought
their cause before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
Lord spake vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="7">The daughters of
Zelophehad speake right: thou shalt surely giue them a possession
of an inheritance among their fathers brethren, and thou shalt
cause the inheritance of their father to passe vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou shalt
speake vnto the children of Israel, saying, If a man die, and haue
no sonne, then yee shall cause his inheritance to passe vnto his
daughter.</ab>
<ab n="9">And if he haue no
daughter, then yee shall giue his inheritance vnto his
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="10">And if he haue
no brethren, then yee shall giue his inheritance vnto his fathers
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="11">And if his
father haue no brethren, then ye shall giue his inheritance vnto
his kinseman that is next to him of his family, and hee shall
possesse it: And it shall be vnto the children of Israel a statute
of iudgement, as the Lord commanded Moses.</ab>

<fw>Ioshua ruler.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Get thee vp into this mount Abarim, and see
the land which I haue giuen vnto the children of
Israel.<note> Deut. 32. 49.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And when thou
hast seene it, thou also shalt be gathered vnto thy people, as
Aaron thy brother was gathered.<note> Chap. 20. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For ye rebelled
against my Commandement (in the desart of Zin, in the strife of the
Congregation) to sanctifie me at the water, before their eyes: that
is the water of Meribah in Kadesh in the wildernesse of
Zin.<note> Chap. 20. 24. , Exod. 17. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And Moses
spake vnto the Lord, saying,</ab>
<ab n="16">Let the Lord,
the God of the spirits of all flesh, set a man ouer the
Congregation,</ab>
<ab n="17">Which may goe
out before them, and which may goe in before them, and which may
lead them out, and which may bring them in, that the Congregation
of the Lord bee not as sheepe which haue no shepheard.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And the
Lord saide vnto Moses, Take thee Ioshua the sonne of Nun, a man in
whom is the spirit, and lay thine hand vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="19">And set him
before Eleazar the Priest, and before all the Congregation: and
giue him a charge in their sight.</ab>
<ab n="20">And thou shalt
put some of thine honour vpon him, that all the Congregation of the
children of Israel may be obedient.</ab>
<ab n="21">And he shall
stand before Eleazar the Priest, who shall aske counsell for him,
after the iudgement of Urim before the Lord: at his word shal they
goe out, and at his word they shal come in, both he, and al the
children of Israel with him, euen all the Congregation.<note> Exod.28. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And Moses did as
the Lord commanded him: and he tooke Ioshua and set him before
Eleazar the Priest, and before all the Congregation.</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee layd his
handes vpon him, and gaue him a charge, as the Lord commaunded by
the hand of Moses.</ab>



</div>