<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-31-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 The Reubenites and Gadites sue for
their inheritance on that side Iorden. 6 Moses reproueth them. 16
They offer him conditions to his content. 33 Moses assigneth them
the land. 39 They conquere it.</head>

<ab n="1">Now the children
of Reuben, and the children of Gad, had a very great multitude of
cattell: and when they saw the land of Iazer, and the land of
Gilead, that behold, the place was a place for cattell;</ab>
<ab n="2">The children of
Gad, and the children of Reuben, came and spake vnto Moses, and to
Eleazar the Priest, and vnto the Princes of the Congregation,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="3">Ataroth, and
Dibon, and Iazer, and Nimrah, and Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Shebam,
and Nebo, and Beon,</ab>
<ab n="4">Euen the countrey
which the Lord smote before the Congregation of Israel, is a land
for cattell, and thy seruants haue cattell.</ab>
<ab n="5">Wherefore, said
they, if wee haue found grace in thy sight, let this lande be giuen
vnto thy seruants for a possession, and bring vs not ouer
Iordane.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Moses
said vnto the children of Gad, and to the children of Reuben, Shall
your brethren goe to warre, and shall ye sit here?</ab>

<fw>The request of Reuben and Gad.</fw>
<ab n="7">And wherefore
discourage yee the heart of the children of Israel from going ouer
into the lande, which the Lord hath giuen them?<note> Hebr. breake.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Thus did your
fathers, when I sent them from Kadesh Barnea to see the
land.</ab>
<ab n="9">For when they
went vp vnto the valley of Eshcol, and saw the land, they
discouraged the heart of the children of Israel, that they should
not goe into the land which the Lord had giuen them.<note> Chap. 13. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the Lords
anger was kindled the same time, and hee sware, saying,</ab>
<ab n="11">Surely none of
the men that came vp out of Egypt, from twentie yeeres old and
vpward, shall see the lande which I sware vnto Abraham, vnto Isaac,
and vnto Iacob, because they haue not wholly followed
me:<note> Chap. 14. 28, 29. , Heb. fulfilled after me.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Saue Caleb the
sonne of Iephunneh the Kenezite, and Ioshua the sonne of Nun: for
they haue wholly followed the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lords
anger was kindled against Israel, and hee made them wander in the
wildernesse fourty yeeres, vntill all the generation that had done
euill in the sight of the Lord was consumed.</ab>
<ab n="14">And beholde, ye
are risen vp in your fathers stead, an increase of sinfull men, to
augment yet the fierce anger of the Lord toward Israel.</ab>
<ab n="15">For if yee turne
away from after him, hee will yet againe leaue them in the
wildernesse, and ye shall destroy all this people.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And they
came neere vnto him, and said, Wee will build sheepfoldes here for
our cattell, and cities for our litle ones.</ab>
<ab n="17">But we ourselues
will goe ready armed before the children of Israel, vntill wee haue
brought them vnto their place: and our litle ones shall dwell in
the fenced cities, because of the inhabitants of the land.</ab>
<ab n="18">Wee will not
returne vnto our houses, vntill the children of Israel haue
inherited euery man his inheritance:</ab>
<ab n="19">For wee will not
inherite with them on yonder side Iordane, or forward, because our
inheritance is fallen to vs on this side Iordane Eastward.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ And Moses
said vnto them, If ye will doe this thing, if ye will goe armed
before the Lord to warre,<note> Iosh. 1.13</note></ab>

<fw>Reubens and Gads inheritance.</fw>
<ab n="21">And will goe all
of you armed ouer Iordane before the Lord, vntill he hath driuen
out his enemies from before him,</ab>
<ab n="22">And the land bee
subdued before the Lord: then afterward ye shall returne, and bee
guiltlesse before the Lord, and before Israel; and this land shall
be your possession before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">But if ye will
not doe so, behold, yee haue sinned against the Lord: and bee sure
your sinne will finde you out.</ab>
<ab n="24">Build ye cities
for your litle ones, and folds for your sheepe, and doe that which
hath proceeded out of your mouth.</ab>
<ab n="25">And the children
of Gad, and the children of Reuben spake vnto Moses, saying, Thy
seruants will doe as my lord commandeth.</ab>
<ab n="26">Our little ones,
our wiues, our flocks, and all our cattell shall be there in the
cities of Gilead.</ab>
<ab n="27">But thy seruants
will passe ouer, euery man armed for warre, before the Lord to
battell, as my lord saith.<note> Iosh. 4.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">So concerning
them Moses commaunded Eleazar the Priest, and Ioshua the sonne of
Nun, and the chiefe fathers of the tribes of the children of
Israel:</ab>
<ab n="29">And Moses said
vnto them, If the children of Gad, and the children of Reuben will
passe with you ouer Iordane, euery man armed to battell before the
Lord, and the land shall be subdued before you, then ye shall giue
them the land of Gilead for a possession:</ab>
<ab n="30">But if they will
not passe ouer with you armed, they shall haue possessions among
you in the land of Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="31">And the children
of Gad, and the children of Reuben answered, saying, As the Lord
hath said vnto thy seruants, so will we doe.</ab>
<ab n="32">Wee will passe
ouer armed before the Lord into the land of Canaan, that the
possession of our inheritance on this side Iordane may be
ours.</ab>

<fw>Reubens and Gads inheritance. The remouings of
the Israelites.</fw>
<ab n="33">And Moses gaue
vnto them, euen to the children of Gad, and to the children of
Reuben; and vnto halfe the tribe of Manasseh the sonne of Ioseph,
the kingdome of Sihon King of the Amorites, and the kingdome of Og
King of Bashan, the land with the cities thereof, in the coastes,
euen the cities of the countrey round about.<note> Deut. 3. 12. iosh. 13. 8. and 22 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">¶ And the
children of Gad built Dibon, and Ataroth, and Aroer,</ab>
<ab n="35">And Atroth,
Shophan, and Iaazer, and Iogbehah,</ab>
<ab n="36">And Bethnimrah,
and Bethharan, fenced cities: and foldes for sheepe.</ab>
<ab n="37">And the children
of Reuben built Heshbon, and Elealeh, and Kiriathaim,</ab>
<ab n="38">And Nebo, and
Baalmeon (their names being changed) and Shibmah: and gaue other
names vnto the cities which they builded.<note> Hebr. they called by names the names of the cities.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">And the children
of Machir, the sonne of Manasseh, went to Gilead, and tooke it, and
dispossessed the Amorite which was in it.<note> Gene. 50. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">And Moses gaue
Gilead vnto Machir the sonne of Manasseh, and he dwelt
therein.</ab>
<ab n="41">And Iair the
sonne of Manasseh went and tooke the small townes thereof, and
called them Hauoth-Iair.<note> Deut. 3. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">And Nobah went
and tooke Kenath, and the villages thereof, and called it Nobah,
after his owne name.</ab>



</div>