<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-7-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-7-7b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 The offering of the Princes at the
dedication of the Tabernacle. 10 Their seuerall offrings at the
dedication of the Altar. 89 God speaketh to Moses from the Mercie
seat.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe on the day that Moses had fully set vp the Tabernacle, and
had anointed it, and sanctified it, and all the instruments
thereof, both the Altar, and all the vessels thereof, and had
anointed them, and sanctified them:<note> Exod.40. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">That the Princes
of Israel, heads of the house of their fathers, (who were the
Princes of the tribes, and were ouer them that were numbred)
offered:<note> Heb. who stood.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And they brought
their offering before the Lord, sixe couered wagons, and twelue
oxen: a wagon for two of the Princes, and for each one an oxe, and
they brought them before the Tabernacle.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the Lord spake
vnto Moses, saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Take it of them,
that they may be to doe the seruice of the Tabernacle of the
Congregation, and thou shalt giue them vnto the Leuites, to euery
man according to his seruice.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Moses tooke
the wagons, and the oxen, and gaue them vnto the Leuites.</ab>
<ab n="7">Two wagons and
foure oxen he gaue vnto the sonnes of Gershon, according to their
seruice.</ab>
<ab n="8">And foure wagons
and eight oxen he gaue vnto the sonnes of Merari, according vnto
their seruice, vnder the hand of Ithamar the sonne of Aaron the
Priest.</ab>
<ab n="9">But vnto the
sonnes of Kohath he gaue none: because the seruice of the Sanctuary
belonging vnto them, was that they should beare vpon their
shoulders.</ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And the
Princes offered for dedicating of the Altar, in the day that it was
anointed, euen the Princes offered their offering before the
Altar.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the Lord said
vnto Moses, They shall offer their offering eche Prince on his day,
for the dedicating of the Altar.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And he
that offered his offring the first day, was Nahshon the sonne of
Amminadab, of the tribe of Iudah.</ab>

<fw>The offerings of the Princes.</fw>
<ab n="13">And his offering
was one siluer charger, the weight thereof was an hundred and
thirty shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the
shekel of the Sanctuary; both of them were full of fine flowre
mingled with oile for a meat offering:<note> Leuit.2.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">One spoone of ten
shekels of gold, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="15">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere, for a burnt
offering,</ab>
<ab n="16">One kid of the
goats for a sinne offering:<note> Leuit.4. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goats, fiue lambes of the first yeere: this was the offering of
Nahshon the sonne of Amminadab.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ On the
second day Nethaneel the sonne of Zuar, Prince of Issachar did
offer.</ab>
<ab n="19">He offered for
his offering one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred
and thirtie shekels, one siluer bowle of seuenty shekels, after the
shekel of the Sanctuary, both of them full of fine flowre mingled
with oile, for a meat offering:</ab>
<ab n="20">One spoone of
gold of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="21">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="22">One kid of the
goats for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="23">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goats, fiue lambes of the first yeere: this was the offering of
Nethaneel the sonne of Zuar.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ On the
third day Eliab the sonne of Helon, Prince of the children of
Zebulun did offer.</ab>
<ab n="25">His offering was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuary, both of them full of fine flowre mingled with oile,
for a meat offering:</ab>
<ab n="26">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="27">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="28">One kid of the
goats for a sinne offering:</ab>

<fw>The offerings of the Princes.</fw>
<ab n="29">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goats, fiue lambes of the first yeere: This was the offring of
Eliab the sonne of Helon.</ab>
<ab n="30">¶ On the
fourth day Elizur the sonne of Shedeur, Prince of the children of
Reuben did offer.</ab>
<ab n="31">His offering was
one siluer charger of an hundred and thirty shekels, one siluer
bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of the Sanctuary, both
of them full of fine flowre mingled with oyle, for a meat
offering:</ab>
<ab n="32">One golden spoone
of tenne shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="33">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="34">One kid of the
goats for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="35">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goats, fiue lambs of the first yere: This was the offering of
Elizur the sonne of Shedeur.</ab>
<ab n="36">¶ On the
fifth day Shelumiel the sonne of Zurishaddai Prince of the children
of Simeon, did offer.</ab>
<ab n="37">His offring was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuary, both of them full of fine flowre, mingled with oyle,
for a meate offering:</ab>
<ab n="38">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="39">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="40">One kidde of the
goates for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="41">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goates, fiue lambes of the first yeere: This was the offering of
Shelumiel the sonne of Zurishaddai.</ab>
<ab n="42">¶ On the
sixt day, Eliasaph the sonne of Deuel, Prince of the children of
Gad, offered:</ab>
<ab n="43">His offering was
one siluer charger of the weight of an hundred and thirtie shekels,
a siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of the
Sanctuarie, both of them ful of fine flowre mingled with oyle, for
a meate offering:</ab>
<ab n="44">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>

<fw>The offerings of the Princes.</fw>
<ab n="45">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere, for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="46">One kid of the
goates for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="47">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goates, fiue lambes of the first yeere. This was the offering of
Eliasaph the sonne of Deuel.</ab>
<ab n="48">¶ On the
seuenth day, Elishama the sonne of Ammiud, Prince of the children
of Ephraim offered.</ab>
<ab n="49">His offering was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuarie, both of them full of fine flowre mingled with oile
for a meat offering:</ab>
<ab n="50">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="51">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere, for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="52">One kid of the
goates for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="53">And for a
sacrifice of peace offrings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee goats,
fiue lambes of the first yeere. This was the offering of Elishama
the sonne of Ammiud.</ab>
<ab n="54">¶ On the
eight day offered Gamaliel the sonne of Pedazur, Prince of the
children of Manasseh.</ab>
<ab n="55">His offering was
one siluer charger of an hundred and thirtie shekels, one siluer
bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of the Sanctuary, both
of them full of fine flowre mingled with oile, for a meate
offering:</ab>
<ab n="56">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="57">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere, for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="58">One kid of the
goates for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="59">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goats, fiue lambes of the first yeere. This was the offering of
Gamaliel the sonne of Pedazur.</ab>
<ab n="60">¶ On the
ninth day, Abidan the sonne of Gideoni, prince of the children of
Beniamin offered.</ab>

<fw>The offerings of the Princes.</fw>
<ab n="61">His offering was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, a siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuary, both of them full of fine flowre mingled with oyle,
for a meate offering:</ab>
<ab n="62">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="63">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="64">One kid of the
goats for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="65">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goates, fiue lambes of the first yeere. This was the offering of
Abidan, the sonne of Gideoni.</ab>
<ab n="66">¶ On the
tenth day Ahiezer the sonne of Ammishaddai, Prince of the children
of Dan offered.</ab>
<ab n="67">His offring was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuarie, both of them full of fine flowre mingled with oyle,
for a meate offering:</ab>
<ab n="68">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="69">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere, for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="70">One kid of the
goates for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="71">And for a
sacrifice of peace offerings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee
goats, fiue lambes of the first yeere. This was the offering of
Ahiezer the sonne of Ammishaddai.</ab>
<ab n="72">¶ On the
eleuenth day, Pagiel the sonne of Ocran, Prince of the children of
Asher offered.</ab>
<ab n="73">His offering was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuarie, both of them full of fine flowre mingled with oyle,
for a meat offering:</ab>
<ab n="74">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="75">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="76">One kid of the
goates for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="77">And for a
sacrifice of peace offrings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee goats,
fiue lambs of the first yeere. This was the offering of Pagiel the
sonne of Ocran.</ab>

<fw>Princes offerings.</fw>
<ab n="78">¶ On the
twelfth day, Ahira the sonne of Enan, Prince of the children of
Naphtali, offered.</ab>
<ab n="79">His offering was
one siluer charger, the weight whereof was an hundred and thirtie
shekels, one siluer bowle of seuentie shekels, after the shekel of
the Sanctuary, both of them full of fine flowre mingled with oyle,
for a meate offering:</ab>
<ab n="80">One golden spoone
of ten shekels, full of incense:</ab>
<ab n="81">One yong
bullocke, one ramme, one lambe of the first yeere for a burnt
offering:</ab>
<ab n="82">One kidde of the
goats for a sinne offering:</ab>
<ab n="83">And for a
sacrifice of peace offrings, two oxen, fiue rammes, fiue hee goats,
fiue lambs of the first yeere. This was the offering of Ahira the
sonne of Enan.</ab>
<ab n="84">This was the
dedication of the Altar (in the day when it was annointed) by the
Princes of Israel: twelue chargers of siluer, twelue siluer bowles,
twelue spoones of gold:</ab>
<ab n="85">Each charger of
siluer weighing an hundred and thirtie shekels, each bowle
seuentie: all the siluer vessels weighed two thousand and foure
hundred shekels, after the shekel of the Sanctuary.</ab>
<ab n="86">The golden
spoones were twelue, full of incense, weighing ten shekels a piece,
after the shekel of the Sanctuary: all the gold of the spoones, was
an hundred and twentie shekels.</ab>
<ab n="87">All the oxen for
the burnt offering, were twelue bullocks, the rams twelue, the
lambes of the first yeere twelue, with their meat offering: and the
kids of the goats for sinne offering, twelue.</ab>
<ab n="88">And all the oxen
for the sacrifice of the peace offerings, were twenty and foure
bullocks, the rammes sixtie, the hee goates sixtie, the lambes of
the first yeere sixtie. This was the dedication of the Altar, after
that it was anoynted.</ab>
<ab n="89">And when Moses
was gone into the Tabernacle of the Congregation, to speake with
him, then he heard the voyce of one speaking vnto him, from off the
Mercie seat, that was vpon the Arke of Testimony from betweene the
two Cherubims: and he spake vnto him.<note> i. God.</note></ab>



</div>