<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CNumbers_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Numbers-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 The water of separation made of
the ashes of a red heifer. 11 The law for the vse of it in
purification of the vncleaue.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Lord
spake vnto Moses, and vnto Aaron, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">This is the
ordinance of the Law, which the Lord hath commaunded, saying,
Speake vnto the children of Israel, that they bring thee a red
heifer without spot, wherein is no blemish, and vpon which neuer
came yoke.</ab>
<ab n="3">And ye shall giue
her vnto Eleazar the Priest, that hee may bring her forth without
the campe, and one shall slay her before his face.<note> Hebr.13. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And Eleazar the
Priest shall take of her blood with his finger, and sprinckle of
her blood directly before the Tabernacle of the Congregation seuen
times.<note> Heb.9.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And one shall
burne the heifer in his sight: her skinne, and her flesh, and her
blood, with her doung, shall he burne.<note> Exod.29. 14. leuit.4. 11, 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And the Priest
shall take Cedarwood, and hysope, and scarlet, and cast it into the
midst of the burning of the heifer.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then the Priest
shall wash his clothes, and hee shall bathe his flesh in water, and
afterward he shall come into the campe, and the Priest shalbe
vncleane vntill the euen.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he that
burneth her, shall wash his clothes in water, and bathe his flesh
in water, and shall be vncleane vntill the Euen.</ab>

<fw>Purifications.</fw>
<ab n="9">And a man that is
cleane, shall gather vp the ashes of the heifer, and lay them vp
without the campe in a cleane place, and it shall bee kept for the
Congregation of the children of Israel, for a water of separation:
it is a purification for sinne.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he that
gathereth the ashes of the heifer, shall wash his clothes, and be
vncleane vntil the Euen: and it shall be vnto the children of
Israel, and vnto the stranger that soiourneth among them, for a
statute for euer.</ab>
<ab n="11">¶ He that
toucheth the dead body of any man, shall bee vncleane seuen
dayes.<note> Heb. soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">He shall purifie
himselfe with it on the third day, and on the seuenth day he shall
be cleane: but if he purifie not himselfe the third day, then the
seuenth day he shall not be cleane.</ab>
<ab n="13">Whosoeuer
toucheth the dead bodie of any man that is dead, and purifieth not
himselfe, defileth the Tabernacle of the Lord, and that soule shall
be cut off from Israel, because the water of separation was not
sprinckled vpon him: he shall be vncleane, his vncleannesse is yet
vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="14">This is the law,
when a man dieth in a tent; all that come into the tent, and all
that is in the tent, shalbe vnclean seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">And euery open
vessel which hath no couering bound vpon it, is vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="16">And whosoeuer
toucheth one that is slaine with a sword in the open fields, or a
dead body, or a bone of a man, or a graue, shall be vncleane seuen
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="17">And for an
vncleane person they shall take of the ashes of the burnt heifer of
purification for sinne, and running water shall bee put thereto in
a vessell:<note> Heb. Dust. , Heb. liuing waters shall be giuen.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And a cleane
person shall take hysope, and dippe it in the water, and sprinckle
it vpon the tent, and vpon all the vessels, and vpon the persons
that were there, and vpon him that touched a bone, or one slaine,
or one dead, or a graue.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the cleane
person shal sprinkle vpon the vncleane on the third day, and on the
seuenth day: and on the seuenth day he shall purifie himselfe, and
wash his clothes, and bathe himselfe in water, and shall be cleane
at Euen.</ab>

<fw>Miriam dieth.</fw>
<ab n="20">But the man that
shall bee vncleane, and shall not purifie himselfe, that soule
shall bee cut off from among the Congregation: because he hath
defiled the Sanctuary of the Lord, the water of separation hath not
beene sprinkled vpon him, he is vncleane.</ab>
<ab n="21">And it shall be
a perpetuall statute vnto them, that he that sprinkleth the water
of separation, shall wash his clothes: and he that toucheth the
water of separation, shall be vncleane vntill Euen.</ab>
<ab n="22">And whatsoeuer
the vncleane person toucheth, shall be vncleane: and the soule that
toucheth it, shall bee vncleane vntill Euen.</ab>



</div>