<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPhilippians_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Philippians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Philippians-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>He exhorteth them to vnitie, and to
all humblenesse of minde, by the example of Christs humilitie and
exaltation: 12 To a carefull proceeding in the way of saluation,
that they bee as lights to the wicked world, 16 and comforts to him
their Apostle, who is now ready to bee offered vp to God. 19 He
hopeth to send Timothie to them, whom hee greatly commendeth, 25 as
Epaphroditus also, whom he presently sendeth to them.</head>

<ab n="1">If there bee
therefore any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of loue, if any
fellowship of the Spirit, if any bowels, &amp; mercies;</ab>
<ab n="2">Fulfill ye my
ioy, that yee be like minded, hauing the same loue, being of one
accord, of one minde.</ab>
<ab n="3">Let nothing
bee done through strife, or vaine glory, but in lowlinesse of minde
let each esteeme other better then themselues.</ab>
<ab n="4">Looke not
euery man on his owne things, but euery man also on the things of
others.</ab>
<ab n="5">Let this minde
bee in you, which was also in Christ Iesus:</ab>
<ab n="6">Who being in
the forme of God, thought it not robbery to bee equall with
God:</ab>

<fw>Christ humbled, and exalted.</fw>
<ab n="7">But made
himselfe of no reputation, and tooke vpon him the forme of a
seruant, and was made in the likenesse of men.<note> Or, habite.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And being
found in fashion as a man, he humbled himselfe, and became obedient
vnto death, euen the death of the Crosse.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore God
also hath highly exalted him, and giuen him a Name which is aboue
euery name:</ab>
<ab n="10">That at the
Name of Iesus euery knee should bow, of things in heauen, and
things in earth, and things vnder the earth:</ab>
<ab n="11">And that
euery tongue should confesse, that Iesus Christ is Lord, to the
glory of God the Father.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wherefore, my
beloued, as yee haue alwayes obeyed, not as in my presence onely,
but now much more in my absence; worke out your owne saluation with
feare, and trembling.</ab>
<ab n="13">For it is God
which worketh in you, both to will, and to doe, of his good
pleasure.</ab>
<ab n="14">Doe all
things without murmurings, and disputings:</ab>
<ab n="15">That yee may
bee blamelesse and harmelesse, the sonnes of God, without rebuke,
in the middes of a crooked and peruerse nation, among whom ye shine
as lights in the world:<note> Or, syncere. , Or, shine ye</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Holding
foorth the word of life, that I may reioyce in the day of Christ,
that I haue not runne in vaine, neither laboured in vaine.</ab>
<ab n="17">Yea, and if I
bee offered vpon the sacrifice and seruice of your faith, I ioy,
and reioyce with you all.<note> Gr. powred foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For the same
cause also doe ye ioy, and reioyce with me.</ab>
<ab n="19">But I trust
in the Lord Iesus, to send Timotheus shortly vnto you, that I also
may bee of good comfort, when I know your state.<note> Or, moreouer.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For I haue no
man like minded, who will naturally care for your
state.<note> Or, so deare vnto mee.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For all seeke
their owne, not the things which are Iesus Christs.</ab>
<ab n="22">But ye know
the proofe of him, That as a sonne with the father, hee hath serued
with me, in the Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="23">Him therefore
I hope to send presently, so soone as I shall see how it wil goe
with me.</ab>
<ab n="24">But I trust
in the Lord, that I also my selfe shall come shortly.</ab>

<fw>The Circumcision.</fw>
<ab n="25">Yet I
supposed it necessary, to send to you Epaphroditus my brother and
companion in labour, and fellow souldiour, but your messenger, and
hee that ministred to my wants.</ab>
<ab n="26">For hee
longed after you all, and was full of heauinesse, because that yee
had heard that he had bene sicke.</ab>
<ab n="27">For indeed he
was sicke nigh vnto death, but God had mercy on him: and not on him
onely, but on mee also, lest I should haue sorow vpon
sorow.</ab>
<ab n="28">I sent him
therefore the more carefully, that when ye see him againe, ye may
reioyce, and that I may bee the lesse sorrowfull.</ab>
<ab n="29">Receiue him
therfore in the Lord with all gladnesse, and hold such in
reputation:<note> Or, honor such.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Because for
the worke of Christ he was nigh vnto death, not regarding his life,
to supply your lacke of seruice toward me.</ab>



</div>