<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPhilippians_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Philippians-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Hee warneth them to beware of the
false teachers of the Circumcision, 4 shewing that himself hath
greater cause then they, to trust in the righteousnesse of the Law:
7 which notwithstanding hee counteth as doung and losse, to gaine
Christ and his righteousnesse, 12 therein acknowledging his owne
imperfection. 15 Hee exhorteth them to be thus minded, 17 and to
imitate him, 18 and to decline the waies of carnall
Christians.</head>

<ab n="1">Finally, my
brethren, reioyce in the Lorde. To write the same things to you, to
me indeed is not grieuous: but for you it is safe.</ab>
<ab n="2">Beware of
dogs, beware of euill workers: beware of the concision.</ab>
<ab n="3">For we are the
circumcision, which worship God in the spirit, and reioyce in
Christ Iesus, and haue no confidence in the flesh.</ab>
<ab n="4">Though I might
also haue confidence in the flesh. If any other man thinketh that
hee hath whereof hee might trust in the flesh, I more:</ab>
<ab n="5">Circumcised
the eight day, of the stocke of Israel, of the tribe of Beniamin,
an Hebrew of the Hebrewes, as touching the Law, a Pharise:</ab>
<ab n="6">Concerning
zeale, persecuting the Church: touching the righteousnesse which is
in the Law, blamelesse.</ab>
<ab n="7">But what
things were gaine to me, those I counted losse for Christ.</ab>

<fw>Belly-gods.</fw>
<ab n="8">Yea
doubtlesse, and I count all things but losse, for the excellencie
of the knowledge of Christ Iesus my Lord: for whom I haue suffered
the losse of all things, and doe count them but doung, that I may
win Christ,</ab>
<ab n="9">And be found
in him, not hauing mine owne righteousnesse, which is of the Law,
but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousnesse
which is of God by faith:</ab>
<ab n="10">That I may
know him, and the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of
his sufferings, being made conformable vnto his death,</ab>
<ab n="11">If by any
meanes I might attaine vnto the resurrection of the dead.</ab>
<ab n="12">Not as though
I had already attained, either were already perfect: but I follow
after, if that I may apprehend that for which also I am apprehended
of Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="13">Brethren, I
count not my selfe to haue apprehended: but this one thing I doe,
forgetting those things which are behinde, and reaching forth vnto
those things which are before,</ab>
<ab n="14">I presse
toward the marke, for the price of the high calling of God in
Christ Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="15">Let vs
therefore, as many as bee perfect, bee thus minded: and if in any
thing ye be otherwise minded, God shal reueale euen this vnto
you.</ab>
<ab n="16">Neuerthelesse,
whereto wee haue alreadie attained, let vs walke by the same rule,
let vs minde the same thing.</ab>
<ab n="17">Brethren, be
followers together of me, and marke them which walke so, as ye haue
vs for an ensample.</ab>
<ab n="18">(For many
walke, of whome I haue told you often, and now tell you euen
weeping, that they are the enemies of the crosse of Christ:</ab>
<ab n="19">Whose end is
destruction, whose God is their belly, and whose glorie is in their
shame, who minde earthly things.)</ab>
<ab n="20">For our
conuersation is in heauen, from whence also we looke for the
Sauiour, the Lord Iesus Christ:</ab>
<ab n="21">Who shall
change our vile bodie, that it may bee fashioned like vnto his
glorious body, according to the working whereby he is able euen to
subdue all things vnto himselfe.</ab>




</div>