<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPhilippians_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Philippians-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Philippians-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>3 He testifieth his thankefulnesse
to God, and his loue toward them, for the fruits of their faith and
fellowship, in his sufferings, 9 dayly praying to him for their
increase in grace: 12 Hee sheweth what good the faith of Christ had
receiued by his troubles at Rome, 21 and how ready he is to
glorifie Christ either by his life or death, 27 exhorting them to
vnitie, 28 and to fortitude in persecution.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul and
Timotheus the seruants of Iesus Christ, to all the Saints in Christ
Iesus, which are at Philippi, with the Bishops and Deacons:</ab>
<ab n="2">Grace be vnto
you, and peace, from God our Father, and from the Lord Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="3">I thanke my
God vpon euery remembrance of you,<note> Or, mention.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Alwayes in
euery prayer of mine for you all making request, with ioy</ab>
<ab n="5">For your
felowship in the Gospel from the first day vntill now;</ab>
<ab n="6">Being
confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work
in you, will performe it vntil the day of Iesus Christ:<note> Or, will finish it.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Euen as it is
meete for mee to thinke this of you all, because I haue you in my
heart, in as much as both in my bonds, and in the defence and
confirmation of the Gospel, ye all are partakers of my
grace.<note> Or, you haue me in your heart. , Or, partakers with me of grace.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For God is my
record, how greatly I long after you all, in the bowels of Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="9">And this I
pray, that your loue may abound yet more &amp; more in knowledge,
and in all iudgment.<note> Or, sence.</note></ab>

<fw>His bonds.</fw>
<ab n="10">That ye may
approue things that are excellent, that ye may be sincere, and
without offence till the day of Christ.<note> Or, trie. , Or, differ.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Being filled
with the fruites of righteousnesse, which are by Iesus Christ vnto
the glory and praise of God.</ab>
<ab n="12">But I would
yee should vnderstand brethren, that the things which happened vnto
mee, haue fallen out rather vnto the furtherance of the
Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="13">So that my
bonds in Christ, are manifest in all the palace, and in all other
places.<note> Or. for Christ. , Or, Cæsars Court. , Or, to all others.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And many of
the brethren in the Lord, waxing confident, by my bonds, are much
more bold to speake the word without feare.</ab>
<ab n="15">Some in deed
preach Christ, euen of enuie and strife, and some also of good
will.</ab>
<ab n="16">The one
preach Christ of contention, not syncerely, supposing to adde
affliction to my bonds:</ab>
<ab n="17">But the other
of loue, knowing that I am set for the defence of the
Gospel.</ab>
<ab n="18">What then?
Notwithstanding euery way, whether in pretence, or in trueth:
Christ is preached, and I therein doe reioyce, yea, and will
reioyce.</ab>
<ab n="19">For I know
that this shall turne to my saluation through your prayer, and the
supplie of the spirit of Iesus Christ,</ab>
<ab n="20">According to
my earnest expectation, and my hope, that in nothing I shalbe
ashamed: but that with all boldnes, as alwayes, so now also Christ
shal be magnified in my body, whether it be by life or by
death.</ab>
<ab n="21">For to me to
liue is Christ, and to die is gaine.</ab>
<ab n="22">But if I liue
in the flesh, this is the fruit of my labour: yet what I shal
chuse, I wote not.</ab>
<ab n="23">For I am in a
strait betwixt two, hauing a desire to depart, &amp; to bee with
Christ, which is farre better.</ab>

<fw>Christ humbled, and exalted.</fw>
<ab n="24">Neuertheles,
to abide in the flesh, is more needfull for you.</ab>
<ab n="25">And hauing
this confidence, I know that I shall abide and continue with you
all, for your furtherance and ioy of faith,</ab>
<ab n="26">That your
reioycing may bee more abundant in Iesus Christ for me, by my
comming to you againe.</ab>
<ab n="27">Onely let
your conuersation bee as it becommeth the Gospel of Christ, that
whether I come and see you, or else be absent, I may heare of your
affaires, that yee stand fast in one spirit, with one minde,
striuing together for the faith of the Gospel,</ab>
<ab n="28">And in
nothing terrified by your aduersaries, which is to them an euident
token of perdition: but to you of saluation, and that of
God.</ab>
<ab n="29">For vnto you
it is giuen in the behalfe of Christ, not onely to beleeue on him,
but also to suffer for his sake,</ab>
<ab n="30">Hauing the
same conflict which ye saw in me, and now heare to be in
me.</ab>



</div>