<?xml-model href="../KJV_1611.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPrayer-of-Manasseh_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Bel-and-the-Dragon-Chapter-1-1b-Prayer-of-Manasseh.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>

<fw>Manasses his prayer.</fw>
<ab n="1">[The
prayer of Manasses King of Iuda, when he was holden captiue in
Babylon.] O Lord, Almightie God of our Fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and
Iacob, and of their righteous seed: who hast made heauen and earth,
with all the ornament thereof: who hast bound the Sea by the word
of thy Commandement: who hast shut vp the deepe, and sealed it by
thy terrible and glorious Name, whome all men feare, and tremble
before thy power: for the Maiestie of thy glory cannot bee borne,
and thine angry threatning towards sinners is importable: but thy
mercifull promise is vnmeasurable and vnsearchable: for thou art
the most High Lord, of great compassion, long suffering, very
mercifull, and repentest of the euils of men. Thou, O Lord,
according to thy great goodnesse hast promised repentance, and
forgiuenesse to them that haue sinned against thee: and of thine
infinite mercies hast appointed repentance vnto sinners that they
may be saued. Thou therefore, O Lord, that art the God of the iust,
hast not appointed repentance to the iust, as to Abraham, and
Isaac, and Iacob, which haue not sinned against thee: but thou hast
appointed repentance vnto me that am a sinner: for I haue sinned
aboue the number of the sands of the Sea. My transgressions, O
Lord, are multiplied: my transgressions are multiplied, and I am
not worthy to behold and see the height of heauen, for the
multitude of mine iniquitie. I am bowed downe with many yron bands,
that I cannot lift vp mine head, neither haue any release: For I
haue prouoked thy wrath, and done euill before thee, I did not thy
will, neither kept I thy Commandements: I haue set vp abominations,
and haue multiplied offences. Now therefore I bow the knee of mine
heart, beseeching thee of grace: I haue sinned, O Lord, I haue
sinned and I acknowledge mine iniquities: wherefore I humbly
beseech thee, forgiue me, O Lord, forgiue me, and destroy me not
with mine iniquities. Be not angry with me for euer, by reseruing
euill for me, neither condemne mee into the lower parts of the
earth. For thou art the God, euen the God of them that repent: and
in me thou wilt shew all thy goodnesse: for thou wilt saue me that
am vnworthy, according to thy great mercie. Therefore I will praise
thee for euer all the dayes of my life: for all the powers of the
heauens doe praise thee, and thine is the glory for euer and euer,
Amen.<note> Or, neither take my breath.</note></ab>



</div>
