<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<ab n="1">The kings heart
is in the hand of the Lord, as the riuers of water: hee turneth it
whithersoeuer he will.</ab>
<ab n="2">Euery way of a
man is right in his owne eyes: but the Lord pondereth the
hearts.<note> Chap. 16. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">To doe iustice
and iudgement, is more acceptable to the Lord, then
sacrifice.<note> 1. Sam.15. 22. isa.1.11. hose.6.6. mich. 6.7. chap. 15.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">An high looke,
and a proud heart, and the plowing of the wicked, is
sinne.<note> Chap.6. 17. , Hebr. hautines of eyes. , Or, the light of the wicked.</note></ab>

<fw>Keepe the mouth.</fw>
<ab n="5">The thoughts of
the diligent tend onely to plenteousnes: but of euery one that is
hastie, onely to want.</ab>
<ab n="6">The getting of
treasures by a lying tongue, is a vanitie tossed to and fro of them
that seeke death.<note> Chap. 10. 2. and 13. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The robbery of
the wicked shall destroy them; because they refuse to doe
iudgement.<note> Heb. saw them, or, dwell with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The way of man
is froward and strange: but as for the pure; his worke is
right.</ab>
<ab n="9">It is better to
dwell in a corner of the house top; then with a brawling woman in a
wide house.<note> Chap.25. 19. and 13. 3. and 27. 15. , Heb. a woman of contentions. , Heb. an house of societie.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The soule of
the wicked desireth euill: his neighbour findeth no fauour in his
eyes.<note> Iam.4.5. , Heb. is not fauoured.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">When the
scorner is punished, the simple is made wise: and when the wise is
instructed, he receiueth knowledge.<note> Chap.19. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The righteous
man wisely considereth the house of the wicked: but God
ouerthroweth the wicked for their wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">Whoso stoppeth
his eares at the cry of the poore, hee also shall cry himselfe, but
shall not be heard.<note> Mat.18. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">A gift in
secret pacifieth anger; and a reward in the bosome, strong
wrath.<note> Cha.17. 8. and 18.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">It is ioy to
the iust to doe iudgement: but destruction shalbe to the workers of
iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="16">The man that
wandreth out of the way of vnderstanding, shall remaine in the
congregation of the dead.</ab>
<ab n="17">He that loueth
pleasure, shall be a poore man: hee that loueth wine and oyle,
shall not be rich.<note> Or, sport.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The wicked
shalbe a ransome for the righteous; and the transgressour for the
vpright.<note> Chap. 11. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">It is better to
dwell in the wildernesse, then with a contentious and an angry
woman.<note> Verse 9. , Heb. in the land of the desert.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">There is
treasure to be desired, and oyle in the dwelling of the wise: but a
foolish man spendeth it vp.</ab>
<ab n="21">Hee that
followeth after righteousnesse and mercy, findeth life,
righteousnesse and honour.</ab>
<ab n="22">A wise man
scaleth the citie of the mightie, and casteth downe the strength of
the confidence thereof.<note> Eccles.9. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Whoso keepeth
his mouth and his tongue, keepeth his soule from
troubles.<note> Chap. 12. 13. and 18.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Proud and
haughtie scorner, is his name, who dealeth in proud
wrath.<note> Heb. in the wrath of pride.</note></ab>

<fw>A good name.</fw>
<ab n="25">The desire of
the slouthfull killeth him: for his hands refuse to
labour.<note> Cha.13.4</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Hee coueteth
greedily all the day long: but the righteous giueth and spareth
not.<note> Psal 112.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">The sacrifice
of the wicked is abomination: how much more, when he bringeth it
with a wicked minde?<note> Cha. 15.8. isa 66.3. ier. 6.20. psal. 50.9. amos 5.22. , Heb. in wickednesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">A false
witnesse shall perish: but the man that heareth, speaketh
constantly.<note> Chap.19. 5,9. , Heb. a witnesse of lyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">A wicked man
hardeneth his face: but as for the vpright, he directeth his
way.<note> Or, considereth.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">There is no
wisedome, nor vnderstanding, nor counsell against the
Lord.<note> Ier. 9.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">The horse is
prepared against the day of battell: but safetie is of the
Lord.<note> Psal.33. 17. , Psal.3.9. , Or, victory.</note></ab>



</div>