<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-15-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<ab n="1">Better is a drie
morsell, and quietnesse therewith; then an house full of sacrifices
with strife.<note> Chap. 15. 17. , Or, good cheere.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">A wise seruant
shall haue rule ouer a son that causeth shame: and shall haue part
of the inheritance among the brethren.</ab>

<fw>To hide sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="3">The fining pot
is for siluer, and the furnace for gold: but the Lord trieth the
hearts.<note> Psal. 26. 2. cha. 27.21. iere. 17. 10 mala.3.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">A wicked doer
giueth heed to false lips: and a liar giueth eare to a naughtie
tongue.</ab>
<ab n="5">Whoso mocketh
the poore, reproacheth his maker: and he that is glad at
calamities, shall not be vnpunished.<note> Chap.14. 13. , Heb. held innocent.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Childrens
children are the crowne of old men: and the glory of children are
their fathers.<note> Psal. 127. 4. and 128. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Excellent speech
becommeth not a foole: much lesse doe lying lippes a
prince.<note> Heb. a lip of excellency. , Heb. a lip of lying.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">A gift is as a
precious stone in the eyes of him that hath it: whithersoeuer it
turneth, it prospereth.<note> Chap. 18. 16. , Hebr. a stone of grace.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">He that couereth
a transgression, seeketh loue; but he that repeateth a matter,
separateth very friends.<note> Chap. 10. 12. , Or, procureth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">A reproofe
entreth more into a wise man, then an hundred stripes into a
foole.<note> Or, a reproofe aweth more a wise man, then to strike a foole an hundred times.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">An euill man
seeketh onely rebellion; therefore a cruell messenger shall be sent
against him.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let a beare
robbed of her whelps meet a man, rather then a foole in his
folly.</ab>
<ab n="13">Whoso rewardeth
euill for good, euill shall not depart from his house.<note> Rom. 12. 17. 1.thess. 5. 15. 1.pet.3.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The beginning
of strife is as when one letteth out water: therfore leaue off
contention, before it be medled with.</ab>
<ab n="15">He that
iustifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the iust: euen they
both are abomination to the Lord.<note> Exod. 23. 7 isa. 5.23. chap. 24. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Wherfore is
there a price in the hand of a foole to get wisedome, seeing he
hath no heart to it?</ab>
<ab n="17">A friend loueth
at all times, and a brother is borne for aduersitie.<note> Chap. 18. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">A man void of
vnderstanding striketh hands, and becommeth suretie in the presence
of his friend.<note> Chap. 6. 1. and 11. 15. , Heb. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">He loueth
transgression, that loueth strife: and he that exalteth his gate,
seeketh destruction.</ab>
<ab n="20">He that hath a
froward heart, findeth no good, and he that hath a peruerse tongue,
falleth into mischiefe.<note> Heb. the froward of heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He that
begetteth a foole, doth it to his sorrow: and the father of a foole
hath no ioy.<note> Cha. 10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">A merrie heart
doth good like a medicine: but a broken spirit drieth the
bones.<note> Chap. 15. 13. and 12. 25. , Or, to a medicine.</note></ab>

<fw>Of tale-bearers.</fw>
<ab n="23">A wicked man
taketh a gift out of the bosome, to peruert the wayes of
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wisedome is
before him that hath vnderstanding: but the eyes of a foole are in
the ends of the earth.<note> Eccles.2. 14. and 8.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">A foolish sonne
is a griefe to his father, &amp; bitternes to her that bare
him.<note> Chap. 10. 1. &amp; 15. 20. and 19. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Also to punish
the iust is not good, nor to strike princes for equitie.</ab>
<ab n="27">He that hath
knowledge, spareth his words: and a man of vnderstanding is of an
excellent spirit.<note> Iam. 1. 19. , Or, a coole spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Euen a foole,
when he holdeth his peace, is counted wise: and he that shutteth
his lips, is esteemed a man of vnderstanding.<note> Iob 13. 5.</note></ab>



</div>