<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-15-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<ab n="1">A soft answere
turneth away wrath: but grieuous words stirre vp anger.<note> Chap. 25. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The tongue of
the wise, vseth knowledge aright: but the mouth of fooles, powreth
out foolishnes.<note> Hebr. belcheth or bubbleth. , Verse 28. and chap. 12. 23. and 13.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The eyes of the
Lord are in euery place, beholding the euill &amp; the
good.<note> Iob 34.21, prou. 5. 21. iere. 16. 17. and 32. 19. hebr.4.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">A wholesome
tongue is a tree of life: but peruersnesse therein is a breach in
the spirit.<note> Hebr. the healing of the tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">A foole
despiseth his fathers instruction: but hee that regardeth reproofe,
is prudent.<note> Chap.10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">In the house of
the righteous is much treasure: but in the reuenues of the wicked
is trouble.</ab>
<ab n="7">The lippes of
the wise disperse knowledge: but the heart of the foolish, doeth
not so.</ab>
<ab n="8">The sacrifice of
the wicked is an abomination to the Lord: but the prayer of the
vpright is his delight.<note> Chap.21. 27. amos 3. 22. isa. 1. 11. and 66. 3. iere.6.20. and 7. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The way of the
wicked is an abomination vnto the Lord: but he loueth him that
followeth after righteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="10">Correction is
grieuous vnto him that forsaketh the way: and he that hateth
reproofe, shall die.<note> Or, instruction, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Hell and
destruction are before the Lord: how much more then, the hearts of
the children of men?<note> Iob 26. 6.</note></ab>

<fw>The fooles ioy.</fw>
<ab n="12">A scorner
loueth not one that reproueth him: neither will he goe vnto the
wise.</ab>
<ab n="13">A merry heart
maketh a cheerefull countenance: but by sorrow of the heart, the
spirit is broken.<note> Chap.17. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The heart of
him that hath vnderstanding, seeketh knowledge: but the mouth of
fooles feedeth on foolishnesse.</ab>
<ab n="15">All the dayes
of the afflicted are euill: but he that is of a merry heart, hath a
continuall feast.</ab>
<ab n="16">Better is
little with the feare of the Lord, then great treasure, and trouble
therewith.<note> Psal. 37. 16. 1.tim.6. 6.prou. 16. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Better is a
dinner of herbes where loue is, then a stalled oxe, and hatred
therewith.<note> Chap. 17. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">A wrathfull man
stirreth vp strife: but he that is slow to anger, appeaseth
strife.<note> Chap. 26. 21. and 29. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The way of the
slouthfull man is as an hedge of thornes: but the way of the
righteous is made plaine.<note> Hebr. is raised vp as a causey.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">A wise sonne
maketh a glad father: but a foolish man despiseth his
mother.<note> Chap. 10. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Folly is ioy to
him that is destitute of wisedome: but a man of vnderstanding
walketh vprightly.<note> Chap. 10. 23. , Hebr. voyd of heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Without
counsell, purposes are disappointed: but in the multitude of
counsellours they are established.<note> See Chap. 11.ver.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">A man hath ioy
by the answere of his mouth: and a word spoken in due season, how
good is it?<note> Hebr. in his season.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The way of life
is aboue to the wise, that he may depart from hell
beneath.<note> Phil.3.20. col.3.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The Lord will
destroy the house of the proud: but he will establish the border of
the widow.<note> Chap. 12. 7. and 14. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The thoughts of
the wicked are an abomination to the Lord: but the wordes of the
pure, are pleasant words.<note> Chap. 6. 18. , Heb. words of pleasantnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Hee that is
greedy of gaine, troubleth his owne house: but he that hateth
gifts, shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="28">The heart of
the righteous studieth to answere: but the mouth of the wicked,
powreth out euil things.</ab>
<ab n="29">The Lord is
farre from the wicked: but hee heareth the prayer of the
righteous.<note> Psal. 34. 16. and 145. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The light of
the eyes reioyceth the heart: and a good report maketh the bones
fat.</ab>

<fw>A iust weight.</fw>
<ab n="31">The eare that
heareth the reproofe of life, abideth among the wise.</ab>
<ab n="32">He that
refuseth instruction, despiseth his owne soule: but he that heareth
reproofe, getteth vnderstanding.<note> Or, correction. , Or, obeyeth. , Heb. possesseth an heart</note></ab>
<ab n="33">The feare of
the Lord is the instruction of wisedome; and before honour is
humilitie.<note> Chap.18. 12</note></ab>



</div>