<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<ab n="1">Euery wise woman
buildeth her house; but the foolish plucketh it downe with her
hands.</ab>
<ab n="2">He that walketh
in his vprightnesse, feareth the Lord: but he that is peruerse in
his wayes, despiseth him.<note> Iob.12. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">In the mouth of
the foolish is a rod of pride: but the lippes of the wise shall
preserue them.</ab>
<ab n="4">Where no Oxen
are, the crib is cleane: but much increase is by the strength of
the Oxe.</ab>
<ab n="5">A faithfull
witnesse will not lye: but a false witnesse will vtter
lyes.<note> Exod.20. 16. &amp; 23. 1. chap.6. 19. &amp;12.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">A scorner
seeketh wisedome, and findeth it not: but knowledge is easie vnto
him that vnderstandeth.<note> Chap.8.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Goe from the
presence of a foolish man, when thou perceiuest not in him the
lippes of knowledge.</ab>

<fw>Rash anger.</fw>
<ab n="8">The wisedome of
the prudent is to vnderstand his way: but the folly of fooles is
deceit.</ab>
<ab n="9">Fooles make a
mocke at sinne: but among the righteous there is
fauour.<note> Chap. 10. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The heart
knoweth his owne bitternesse; and a stranger doth not intermeddle
with his ioy.<note> Heb. the bitternesse of his soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The house of
the wicked shall bee ouerthrowen: but the tabernacle of the vpright
shall flourish.</ab>
<ab n="12">There is a way
which seemeth right vnto a man: but the end thereof are the wayes
of death.<note> Chap.16. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Euen in
laughter the heart is sorrowfull; and the end of that mirth is
heauinesse.</ab>
<ab n="14">The backslider
in heart shall be filled with his owne wayes: and a good man shall
be satisfied from himselfe.<note> Chap.1. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The simple
beleeueth euery word: but the prudent man looketh well to his
going.</ab>
<ab n="16">A wise man
feareth, and departeth from euill: but the foole rageth, and is
confident.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hee that is
soone angry, dealeth foolishly: and a man of wicked deuices is
hated.</ab>
<ab n="18">The simple
inherite folly: but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="19">The euill bowe
before the good: and the wicked at the gates of the
righteous.</ab>
<ab n="20">The poore is
hated euen of his owne neighbour: but the rich hath many
friends.<note> Chap.19. 7. , Heb. many are the louers of the rich.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He that
despiseth his neighbour, sinneth: but he that hath mercy on the
poore, happy is he.<note> Psal. 112. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Doe they not
erre that deuise euil? but mercy and trueth shall be to them that
deuise good.</ab>
<ab n="23">In all labour
there is profit: but the talke of the lippes tendeth onely to
penury.</ab>
<ab n="24">The crowne of
the wise is their riches: but the foolishnesse of fooles is
folly.</ab>
<ab n="25">A true witnesse
deliuereth soules: but a deceitfull witnesse speaketh
lyes.<note> Ver. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">In the feare of
the Lord is strong confidence: and his children shall haue a place
of refuge.</ab>
<ab n="27">The feare of
the Lord, is a fountaine of life, to depart from the snares of
death.<note> Chap.13. 14.</note></ab>

<fw>The wickeds sacrifice.</fw>
<ab n="28">In the
multitude of people is the kings honour: but in the want of people
is the destruction of the prince.</ab>
<ab n="29">Hee that is
slow to wrath, is of great vnderstanding: but hee that is hasty of
spirit, exalteth folly.<note> Hebr. short of spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">A sound heart,
is the life of the flesh: but enuie, the rottennesse of the
bones.</ab>
<ab n="31">Hee that
oppresseth the poore, reprocheth his Maker: but hee that honoureth
him, hath mercy on the poore.<note> Chap. 17. 5. matt. 25. 40.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">The wicked is
driuen away in his wickednes: but the righteous hath hope in his
death.</ab>
<ab n="33">Wisedome
resteth in the heart of him that hath vnderstanding: but that which
is in the midst of fooles, is made knowen.</ab>
<ab n="34">Righteousnes
exalteth a nation: but sinne is a reproch to any
people.<note> Hebr. to nations.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">The Kings
fauour is toward a wise seruant: but his wrath, is against him that
causeth shame.</ab>



</div>