<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>From this Chapter to the fiue and
twentieth, are sundry obseruations of morall vertues, and their
contrary vices.</head>

<ab n="1">The Prouerbes of
Solomon: A wise sonne maketh a glad father: but a foolish sonne is
the heauinesse of his mother.<note> Chap. 15. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Treasures of
wickednesse profit nothing: but righteousnes deliuereth from
death.<note> Chap. 11. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The Lord will
not suffer the soule of the righteous to famish: but he casteth
away the substance of the wicked.<note> Psal.37. 25. , Or, the wicked for their wickednesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Hee becommeth
poore that dealeth with a slacke hand: but the hand of the
diligent, maketh rich.<note> Chap. 12. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Hee that
gathereth in Summer, is a wise sonne: but hee that sleepeth in
haruest, is a sonne that causeth shame.</ab>
<ab n="6">Blessings are
vpon the head of the iust: but violence couereth the mouth of the
wicked.<note> Verse 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The memorie of
the iust is blessed: but the name of the wicked shall
rot.<note> Psal. 112. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The wise in
heart will receiue commaundements: but a prating foole shall
fall.<note> Hebr. a foole of lips. , Or, shalbe beaten.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">He that walketh
vprightly, walketh surely: but he that peruerteth his wayes, shalbe
knowen.<note> Psal. 23.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee that
winketh with the eye, causeth sorrow: but a prating foole shall
fall.<note> Cha.6.13. , Or, shalbe beaten.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The mouth of a
righteous man is a well of life: but violence couereth the mouth of
the wicked.<note> Chap. 13. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Hatred stirreth
vp strifes: but loue couereth all sinnes.<note> 1.Pet.4.8. 1.cor.13.4.</note></ab>

<fw>The good tongue.</fw>
<ab n="13">In the lips of
him that hath vnderstanding, wisedome is found: but a rod is for
the backe of him that is voyd of vnderstanding.<note> Hebr. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Wise men lay vp
knowledge: but the mouth of the foolish is neere
destruction.</ab>
<ab n="15">The rich mans
wealth is his strong citie: the destruction of the poore is their
pouertie.<note> Chap. 18. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The labour of
the righteous tendeth to life: the fruite of the wicked to
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="17">He is in the
way of life that keepeth instruction: but hee that refuseth
reproofe, erreth.<note> Or, causeth to erre.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Hee that hideth
hatred with lying lippes, and he that vttereth a slander, is a
foole.</ab>
<ab n="19">In the
multitude of words there wanteth not sinne: but he that refraineth
his lippes, is wise.</ab>
<ab n="20">The tongue of
the iust is as choise siluer: the heart of the wicked is little
worth.</ab>
<ab n="21">The lippes of
the righteous feed many: but fooles die for want of
wisedome.<note> Hebr. of heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The blessing of
the Lord, it maketh rich, and hee addeth no sorrow with it.</ab>
<ab n="23">It is as a
sport to a foole to doe mischiefe: but a man of vnderstanding hath
wisedome.<note> Chap. 14. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">The feare of
the wicked, it shall come vpon him: but the desire of the righteous
shalbe granted.</ab>
<ab n="25">As the
whirlewinde passeth, so is the wicked no more: but the righteous is
an euerlasting foundation.</ab>
<ab n="26">As vineger to
the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to them
that send him.</ab>
<ab n="27">The feare of
the Lord prolongeth dayes: but the yeeres of the wicked shalbe
shortened.<note> Chap.9. 11. , Hebr. addeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">The hope of the
righteous shall bee gladnesse: but the expectation of the wicked
shall perish.<note> Iob 8. 13. and 11. 20. psal.112. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The way of the
Lord is strength to the vpright: but destruction shall bee to the
workers of iniquitie.</ab>
<ab n="30">The righteous
shall neuer bee remooued: but the wicked shall not inhabite the
earth.<note> Psal.125. 1. and 37. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">The mouth of
the iust bringeth foorth wisedome: but the froward tongue shalbe
cut out.</ab>
<ab n="32">The lips of the
righteous know what is acceptable: but the mouth of the wicked
speaketh frowardnesse.<note> Hebr. frowardnesses.</note></ab>



</div>