<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-149-150-Proverbs.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 The vse of the Prouerbes. 7 An
exhortation to feare God and beleeue his word. 10 To auoyd the
intisings of sinners. 20 Wisdome complaineth of her contempt. 24
She threatneth her contemners.</head>

<ab n="1">The Prouerbes of
Solomon the sonne of Dauid, King of Israel,</ab>
<ab n="2">To knowe wisedome
and instruction, to perceiue the words of vnderstanding,</ab>
<ab n="3">To receiue the
instruction of wisdome, iustice, and iudgement &amp;
equitie,<note> Hebr. equities.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">To giue subtiltie
to the simple, to the yong man knowledge and
discretion.<note> Or, aduisement.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">A wise man wil
heare, and wil increase learning: and a man of vnderstanding shall
attaine vnto wise counsels:</ab>
<ab n="6">To vnderstand a
prouerbe, and the interpretation; the wordes of the wise, and their
darke sayings.<note> Or, an eloquent speach.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ The feare
of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge: but fooles despise
wisedome and instruction.<note> Iob 28.28. psal. 111. 10. prou.9. 10. , Or, the principall part.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">My sonne, heare
the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy
mother.</ab>
<ab n="9">For they shall be
an ornament of grace vnto thy head, and chaines about thy
necke.<note> Hebr. an adding.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ My sonne,
if sinners entise thee, consent thou not.</ab>
<ab n="11">If they say,
Come with vs, let vs lay wait for blood, let vs lurke priuily for
the innocent without cause:</ab>
<ab n="12">Let vs swallow
them vp aliue, as the graue, and whole, as those that goe downe
into the pit:</ab>
<ab n="13">Wee shall finde
all precious substance, wee shall fill our houses with
spoile:</ab>
<ab n="14">Cast in thy lot
among vs, let vs all haue one purse:</ab>
<ab n="15">My sonne, walke
not thou in the way with them; refraine thy foot from their
path:</ab>
<ab n="16">For their feete
runne to euil, and make haste to shed blood.<note> Isa.59.7. rom.3. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Surely in vaine
the net is spread in the sight of any bird.<note> Hebr. in the eyes of euery thing that hath a wing.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And they lay
wait for their owne blood, they lurke priuily for their owne
liues.</ab>
<ab n="19">So are the waies
of euery one that is greedie of gaine: which taketh away the life
of the owners thereof.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ Wisedome
crieth without, she vttereth her voice in the streets:<note> Hebr. wisedomes, that is, excellent wisedome. , Prou.8. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Shee crieth in
the chiefe place of concourse, in the openings of the gates: in the
city she vttereth her words, saying,</ab>
<ab n="22">How long, ye
simple ones, will ye loue simplicitie? and the scorners delight in
their scorning, and fooles hate knowledge?</ab>

<fw>Reward of fooles.</fw>
<ab n="23">Turne you at my
reproofe: behold, I will powre out my spirit vnto you, I will make
knowen my wordes vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Because I
haue called, and yee refused, I haue stretched out my hand, and no
man regarded:<note> Isa.65.12. and 66.4. ier.7.13. ezech.8.18</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But ye haue set
at nought all my counsell, &amp; would none of my reproofe:</ab>
<ab n="26">I also will
laugh at your calamitie, I wil mocke when your feare
commeth.</ab>
<ab n="27">When your feare
commeth as desolation, and your destruction commeth as a
whirlewinde; when distresse and anguish commeth vpon
you:<note> Iob.27. 9 isa. 1. 15. ier.11.11. &amp; 14. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Then shall they
call vpon mee, but I will not answere; they shall seeke me early,
but they shall not finde me:<note> Micah.3.4</note></ab>
<ab n="29">For that they
hated knowledge, and did not choose the feare of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="30">They would none
of my counsel: they despised all my reproofe.</ab>
<ab n="31">Therefore shall
they eate of the fruite of their owne way, and be filled with their
owne deuices.</ab>
<ab n="32">For the turning
away of the simple shall slay them, and the prosperity of fooles
shall destroy them.<note> Or, ease of the simple.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">But who so
hearkneth vnto mee, shall dwell safely, and shall be quiet from
feare of euill.</ab>



</div>