<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_24" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-23-24.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIV.</head>
<ab n="1">Be not thou
enuious against euill men, neither desire to be with
them.<note> Chap. 23.17. and 24.19. psal. 37.1. &amp;c. and 73.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For their heart
studieth destruction, and their lippes talke of
mischiefe.<note> Psal.10.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Through wisedome
is an house builded, and by vnderstanding it is
established.</ab>
<ab n="4">And by knowledge
shall the chambers bee filled with all precious and pleasant
riches.</ab>
<ab n="5">A wise man is
strong, yea a man of knowledge encreaseth strength.<note> Heb. is in strength. , Heb. strengtheneth might.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For by wise
counsell thou shalt make thy warre: and in multitude of counsellers
there is safetie.<note> Chap. 20. 18. and 11. 14. and 15. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Wisedome is too
high for a foole: he openeth not his mouth in the gate.</ab>
<ab n="8">He that deuiseth
to doe euill, shall be called a mischieuous person.</ab>
<ab n="9">The thought of
foolishnesse is sinne: and the scorner is an abomination to
men.</ab>
<ab n="10">If thou faint
in the day of aduersitie, thy strength is small:<note> Heb. narrow.</note></ab>

<fw>The iust falleth.</fw>
<ab n="11">If thou
forbeare to deliuer them that are drawen vnto death, and those that
are ready to be slaine:<note> Psal. 82.4</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If thou sayest,
Behold, we knew it not: doth not he that pondereth the heart,
consider it? and he that keepeth thy soule, doth not he know it?
and shall not hee render to euery man according to his
workes?<note> Iob.34. 11. psal.62. 12. ier.32. 19. rom.2. 6. apoc.22. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">My sonne, eate
thou honie, because it is good, and the honie combe, which is
sweete to thy taste.<note> Psal.19. 9. &amp; 119. 103. , Heb. vpon thy palate.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">So shall the
knowledge of wisedome be vnto thy soule: when thou hast found it,
then there shall be a reward, and thy expectation shall not be cut
off.<note> Chap.23. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Lay not waite,
(O wicked man) against the dwelling of the righteous: spoile not
his resting place.</ab>
<ab n="16">For a iust man
falleth seuen times, and riseth vp againe: but the wicked shall
fall into mischiefe.<note> Psal.34. 18. and 37. 24. iob.5. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Reioyce not
when thine enemie falleth: and let not thine heart be glad when he
stumbleth:<note> Psal.35. 15.chap.17 5. iob.31. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Lest the Lord
see it, and it displease him, and hee turne away his wrath from
him.<note> Heb. it be euill in his eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Fret not thy
selfe because of euill men; neither be thou enuious at the
wicked.<note> Psal. 37.1. chap.23. 17. , Or, keepe not company with the wicked.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For there shall
be no reward to the euill man: the candle of the wicked shall be
put out.<note> Chap.13. 9. iob.21.17 , Or, lampe.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">My sonne, feare
thou the Lord, and the king: and medle not with them that are giuen
to change.<note> Heb. changers.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For their
calamity shall rise suddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them
both?</ab>
<ab n="23">These things
also belong to the wise: It is not good to haue respect of persons
in iudgement.<note> Leuit. 19. 15.chap.18. 5. and 28. 21. deut.1. 17. and 16. 19. ioh. 7. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">He that sayth
vnto the wicked, Thou art righteous, him shall the people curse;
nations shall abhorre him:<note> Chap.17. 15. isa.5.23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But to them
that rebuke him shall be delight, and a good blessing shall come
vpon them.<note> Heb. a blessing of good.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Euery man shall
kisse his lippes that giueth a right answere.<note> Heb. that answereth right words.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Prepare thy
worke without, and make it fit for thy selfe in the field; and
afterwards build thine house.</ab>
<ab n="28">Be not a
witnesse against thy neighbour without cause: and deceiue not with
thy lippes.</ab>

<fw>Of slouthfulnesse.</fw>
<ab n="29">Say not, I will
doe so to him as he hath done to mee: I will render to the man
according to his worke.<note> Chap.20. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">I went by the
field of the slouthfull, and by the vineyard of the man voyd of
vnderstanding:</ab>
<ab n="31">And loe, it was
all growen ouer with thornes, and nettles had couered the face
thereof, and the stone wall therof was broken downe:</ab>
<ab n="32">Then I saw, and
considered it well, I looked vpon it, and receiued
instruction.<note> Hebr. set my heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Yet a little
sleepe, a little slumber, a little folding of the handes to
sleepe:<note> Chap.6. 9. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">So shall thy
pouertie come, as one that traueileth, and thy want, as an armed
man.<note> Hebr. a man of shield.</note></ab>



</div>