<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 Isaac is borne. 4 He is
circumcised. 6 Sarahs ioy. 9 Hagar &amp; Ishmael are cast forth. 15
Hagar in distresse. 17 The Angel comforteth her. 22 Abimelechs
couenant with Abraham at Beer-sheba.</head>

<ab n="1">And the LORD
visited Sarah as he had said, and the LORD did vnto Sarah as he had
spoken.<note> Chap.17. 19. and 18. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For Sarah
conceiued, and bare Abraham a sonne in his old age, at the set
time, of which God had spoken to him.<note> Acts 7 8. Gal.4.22. Heb.11.11</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And Abraham
called the name of his sonne, that was borne vnto him, whom Sarah
bare to him, Isaac.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Abraham
circumcised his sonne Isaac, being eight dayes old, as God had
commanded him.<note> Chap.17. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And Abraham was
an hundred yeeres old, when his sonne Isaac was borne vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And Sarah
said, God hath made me to laugh, so that all that heare, will laugh
with me.</ab>
<ab n="7">And she said, Who
would haue said vnto Abraham, that Sarah should haue giuen children
sucke? for I haue borne him a sonne in his old age.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the child
grew, and was weaned: and Abraham made a great feast, the same day
that Isaac was weaned.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Sarah
saw the sonne of Hagar the Egyptian, which shee had borne vnto
Abraham, mocking.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wherfore she
said vnto Abraham, Cast out this bond woman, and her sonne: for the
sonne of this bond woman shall not be heire with my sonne, euen
with Isaac.<note> Gal.4.30</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And the thing
was very grieuous in Abrahams sight, because of his sonne.</ab>

<fw>Hagar comforted.</fw>
<ab n="12">¶ And God
said vnto Abraham, Let it not be grieuous in thy sight, because of
the lad, and because of thy bond woman. In all that Sarah hath said
vnto thee, hearken vnto her voice: for in Isaac shall thy seed be
called.</ab>
<ab n="13">And also, of the
sonne of the bond woman will I make a nation, because he is thy
seed.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Abraham rose
vp earely in the morning, and tooke bread, and a bottle of water,
and gaue it vnto Hagar, (putting it on her shoulder,) and the
child, and sent her away: and shee departed, and wandered in the
wildernesse of Beer-sheba.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the water
was spent in the bottle, and shee cast the child vnder one of the
shrubs.</ab>
<ab n="16">And she went,
and sate her downe ouer against him, a good way off, as it were a
bow shoot: for she said, Let me not see the death of the child. And
shee sate ouer against him, and lift vp her voice, and
wept.</ab>
<ab n="17">And God heard
the voice of the lad, and the Angel of God called to Hagar out of
heauen, and said vnto her, What aileth thee, Hagar? feare not: for
God hath heard the voice of the ladde, where he is.</ab>
<ab n="18">Arise, lift vp
the lad, and hold him in thine hand: for I will make him a great
nation.</ab>
<ab n="19">And God opened
her eyes, and she saw a well of water, and shee went, and filled
the bottle with water, and gaue the lad drinke.</ab>
<ab n="20">And God was with
the lad, and he grew, and dwelt in the wildernesse, and became an
archer.</ab>
<ab n="21">And hee dwelt in
the wildernesse of Paran: and his mother tooke him a wife out of
the land of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="22">¶ And it
came to passe at that time, that Abimelech and Phichol the chiefe
captaine of his hoste spake vnto Abraham, saying, God is with thee
in all that thou doest.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now therefore
sweare vnto mee here by God, that thou wilt not deale falsly with
me, nor with my sonne, nor with my sonnes sonne: but according to
the kindnesse that I haue done vnto thee, thou shalt doe vnto me,
and to the land wherein thou hast soiourned.<note> Hebrew, if thou shalt lie vnto me.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Abraham
saide, I will sweare.</ab>
<ab n="25">And Abraham
reproued Abimelech, because of a well of water, which Abimelechs
seruants had violently taken away.</ab>

<fw>Abraham is tempted.</fw>
<ab n="26">And Abimelech
saide, I wote not who hath done this thing: neither didst thou tell
me, neither yet heard I of it, but to day.</ab>
<ab n="27">And Abraham
tooke sheepe and oxen, and gaue them vnto Abimelech: and both of
them made a couenant.</ab>
<ab n="28">And Abraham set
seuen ewe lambes of the flocke by themselues.</ab>
<ab n="29">And Abimelech
said vnto Abraham, What meane these seuen ewe lambes, which thou
hast set by themselues?</ab>
<ab n="30">And he said, For
these seuen ewe lambs shalt thou take of my hand, that they may be
a witnesse vnto me, that I haue digged this well.</ab>
<ab n="31">Wherefore he
called that place, Beer-sheba: because there they sware both of
them.<note> That is, The well of the othe.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Thus they made a
couenant at Beeer-sheba: then Abimelech rose vp, and Phichol the
chiefe captaine of his hoste, and they returned into the land of
the Philistines.</ab>
<ab n="33">¶ And
Abraham planted a groue in Beer-sheba, and called there on the Name
of the LORD, the euerlasting God.<note> Or, Tree.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">And Abraham
soiourned in the Philistines land, many dayes.</ab>



</div>