<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-15-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<ab n="1">The preparations
of the heart in man, and the answere of the tongue, is from the
Lord.<note> Vers.9. and chap. 19.21. and 20.24. ier. 10.23. , Or. disposings.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">All the wayes of
a man are cleane in his owne eyes: but the Lord weigheth the
spirits.<note> Cha.21.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Commit thy
workes vnto the Lord, and thy thoughts shalbe
established.<note> Psal. 37. 5. and 55. 23. mat. 6. 25. luke 12. 22. 1.pet.5.4. , Heb. rolle.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The Lord hath
made all things for himselfe: yea, euen the wicked for the day of
euill.<note> Iob 21.30.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Euery one that
is proud in heart, is an abomination to the Lord: though hand ioyne
in hand, he shall not be vnpunished.<note> Chap.6.7. and 8.13. , Heb. helde innocent.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">By mercy and
trueth iniquitie is purged: and by the feare of the Lord, men
depart from euill.</ab>
<ab n="7">When a mans
wayes please the Lord, he maketh euen his enemies to be at peace
with him.</ab>
<ab n="8">Better is a
little with righteousnesse, then great reuenewes without
right.<note> Psal. 37. 16. chap. 15. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">A mans heart
deuiseth his way: but the Lord directeth his steps.<note> Vers. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">A diuine
sentence is in the lips of the king: his mouth transgresseth not in
iudgement.<note> Heb. diuination.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">A iust weight
and ballance are the Lords: all the weights of the bagge are his
worke.<note> Leuit. 19. 36. chap. 11. 1. , Heb. all the stones.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">It is an
abomination to kings to commit wickednesse: for the throne is
established by righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">Righteous lips
are the delight of kings: and they loue him that speaketh
right.</ab>
<ab n="14">The wrath of a
king is as messengers of death: but a wise man will pacifie
it.</ab>
<ab n="15">In the light of
the kings countenance is life, and his fauour is as a cloude of the
latter raine.<note> Chap. 19. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">How much better
is it to get wisedome, then gold? and to get vnderstanding, rather
to be chosen then siluer?<note> Cha.8.11.</note></ab>

<fw>Slow to anger.</fw>
<ab n="17">The high way of
the vpright is to depart from euill: hee that keepeth his way,
preserueth his soule.</ab>
<ab n="18">Pride goeth
before destruction: and an hautie spirit before a fall.<note> Cha. 11. 2. and 18.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Better it is to
be of an humble spirit with the lowly, then to diuide the spoile
with the proud.</ab>
<ab n="20">He that
handleth a matter wisely, shall finde good: and who so trusteth in
the Lord, happy is hee.<note> Or, he that vnderstandeth a matter. , Psal.2.12. and 34.9. and 125.1. isa. 30. 18. iere.17.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The wise in
heart shall be called prudent; and the sweetnesse of the lips
increaseth learning.</ab>
<ab n="22">Understanding
is a well-spring of life vnto him that hath it: but the instruction
of fooles is folly.<note> Chap. 13. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">The heart of
the wise teacheth his mouth, and addeth learning to his
lippes.<note> Heb. maketh wise.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Pleasant words
are as an honycombe, sweete to the soule, and health to the
bones.</ab>
<ab n="25">There is a way
that seemeth right vnto a man; but the end thereof are the wayes of
death.<note> Chap.14. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Hee that
laboureth, laboureth for himselfe; for his mouth craueth it of
him.<note> Heb. the soule of him that laboureth. , Heb. boweth vnto him.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">An vngodly man
diggeth vp euill: and in his lips there is as a burning
fire.<note> Heb. a man of Belial.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">A froward man
soweth strife; &amp; a whisperer separateth chiefe
friends.<note> Chap.6. 14,19. and 15. 18. and 26. 21. and 29. 22. , Heb. sendeth foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">A violent man
enticeth his neighbour, and leadeth him into the way that is not
good.</ab>
<ab n="30">He shutteth his
eyes to deuise froward things: moouing his lips he bringeth euill
to passe.</ab>
<ab n="31">The hoary head
is a crowne of glory, if it be found in the way of
righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="32">He that is slow
to anger, is better then the mighty: and he that ruleth his spirit,
then he that taketh a citie.</ab>
<ab n="33">The lot is cast
into the lap: but the whole disposing thereof is of the
Lord.</ab>



</div>