<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_29" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-28-29.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXIX.</head>
<head>1 Obseruations of publike
gouernement, 15 And of priuate. 22 Of anger, pride, the euery,
cowardize, and corruption.</head>

<ab n="1">He that being
often reproued, hardeneth his necke, shal suddenly be destroied,
and that without remedy.<note> Heb. a man of reproofes.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">When the
righteous are in authoritie, the people reioyce: but when the
wicked beareth rule, the people mourne.<note> Chap. 11. 10. and 28. 28. eccles. 10.5. , Or, increased.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Whoso loueth
wisedome, reioyceth his father: but hee that keepeth company with
harlots, spendeth his substance.<note> Chap. 10. 1. and 15. 20. and 27. 11. , Luk.15. 13.chap. 5. 9. and 28.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The king by
iudgement stablisheth the land: but he that receiueth gifts,
ouerthroweth it.<note> Heb. a man of oblations.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">A man that
flattereth his neighbour, spreadeth a net for his feet.</ab>
<ab n="6">In the
transgression of an euill man there is a snare: but the righteous
doth sing and reioyce.</ab>
<ab n="7">The righteous
considereth the cause of the poore: but the wicked regardeth not to
know it.<note> Iob 29. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Scornefull men
bring a citie into a snare: but wise men turne away
wrath.<note> Or, set a citie on fire.</note></ab>

<fw>Correct children.</fw>
<ab n="9">If a wise man
contendeth with a foolish man, whether hee rage or laugh, there is
no rest.</ab>
<ab n="10">The
bloodthirstie hate the vpright: but the iust seeke his
soule.<note> Heb. men of blood.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">A foole
vttereth all his mind: but a wise man keepeth it in till
afterwards.</ab>
<ab n="12">If a ruler
hearken to lies, all his seruants are wicked.</ab>
<ab n="13">The poore and
the deceitful man meet together: the Lord lightneth both their
eyes.<note> Cha.22.2. , Or, the vsurer.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The King that
faithfully iudgeth the poore, his throne shall be established for
euer.<note> Chap. 20. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The rod and
reproofe giue wisedome: but a child left to himselfe bringeth his
mother to shame.<note> See ver. 17 , Chap. 10. 1. and 17.21 and 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">When the wicked
are multiplied, transgression increaseth: but the righteous shall
see their fall.<note> Psal. 37. 36. and 58 11. and 91.8</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Correct thy
sonne, and hee shall giue thee rest: yea he shall giue delight vnto
thy soule.<note> Chap. 13. 24. and 22. 15. and 23. 13, 14</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Where there is
no vision, the people perish: but he that keepeth the Law, happy is
he.<note> Or, is made naked.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">A seruant will
not be corrected by words: for though hee vnderstand, hee will not
answere.</ab>
<ab n="20">Seest thou a
man that is hasty in his words? there is more hope of a foole then
of him.<note> Or, in his matters.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">He that
delicately bringeth vp his seruant from a child, shall haue him
become his sonne at the length.</ab>
<ab n="22">An angry man
stirreth vp strife, and a furious man aboundeth in
transgression.<note> Chap.15. 18. &amp; 26.21</note></ab>
<ab n="23">A mans pride
shall bring him lowe: but honour shall vpholde the humble in
spirit.<note> Chap. 15. 33. and 18. 12. iob 22.29. luk.14. 11. mat. 23. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Who so is
partner with a thiefe, hateth his owne soule: hee heareth cursing,
and bewrayeth it not.</ab>
<ab n="25">The feare of
man bringeth a snare: but who so putteth his trust in the Lord,
shall be safe.<note> Heb. shalbe set on high.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Many seeke the
rulers fauour, but euery mans iudgement commeth from the
Lord.<note> Cha. 19.6 , Hebr. the face of a ruler.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">An vniust man
is an abomination to the iust: and he that is vpright in the way,
is abomination to the wicked.</ab>



</div>