<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-24-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-25-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Obseruations about Kings, 8 and
about auoyding causes of quarrels, and sundry causes
thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">These are also
Prouerbes of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Iudah
copied out.</ab>
<ab n="2">It is the glory
of God to conceale a thing: but the honour of Kings is to search
out a matter.</ab>
<ab n="3">The heauen for
height, and the earth for depth, and the heart of Kings is
vnsearchable.<note> Heb. there is no searching.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Take away the
drosse from the siluer, and there shall come foorth a vessell for
the finer.</ab>
<ab n="5">Take away the
wicked from before the king, and his throne shalbe established in
righteousnes.<note> Chap. 20. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Put not forth
thy selfe in the presence of the king, and stand not in the place
of great men.<note> Hebr. set not out thy glory.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For better it is
that it be said vnto thee, Come vp hither; then that thou shouldest
be put lower in the presence of the Prince whom thine eies haue
seene.<note> Luke 14. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Goe not forth
hastily to striue, lest thou know not what to doe in the ende
thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to shame.</ab>
<ab n="9">Debate thy cause
with thy neighbour himselfe; and discouer not a secret to
another:<note> Matth. 5. 25. and 18. 15. , Or, discouer not the secret of another.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Lest he that
heareth it, put thee to shame, and thine infamie turne not
away.</ab>
<ab n="11">A word fitly
spoken is like apples of gold in pictures of siluer.<note> Heb. spoken vpon his wheeles.</note></ab>

<fw>A shrewd wife.</fw>
<ab n="12">As an eare-ring
of gold, and an ornament of fine gold, so is a wise reprouer vpon
an obedient eare.</ab>
<ab n="13">As the cold of
snow in the time of haruest, so is a faithfull messenger to them
that send him: for hee refresheth the soule of his
masters.<note> Chap. 13. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Who so boasteth
himselfe of a false gift, is like cloudes and winde without
raine.<note> Hebr. in a gift of falshood.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">By long
forbearing is a Prince perswaded, and a soft tongue breaketh the
bone.<note> Chap. 15. 1. gene.32. 4. and 16. 14. 1.sam. 25.24.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Hast thou found
hony? eate so much as is sufficient for thee: lest thou be filled
therewith, and vomit it.</ab>
<ab n="17">Withdraw thy
foote from thy neighbours house: lest he be weary of thee, and so
hate thee.<note> Or, let thy foote be seldome in thy neighbours house. , Hebr. full of thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">A man that
beareth false witnes against his neighbour, is a maule, and a
sword, and a sharpe arrow.<note> Psal. 120. 4. chap. 12. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Confidence in
an vnfaithfull man in time of trouble, is like a broken tooth, and
a foot out of ioynt.</ab>
<ab n="20">As hee that
taketh away a garment in cold weather; and as vineger vpon nitre;
so is he that singeth songs to an heauy heart.</ab>
<ab n="21">If thine enemie
be hungry, giue him bread to eate: and if hee be thirstie, giue him
water to drinke.<note> Exod.23. 4. rom.12. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For thou shalt
heape coales of fire vpon his head, and the Lord shall reward
thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">The North winde
driueth away raine: so doeth an angrie countenance a backbiting
tongue.<note> Or, The Northwinde bringeth foorth raine, so doeth a backbiting tongue, an angry countenance.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">It is better to
dwell in a corner of the house top, then with a brawling woman, and
in a wide house.<note> Chap. 21. 9. and 19. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">As cold waters
to a thirstie soule: so is good newes from a farre
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="26">A righteous man
falling downe before the wicked, is as a troubled fountaine, aud a
corrupt spring.</ab>
<ab n="27">It is not good
to eat much hony: so for men to search their owne glory, is not
glory.</ab>
<ab n="28">Hee that hath
no rule ouer his owne spirit, is like a citie that is broken downe,
and without walles.<note> Chap. 16. 32.</note></ab>



</div>