<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-31-31.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 Lemuels lesson of chastitie and
temperance. 6 The afflicted are to be comforted and defended. 10
The praise and properties of a good wife.</head>

<ab n="1">The wordes of
King Lemuel, the prophecie that his mother taught him.</ab>
<ab n="2">What, my sonne!
and what, the sonne of my wombe! and what, the sonne of my
vowes!</ab>
<ab n="3">Giue not thy
strength vnto women, nor thy wayes to that which destroyeth
kings.</ab>
<ab n="4">It is not for
kings, O Lemuel, it is not for kings to drinke wine, nor for
Princes, strong drinke:</ab>
<ab n="5">Lest they
drinke, and forget the Law, and peruert the iudgement of any of the
afflicted.<note> Hebr. alter. , Hebr. of all the sonnes of affliction.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Giue strong
drinke vnto him that is ready to perish, and wine vnto those that
be of heauie hearts.<note> Psal. 104. 15. , Hebr. bitter of soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Let him drinke,
and forget his pouertie, and remember his misery no more.</ab>
<ab n="8">Open thy mouth
for the dumbe in the cause of all such as are appointed to
destruction.<note> Hebr. the sonnes of destruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Open thy mouth,
iudge righteously, and plead the cause of the poore and
needy.<note> Leuit. 19. 15. deut. 1. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ Who can
finde a vertuous woman? for her price is farre aboue
Rubies.<note> Chap. 12. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The heart of
her husband doeth safely trust in her, so that he shall haue no
need of spoile.</ab>
<ab n="12">She will doe
him good, and not euill, all the dayes of her life.</ab>
<ab n="13">She seeketh
wooll and flaxe, and worketh willingly with her hands.</ab>
<ab n="14">She is like the
merchants ships, she bringeth her food from afarre.</ab>

<fw>The description of a good
woman.</fw>
<ab n="15">Shee riseth
also while it is yet night, and giueth meate to her household, and
a portion to her maydens.</ab>
<ab n="16">She considereth
a field, and buyeth it: with the fruit of her handes she planteth a
Uineyard.<note> Hebr. taketh.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">She girdeth her
loynes with strength, and strengtheneth her armes.</ab>
<ab n="18">She perceiueth
that her merchandise is good; her candle goeth not out by
night.<note> Hebr. she tasteth.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">She layeth her
handes to the spindle, and her handes hold the distaffe.</ab>
<ab n="20">She stretcheth
out her hand to the poore, yea she reacheth foorth her handes to
the needy.<note> Hebr she spreadeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">She is not
afraid of the snow for her houshold: for all her houshold are
cloathed with scarlet.<note> Or, double garments.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">She maketh
herselfe couerings of tapestrie; her cloathing is silke and
purple.</ab>
<ab n="23">Her husband is
knowen in the gates, when he sitteth among the Elders of the
land.</ab>
<ab n="24">She maketh fine
linnen, and selleth it, and deliuereth girdles vnto the
merchant.</ab>
<ab n="25">Strength and
honour are her cloathing; and she shall reioyce in time to
come.</ab>
<ab n="26">She openeth her
mouth with wisedome; and in her tongue is the law of
kindnesse.</ab>
<ab n="27">She looketh
well to the wayes of her housholde, and eateth not the bread of
idlenesse.</ab>
<ab n="28">Her children
arise vp, and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praiseth
her.</ab>
<ab n="29">Many daughters
haue done vertuously, but thou excellest them all.<note> Or, haue gotten riches.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Fauour is
deceitfull, and beautie is vaine: but a woman that feareth the
Lord, she shalbe praised.</ab>
<ab n="31">Giue her of the
fruit of her hands, and let her owne workes praise her in the
gates.</ab>



</div>