<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<ab n="1">Better is the
poore that walketh in his integrity, then he that is peruerse in
his lippes, and is a foole.<note> Chap.28.6</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Also, that the
soule be without knowledge, it is not good, and hee that hasteth
with his feete, sinneth.</ab>
<ab n="3">The foolishnesse
of man peruerteth his way: and his heart fretteth against the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">Wealth maketh
many friends: but the poore is separated from his
neighbour.<note> Chap. 14. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">A false witnesse
shall not be vnpunished: and he that speaketh lyes, shal not
escape.<note> Exod. 23. 1. deut. 19. 16. prou. 6. 9. and 21. 28. , Heb. held innocent.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Many will
entreate the fauour of the Prince: and euery man is a friend to him
that giueth gifts.<note> Heb. a man of gifts.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">All the brethren
of the poore doe hate him: howe much more doe his friends goe farre
from him? Hee pursueth them with words, yet they are wanting to
him.<note> Chap. 14. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He that getteth
wisedome loueth his owne soule: he that keepeth vnderstanding shall
find good.<note> Heb. an heart.</note></ab>

<fw>The kings wrath.</fw>
<ab n="9">A false witnesse
shall not be vnpunished, and hee that speaketh lyes, shall
perish.<note> Ver.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Delight is not
seemely for a foole: much lesse for a seruant to haue rule ouer
princes.<note> Eccle. 10. 6. prou. 30. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The discretion
of a man deferreth his anger: and it is his glory to passe ouer a
transgression.<note> Chap. 14. 29. , Or, prudence.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The kings wrath
is as the roaring of a lyon: but his fauour is as dewe vpon the
grasse.<note> Chap.16. 15. and 20. 2. &amp; 28. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">A foolish sonne
is the calamity of his father; and the contentions of a wife are a
continuall dropping.<note> Chap. 10. 1. &amp; 15.20. and 17 21. &amp; 25. and chap. 21.9. , Chap. 27.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">House and
riches, are the inheritance of fathers; and a prudent wife is from
the Lord.<note> Chap.18. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Slouthfulnesse
casteth into a deep sleepe: and an idle soule shall suffer
hunger.<note> Chap. 10. 4. and 20. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">He that keepeth
the commandement, keepeth his owne soule: but hee that despiseth
his wayes, shall die.<note> Luc.11. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Hee that hath
pity vpon the poore, lendeth vnto the Lord; and that which he hath
giuen, will he pay him againe.<note> Mat. 10. 42. and 25. 40. 2.cor. 9.6. and 7. , Or, his deed.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Chasten thy
sonne while there is hope; and let not thy soule spare for his
crying.<note> Chap. 13. 24. &amp; 23. 13. , Or, to his destruction: or, to cause him to die.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">A man of great
wrath shall suffer punishment: for if thou deliuer him, yet thou
must doe it againe.<note> Heb. add.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Heare counsell,
and receiue instruction, that thou mayest be wise in thy latter
end.</ab>
<ab n="21">There are many
deuices in a mans heart: neuerthelesse the counsell of the Lord,
that shall stand.<note> Iob.23.13 psal.33.10, 11. prou. 16 1. and 9. isa. 46.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The desire of a
man is his kindnesse: and a poore man is better then a
lyar.</ab>
<ab n="23">The feare of
the Lord tendeth to life, and he that hath it shall abide
satisfied: he shall not be visited with euill.</ab>
<ab n="24">A slouthfull
man hideth his hand in his bosome, and wil not so much as bring it
to his mouth againe.<note> Chap.15. 19. &amp; 26.13. and 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Smite a
scorner, and the simple will beware; and reprooue one that hath
vnderstanding, and he will vnderstand knowledge.<note> Chap.21. 11. , Heb. will be cunning.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He that wasteth
his father, and chaseth away his mother, is a sonne that causeth
shame, and bringeth reproch.</ab>

<fw>None is cleane.</fw>
<ab n="27">Cease, my
sonne, to heare the instruction, that causeth to erre from the
words of knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="28">An vngodly
witnesse scorneth iudgement: and the mouth of the wicked deuoureth
iniquitie.<note> Hebr. A witnesse of Belial.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Iudgements are
prepared for scorners, and stripes for the backe of fooles.</ab>



</div>