<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<ab n="1">Wine is a
mocker, strong drinke is raging: and whosoeuer is deceiued thereby,
is not wise.</ab>
<ab n="2">The feare of a
king, is as the roaring of a Lion: who so prouoketh him to anger,
sinneth against his owne soule.<note> Chap.19. 12. and 16. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">It is an honour
for a man to cease from strife: but euery foole will be
medling.</ab>
<ab n="4">The sluggard
will not plow by reason of the cold; therefore shall he begge in
haruest, and haue nothing.<note> Chap. 20. 4. , Or, winter.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Counsell in the
heart of man is like deepe water: but a man of vnderstanding will
draw it out.<note> Chap. 18.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Most men will
proclaime euery one his owne goodnes: but a faithfull man who can
finde?<note> Or, bountie.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The iust man
walketh in his integritie: his children are blessed after
him.<note> Psal.112. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">A king that
sitteth in the throne of iudgement, scattereth away all euill with
his eyes.</ab>
<ab n="9">Who can say, I
haue made my heart cleane, I am pure from my sinne?<note> Psal.51.5. iob 14.4. 1.king.8. 46. 2.chro. 6.36. eccles. 7.28. 1.ioh. 1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Diuers weights,
and diuers measures, both of them are alike abomination to the
Lord.<note> Deut. 25. 15. chap.11. 1. and .16.2. , Hebr. a stone, and a stone. , Hebr. an ephah, and an ephah.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Euen a childe
is knowen by his doings, whether his worke be pure, and whether it
be right.</ab>
<ab n="12">The hearing
eare, and the seeing eye, the Lord hath made euen both of
them.<note> Exod.4. 11. psal. 94. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Loue not
sleepe, lest thou come to pouertie: open thine eyes, and thou shalt
be satisfied with bread.<note> Chap. 19. 15. and 12. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">It is nought,
it is nought (saith the buyer:) but when he is gone his way, then
he boasteth.</ab>
<ab n="15">There is gold,
and a multitude of Rubies: but the lips of knowledge are a precious
iewell.</ab>
<ab n="16">Take his
garment that is suerty for a stranger: and take a pledge of him for
a strange woman.<note> Chap. 27. 13.</note></ab>

<fw>False ballance.</fw>
<ab n="17">Bread of deceit
is sweet to a man: but afterwards his mouth shall be filled with
grauell.<note> Cha.9.17. , Heb. bread of lying, or falshood.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Euery purpose
is established by counsell: and with good aduice make
warre.<note> Chap. 15. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">He that goeth
about as a tale-bearer, reueileth secrets; therefore meddle not
with him that flattereth with his lippes.<note> Chap. 11. 13. , Or, entiseth.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Who so curseth
his father or his mother, his lampe shall be put out in obscure
darkenesse.<note> Exod.21. 17. leuit.20. 9. matt.15. 4. , Or, candle.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">An inheritance
may be gotten hastily at the beginning: but the ende thereof shall
not be blessed.</ab>
<ab n="22">Say not thou, I
will recompence euil: but wait on the Lord, and he shall saue
thee.<note> Deut.32. 35. cha.17. 13. and 24. 29. rom.12. 17. 1. thess. 5.15. 1.pet. 3.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Diuers waights
are an abomination vnto the Lord: and a false ballance is not
good.<note> Verse 10. , Hebr. ballances of deceit.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Mans goings are
of the Lord; how can a man then vnderstand his owne
way?<note> Psal. 37. 23. cha. 16. 9. iere.10. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">It is a snare
to the man who deuoureth that which is holy: and after vowes, to
make inquirie.</ab>
<ab n="26">A wise king
scattereth the wicked, &amp; bringeth the wheele ouer
them.<note> Verse 8. psal.101.5. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">The spirit of
man is the candle of the Lord, searching all the inward parts of
the belly.<note> Or, lampe.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Mercy and
trueth preserue the king: and his throne is vpholden by
mercy.<note> Psal. 101. 1. chap. 29. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">The glory of
yong men is their strength: and the beautie of old men is the gray
head.<note> Chap.16. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The blewnes of
a wound cleanseth away euill: so doe stripes the inward parts of
the belly.<note> Hebr. is a purging medicine against euill.</note></ab>



</div>