<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-22-23.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<ab n="1">A Good name is
rather to be chosen then great riches, and louing fauour rather
then siluer &amp; golde.<note> Eccles.7.2 , Or, fauour is better then, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The rich and
poore meet together: the Lord is the maker of them all.<note> Chap. 29. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">A prudent man
foreseeth the euill, and hideth himselfe: but the simple passe on,
and are punished.<note> Chap.27. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">By humilitie and
the feare of the Lord, are riches, and honour, and
life.<note> Psal. 112. 13. , Or, the reward of humilitie, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thornes and
snares are in the way of the froward: he that doeth keepe his
soule, shalbe farre from them.</ab>
<ab n="6">Traine vp a
childe in the way he should goe: and when he is olde, hee will not
depart from it.<note> Or, catechize. , Heb. in his way.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The rich ruleth
ouer the poore, and the borrower is seruant to the
lender.<note> Heb. to the man that lendeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Hee that soweth
iniquitie, shall reape vanitie: and the rodde of his anger shall
faile.<note> Iob 4.8. hos.10.13. , Or, and with the rod of his anger he shalbe consumed.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Hee that hath a
bountifull eye, shall bee blessed: for hee giueth of his bread to
the poore.<note> 2.Cor.9.6 , Heb. good of eye.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Cast out the
scorner, and contention shall goe out; yea strife, and reproch
shall cease.<note> Psal.101.6</note></ab>
<ab n="11">He that loueth
purenesse of heart, for the grace of his lips the king shall be his
friend.<note> Or, and hath grace in his lips.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The eyes of the
Lord preserue knowledge, and he ouerthroweth the words of the
transgressour.<note> Or, the matters.</note></ab>

<fw>Of oppression.</fw>
<ab n="13">The slothfull
man sayth, There is a lyon without, I shall be slaine in the
streetes.<note> Chap. 26. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The mouth of
strange women is a deepe pit: he that is abhorred of the Lord shall
fall therein.<note> Chap. 2. 16. and 23. 27. and 5.3. and 7.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Foolishnesse is
bound in the heart of a child: but the rod of correction shal driue
it farre from him.<note> Chap. 13. 24. and 19. 18. and 23. 13. and 29. 15, 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Hee that
oppresseth the poore to increase his riches, and he that giueth to
the rich, shall surely come to want.</ab>
<ab n="17">Bow downe thine
eare, and heare the words of the wise, and apply thine heart vnto
my knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="18">For it is a
pleasant thing, if thou keepe them within thee; they shall withall
be fitted in thy lippes.<note> Heb. in thy belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">That thy trust
may bee in the Lord, I haue made knowen to thee this day, euen to
thee.<note> Or, trust thou also.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Haue not I
written to thee excellent things in counsailes and
knowledge:</ab>
<ab n="21">That I might
make thee knowe the certainty of the words of truth; that thou
mightest answere the words of trueth to them that send vnto
thee?<note> Or, to those that send thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Rob not the
poore because he is poore, neither oppresse the afflicted in the
gate.<note> Zach.7.10</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For the Lord
will plead their cause, and spoile the soule of those that spoiled
them.<note> Chap. 23. 11. iob.31. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Make no
friendship with an angrie man: and with a furious man thou shalt
not goe;</ab>
<ab n="25">Lest thou
learne his wayes, and get a snare to thy soule.</ab>
<ab n="26">Be not thou one
of them that strike hands, or of them that are sureties for
debts.<note> Chap.6.1. and 11. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">If thou hast
nothing to pay, why should he take away thy bed from vnder
thee?</ab>
<ab n="28">Remoue not the
ancient land marke, which thy fathers haue set.<note> Chap. 13. 10. deut. 19 14. &amp; 27.7. , Or, bound.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Seest thou a
man diligent in his businesse? hee shall stand before kings, he
shall not stand before meane men.<note> Heb. obscure men.</note></ab>



</div>