<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-30-30.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 Agurs confession of his faith. 7
The two points of his prayer. 10 The meanest are not to bee
wronged. 11 Foure wicked generations. 15 Foure things insatiable.
17 Parents are not to bee despised. 18 Foure things hard to be
knowen, 21 Foure things vntollerable. 24 Foure things exceeding
wise. 29 Foure things stately. 32 Wrath is to bee
preuented.</head>


<fw>Gods word pure.</fw>
<ab n="1">The words of
Agur the sonne of Iakeh, euen the prophecy: The man spake vnto
Ithiel, euen vnto Ithiel and Ucal.</ab>
<ab n="2">Surely I am more
brutish then any man, and haue not the vnderstanding of a
man.</ab>
<ab n="3">I neither
learned wisedome, nor haue the knowledge of the holy.<note> Heb. know.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Who hath
ascended vp into heauen, or descended? who hath gathered the wind
in his fists? who hath bound the waters in a garment? who hath
established all the ends of the earth? what is his name, and what
is his sonnes name, if thou canst tell?<note> Iohn. 3. 13. iob.38. 4. psal.104.3 isa. 40.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Euery word of
God is pure: he is a shield vnto them that put their trust in
him.<note> Psal.12.7. and 18. 32. &amp; 19. 8. &amp; 119.140. , Heb. purified.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Adde thou not
vnto his words, lest he reproue thee, and thou be found a
lyar.<note> Deut.4.2. and 12. 32. apoc.21.19</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Two things haue
I required of thee, deny me them not before I die.<note> Heb. withhold not from me.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Remoue farre
from mee vanity, and lyes; giue me neither pouerty, nor riches,
feede me with food conuenient for me.<note> Mat.6. 11. , Heb. of my allowance.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Lest I be full,
and deny thee, and say, Who is the Lord? or lest I be poore, and
steale, and take the name of my God in vaine.<note> Deut. 32. 15. , Heb. belye thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Accuse not a
seruant vnto his master; lest he curse thee, and thou be found
guilty.<note> Heb. hurt not with thy tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">There is a
generation that curseth their father, and doth not blesse their
mother.</ab>
<ab n="12">There is a
generation that are pure in their owne eyes, and yet is not washed
from their filthinesse.</ab>
<ab n="13">There is a
generation, O howe lofty are their eyes! and their eye-lids are
lifted vp.<note> Chap.6. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">There is a
generation, whose teeth are as swords, and their iaw-teeth as
kniues, to deuoure the poore from off the earth, and the needy from
among men.<note> Psal.52. 3. and 57.5. iob. 29.17.</note></ab>

<fw>Things vnsatiable.</fw>
<ab n="15">The horse-leach
hath two daughters, crying, Giue, giue. There are three things that
are neuer satisfied, yea foure things say not, It is
enough:<note> Heb. wealth.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The graue; and
the barren wombe; the earth that is not filled with water; and the
fire that saith not, It is enough.</ab>
<ab n="17">The eye that
mocketh at his father, and despiseth to obey his mother; the rauens
of the valley shall picke it out, and the young Eagles shall eate
it.<note> Or, the brooke.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">There be three
things which are too wonderfull for me; yea foure, which I know
not:</ab>
<ab n="19">The way of an
Eagle in the ayre; the way of a serpent vpon a rocke; the the way
of a ship in the midst of the sea; and the way of a man with a
maid.<note> Heb. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Such is the way
of an adulterous woman: she eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and
saith, I haue done no wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="21">For three
things the earth is disquieted, and for foure which it cannot
beare:</ab>
<ab n="22">For a seruant
when he reigneth, and a foole when hee is filled with
meate:<note> Chap. 19. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For an odious
woman when shee is married, and an handmayd that is heire to her
mistresse.</ab>
<ab n="24">There be foure
things which are little vpon the earth; but they are exceeding
wise:<note> Heb. wise made wise.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">The Ants are a
people not strong, yet they prepare their meate in the
summer.<note> Chap.6.7</note></ab>
<ab n="26">The conies are
but a feeble folke, yet make they their houses in the rocks</ab>
<ab n="27">The locustes
haue no king, yet goe they forth all of them by bands.<note> Heb. gathered together.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">The spider
taketh hold with her hands, and is in kings palaces.</ab>
<ab n="29">There be three
things which goe well, yea foure are comely in going:</ab>
<ab n="30">A lyon which is
strongest among beastes, and turneth not away for any:</ab>
<ab n="31">A gray-hound;
an hee-goate also; and a king, against whom there is no rising
vp.<note> Or, horse. Heb. girt in the loynes.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">If thou hast
done foolishly in lifting vp thy selfe, or if thou hast thought
euill, lay thine hand vpon thy mouth.<note> Iob.21.5. and 39. 37. &amp;c. and 40. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Surely the
churning of milke bringeth forth butter; and the wringing of the
nose bringeth forth blood: so the forcing of wrath bringeth forth
strife.</ab>



</div>