<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_26" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-25-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXVI.</head>
<head>1 Obseruations about fooles, 13
about sluggards, 17 and about contentious
busie-bodies.</head>


<fw>Busie-bodies.</fw>
<ab n="1">As snow in
summer, and as raine in haruest: so honour is not seemely for a
foole.</ab>
<ab n="2">As the bird by
wandring, as the swallow by flying: so the curse causelesse shall
not come.</ab>
<ab n="3">A whip for the
horse, a bridle for the asse; and a rod for the fooles
backe.<note> Chap. 10. 13. psal. 32.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Answere not a
foole according to his folly, lest thou also be like vnto
him.</ab>
<ab n="5">Answere a foole
according to his folly, lest hee be wise in his owne
conceit.<note> Heb. his owne eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He that sendeth
a message by the hand of a foole, cutteth off the feete, and
drinketh dammage.<note> Or, violence.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The legges of
the lame are not equall: so is a parable in the mouth of
fooles.<note> Heb. are lifted vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">As hee that
bindeth a stone in a sling; so is hee that giueth honour to a
foole.<note> Or, as he that putteth a pretious stone in an heape of stones.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">As a thorne
goeth vp into the hand of a drunkard; so is a parable in the mouth
of fooles.</ab>
<ab n="10">The great God
that formed all things, both rewardeth the foole, and rewardeth
transgressours.<note> Or, a great man grieueth all, and hee hireth the foole, he hireth also transgressors.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">As a dogge
returneth to his vomite: so a foole returneth to his
folly.<note> 2.Pet.2. 22. , Heb. iterateth his folly.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Seest thou a
man wise in his owne conceit? there is more hope of a foole then of
him.</ab>
<ab n="13">The slothfull
man sayth, There is a lion in the way, a lion is in the
streets.<note> Chap. 22. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">As the doore
turneth vpon his hinges: so doeth the slothfull vpon his
bedde.</ab>
<ab n="15">The slothfull
hideth his hand in his bosome, it grieueth him to bring it againe
to his mouth.<note> Chap.19. 24. , Or he is weary.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The sluggard is
wiser in his owne conceit, then seuen men that can render a
reason.</ab>
<ab n="17">He that passeth
by, and medleth with strife belonging not to him, is like one that
taketh a dog by the eares.<note> Or, is enraged.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">As a mad man,
who casteth firebrands, arrowes, and death:<note> Heb. flames or sparkes.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">So is the man
that deceiueth his neighbour, &amp; sayth, Am not I in
sport?</ab>
<ab n="20">Where no wood
is, there the fire goeth out: so where there is no tale-bearer, the
strife ceaseth.<note> Heb. without wood. , Chap. 22. 10. , Or, whisperer. , Heb. is silent.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">As coales are
to burning coales, and wood to fire; so is a contentious man to
kindle strife.<note> Chap.15. 18. &amp; 29.22.</note></ab>

<fw>Of selfe-loue.</fw>
<ab n="22">The words of a
tale-bearer are as woundes, and they goe downe into the innermost
parts of the belly.<note> Cha.18.8 , Heb. chambers.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Burning lips,
and a wicked heart, are like a potsheard couered with siluer
drosse.</ab>
<ab n="24">Hee that
hateth, dissembleth with his lips, and layeth vp deceit within
him.<note> Or, is knowen.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">When he
speaketh faire, beleeue him not: for there are seuen abominations
in his heart.<note> Heb. maketh his voice gracious.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Whose hatred is
couered by deceit, his wickednesse shall be shewed before the whole
congregation.<note> Or, hatred is couered in secret.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Whoso diggeth a
pit, shall fall therein: and he that rolleth a stone, it will
returne vpon him.<note> Eccles.10. 5. psal.17. 16. &amp; 9.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">A lying tongue
hateth those that are afflicted by it, and a flattering mouth
worketh ruine.</ab>



</div>