<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation to obedience, 5 to
faith, 7 to mortification, 9 to deuotion, 11 to patience. 13 The
happy gaine of wisedome. 19 The power, 21 and the benefits of
wisedome. 27 An exhortation to charitablenesse, 30 peaceablenesse,
31 and contentednesse. 33 The cursed state of the
wicked.</head>

<ab n="1">My sonne, forget
not my lawe; but let thine heart keepe my
commaundements:<note> Deut.8.1. &amp; 30. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For length of
dayes, and long life, and peace shall they adde to
thee.<note> Heb. yeeres of life.</note></ab>

<fw>Wisdomes praise.</fw>
<ab n="3">Let not mercy and
trueth forsake thee: bind them about thy necke, write them vpon the
table of thine heart.<note> Exod. 13. 9 deut. 6.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">So shalt thou
find fauour, and good vnderstanding in the sight of God, and
man.<note> Psal. 111. 10. , Or, good successe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Trust in
the Lord with all thine heart; and leaue not vnto thine owne
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="6">In all thy wayes
acknowledge him, and he shall direct thy pathes.<note> 1.Chron. 28.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Be not
wise in thine owne eyes: feare the Lord, and depart from
euill.<note> Rom. 12. 16</note></ab>
<ab n="8">It shalbe health
to thy nauill, and marrow to thy bones.<note> Hebr. medicine. , Hebr. watring, or moystning.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Honour the Lord
with thy substance, and with the first fruits of all thine
increase.<note> Exod. 23. 19. and 34. 36. deut. 26.2 &amp;c. mala. 3. 10. &amp;c. luke 14. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">So shall thy
barnes be filled with plenty, and thy presses shall burst out with
new wine.<note> Deut. 28. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">¶ My sonne,
despise not the chastening of the Lord: neither be weary of his
correction.<note> Iob 5. 17 hebr. 12. 5. apoc. 3. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For whom the
Lord loueth, he correcteth, euen as a father the sonne, in whom he
delighteth.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ Happy is
the man that findeth wisedome, and the man that getteth
vnderstanding.<note> Hebr. the man that draweth out vnderstanding.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the
merchandise of it is better then the merchandise of siluer, and the
gaine thereof, then fine gold.<note> Iob 28. 15. &amp;c. psal. 19. 10. pro. 8. vers. 11. and 19 and 16. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">She is more
precious then Rubies: and all the things thou canst desire, are not
to be compared vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="16">Length of dayes
is in her right hand: and in her left hand, riches and
honour.</ab>
<ab n="17">Her wayes are
wayes of plesantnesse: and all her pathes are peace.</ab>
<ab n="18">She is a tree of
life, to them that lay hold vpon her: and happy is euery one that
retaineth her.</ab>
<ab n="19">The Lord by
wisedome hath founded the earth; by vnderstanding hath he
established the heauens.<note> Or, prepared</note></ab>
<ab n="20">By his knowledge
the depthes are broken vp; and the cloudes droppe downe the
dew.</ab>
<ab n="21">¶ My sonne,
let not them depart from thine eyes: keepe sound wisedome and
discretion.</ab>
<ab n="22">So shall they
bee life vnto thy soule, and grace to thy necke.</ab>
<ab n="23">Then shalt thou
walke in thy way safely, &amp; thy foot shall not
stumble.<note> Psal. 37. 24. and 91. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids care.</fw>
<ab n="24">When thou lyest
downe, thou shalt not be afraide: yea, thou shalt lye downe, and
thy sleepe shalbe sweet.</ab>
<ab n="25">Be not afraid of
sudden feare, neither of the desolation of the wicked, when it
commeth.</ab>
<ab n="26">For the Lord
shalbe thy confidence, and shall keepe thy foote from being
taken.</ab>
<ab n="27">¶ Withhold
not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of
thine hand to doe it.<note> Hebr. the owners therof.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Say not vnto thy
neighbour, Goe, and come againe, and to morrow I will giue, when
thou hast it by thee.</ab>
<ab n="29">Deuise not euil
against thy neighbour, seeing hee dwelleth securely by
thee.<note> Or, practise no euill.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">¶ Striue
not with a man without cause, if hee haue done thee no
harme.</ab>
<ab n="31">¶ Enuie
thou not the oppressour, and choose none of his wayes.<note> Psal. 37 1. , Hebr. a man of violence.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For the froward
is abomination to the Lord: but his secret is with the
righteous.<note> Psal.25. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">¶ The curse
of the Lord is in the house of the wicked: but he blesseth the
habitation of the iust.<note> Mala. 2.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Surely he
scorneth the scorners: but he giueth grace vnto the
lowly.<note> Iam. 4.6. 1.pet.5. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">The wise shall
inherite glory, but shame shalbe the promotion of
fooles.<note> Hebr. exalteth the fooles.</note></ab>



</div>