<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Solomon perswadeth to a sincere
and kind familiaritie with wisedome. 6 In an example of his owne
experience, he sheweth 10 the cunning of an whore, 22 And the
desperate simplicitie of a yong wanton. 24 Hee dehorteth from such
wickednesse.</head>

<ab n="1">My sonne, keepe
my words, and lay vp my commaundements with thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">Keepe my
commandements, and liue: and my law as the apple of thine
eye.<note> Deut.6.8. &amp; 11.18. chap.3. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Bind them vpon
thy fingers, write them vpon the table of thine heart.</ab>
<ab n="4">Say vnto
Wisedome, Thou art my sister, and call Understanding thy kinse
woman,</ab>
<ab n="5">That they may
keepe thee from the strange woman, from the stranger which
flattereth with her words.<note> Chap.5.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ For at the
windowe of my house I looked through my casement,</ab>
<ab n="7">And behelde among
the simple ones, I discerned among the youths, a yong man void of
vnderstanding,<note> Heb. the sonnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Passing through
the streete neere her corner, and he went the way to her
house,</ab>
<ab n="9">In the twilight
in the euening, in the blacke and darke night:<note> Heb. in the euening of the day.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And behold,
there met him a woman, with the attire of an harlot, and subtill of
heart.</ab>
<ab n="11">(She is loud and
stubburne, her feet abide not in her house:<note> Chap.9.13</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Now is shee
without, now in the streetes, and lieth in waite at euery
corner.)</ab>
<ab n="13">So she caught
him, and kissed him, and with an impudent face, said vnto
him,<note> Heb. shee strengthened her face and sayd.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I haue peace
offerings with me: this day haue I paid my vowes.<note> Heb. peace offerings are vpon me.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Therefore came I
forth to meete thee, diligently to seeke thy face, and I haue found
thee.</ab>
<ab n="16">I haue deckt my
bed with couerings of tapestrie, with carued workes, with fine
linnen of Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="17">I haue perfumed
my bed with myrrhe, aloes, and cynamom.</ab>
<ab n="18">Come, let vs
take our fill of loue vntill the morning, let vs solace our selues
with loues.</ab>
<ab n="19">For the good-man
is not at home, he is gone a long iourney.</ab>

<fw>The description of a harlot.</fw>
<ab n="20">He hath taken a
bag of money with him, and will come home at the day
appointed.<note> Heb. in his hand. , Or, the New moone.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">With much faire
speech she caused him to yeeld, with the flattering of her lips she
forced him.</ab>
<ab n="22">He goeth after
her straightway, as an oxe goeth to the slaughter, or as a foole to
the correction of the stocks,<note> Heb. suddenly.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Til a dart
strike through his liuer, as a bird hasteth to the snare, and
knoweth not that it is for his life.</ab>
<ab n="24">¶ Hearken
vnto me now therefore, O ye children, and attend to the words of my
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="25">Let not thine
heart decline to her wayes, goe not astray in her paths.</ab>
<ab n="26">For shee hath
cast downe many wounded: yea many strong men haue bene slaine by
her.</ab>
<ab n="27">Her house is the
way to hell, going downe to the chambers of death.<note> Chap.2. 18. &amp; 5.5.</note></ab>



</div>