<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Solomon, to perswade obedience, 3
sheweth what instruction hee had of his parents, 5 to study
wisdome, 14 and to shun the path of the wicked. 20 Hee exhorteth to
faith, 23 and sanctification.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare, ye
children, the instruction of a father, and attend to know
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="2">For I giue you
good doctrine: forsake you not my law.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I was my
fathers sonne, tender and onely beloued in the sight of my
mother.<note> 1. Chron. 29.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">He taught me
also, and said vnto me, Let thine heart reteine my wordes: keepe my
commandements, and liue.<note> 1. Chron. 28.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Get wisedome, get
vnderstanding: forget it not, neither decline from the wordes of my
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="6">Forsake her not,
and she shall preserue thee: loue her, and she shall keepe
thee.</ab>

<fw>Keepe the heart.</fw>
<ab n="7">Wisedome is the
principall thing, therefore get wisedome: and with all thy getting,
get vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="8">Exalt her, and
shee shall promote thee: shee shall bring thee to honour, when thou
doest imbrace her.</ab>
<ab n="9">She shall giue to
thine head an ornament of grace, a crowne of glory shall she
deliuer to thee.<note> Chap. 1.9 , Or, shee shall compasse thee with a crowne of glory.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Heare, O my
sonne, and receiue my sayings: and the yeeres of thy life shalbe
many.</ab>
<ab n="11">I haue taught
thee in the way of wisedome: I haue lead thee in right
pathes.</ab>
<ab n="12">When thou goest,
thy steps shall not be straitned, and when thou runnest, thou shalt
not stumble.<note> Psal.91. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Take fast hold
of instruction, let her not goe; keepe her, for she is thy
life.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Enter not
into the path of the wicked, and goe not in the way of euill
men.<note> Chap. 1. 10,15. psal.1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Auoid it, passe
not by it, turne from it, and passe away.</ab>
<ab n="16">For they sleepe
not except they haue done mischiefe: and their sleepe is taken away
vnlesse they cause some to fall.</ab>
<ab n="17">For they eate
the bread of wickednesse, and drinke the wine of violence.</ab>
<ab n="18">But the path of
the iust is as the shining light that shineth more and more vnto
the perfect day.</ab>
<ab n="19">The way of the
wicked is as darknes: they know not at what they stumble.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ My sonne,
attend to my words, incline thine eare vnto my sayings.</ab>
<ab n="21">Let them not
depart from thine eyes: keepe them in the midst of thine
heart.</ab>
<ab n="22">For they are
life vnto those that find them, and health to all their
flesh.<note> Heb. medicine.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">¶ Keepe thy
heart with all diligence: for out of it are the issues of
life.<note> Heb. aboue all keeping.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Put away from
thee a froward mouth, and peruerse lips put farre from
thee.<note> Heb. frowardnesse of mouth and peruersnes of lips.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Let thine eyes
looke right on, and let thine eye lids looke straight before
thee.</ab>
<ab n="26">Ponder the path
of thy feet, and let all thy wayes be established.<note> Or, all thy wayes shalbe ordered aright.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Turne not to the
right hande nor to the left: remoue thy foot frō
euil.<note> Deut. 5.32</note></ab>



</div>