<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Against suretiship, 6 Idlenesse,
12 And mischieuousnesse. 16 Seuen things hatefull to God. 20 The
blessings of obedience. 25 The mischiefes of
whoredome.</head>

<ab n="1">My sonne, if thou
bee surety for thy friend, it thou hast stricken thy hand with a
stranger,</ab>
<ab n="2">Thou art snared
with the words of thy mouth, thou art taken with the wordes of thy
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="3">Doe this now, my
sonne, and deliuer thy selfe, when thou art come into the hand of
thy friend: goe, humble thy selfe, and make sure thy
friend.<note> Or, so shalt thou preuaile with thy friend.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Giue not sleepe
to thine eyes, nor slumber to thine eyelids.</ab>
<ab n="5">Deliuer thy selfe
as a Roe from the hand of the hunter, and as a bird from the hand
of the fowler.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Goe to the
Ant, thou sluggard, consider her wayes, and be wise.</ab>
<ab n="7">Which hauing no
guide, ouerseer, or ruler,</ab>
<ab n="8">Prouideth her
meat in the Summer, and gathereth her food in the haruest.</ab>
<ab n="9">How long wilt
thou sleepe, O sluggard? when wilt thou arise out of thy
sleepe?<note> Cha.13.4. and 20.4. and 24. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Yet a little
sleepe, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to
sleepe.</ab>
<ab n="11">So shall thy
pouertie come as one that trauaileth, and thy want as an armed
man.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ A
naughtie person, a wicked man walketh with a froward mouth.</ab>
<ab n="13">He winketh with
his eyes, he speaketh with his feete, hee teacheth with his
fingers.</ab>
<ab n="14">Frowardnesse is
in his heart, he deuiseth mischiefe continually, he soweth
discord.<note> Heb. casteth forth.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Therefore shall
his calamitie come suddenly; suddenly shall hee be broken without
remedie.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ These
sixe things doeth the Lord hate; yea seuen are an abomination vnto
him:<note> Heb. of his soule.</note></ab>

<fw>Adulterie</fw>
<ab n="17">A proude looke,
a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood:<note> Hebr. haughtie eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">An heart that
deuiseth wicked imaginations, feet that be swift in running to
mischiefe:<note> Rom.3. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">A false witnesse
that speaketh lies; and him that soweth discord among
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="20">¶ My sonne,
keepe thy fathers commandement, and forsake not the law of thy
mother.<note> Chap.1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Binde them
continually vpon thine heart, and tie them about thy necke.</ab>
<ab n="22">When thou goest,
it shall leade thee; when thou sleepest, it shall keepe thee; and
when thou awakest, it shall talke with thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">For the
Commandement is a lampe, and the Lawe is light: and reproofes of
instruction are the way of life:<note> Psal. 19.9. &amp; 119.105. , Or, candle.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">To keepe thee
from the euill woman, from the flatterie of the tongue of a strange
woman.<note> Cha.2.16. and 5.3. and 7.5. , Or, of the strange tongue.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Lust not after
her beautie in thine heart; neither let her take thee with her
eyelids.<note> Mat.5.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For by meanes of
a whorish woman, a man is brought to a piece of bread: and the
adulteresse will hunt for the precious life.<note> Heb. the woman of a man, or a mans wife.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Can a man take
fire in his bosome, and his clothes not be burnt?</ab>
<ab n="28">Can one goe vpon
hote coales, and his feete not be burnt?</ab>
<ab n="29">So he that goeth
in to his neighbours wife; whosoeuer toucheth her, shall not be
innocent.</ab>
<ab n="30">Men doe not
despise a thiefe, if he steale to satisfie his soule, when hee is
hungry:</ab>
<ab n="31">But if he be
found, he shall restore seuenfold, he shall giue all the substance
of his house.</ab>
<ab n="32">But who so
committeth adultery with a woman, lacketh vnderstanding: hee that
doeth it, destroyeth his owne soule.<note> Heb. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">A wound and
dishonour shall he get, and his reproch shall not be wiped
away.</ab>
<ab n="34">For iealousie is
the rage of a man: therefore he will not spare in the day of
vengeance.</ab>
<ab n="35">He will not
regard any ransome; neither will hee rest content, though thou
giuest many giftes.<note> Hebr. he will not accept the face of any ransome.</note></ab>



</div>