<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The fame, 6 and euidencie of
wisedome. 10 The excellencie, 12 the nature, 15 the power, 18 the
riches, 22 and the eternitie of wisedome. 32 Wisedome is to be
desired for the blessednesse it bringeth.</head>

<ab n="1">Doeth not
Wisedome crie? &amp; Understanding put foorth her
voice?<note> Cha. 1. 20</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Shee standeth in
the top of high places, by the way in the places of the
pathes.</ab>
<ab n="3">She cryeth at the
gates, at the entrie of the citie, at the comming in at the
doores.</ab>
<ab n="4">Unto you, O men,
I call, and my voice is to the sonnes of man.</ab>
<ab n="5">O yee simple,
vnderstand wisedome: and yee fooles, be yee of an vnderstanding
heart.</ab>
<ab n="6">Heare, for I will
speake of excellent things: and the opening of my lippes shalbe
right things.</ab>
<ab n="7">For my mouth
shall speake truth, and wickednesse is an abomination to my
lippes.<note> Heb. the abomination of my lips.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">All the words of
my mouth are in righteousnes, there is nothing froward or peruerse
in them.<note> Heb. wreathed.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">They are all
plaine to him that vnderstandeth: and right to them that find
knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="10">Receiue my
instruction, and not siluer: and knowledge rather then choise
gold.</ab>

<fw>Christs eternitie.</fw>
<ab n="11">For wisedome is
better then rubies: and all the things that may be desired, are not
to be compared to it.<note> Iob 28. 15 psal.19.11. chap.3.15. &amp; 16.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I wisedome dwell
with prudence, and find out knowledge of witty
inuentions.<note> Or, subtiltie.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The feare of the
Lord is to hate euill: pride and arrogancie, and the euill way, and
the froward mouth doe I hate.</ab>
<ab n="14">Counsell is
mine, and sound wisedome: I am vnderstanding, I haue
strength.</ab>
<ab n="15">By me kings
reigne, and princes decree iustice.</ab>
<ab n="16">By me Princes
rule, and Nobles, euen all the Iudges of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">I loue them that
loue me, and those that seeke me early, shall find me.</ab>
<ab n="18">Riches and
honour are with me, yea durable riches and
righteousnesse.<note> Prou.3. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">My fruite is
better then gold, yea then fine gold, and my reuenue then choise
siluer.<note> Prou.3. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">I leade in the
way of righteousnesse, in the midst of the pathes of
iudgment.<note> Or, walke.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">That I may cause
those that loue me, to inherite substance: and I will fill their
treasures.</ab>
<ab n="22">The Lord
possessed me in the beginning of his way, before his works of
old.</ab>
<ab n="23">I was set vp
from euerlasting, from the beginning, or euer the earth
was.</ab>
<ab n="24">When there were
no depthes, I was brought forth: when there were no fountaines
abounding with water.</ab>
<ab n="25">Before the
mountaines were setled: before the hilles, was I brought
foorth:</ab>
<ab n="26">While as yet he
had not made the earth, nor the fields, nor the highest part of the
dust of the world.<note> Or, open places. , Or, the chiefe part.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">When hee
prepared the heauens, I was there: when he set a compasse vpon the
face of the depth.<note> Or, a circle.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">When he
established the cloudes aboue: when he strengthned the fountaines
of the deepe.</ab>
<ab n="29">When he gaue to
the sea his decree, that the waters should not passe his
commandement: when he appointed the foundations of the
earth:<note> Gen.1.10. iob.38.10. psal.14.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">Then I was by
him, as one brought vp with him: and I was daily his delight,
reioycing alwayes before him:</ab>

<fw>Wisedomes feast.</fw>
<ab n="31">Reioycing in the
habitable part of his earth, and my delights were with the sonnes
of men.</ab>
<ab n="32">Nowe therefore
hearken vnto me, O yee children: for blessed are they that keepe my
wayes.<note> Psal.119. 1, 2. and 128. 1.luc.11.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Heare
instruction, and bee wise, and refuse it not.</ab>
<ab n="34">Blessed is the
man that heareth me: watching daily at my gates, waiting at the
postes of my doores.</ab>
<ab n="35">For whoso
findeth mee, findeth life, and shall obtaine fauour of the
Lord.<note> Heb. bring foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">But hee that
sinneth against me, wrongeth his owne soule; all they that hate me,
loue death.</ab>



</div>