<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CProverbs_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Proverbs-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 The discipline, 4 and doctrine of
wisedome. 13 The custome, 16 and error of folly.</head>

<ab n="1">Wisedome hath
builded her house: she hath hewen out her seuen pillars.</ab>
<ab n="2">She hath killed
her beastes; she hath mingled her wine: she hath also furnished her
table.<note> Heb. her killing.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">She hath sent
forth her maidens; she cryeth vpon the highest places of the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="4">Who so is simple,
let him turne in hither: as for him that wanteth vnderstanding, she
sayth to him:</ab>
<ab n="5">Come, eate of my
bread, and drinke of the wine, which I haue mingled.</ab>
<ab n="6">Forsake the
foolish, and liue; and goe in the way of vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="7">He that reproueth
a scorner, getteth to himselfe shame: and he that rebuketh a wicked
man, getteth himselfe a blot.</ab>
<ab n="8">Reproue not a
scorner, lest hee hate thee: rebuke a wise man, and hee will loue
thee.<note> Mat.7. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Giue instruction
to a wise man, and he will be yet wiser: teach a iust man, and he
will increase in learning.</ab>
<ab n="10">The feare of the
Lord is the beginning of wisedome: and the knowledge of the holy is
vnderstanding.<note> Iob.28. 28. psal.111. 10. chap. 1.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For by me thy
dayes shall be multiplied: and the yeeres of thy life shalbe
increased.<note> Chap. 10.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If thou be wise,
thou shalt be wise for thy selfe: but if thou scornest, thou alone
shalt beare it.</ab>
<ab n="13">¶ A foolish
woman is clamorous: she is simple, &amp; knoweth
nothing.<note> Chap.7. 11.</note></ab>

<fw>The iust blessed.</fw>
<ab n="14">For she sitteth
at the doore of her house on a seate, in the high places of the
Citie:</ab>
<ab n="15">To call
passengers who go right on their wayes:</ab>
<ab n="16">Who so is
simple, let him turne in hither: and as for him that wanteth
vnderstanding, she saith to him;</ab>
<ab n="17">Stollen waters
are sweet, and bread eaten in secret is pleasant.<note> Hebr. of secrecies.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">But hee knoweth
not that the dead are there, and that her guests are in the depths
of hell.</ab>



</div>