<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_59" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-56-59.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-59-61.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth to be deliuered from
his enemies. 6 Hee complaineth of their cruelty. 8 Hee trusteth in
God. 11 He prayeth against them. 16 He praiseth God.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician Al-taschith, Michtam of Dauid: when Saul sent, and they
watcht the house to kill him.] Deliuer me from mine enemies, O my
God: defend mee from them that rise vp against me.<note> Heb. set me on high.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Deliuer mee from
the workers of iniquitie, and saue me from bloodie men.</ab>

<fw>The wickeds furie.</fw>
<ab n="3">For loe, they lye
in waite for my soule; the mighty are gathered against me, not for
my transgression, nor for my sinne, O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">They runne and
prepare themselues without my fault: awake to helpe me, and
behold.<note> Hebr. to meete me.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou therefore, O
Lord God of hostes, the God of Israel, awake to visite all the
heathen: be not mercifull to any wicked transgressours.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="6">They returne at
euening: they make a noise like a dogge, and go round about the
citie.</ab>
<ab n="7">Behold, they belch
out with their mouth: swords are in their lippes; for who, say
they, doeth heare?<note> Psal. 10. 11. and 73. 11. and 94. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But thou, O Lord,
shalt laugh at them; thou shalt haue all the heathen in
derision.</ab>
<ab n="9">Because of his
strength will I wait vpon thee: for God is my defence.<note> Hebr. my high place.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The God of my
mercy shall preuent me; God shall let mee see my desire vpon mine
enemies.<note> Hebr. mine obseruers.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Slay them not,
lest my people forget: scatter them by thy power; and bring them
downe, O Lord our shield.</ab>
<ab n="12">For the sinne of
their mouth, and the words of their lips, let them euen be taken in
their pride: and for cursing and lying which they speake.</ab>
<ab n="13">Consume them in
wrath, consume them, that they may not be: and let them know that
God ruleth in Iacob, vnto the ends of the earth. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="14">And at euening
let them returne, and let them make a noise like a dogge, and goe
round about the citie.</ab>
<ab n="15">Let them wander
vp and downe for meate, and grudge if they be not
satisfied.<note> Hebr. to eate. , Or, if they be not satisfied, then they will stay all night.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But I will sing
of thy power; yea I will sing alowd of thy mercy in the morning:
for thou hast bene my defence and refuge, in the day of my
trouble.</ab>
<ab n="17">Vnto thee, O my
strength, wil I sing: for God is my defence, and the God of my
mercy.</ab>



</div>