<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_89" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-88-89.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-89-90.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXXIX.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist praiseth God for his
couenant, 5 For his wonderfull power, 15 For the care of his
Church, 19 For his fauour to the kingdome of Dauid. 38 Then
complaining of contrary euents, 46 He expostulateth, prayeth, and
blesseth God.</head>

<ab n="1">[Maschil of Ethan
the Ezrahite.] I will sing of the mercies of the Lord for euer:
with my mouth will I make knowen thy faithfulnesse to all
generations.<note> Hebr. to generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For I haue said,
Mercie shall bee built vp for euer: thy faithfulnesse shalt thou
establish in the very heauens.</ab>

<fw>Gods power.</fw>
<ab n="3">I haue made a
couenant with my chosen: I haue sworne vnto Dauid my
seruant.<note> 2.Sam. 7. 11,&amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Thy seed will I
stablish for euer: and build vp thy throne to all generations.
Selah.<note> Heb. to generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the heauens
shall praise thy wonders, O Lord: thy faithfulnes also in the
congregation of the Saints.</ab>
<ab n="6">For who in the
heauen can be compared vnto the Lord? who among the sonnes of the
mightie can be likened vnto the Lord?</ab>
<ab n="7">God is greatly to
be feared in the assembly of the Saints: and to bee had in
reuerence of all them that are about him.</ab>
<ab n="8">O Lord God of
hosts, who is a strong Lord like vnto thee? or to thy faithfulnesse
round about thee?</ab>
<ab n="9">Thou rulest the
raging of the sea: when the waues thereof arise; thou stillest
them.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou hast broken
Rahab in pieces, as one that is slaine: thou hast scattered thine
enemies with thy strong arme.<note> Or, Egypt. , Heb. with the arme of thy strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The heauens are
thine, the earth also is thine: as for the world and the fulnes
thereof, thou hast founded them.<note> Gen.1.1. psal. 24.1. psal. 50.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The North and the
South, thou hast created them: Tabor and Hermon shall reioyce in
thy Name.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou hast a
mighty arme: strong is thy hand, and high is thy right
hand.<note> Heb. an arme with might.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Iustice and
iudgement are the habitation of thy throne: mercie and trueth shall
goe before thy face.<note> Or, establishment.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Blessed is the
people that knowe the ioyfull sound: they shall walke O Lord in the
light of thy countenance.<note> Num.10.6</note></ab>
<ab n="16">In thy name shall
they reioyce all the day: and in thy righteousnes shall they be
exalted.</ab>
<ab n="17">For thou art the
glory of their strength: and in thy fauour our horne shall be
exalted.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the Lord is
our defence: and the holy One of Israel is our king.<note> Or, our shield is of the LORD, and our king is of the holy One of Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Then thou spakest
in vision to thy holy one, and saidst, I haue laid helpe vpon one
that is mightie: I haue exalted one chosen out of the
people.</ab>
<ab n="20">I haue found
Dauid my seruant: with my holy oile haue I anointed
him.<note> 1.Sam. 16 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">With whome my
hand shall bee established: mine arme also shall strengthen
him.</ab>

<fw>Gods promises made to Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="22">The enemie shall
not exact vpon him: nor the sonne of wickednesse afflict
him.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I will beate
downe his foes before his face: and plague them that hate
him.</ab>
<ab n="24">But my
faithfulnesse and my mercy shalbe with him: and in my name shall
his horne be exalted.</ab>
<ab n="25">I will set his
hand also in the sea: and his right hand in the riuers.</ab>
<ab n="26">He shall crie
vnto mee, Thou art my father: my God, and the rocke of my
saluation.</ab>
<ab n="27">Also I will make
him my first borne: higher then the kings of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="28">My mercy will I
keepe for him for euermore: and my couenant shall stand fast with
him.</ab>
<ab n="29">His seed also
will I make to indure for euer: and his throne as the dayes of
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="30">If his children
forsake my lawe, and walke not in my iudgements;</ab>
<ab n="31">If they breake my
statutes, and keepe not my commandements:<note> Heb. profane my statutes.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Then will I
visite their transgression with the rod, and their iniquitie with
stripes.</ab>
<ab n="33">Neuerthelesse, my
louing kindnesse will I not vtterly take from him: nor suffer my
faithfulnesse to faile.<note> Heb. I will not make voyd from him. , Heb. to lye.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">My couenant will
I not breake: nor alter the thing that is gone out of my
lippes.</ab>
<ab n="35">Once haue I
sworne by my holinesse; that I will not lye vnto Dauid.<note> Heb. if I lie.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">His seede shall
endure for euer; and his throne as the sunne before me.<note> Rom.7. 16. Luc.1. 33. Iohn.12 34.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">It shalbe
established for euer as the Moone: and as a faithfull witnesse in
heauen. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="38">But thou hast
cast off and abhorred: thou hast bene wroth with thine
anointed.</ab>
<ab n="39">Thou hast made
voyd the couenant of thy seruant: thou hast profaned his crowne, by
casting it to the ground.</ab>
<ab n="40">Thou hast broken
downe all his hedges: thou hast brought his strong holds to
ruine.</ab>
<ab n="41">All that passe by
the way; spoile him: hee is a reproach to his neighbours.</ab>
<ab n="42">Thou hast set vp
the right hand of his aduersaries: thou hast made all his enemies
to reioyce.</ab>

<fw>Gods promises made to Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="43">Thou hast also
turned the edge of his sword: and hast not made him to stand in the
battaile.</ab>
<ab n="44">Thou hast made
his glory to cease: and cast his throne downe to the
ground.<note> Heb. brightnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">The dayes of his
youth hast thou shortned: thou hast couered him with shame.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="46">How long, Lord,
wilt thou hide thy selfe, for euer? shall thy wrath burne like
fire?</ab>
<ab n="47">Remember how
short my time is: wherefore hast thou made all men in
vaine?</ab>
<ab n="48">What man is he
that liueth, and shall not see death? shall he deliuer his soule
from the hand of the graue? Selah.</ab>
<ab n="49">Lord, where are
thy former louing kindnesses, which thou swarest vnto Dauid in thy
trueth?<note> 2.Sam.7. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="50">Remember (Lord)
the reproach of thy seruants: how I doe beare in my bosome the
reproache of all the mighty people.</ab>
<ab n="51">Wherewith thine
enemies haue reproached, O Lord: wherewith they haue reproached the
foote-steppes of thine Annointed.</ab>
<ab n="52">Blessed be the
Lord for euermore, Amen, and Amen.</ab>



</div>