<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_35" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-35-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth for his owne safety,
&amp; his enemies confusion. 11 He complaineth of their wrongfull
dealing. 22 Thereby he inciteth God against them.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid.] Plead my cause (O Lord) with them that striue with mee:
fight against them that fight against me.</ab>
<ab n="2">Take hold of
shield and buckler, and stand vp for mine helpe.</ab>
<ab n="3">Draw out also the
speare, and stop the way against them that persecute me: say vnto
my soule, I am thy saluation.</ab>
<ab n="4">Let them be
confounded and put to shame that seeke after my soule: let them be
turned backe and brought to confusion, that deuise my
hurt.<note> Psal.40. 15. &amp; 70. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Let them be as
chaffe before the wind: and let the Angel of the Lord chase
them.<note> Iob 21.18. psal.1.4. Esa.29.6. Ose. 13.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Let their way be
darke and slippery, and let the Angel of the Lord persecute
them.<note> Heb. darknesse and slipperinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For without cause
haue they hid for me their net in a pit, which without cause they
haue digged for my soule.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let destruction
come vpon him at vnawares, and let his net that hee hath hid, catch
himselfe: into that very destruction let him fall.<note> He. which he knoweth not of.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And my soule
shalbe ioyfull in the Lord: it shall reioyce in his
saluation.</ab>
<ab n="10">All my bones
shall say, Lord, who is like vnto thee which deliuerest the poore
from him that is too strong for him, yea the poore and the needy,
from him that spoileth him?</ab>
<ab n="11">False witnesses
did rise vp they layd to my charge things that I knew
not.<note> Heb. witnesses of wrong. , Heb. they asked me.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">They rewarded mee
euill for good, to the spoiling of my soule.<note> Heb. depriuing.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">But as for me,
when they were sicke, my clothing was sack-cloth: I humbled my
soule with fasting, and my prayer returned into mine owne
bosome.<note> Or, afflicted.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I behaued my
selfe as though he had bene my friend, or brother: I bowed downe
heauily, as one that mourneth for his mother.<note> Heb. walked. , Heb. as a friend, as a brother to me.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids complaint, and prayer.</fw>
<ab n="15">But in mine
aduersitie they reioyced, and gathered themselues together: yea,
the abiects gathered themselues together against me, &amp; I knew
it not, they did teare me, and ceased not,<note> Heb. halting.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">With
hypocriticall mockers in feasts: they gnashed vpon mee with their
teeth.</ab>
<ab n="17">Lord, how long
wilt thou looke on? rescue my soule from their destructions, my
darling from the lyons.<note> Heb. my onely one.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">I will giue thee
thankes in the great congregation: I will praise thee among much
people.<note> Psal.40.11 and 111.1. , Heb. strong</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Let not them that
are mine enemies wrongfully, reioyce ouer me: neither let them
winke with the eye, that hate me without a cause.<note> Heb. falsly.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For they speake
not peace: but they deuise deceitfull matters against them that are
quiet in the land.</ab>
<ab n="21">Yea they opened
their mouth wide against me, and saide, Aha, Aha, our eye hath
seene it.</ab>
<ab n="22">This thou hast
seene (O Lord) keepe not silence: O Lord be not farre from
me.</ab>
<ab n="23">Stirre vp thy
selfe and awake to my iudgement, euen vnto my cause, my God and my
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">Iudge me O Lord
my God, according to thy righteousnesse, and let them not reioyce
ouer me.</ab>
<ab n="25">Let them not say
in their hearts, Ah, so would we haue it: let them not say, We haue
swallowed him vp.<note> Heb. ah, ah our soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Let them be
ashamed and brought to confusion together, that reioyce at mine
hurt: let them bee cloathed with shame and dishonour, that magnifie
themselues against me.</ab>
<ab n="27">Let them shoute
for ioy, and bee glad that fauour my righteous cause: yea let them
say continually, Let the Lord bee magnified, which hath pleasure in
the prosperity of his seruant<note> Hebr. my righteousnes.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And my tongue
shall speake of thy righteousnesse, and of thy praise all the day
long.</ab>



</div>