<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-3-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth, and professeth his
studie in prayer. 4 God fauoureth not the wicked. 7 Dauid
professing his faith, prayeth vnto God, to guide him, 10 To destroy
his enemies, 11 and to preserue the godly.</head>


<fw>Dauids prayer.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the
chiefe musician vpon Nehiloth, A Psalme of Dauid.] Giue eare to my
words, O Lord, consider my meditation.</ab>
<ab n="2">Hearken vnto
the voice of my crie, my King, and my God: for vnto thee will I
pray.</ab>
<ab n="3">My voyce
shalt thou heare in the morning, O Lord; in the morning will I
direct my prayer vnto thee, and will looke vp.<note> Psal.130. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For thou art
not a God that hath pleasure in wickednesse: neither shall euill
dwell with thee.</ab>
<ab n="5">The foolish
shall not stand in thy sight: thou hatest al workers of
iniquity<note> Heb. before thine eyes.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou shalt
destroy them that speake leasing: the Lord will abhorre the bloodie
and deceitfull man.<note> Heb. the man of bloods and deceit.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But as for
me, I will come into thy house in the multitude of thy mercy: and
in thy feare will I worship toward thy holy temple.<note> Heb. the temple of thy holinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Lead me O
Lord, in thy righteousnesse, because of mine enemies; make thy way
straight before my face.<note> Heb. those which obserue me.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For there is
no faithfulnes in their mouth, their inward part is very
wickednesse: their throat is an open sepulchre, they flatter with
their tongue.<note> Or stedfastnesse. , Heb. in his mouth .i. in the mouth of any of them. , Heb. wickednesse. , Rom.3.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Destroy thou them,
O God, let them fall by their owne counsels: cast them out in the
multitude of their transgressions, for they haue rebelled against
thee.<note> Or, make them guilty. , Or, from their counsels.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But let all those
that put their trust in thee, reioyce: let them euer shout for ioy;
because thou defendest them: let them also that loue thy name, be
ioyfull in thee.<note> Heb. thou couerest, ouer, or protectest them.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For thou, Lord,
wilt blesse the righteous: with fauour wilt thou compasse him as
with a shield.<note> Hebr. crowne him.</note></ab>



</div>