<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_44" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-41-44.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-44-45.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIV.</head>
<head>1 The Church, in memory of former
fauours, 7 complaineth of their present euils. 17 Professing her
integritie, 24 She feruently prayeth for succour.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician for the sonnes of Korah.] Wee haue heard with our eares, O
God, our fathers haue told vs, what worke thou didst in their
dayes, in the times of old.</ab>
<ab n="2">How thou didst
driue out the heathen with thy hand, &amp; plantedst them; how thou
didst afflict the people, and cast them out.</ab>
<ab n="3">For they got not
the land in possession by their owne sword, neither did their owne
arme saue them: but thy right hand, and thine arme, and the light
of thy countenance, because thou hadst a fauour vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou art my King,
O God: command deliuerances for Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="5">Through thee will
wee push downe our enemies: through thy Name will wee tread them
vnder that rise vp against vs.</ab>
<ab n="6">For I will not
trust in my bow, neither shall my sword saue me.</ab>

<fw>Prayer in trouble.</fw>
<ab n="7">But thou hast
saued vs from our enemies, and hast put them to shame that hated
vs.</ab>
<ab n="8">In God we boast
all the day long: and praise thy Name for euer. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="9">But thou hast cast
off and put vs to shame; and goest not forth with our
armies.</ab>
<ab n="10">Thou makest vs to
turne backe from the enemie: and they which hate vs, spoile for
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thou hast giuen
vs like sheepe appointed for meate: and hast scattered vs among the
heathen.<note> Hebr. as sheepe of meate.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Thou sellest thy
people for nought, and doest not increase thy wealth by their
price.<note> Heb. without riches.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Thou makest vs a
reproch to our neighbours, a scorne and a derision to them that are
round about vs.<note> Psal.79.4</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thou makest vs a
by-word among the heathen: a shaking of the head among the
people.<note> Iere.24.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">My confusion is
continually before me, and the shame of my face hath couered
me.</ab>
<ab n="16">For the voice of
him that reproacheth, and blasphemeth: by reason of the enemie and
auenger.</ab>
<ab n="17">All this is come
vpon vs; yet haue wee not forgotten thee, neither haue we dealt
falsly in thy couenant.</ab>
<ab n="18">Our heart is not
turned backe: neither haue our steps declined from thy
way,<note> Or, goings</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Though thou hast
sore broken vs in the place of dragons, and couered vs with the
shadow of death.</ab>
<ab n="20">If wee haue
forgotten the name of our God, or stretched out our hands to a
strange God:</ab>
<ab n="21">Shall not God
search this out? for he knoweth the secrets of the heart.</ab>
<ab n="22">Yea for thy sake
are wee killed all the day long: wee are counted as sheepe for the
slaughter.<note> Rom.8.36</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Awake, why
sleepest thou, O Lord? arise, cast vs not off for euer.</ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore hidest
thou thy face? and forgettest our affliction, and our
oppression?</ab>
<ab n="25">For our soule is
bowed downe to the dust; our belly cleaueth vnto the earth.</ab>
<ab n="26">Arise for our
helpe, and redeeme vs for thy mercies sake.<note> Heb. a help for vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>