<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_39" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauids care of his thoughts, 4 the
consideration of the breuity and vanitie of life, 7 the reuerence
of Gods iudgements, 10 and prayer, are his bridles of
impatiencie.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, euen to Ieduthun, A Psalme of Dauid.] I sayd, I will take
heede to my waies, that I sinne not with my tongue: I will keepe my
mouth with a bridle, while the wicked is before me.<note> Heb. a bridle, or mousell for my mouth.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I was dumbe with
silence, I held my peace, euen from good, and my sorrow was
stirred.<note> Heb. troubled.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">My heart was hot
within mee, while I was musing the fire burned: then spake I with
my tongue.</ab>
<ab n="4">Lord, make me to
know mine end, and the measure of my dayes, what it is: that I may
know how fraile I am.<note> Or, what time I haue here.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Behold, thou hast
made my dayes as an hand breadth, and mine age is as nothing before
thee: verily euery man at his best state is altogether vanitie.
Selah.<note> Heb. setled. , Psal.62.9. &amp; 144.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Surely euery man
walketh in a vaine shew: surely they are disquieted in vaine: he
heapeth vp riches, and knoweth not who shall gather
them.<note> Hebr. image.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And now Lord, what
wait I for? my hope is in thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Deliuer me from
all my transgressions: make mee not the reproch of the
foolish.</ab>
<ab n="9">I was dumbe, I
opened not my mouth; because thou diddest it.</ab>
<ab n="10">Remooue thy
stroke away from mee: I am consumed by the blowe of thine
hand.<note> Heb. conflict.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">When thou with
rebukes doest correct man for iniquitie, thou makest his beautie to
consume away like a moth: surely euery man is vanitie.
Selah.<note> Heb. that which is to be desired in him, to melt away.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Heare my prayer,
O Lord, and giue eare vnto my crie, hold not thy peace at my
teares: for I am a straunger with thee, and a soiourner, as all my
fathers were.<note> Leuit.25. 23. 1.Chron. 29.15. Psal.119.19. Heb.11.13. 1.Pet. 2.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">O spare me, that
I may recouer strength: before I goe hence, and be no more.</ab>



</div>