<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_85" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-83-85.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-85-88.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXXV.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist out of the experience
of former mercies prayeth for the continuance thereof. 8 He
promiseth to waite thereon, out of confidence of Gods
goodnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician, a Psalme for the sonnes of Korah.] Lord, thou hast bene
fauourable vnto thy land: thou hast brought backe the captiuity of
Iacob.<note> Or, well pleased.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thou hast forgiuen
the iniquitie of thy people, thou hast couered all their sinne.
Selah.<note> Psal.32.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thou hast taken
away all thy wrath: thou hast turned thy selfe from the fiercenesse
of thine anger.<note> Or, thou hast turned thine anger from waxing hot.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Turne vs, O God of
our saluation: and cause thine anger towards vs to cease.</ab>
<ab n="5">Wilt thou be angry
with vs for euer? wilt thou drawe out thine anger to all
generations?</ab>
<ab n="6">Wilt thou not
reuiue vs againe: that thy people may reioyce in thee?</ab>
<ab n="7">Shew vs thy mercy,
O Lord; and graunt vs thy saluation.</ab>
<ab n="8">I will heare what
God the Lord will speake: for hee will speake peace vnto his
people, and to his Saints: but let them not turne againe to
folly.</ab>
<ab n="9">Surely his
saluation is nigh them that feare him; that glory may dwell in our
land.</ab>
<ab n="10">Mercy and truth
are met together: righteousnesse and peace haue kissed each
other.</ab>
<ab n="11">Truth shall
spring out of the earth: and righteousnesse shall looke downe from
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="12">Yea the Lord
shall giue that which is good: and our land shall yeeld her
increase.</ab>

<fw>Dauids prayer in affliction.</fw>
<ab n="13">Righteousnes
shall go before him: and shall set vs in the way of his
steps.</ab>



</div>