<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_79" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-78-79.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-79-80.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXIX.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist complaineth of the
desolation of Ierusalem. 8 Hee prayeth for deliuerance, 13 And
promiseth thankefulnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">[A psalme of
Asaph.] O God, the heathen are come into thine, inheritance, thy
holy temple haue they defiled: they haue layd Ierusalem on
heapes.</ab>

<fw>The troubles of the Church.</fw>
<ab n="2">The dead bodies of
thy seruants haue they giuen to bee meate vnto the foules of the
heauen: the flesh of thy Saints vnto the beasts of the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="3">Their blood haue
they shed like water round about Ierusalem: and there was none to
burie them.</ab>
<ab n="4">We are become a
reproach to our neighbours: a scorne and derision to them that are
round about vs.<note> Psa. 44.14</note></ab>
<ab n="5">How long, Lord,
wilt thou be angry, for euer? shall thy ielousie burne like
fire?<note> Psa 89.45</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Powre out thy
wrath vpon the heathen that haue not knowen thee, and vpon the
kingdomes that haue not called vpon thy name.<note> Ier.10.25</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For they haue
deuoured Iacob: and laid waste his dwelling place.</ab>
<ab n="8">O remember not
against vs former iniquities, let thy tender mercies speedily
preuent vs: for we are brought very low.<note> Esa.64.9. , Or, the iniquities of them that were before vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Helpe vs, O God of
our saluation, for the glory of thy Name: and deliuer vs, and purge
away our sinnes for thy Names sake.</ab>
<ab n="10">Wherfore should
the heathen say, Where is their God? let him be knowen among the
heathen in our sight by the reuenging of the blood of thy seruants
which is shed.<note> Heb. vengeance.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Let the sighing
of the prisoner come before thee, according to the greatnesse of
thy power: preserue thou those that are appointed to
die.<note> Heb. thine arme. , Hebr. reserue the children of death.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And render vnto
our neighbours seuen fold into their bosome, their reproach
wherewith they haue reproched thee, O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">So we thy people
and sheepe of thy pasture, will giue thee thankes for euer: we will
shew forth thy praise to all generations.<note> Heb. to generation and generation.</note></ab>



</div>