<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_135" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-132-136.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXXXV.</head>
<head>An exhortation to praise God for his
mercy, 5 for his power, 8 for his iudgements. 15 The vanitie of
Idoles. 19 An exhortation to blesse God.</head>

<ab n="1">Praise ye the
Lord, Praise ye the Name of the Lord: prayse him, O ye seruants of
the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="2">Yee that stand in
the House of the Lord: in the courts of the house of our
God.</ab>
<ab n="3">Praise the Lord,
for the Lord is good: sing praises vnto his Name, for it is
pleasant.</ab>
<ab n="4">For the Lord hath
chosen Iacob vnto himselfe: and Israel for his peculiar
treasure.</ab>

<fw>Idoles are vanitie.</fw>
<ab n="5">For I know that
the Lord is great: and that our Lord is aboue all gods.</ab>
<ab n="6">Whatsoeuer the
Lord pleased, that did he in heauen and in earth: in the Seas, and
all deepe places.</ab>
<ab n="7">Hee causeth the
vapours to ascend from the ends of the earth, he maketh lightnings
for the raine: he bringeth the winde out of his
treasuries.<note> Ier.10.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Who smote the
first borne of Egypt: both of man and beast.<note> Exod. 12. 29. , Heb. from man vnto beast.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Who sent tokens
and woonders into the midst of thee, O Egypt: vpon Pharaoh, and
vpon all his seruants.</ab>
<ab n="10">Who smote great
nations: and slew mightie kings:<note> Num.21. 2. and 4.25, 26,34,35.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Sihon king of
the Amorites, and Og king of Bashan: and all the kingdomes of
Canaan,</ab>
<ab n="12">And gaue their
land for an heritage: an heritage vnto Israel his
people.<note> Ios.12.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Thy Name, O
Lord, endureth for euer: and thy memoriall, O Lord, throughout all
generations.<note> Heb. to generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the Lord
will iudge his people: and he will repent himselfe concerning his
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="15">The idoles of
the heathen are siluer and golde: the worke of mens
hands.<note> Psal. 115. 4,5,6,7,8,9,10.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">They haue
mouthes, but they speake not: eyes haue they, but they see
not:</ab>
<ab n="17">They haue eares,
but they heare not: neither is there any breath in their
mouthes.</ab>
<ab n="18">They that make
them are like vnto them: so is euery one that trusteth in
them.</ab>
<ab n="19">Blesse the Lord,
O house of Israel: blesse the Lord, O house of Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="20">Blesse the Lord,
O house of Leui: ye that feare the Lord, blesse the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="21">Blessed be the
Lord out of Zion; which dwelleth at Ierusalem. Praise ye the
Lord.</ab>



</div>