<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_147" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-145-147.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-147-149.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXLVII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet exhorteth to praise
God, for his care of the Church: 4 his power, 6 and his mercy: 7 To
praise him for his prouidence: 12 To praise him for his blessings
vpon the kingdome: 15 for his power ouer the Meteors: 19 and for
his ordinances in the Church.</head>

<ab n="1">Praise ye the
Lord: for it is good to sing praises vnto our God: for it is
pleasant, and praise is comely.</ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord doeth
build vp Ierusalem: he gathereth together the out-casts of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">Hee healeth the
broken in heart: and bindeth vp their wounds.<note> Heb. griefs.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">He telleth the
number of the stars: he calleth them all by their names.</ab>
<ab n="5">Great is our
Lord, and of great power: his vnderstanding is
infinite.<note> Heb. of his vnderstanding there is no number.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord lifteth
vp the meeke: hee casteth the wicked downe to the ground.</ab>
<ab n="7">Sing vnto the
Lord with thankesgiuing: sing prayse vpon the harpe vnto our
God:</ab>

<fw>Gods great power: His praise.</fw>
<ab n="8">Who couereth the
heauen with cloudes, who prepareth raine for the earth: who maketh
grasse to growe vpon the mountaines.</ab>
<ab n="9">He giueth to the
beast his foode: and to the yong rauens which crie.<note> Iob 39. 3. psal.104. 27.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Hee delighteth
not in the strength of the horse: he taketh not pleasure in the
legs of a man.</ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord taketh
pleasure in them that feare him: in those that hope in his
mercie.</ab>
<ab n="12">Praise the Lord,
O Ierusalem: praise thy God, O Zion.</ab>
<ab n="13">For hee hath
strengthened the barres of thy gates: hee hath blessed thy children
within thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">He maketh peace
in thy borders: and filleth thee with the finest of the
wheate.<note> Heb. who maketh thy border peace , Heb. fat of wheate.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">He sendeth forth
his commandement vpon earth: his word runneth very swiftly.</ab>
<ab n="16">He giueth snow
like wooll: he scattereth the hoare frost like ashes.</ab>
<ab n="17">He casteth forth
his yce like morsels: who can stand before his cold?</ab>
<ab n="18">He sendeth out
his word, and melteth them: he causeth his wind to blow, and the
waters flow.</ab>
<ab n="19">He sheweth his
word vnto Iacob: his statutes and his iudgements vnto
Israel.<note> Heb. his words.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">He hath not
dealt so with any nation: and as for his iudgements, they haue not
knowen them. Praise yee the Lord.</ab>



</div>