<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayseth God for executing
of iudgement. 11 He inciteth others to prayse him. 13 Hee prayeth,
that hee may haue cause to prayse him.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the
chiefe musician vpon MuthLabben. A Psalme of Dauid.] I wil praise
thee, O Lord, with my whole heart: I will shewe foorth all thy
maruellous workes.</ab>
<ab n="2">I will bee
glad and reioyce in thee: I will sing prayse to thy name, O thou
most High.</ab>
<ab n="3">When mine
enemies are turned backe, they shall fall and perish at thy
presence.</ab>
<ab n="4">For thou hast
maintained my right, and my cause: thou satest in the throne
iudging right.<note> Hebr. thou hast made my iudgement. , Hebr. in righteousnes</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou hast
rebuked the heathen, thou hast destroyed the wicked; thou hast put
out their name for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="6">O thou
enemie, destructions are come to a perpetuall end; and thou hast
destroyed cities, their memoriall is perished with
them.<note> Or, the destructions of the enemy are come to a perpetuall end: and their cities hast thou destroyed, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But the Lord
shall endure for euer: he hath prepared his throne for
iudgement.<note> Psal.96. 13. and 98. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And hee shall
iudge the world in righteousnesse; he shall minister iudgement to
the people in vprightnesse.</ab>
<ab n="9">The Lord also
will bee a refuge for the oppressed: a refuge, in times of
trouble.<note> Psal.37. 39. and 46. 1. and 91.2. , Heb. an high place.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And they that know
thy name will put their trust in thee: for thou Lord hast not
forsaken them that seeke thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">Sing praises to
the Lord, which dwelleth in Sion: declare among the people his
doings.</ab>
<ab n="12">When he maketh
inquisition for blood, he remembreth them: he forgetteth not the
crie of the humble.<note> Gen.9.5. , Or, afflicted.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Haue mercie vpon
me O Lord, consider my trouble which I suffer of them that hate me,
thou that liftest mee vp from the gates of death:</ab>

<fw>His complaint.</fw>
<ab n="14">That I may shew
foorth all thy prayse in the gates of the daughter of Sion: I will
reioyce in thy saluation.</ab>
<ab n="15">The heathen are
sunke downe in the pit that they made: in the net which they hid,
is their own foot taken.<note> Psal.7.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The Lord is knowen
by the iudgement which he executeth: the wicked is snared in the
worke of his owne hands. Higgaion. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="17">The wicked shall
be turned into hell, and all the nations that forget God.</ab>
<ab n="18">For the needie
shall not alway be forgotten: the expectation of the poore shall
not perish for euer.</ab>
<ab n="19">Arise, O Lord, let
not man preuaile: let the heathen bee iudged in thy sight.</ab>
<ab n="20">Put them in feare,
O Lord: that the nations may know themselues to be but men.
Selah.</ab>



</div>