<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_103" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-101-103.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-103-104.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CIII.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation to blesse God for
his mercie, 15 And for the constancie thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid.] Blesse the Lord, O my soule: and all that is within me,
blesse his holy Name.</ab>
<ab n="2">Blesse the Lord,
O my soule: &amp; forget not all his benefits.</ab>

<fw>Gods great mercie:</fw>
<ab n="3">Who forgiueth all
thine iniquities: who healeth all thy diseases.</ab>
<ab n="4">Who redeemeth thy
life from destruction: who crowneth thee with louing kindnesse and
tender mercies.</ab>
<ab n="5">Who satisfieth
thy mouth with good things: so that thy youth is renewed like the
Eagles.</ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord
executeth righteousnesse: and iudgement for all that are
oppressed.</ab>
<ab n="7">He made knowen
his wayes vnto Moses: his actes vnto the children of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord is
mercifull and gracious: slow to anger, and plenteous in
mercy.<note> Exod.34.7. deut.34.6 nnm. 14.18 nehe. 9.17. psal.86.15. ier. 32.18. , Heb. great of mercie.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Hee will not
alwayes chide: neither will he keepe his anger for euer.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee hath not
dealt with vs after our sinnes: nor rewarded vs according to our
iniquities.</ab>
<ab n="11">For as the
heauen is high aboue the earth: so great is his mercy toward them
that feare him.<note> Heb. according to the height of the heauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">As farre as the
East is from the West: so farre hath hee remooued our
transgressions from vs.</ab>
<ab n="13">Like as a father
pitieth his children: so the Lord pitieth them that feare
him.</ab>
<ab n="14">For he knoweth
our frame: hee remembreth that we are dust.</ab>
<ab n="15">As for man, his
dayes are as grasse: as a flower of the field, so he
flourisheth.</ab>
<ab n="16">For the winde
passeth ouer it, and it is gone; and the place thereof shall know
it no more.<note> Heb. it is not.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">But the mercy of
the Lord is from euerlasting to euerlasting vpon them that feare
him: and his righteousnesse vnto childrens children:</ab>
<ab n="18">To such as keepe
his couenant: and to those that remember his commandements to doe
them.<note> Deut.7.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">The Lord hath
prepared his throne in the heauens: and his kingdome ruleth ouer
all.</ab>
<ab n="20">Blesse the Lord
yee his Angels, that excell in strength, that do his commandements:
hearkening vnto the voice of his word.<note> Heb. mighty in strength</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Blesse ye the
Lord all yee his hostes: ye ministers of his that doe his
pleasure.</ab>
<ab n="22">Blesse the Lord
all his works in all places of his dominion: blesse the Lord, O my
soule.</ab>



</div>