<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_94" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-92-94.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-94-97.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XCIV.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet calling for Iustice,
complaineth of tyrannie and impietie. 8 Hee teacheth Gods
prouidence. 12 He sheweth the blessednesse of affliction. 16 God is
the defender of the afflicted.</head>

<ab n="1">O Lord God, to
whome vengeance belongeth: O God to whome vengeance belongeth, shew
thy selfe.<note> Heb. God of reuenges. , Heb. shine forth.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods correction.</fw>
<ab n="2">Lift vp thy selfe,
thou iudge of the earth: render a reward to the proud.</ab>
<ab n="3">Lord, how long
shall the wicked? how long shall the wicked triumph?</ab>
<ab n="4">How long shal they
vtter, and speake hard things? and all the workers of iniquitie
boast themselues?</ab>
<ab n="5">They breake in
pieces thy people, O Lord: and afflict thine heritage.</ab>
<ab n="6">They slay the
widowe and the stranger: and murder the fatherlesse.</ab>
<ab n="7">Yet they say, The
Lord shall not see: neither shall the God of Iacob regard
it.<note> Psal.10.11,13. pro. 20.12,</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Understand, yee
brutish among the people: and ye fooles, when will ye be
wise?</ab>
<ab n="9">He that planted
the eare, shall he not heare? he that formed the eye, shall he not
see?<note> Exo.4.11</note></ab>
<ab n="10">He that
chastiseth the heathen, shall not he correct? hee that teacheth man
knowledge, shall not he know?</ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord knoweth
the thoughts of man: that they are vanitie.<note> 1.Cor.3. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Blessed is the
man whome thou chastenest, O Lord: and teachest him out of thy
Law:</ab>
<ab n="13">That thou mayest
giue him rest from the dayes of aduersitie: vntill the pit be
digged for the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="14">For the Lord will
not cast off his people: neither will he forsake his
inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="15">But iudgement
shall returne vnto righteousnesse: and all the vpright in heart
shall follow it.<note> Hebr. shall be after it.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Who will rise vp
for mee against the euill doers? or who will stand vp for me
against the workers of iniquitie?</ab>
<ab n="17">Unlesse the Lord
had bene my helpe: my soule had almost dwelt in
silence.<note> Or, quickly</note></ab>
<ab n="18">When I said, My
foote slippeth: thy mercie, O Lord, held me vp.</ab>
<ab n="19">In the multitude
of my thoughts within me, thy comforts delight my soule.</ab>
<ab n="20">Shal the throne
of iniquitie haue fellowship with thee: which frameth mischiefe by
a lawe?</ab>
<ab n="21">They gather
themselues together against the soule of the righteous: and
condemne the innocent blood.</ab>
<ab n="22">But the Lord is
my defence: and my God is the rocke of my refuge.</ab>

<fw>Gods greatnesse, and maiestie.</fw>
<ab n="23">And hee shall
bring vpon them their owne iniquitie, and shall cut them off in
their owne wickednesse: yea the Lord our God shall cut them
off.</ab>



</div>