<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_77" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-75-77.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXVII.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist sheweth what fierce
combate hee had with diffidence. 10 The victory which he had by
consideration of Gods great and gratious workes.</head>

<ab n="1">I cryed vnto God
with my voice: euen vnto God with my voice, and he gaue eare vnto
me.</ab>

<fw>Gods power.</fw>
<ab n="2">In the day of my
trouble, I sought the Lord; my sore ranne in the night, and ceased
not: my soule refused to be comforted.<note> Heb. my hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I remembred God,
and was troubled: I complained, and my spirit was ouerwhelmed.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou holdest mine
eyes waking: I am so troubled that I cannot speake.</ab>
<ab n="5">I haue considered
the dayes of old, the yeeres of auncient times.</ab>
<ab n="6">I call to
remembrance my song in the night: I commune with mine owne heart,
and my spirit made diligent search.</ab>
<ab n="7">Will the Lord cast
off for euer? and will hee be fauourable no more?</ab>
<ab n="8">Is his mercy
cleane gone for euer? doth his promise faile for
euermore?<note> Heb. to generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Hath God forgotten
to be gracious? hath he in anger shut vp his tender mercies?
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="10">And I sayd, This
is my infirmitie: but I will remember the yeeres of the right hand
of the most high.</ab>
<ab n="11">I will remember
the workes of the Lord: surely I will remember thy wonders of
old.</ab>
<ab n="12">I will meditate
also of all thy worke, and talke of thy doings.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thy way, O God,
is in the Sanctuarie: who is so great a God, as our God?</ab>
<ab n="14">Thou art the God
that doest wonders; thou hast declared thy strength among the
people.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou hast with
thine arme redeemed thy people, the sonnes of Iacob and Ioseph.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="16">The waters saw
thee, O God, the waters saw thee: they were afraid; the depths also
were troubled.</ab>
<ab n="17">The cloudes
powred out water, the skies sent out a sound; thine arrowes also
went abroad.<note> Heb. the clouds were powred forth with water.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The voice of thy
thunder was in the heauen: the lightnings lightned the world, the
earth trembled and shooke.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thy way is in the
sea, and thy path in the great waters: and thy foot-steps are not
knowen.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou leddest thy
people like a flock, by the hand of Moses and Aaron.<note> Exod. 14. 19.</note></ab>



</div>