<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_139" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-138-140.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXXXIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid praiseth God for his
all-seeing prouidence, 17 And for his infinite mercies. 19 He
defieth the wicked. 23 Hee prayeth for sinceritie.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, A Psalme of Dauid.] O Lord, thou hast searched mee, and
knowen me.</ab>
<ab n="2">Thou knowest my
downe sitting, and mine vprising: thou vnderstandest my thought
afarre off.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou compassest
my path, and my lying downe, and art acquainted with all my
wayes.<note> Or, winnowest.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For there is not
a worde in my tongue: but lo, O Lord, thou knowest it
altogether.</ab>
<ab n="5">Thou hast beset
me behind, and before: and laid thine hand vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="6">Such knowledge is
too wonderfull for me: it is high, I cannot attaine vnto
it.</ab>
<ab n="7">Whither shall I
goe from thy spirit? or whither shall I flie from thy
presence?</ab>
<ab n="8">If I ascend vp
into heauen, thou art there: if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou
art there.<note> Amos 9. 2,3,4.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">If I take the
wings of the morning: and dwell in the vttermost parts of the
Sea:</ab>
<ab n="10">Euen there shall
thy hand leade me: and thy right hand shall hold me.</ab>
<ab n="11">If I say, Surely
the darkenes shall couer me: euen the night shall bee light about
me.<note> Iob 26.6. heb.4.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Yea the
darkenesse hideth not from thee, but the night shineth as the day:
the darknes and the light are both alike to thee.<note> Heb. darkeneth not. , Heb. as is the darkenes so is the light</note></ab>

<fw>Nothing secret to the eyes of
God.</fw>
<ab n="13">For thou hast
possessed my reines: thou hast couered me in my mothers
wombe.</ab>
<ab n="14">I will praise
thee, for I am fearefully and wonderfully made, marueilous are thy
works: and that my soule knoweth right well.<note> Hebr. greatly.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">My substance was
not hid from thee, when I was made in secret: and curiously wrought
in the lowest parts of the earth.<note> Or, strength or body.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Thine eyes did
see my substance yet being vnperfect, and in thy booke all my
members were written, which in continuance were fashioned: when as
yet there was none of them.<note> Heb. all of them. , Or, what dayes they should be fashioned.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Howe precious
also are thy thoughts vnto me, O God: how great is the summe of
them?<note> Psal.40.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">If I should
count them, they are moe in number then the sand: when I awake, I
am still with thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">Surely thou wilt
slay the wicked, O God: depart from me therefore, ye bloody
men.</ab>
<ab n="20">For they speake
against thee wickedly: and thine enemies take thy name in
vaine.</ab>
<ab n="21">Doe not I hate
them, O Lord, that hate thee? and am not I grieued with those that
rise vp against thee?</ab>
<ab n="22">I hate them with
perfect hatred: I count them mine enemies.</ab>
<ab n="23">Search me, O
God, and knowe my heart: trie mee, and knowe my thoughts:</ab>
<ab n="24">And see if there
bee any wicked way in me: and leade me in the way
euerlasting.<note> Heb. way of paine, or griefe.</note></ab>



</div>