<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_110" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-49-50.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-50-50-Exodus.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. L.</head>
<head>1 The mourning for Iacob. 4 Ioseph
getteth leaue of Pharaoh to goe to bury him. 7 The funerall. 15
Ioseph comforteth his brethren, who craued his pardon. 22 His age.
23 He seeth the third generation of his sonnes. 24 He prophesieth
vnto his brethren of their returne. 25 He taketh an oath of them
for his bones. 26 He dieth, and is chested.</head>

<ab n="1">And Ioseph fell
vpon his fathers face, and wept vpon him, and kissed him.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Ioseph
commanded his seruants the physicians to imbalme his father: and
the physicians imbalmed Israel.</ab>
<ab n="3">And fortie dayes
were fulfilled for him, (for so are fulfilled the dayes of those
which are imbalmed) and the Egyptians mourned for him threescore
and ten dayes.<note> Heb. wept.</note></ab>

<fw>His buriall.</fw>
<ab n="4">And when the
dayes of his mourning were past, Ioseph spake vnto the house of
Pharaoh, saying, If now I haue found grace in your eyes, speake, I
pray you, in the eares of Pharaoh, saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">My father made me
sweare, saying, Loe, I die: in my graue which I haue digged for me,
in the land of Canaan, there shalt thou bury me. Now therfore let
me goe vp, I pray thee, and bury my father, and I will come
againe.<note> Chap.47. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Pharaoh said,
Goe vp, and bury thy father, according as he made thee
sweare.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ And Ioseph
went vp to bury his father: and with him went vp all the seruants
of Pharaoh, the elders of his house, and all the elders of the land
of Egypt,</ab>
<ab n="8">And all the house
of Ioseph, and his brethren, and his fathers house: onely their
litle ones, and their flockes, and their heards, they left in the
land of Goshen.</ab>
<ab n="9">And there went vp
with him both charets and horsemen: and it was a very great
company.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they came to
the threshing floore of Atad, which is beyond Iordan, and there
they mourned with a great and very sore lamentation: and he made a
mourning for his father seuen dayes.</ab>
<ab n="11">And when the
inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites sawe the mourning in the
floore of Atad, they saide, This is a grieuous mourning to the
Egyptians: wherfore the name of it was called, Abel Mizraim, which
is beyond Iordan.<note> That is, the mourning of the Egyptians.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And his sonnes
did vnto him according as he commanded them.</ab>
<ab n="13">For his sonnes
caried him into the land of Canaan, and buried him in the caue of
the field of Machpelah, which Abraham bought with the field for a
possession of a burying place, of Ephron the Hittite, before
Mamre.<note> Act.7. 16 , Chap. 23. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
Ioseph returned into Egypt, he and his brethren, and all that went
vp with him, to bury his father, after he had buried his
father.</ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And when
Iosephs brethren saw that their father was dead, they said, Ioseph
will peraduenture hate vs, and will certainely requite vs all the
euill which we did vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="16">And they sent a
messenger vnto Ioseph, saying, Thy father did command before he
died, saying,<note> Heb charged.</note></ab>

<fw>Iosephs kindnesse.</fw>
<ab n="17">So shall ye say
vnto Ioseph, Forgiue, I pray thee now, the trespasse of thy
brethren, and their sinne: for they did vnto thee euill: And now
wee pray thee, forgiue the trespasse of the seruants of the God of
thy father. And Ioseph wept, when they spake vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="18">And his brethren
also went and fell downe before his face, and they said, Behold, we
be thy seruants.</ab>
<ab n="19">And Ioseph saide
vnto them, Feare not: for am I in the place of God?<note> Chap. 45. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But as for you,
yee thought euill against me, but God meant it vnto good, to bring
to passe, as it is this day, to saue much people aliue.</ab>
<ab n="21">Now therefore
feare yee not: I will nourish you, and your litle ones. And hee
comforted them, and spake kindly vnto them.<note> Hebr. to their hearts.</note></ab>

<fw>His age, and death.</fw>
<ab n="22">¶ And
Ioseph dwelt in Egypt, he, and his fathers house: and Ioseph liued
an hundred and ten yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="23">And Ioseph sawe
Ephraims children, of the third generation: the children also of
Machir, the sonne of Manasseh were brought vp vpon Iosephs
knees.<note> Num. 32. 39. , Heb. borne.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And Ioseph saide
vnto his brethren, I die: and God will surely visit you, and bring
you out of this land, vnto the land which hee sware to Abraham, to
Isaac, and to Iacob.<note> Heb.12. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And Ioseph tooke
an othe of the children of Israel, saying, God will surely visite
you, and ye shal carie vp my bones from hence.<note> Exod. 13. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">So Ioseph died,
being an hundred and ten yeeres old: and they imbalmed him, and he
was put in a coffin, in Egypt.</ab>



</div>