<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_144" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-143-145.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXLIV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid blesseth God for his mercie
both to him and to man. 5 Hee prayeth that God would powerfully
deliuer him from his enemies. 9 He promiseth to praise God. 11 Hee
prayeth for the happy state of the kingdome.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid.] Blessed be the Lord my strength, which teacheth my hands to
warre, and my fingers to fight.<note> Hebr. my rocke. , Heb. to the warre, &amp;c</note></ab>
<ab n="2">My goodnes and my
fortresse, my high tower and my deliuerer, my shield, and he in
whome I trust: who subdueth my people vnder me.<note> 2.Sam.22 2. 3. &amp; .35. and 49. verses. , Or, my mercie.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Lord, what is
man, that thou takest knowledge of him? or the sonne of man, that
thou makest account of him?<note> Iob 7.17. psal.8.5. heb.2.6.</note></ab>

<fw>Mans life is but vanitie.</fw>
<ab n="4">Man is like to
vanity: his dayes are as a shadow that passeth away.<note> Psal.39.6. iob 14.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Bow thy heauens,
O Lord, and come downe: touch the mountaines, and they shall
smoke.</ab>
<ab n="6">Cast forth
lightning, and scatter them: shoote out thine arrowes, and destroy
them.<note> Psal. 18. 13,14.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Send thine hand
from aboue, rid me, and deliuer me out of great waters: from the
hand of strange children,<note> Heb. hands</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Whose mouth
speaketh vanitie: and their right hand is a right hand of
falshood.</ab>
<ab n="9">I will sing a new
song vnto thee, O God: vpon a psalterie, and an instrument of ten
strings will I sing praises vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">It is he that
giueth saluation vnto kings: who deliuereth Dauid his seruant from
the hurtfull sword.<note> Or, victory.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Rid me, and
deliuer me from the hand of strange children, whose mouth speaketh
vanitie: and their right hand is a right hand of falshood.</ab>
<ab n="12">That our sonnes
may be as plants growen vp in their youth; that our daughters may
be as corner stones, polished after the similitude of a
palace:<note> Heb. cut.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">That our garners
may bee full, affoording all maner of store; that our sheepe may
bring forth thousands, and tenne thousands in our
streetes.<note> Heb from kind to kind.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">That our oxen
may be strong to labour, that there be no breaking in, nor going
out; that there be no complaining in our streetes.<note> Heb. able to beare burdens, or loaden with flesh.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Happy is that
people that is in such a case: yea, happy is that people, whose God
is the Lord.<note> Psal.33.12 and 65.4.</note></ab>



</div>