<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_36" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-35-37.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVI.</head>
<head>1 The grieuous estate of the wicked.
5 The excellencie of Gods mercie. 10 Dauid prayeth for fauour to
Gods children.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician, A Psalme of Dauid, the seruant of the Lord.] The
transgression of the wicked saith within my heart, that there is no
feare of God before his eyes.</ab>

<fw>Gods kindnesse.</fw>
<ab n="2">For he flatterech
himselfe in his owne eyes, vntill his iniquitie be found to be
hatefull.<note> Heb. to find his iniquitie to hate.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The words of his
mouth are iniquitie and deceit: he hath left off to bee wise, and
to doe good.</ab>
<ab n="4">Hee deuiseth
mischiefe vpon his bed, he setteth himselfe in a way that is not
good; he abhorreth not euill.<note> Or, vanitie</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thy mercie (O
Lord) is in the heauens; and thy faithfulnesse reacheth vnto the
cloudes.<note> Psal.57.11 and 108.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thy righteousnesse
is like the great mountaines; thy iudgements are a great deepe; O
Lord, thou preseruest man and beast.<note> Hebr. the mountaines of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">How excellent is
thy louing kindnesse, O God! therefore the children of men put
their trust vnder the shadowe of thy wings.<note> Heb. precious.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">They shall be
abundantly satisfied with the fatnesse of thy house: and thou shalt
make them drinke of the riuer of thy pleasures.<note> Heb. watered.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For with thee is
the fountaine of life: in thy light shall we see light.</ab>
<ab n="10">O continue thy
louing kindnesse vnto them that know thee; and thy righteousnesse
to the vpright in heart.<note> Heb. draw out at length</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Let not the foot
of pride come against me, and let not the hand of the wicked remoue
me.</ab>
<ab n="12">There are the
workers of iniquitie fallen: they are cast downe, and shal not be
able to rise.</ab>



</div>