<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_25" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-22-25.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-25-27.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXV.</head>
<head>1 Dauids confidence in prayer. 7 Hee
prayeth for remission of sinnes, 16 and for helpe in
affliction.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid.] Vnto thee, O Lord, doe I lift vp my soule.</ab>
<ab n="2">O my God, I trust
in thee, let me not be ashamed: let not mine enemies triumph ouer
me.<note> Psal.22.5. &amp; 31.2. &amp; 34 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Yea let none that
waite on thee, be ashamed: let them bee ashamed which transgresse
without cause.<note> Esa.28.16 Rom.10.11</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Shewe mee thy
wayes, O Lord: teach me thy pathes.<note> Psa.27.11 &amp; 86.11. &amp; 119.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Lead me in thy
trueth, and teach me: for thou art the God of my saluation, on thee
doe I waite all the day.</ab>
<ab n="6">Remember, O Lord,
thy tender mercies, and thy louing kindnesses: for they haue beene
euer of old.<note> Psal.103. 17. &amp; . 106. 1. &amp; 107. 1. Iere.33.3. , Heb. thy bowels.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Remember not the
sinnes of my youth, nor my transgressions: according to thy mercie
remember thou me, for thy goodnesse sake, O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">Good and vpright
is the Lord: therefore will hee teach sinners in the way.</ab>
<ab n="9">The meeke will he
guide in iudgement: and the meeke will he teach his way.</ab>
<ab n="10">All the pathes of
the Lord are mercy and truth: vnto such as keepe his couenant, and
his testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="11">For thy names
sake, O Lord, pardon mine iniquitie: for it is great.</ab>
<ab n="12">What man is he
that feareth the Lord? him shall he teach in the way that he shall
chuse.</ab>
<ab n="13">His soule shall
dwell at ease: and his seede shall inherite the earth.<note> Heb. shall lodge in goodnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The secret of the
Lord is with them that feare him: and he will shew them his
couenant.<note> Pro.3. 32. , Or, and his couenant to make them know it.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Mine eyes are
euer towards the Lord: for hee shall plucke my feete out of the
net.<note> Heb. bring foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Turne thee vnto
me, and haue mercy vpon me: for I am desolate and
afflicted.</ab>
<ab n="17">The troubles of
my heart are inlarged: O bring thou me out of my
distresses.</ab>

<fw>Dauids integritie.</fw>
<ab n="18">Looke vpon mine
affliction, aud my paine, and forgiue all my sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="19">Consider mine
enemies: for they are many, and they hate me with cruell
hatred.<note> Heb. hatred of violence.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">O keepe my soule
and deliuer me: let me not bee ashamed, for I put my trust in
thee.</ab>
<ab n="21">Let integritie
and vprightnesse preserue me: for I wait on thee.</ab>
<ab n="22">Redeeme Israel, O
God, out of all his troubles.</ab>



</div>