<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_71" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-69-71.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-71-72.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in confidence of faith and
experience of Gods fauour, prayeth both for himselfe, and against
the enemies of his soule. 14 He promiseth constancie. 17 Hee
prayeth for perseuerance. 19 He praiseth God, and promiseth to doe
it cheerefully.</head>

<ab n="1">In thee, O Lord,
doe I put my trust, let me neuer be put to confusion.<note> Psal.31.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Deliuer mee in thy
righteousnesse, and cause me to escape: incline thine eare vnto me,
and saue me.</ab>

<fw>Dauids hope.</fw>
<ab n="3">Bee thou my strong
habitation, whereunto I may continually resort: thou hast giuen
commandement to saue mee, for thou art my rocke, and my
fortresse.<note> Hebr. be thou to me for a rocke of habitation</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Deliuer me, O my
God, out of the hand of the wicked, out of the hand of the
vnrighteous, and cruel man.</ab>
<ab n="5">For thou art my
hope, O Lord God: thou art my trust from my youth.</ab>
<ab n="6">By thee haue I
bene holden vp from the wombe: thou art hee that tooke mee out of
my mothers vowels, my praise shalbe continually of thee.</ab>
<ab n="7">I am as a wonder
vnto many, but thou art my strong refuge.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let my mouth bee
filled with thy praise, and with thy honour all the day.</ab>
<ab n="9">Cast me not off in
the time of old age; forsake me not when my strength
faileth.</ab>
<ab n="10">For mine enemies
speake against mee: and they that lay waite for my soule, take
counsell together,<note> Hebr. watch, or obserue.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Saying, God hath
forsaken him: persecute and take him, for there is none to deliuer
him.</ab>
<ab n="12">O God, be not
farre from mee: O my God, make haste for my helpe.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let them be
confounded and consumed, that are aduersaries to my soule: let them
bee couered with reproch and dishonour, that seeke my hurt.</ab>
<ab n="14">But I wil hope
continually, and will yet praise thee more and more.</ab>
<ab n="15">My mouth shall
shew foorth thy righteousnesse, and thy saluation all the day: for
I know not the numbers thereof.</ab>
<ab n="16">I will goe in the
strength of the Lord God: I will make mention of thy
righteousnesse, euen of thine onely.</ab>
<ab n="17">O God, thou hast
taught me from my youth: and hitherto haue I declared thy wonderous
workes.</ab>
<ab n="18">Now also when I
am old and gray headed, O God, forsake me not: vntill I haue shewed
thy strength vnto this generation, and thy power to euery one that
is to come.<note> Hebr. vnto old age, and gray haires. , Hebr. thine arme.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Thy righteousnes
also, O God, is very high, who hast done great things: O God, who
is like vnto thee?</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou which hast
shewed mee great, and sore troubles, shalt quicken mee againe, and
shalt bring mee vp againe from the depthes of the earth.</ab>

<fw>Gods benefits.</fw>
<ab n="21">Thou shalt
increase my greatnesse, and comfort me on euery side.</ab>
<ab n="22">I will also
praise thee with the psalterie, euen thy trueth, O my God: vnto
thee will I sing withthe harpe, O thou Holy one of
Israel.<note> Hebr. with the instrument of psalterie.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">My lippes shall
greatly reioyce when I sing vnto thee: and my soule, which thou
hast redeemed.</ab>
<ab n="24">My tongue also
shall talke of thy righteousnesse all the day long: for they are
confounded, forthey are brought vnto shame, that seeke my
hurt.</ab>



</div>