<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_86" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-85-88.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXXVI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid strengtheneth his prayer by
the conscience of his Religion, 5 by the goodnesse and power of
God. 11 He desireth the continuance of former grace. 14 Complayning
of the proud, he craueth some token of Gods goodnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">[A prayer of
Dauid.] Bow downe thine eare, O Lord, heare me: for I am poore
&amp; needy.</ab>
<ab n="2">Preserue my soule,
for I am holy: O thou my God, saue thy seruant, that trusteth in
thee.<note> Or, one whom thou fauourest.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Be merciful vnto
me, O Lord: for I cry vnto thee daily.<note> Or, all the day.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Reioyce the soule
of thy seruant: for vnto thee (O Lord) doe I lift vp my
soule.</ab>
<ab n="5">For thou Lord art
good, and ready to forgiue: and plenteous in mercie vnto all them
that call vpon thee.<note> Ioel 2.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Giue eare O Lord,
vnto my prayer: and attend to the voice of my
supplications.</ab>
<ab n="7">In the day of my
trouble I will call vpon thee: for thou wilt answere mee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Among the gods
there is none like vnto thee (O Lord:) neither are there any workes
like vnto thy workes.<note> Deut. 3. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">All nations whom
thou hast made, shall come and worship before thee, O Lord: and
shall glorifie thy Name.</ab>
<ab n="10">For thou art
great, and doest wonderous things: thou art God alone.<note> Deut. 6. 4. and 32. 39. isa. 37. 16. and 44. 6. mar. 12. 29. ephes.4. 6. 1.cor. 8. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Teach me thy way,
O Lord, I will walke in thy trueth: vnite my heart to feare thy
Name.<note> Psal.25. 3. and 119. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I will praise
thee, O Lord my God, with all my heart: and I wil glorifie thy Name
for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="13">For great is thy
mercy toward me: and thou hast deliuered my soule from the lowest
hell.<note> Or, graue.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">O God, the proud
are risen against mee, and the assemblies of violent men haue
sought after my soule: and haue not set thee before
them.<note> Hebr. terrible.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But thou, O Lord,
art a God full of compassion, and gracious: long suffering, and
plenteous in mercy and trueth.<note> Deut. 34. 6. num. 14. 18. psal. 103.8. and 139.4. and 145.8.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids prayer in affliction.</fw>
<ab n="16">O turne vnto me,
and haue mercie vpon me, giue thy strength vnto thy seruant: and
saue the sonne of thine handmaid.</ab>
<ab n="17">Shew me a token
for good, that they which hate me may see it, and bee ashamed:
because thou, Lord, hast holpen me, and comforted me.</ab>



</div>