<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_140" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-138-140.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-140-143.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXL.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth to be deliuered from
Saul and Doeg. 8 He prayeth against them. 12 Hee comforteth
himselfe by confidence in God.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, A Psalme of Dauid.] Deliuer me, O Lord, from the euill
man: preserue me from the violent man.<note> Heb. man of violences.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Which imagine
mischiefes in their heart: continually are they gathered together
for warre.</ab>
<ab n="3">They haue
sharpned their tongues like a serpent: adders poison is vnder their
lips. Selah.<note> Rom.3.14 psal.58.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Keepe me, O Lord,
from the hands of the wicked, preserue me from the violent man: who
haue purposed to ouerthrow my goings.</ab>

<fw>Prayers against the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="5">The proude haue
hid a snare for me and cords, they haue spread a net by the way
side: they haue set grinnes for me. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="6">I said vnto the
Lord, Thou art my God: heare the voyce of my supplications, O
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">O God the Lord,
the strength of my saluation: thou hast couered my head in the day
of battell.</ab>
<ab n="8">Grant not, O
Lord, the desires of the wicked: further not his wicked deuice,
lest they exalt themselues. Selah.<note> Or, let them not be exalted.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">As for the head
of those that compasse me about: let the mischiefe of their owne
lips couer them.</ab>
<ab n="10">Let burning
coales fall vpon them, let them be cast into the fire: into deepe
pits, that they rise not vp againe.</ab>
<ab n="11">Let not an euill
speaker bee established in the earth: euill shall hunt the violent
man to ouerthrow him.<note> Heb. a man of tongue: or, an euill speaker, a wicked man of violence be established in the earth: let him be hunted to his ouerthrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I know that the
Lord will maintaine the cause of the afflicted: and the right of
the poore.</ab>
<ab n="13">Surely the
righteous shall giue thankes vnto thy Name: the vpright shall dwell
in thy presence.</ab>



</div>