<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_50" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-48-50.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-50-51.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. L.</head>
<head>1 The Maiestie of God in the Church.
5 His order to gather Saints. 7 The pleasure of God is not in
Ceremonies, 14 but in sinceritie of Obedience.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Asaph.] The mightie God, euen the Lord hath spoken, and called the
earth from the rising of the sunne, vnto the going downe
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="2">Out of Sion the
perfection of beautie, God hath shined.</ab>
<ab n="3">Our God shall
come, and shall not keepe silence: a fire shall deuoure before him,
and it shalbe very tempestuous round about him.</ab>
<ab n="4">He shall call to
the heauens from aboue, and to the earth, that hee may iudge his
people.</ab>
<ab n="5">Gather my Saints
together vnto mee: those that haue made a couenant with me, by
sacrifice.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the heauens
shall declare his righteousnes; for God is iudge himselfe.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="7">Heare, O my
people, and I will speake, O Israel, and I will testifie against
thee; I am God, euen thy God.</ab>
<ab n="8">I will not reproue
thee for thy sacrifices, or thy burnt offerings, to haue bene
continually before me.</ab>
<ab n="9">I will take no
bullocke out of thy house, nor hee goates out of thy folds.</ab>
<ab n="10">For euery beast
of the forrest is mine, and the cattell vpon a thousand
hilles.</ab>

<fw>Pay thy vowes.</fw>
<ab n="11">I know all the
foules of the mountaines: and the wild beasts of the field are
mine.<note> Hebr. with me.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If I were hungry,
I would not tell thee, for the world is mine, and the fulnesse
thereof.<note> Exod. 19. 5. deut. 10. 14. psal. 24. 1. , Iob 41. 2. 1.cor.10. 23,26.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Will I eate the
flesh of bulles, or drinke the blood of goats?</ab>
<ab n="14">Offer vnto God
thankesgiuing, and pay thy vowes vnto the most high.</ab>
<ab n="15">And call vpon mee
in the day of trouble; I will deliuer thee, and thou shalt glorifie
me.</ab>
<ab n="16">But vnto the
wicked God saith, What hast thou to doe, to declare my Statutes, or
that thou shouldest take my Couenant in thy mouth?</ab>
<ab n="17">Seeing thou
hatest instruction, and castest my words behinde thee.<note> Rom. 2. 21, 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">When thou sawest
a thiefe, then thou consentedst with him, and hast bene partaker
with adulterers.<note> Hebr. thy portion was with adulterers.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Thou giuest thy
mouth to euill, and thy tongue frameth deceit.<note> Hebr. thou sendest.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Thou sittest and
speakest against thy brother; thou slanderest thine owne mothers
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="21">These things hast
thou done, and I kept silence: thou thoughtest that I was
altogether such a one as thy selfe: but I will reproue thee, and
set them in order before thine eyes.</ab>
<ab n="22">Now consider
this, ye that forget God, lest I teare you in pieces, and there be
none to deliuer.</ab>
<ab n="23">Who so offereth
praise, glorifieth me: and to him that ordereth his conuersation
aright, will I shew the saluation of God.<note> Hebr. that disposeth his way.</note></ab>



</div>