<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_106" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-105-106.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-106-107.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CVI.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist exhorteth to praise
God. 4 He prayeth for pardon of sinne, as God did with the fathers.
7 The storie of the peoples rebellion, and Gods mercie. 47 Hee
concludeth with prayer, and praise.</head>

<ab n="1">Praise ye the
Lord. O giue thankes vnto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercie
endureth for euer.<note> Heb. Halleluiah. , Psal. 107. 1. 118. 1. and 136. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Who can vtter the
mighty acts of the Lord? who can shew foorth all his
praise?<note> Iudg. 13. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Blessed are they
that keepe iudgement: and he that doeth righteousnesse at all
times.</ab>
<ab n="4">Remember me, O
Lord, with the fauour that thou bearest vnto thy people: O visite
me with thy saluation:</ab>
<ab n="5">That I may see
the good of thy chosen, that I may reioyce in the gladnesse of thy
nation: that I may glory with thine inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="6">Wee haue sinned
with our fathers: we haue committed iniquitie, we haue done
wickedly.<note> Iudg.7. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Our fathers
vnderstood not thy wonders in Egypt, they remembred not the
multitude of thy mercies: but prouoked him at the sea, euen at the
Red-sea.<note> Exod. 14. 11,12,21.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Neuerthelesse hee
saued them for his Names sake: that hee might make his mighty power
to be knowen.</ab>
<ab n="9">He rebuked the
Red sea also, and it was dried vp: so hee led them through the
depthes, as through the wildernes.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he saued
them from the hand of him that hated them: and redeemed them from
the hand of the enemie.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the waters
couered their enemies: there was not one of them left.<note> Exod. 14. 27. and 15. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Then beleeued
they his words: they sang his praise.<note> Exod. 14. 31. &amp;15.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">They soone
forgate his works: they waited not for his counsell:<note> Exod. 15. 14. &amp; 17.2. , Heb. they made haste, they forgate.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But lusted
exceedingly in the wildernes: &amp; tempted God in the
desert.<note> Exod. 17. 2. 1.cor. 10. 6. , Heb. lusted a lust.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels rebellion, and
idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="15">And he gaue them
their request: but sent leannesse into their soule.<note> Num.11. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">They enuied
Moses also in the campe: and Aaron the Saint of the
Lord.<note> Num. 16. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The earth opened
and swallowed vp Dathan: and couered the company of
Abiram.<note> Numb.16 31. deut. 11.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And a fire was
kindled in their company: the flame burnt vp the
wicked.<note> Num.16. 35. and 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">They made a
calfe in Horeb: and worshipped the molten image.<note> Exo.32.4</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Thus they
changed their glory, into the similitude of an oxe that eateth
grasse.</ab>
<ab n="21">They forgate God
their Sauiour: which had done great things in Egypt:</ab>
<ab n="22">Wonderous workes
in the lande of Ham: and terrible things by the red Sea.</ab>
<ab n="23">Therefore he
said that he would destroy them, had not Moses his chosen stood
before him in the breach: to turne away his wrath, lest hee should
destroy them.<note> Exod. 33. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Yea, they
despised the pleasant land: they beleeued not his word:<note> Hebr. a land of desire.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">But murmured in
their tents: and hearkened not vnto the voyce of the
Lord.<note> Num. 14. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore he
lifted vp his hande against them: to ouerthrow them in the
wildernesse:</ab>
<ab n="27">To ouerthrow
their seed also among the nations, and to scatter them in the
lands.<note> Heb. to make them fall.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">They ioyned
themselues also vnto Baal-Peor: and ate the sacrifices of the
dead.<note> Num. 25. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Thus they
prouoked him to anger with their inuentions: and the plague brake
in vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="30">Then stood vp
Phinehas, and executed iudgement: and so the plague was
stayed.<note> Num. 25. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And that was
counted vnto him for righteousnesse: vnto all generations for
euermore.</ab>
<ab n="32">They angred him
also at the waters of strife: so that it went ill with Moses for
their sakes:<note> Num. 20. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Because they
prouoked his spirit: so that hee spake vnaduisedly with his
lippes.</ab>
<ab n="34">They did not
destroy the nations, concerning whom the Lord commanded
them:<note> Deut.7.1.</note></ab>

<fw>Israels rebellion, and
idolatrie.</fw>
<ab n="35">But were mingled
among the heathen, and learned their workes.<note> Iudg.1.21</note></ab>
<ab n="36">And they serued
their idoles: which were a snare vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="37">Yea they
sacrificed their sonnes, and their daughters vnto deuils,</ab>
<ab n="38">And shed
innocent blood, euen the blood of their sons and of their
daughters, whome they sacrificed vnto the idoles of Canaan: and the
land was polluted with blood.</ab>
<ab n="39">Thus were they
defiled with their owne works: and went a whoring with their owne
inuentions.</ab>
<ab n="40">Therefore was
the wrath of the Lord kindled against his people: insomuch that he
abhorred his owne inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="41">And he gaue them
into the hand of the heathen: and they that hated them, ruled ouer
them.</ab>
<ab n="42">Their enemies
also oppressed them: and they were brought into subiection vnder
their hand.</ab>
<ab n="43">Many times did
he deliuer them: but they prouoked him with their counsell, and
were brought low for their iniquitie.<note> Iudg.2. 16. , Or, impouerished, or weakened.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">Neuertheles he
regarded their affliction: when he heard their crie.</ab>
<ab n="45">And hee
remembred for them his couenant: and repented according to the
multitude of his mercies.<note> Deu.30.2</note></ab>
<ab n="46">He made them
also to be pitied, of all those that caried them captiues.</ab>
<ab n="47">Saue vs, O Lord
our God, and gather vs from among the heathen to giue thankes vnto
thy holy Name: and to triumph in thy praise.</ab>
<ab n="48">Blessed bee the
Lord God of Israel from euerlasting to euerlasting: and let all the
people say, Amen. Praise ye the Lord.</ab>



</div>