<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_38" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-37-38.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-38-39.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVIII.</head>
<head>Dauid mooueth God to take compassion
of his pitifull case.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid, to bring to remembrance.] O Lord, rebuke me not in thy
wrath: neither chasten me in thy hot displeasure.</ab>

<fw>Great afflictions.</fw>
<ab n="2">For thine arrowes
sticke fast in me; and thy hand presseth me sore.</ab>
<ab n="3">There is no
soundnesse in my flesh, because of thine anger: neither is there
any rest in my bones, because of my sinne.<note> Heb. peace, or health.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For mine
iniquities are gone ouer mine head: as an heauy burden, they are
too heauie for me.</ab>
<ab n="5">My wounds stinke,
and are corrupt: because of my foolishnesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">I am troubled, I
am bowed downe greatly; I goe mourning all the day
long.<note> Hebr. wryed.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For my loynes are
filled with a loathsome disease: and there is no soundnesse in my
flesh.</ab>
<ab n="8">I am feeble and
sore broken; I haue roared by reason of the disquietnesse of my
heart.</ab>
<ab n="9">Lord, all my
desire is before thee: and my groning is not hid from thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">My heart panteth,
my strength faileth me: as for the light of mine eies, it also is
gone from me.<note> Heb. is not with me.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">My louers and my
friends stand a loofe from my sore: and my kinsmen stand a farre
off.<note> Heb. stroke , Or, my neighbours.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">They also that
seeke after my life, lay snares for me: and they that seeke my
hurt, speake mischieuous things, and imagine deceits all the day
long.</ab>
<ab n="13">But I, as a deafe
man, heard not; and I was as a dumbe man that openeth not his
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="14">Thus I was as a
man that heareth not; and in whose mouth are no reproofes.</ab>
<ab n="15">For in thee, O
Lord, doe I hope: thou wilt heare, O Lord my God.<note> Or, thee do I wast for. , Or, answere.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For I said, heare
me, least otherwise they should reioyce ouer me: when my foot
slippeth, they magnifie themselues against me.</ab>
<ab n="17">For I am ready to
halt, and my sorrow is continually before me.<note> Heb. for haulting.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For I will
declare mine iniquitie; I will be sory for my sinne.</ab>
<ab n="19">But mine enemies
are liuely, and they are strong: and they that hate mee wrongfully,
are multiplied.<note> Heb. being liuing, are strong.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">They also that
render euill for good, are mine aduersaries: because I follow the
thing that good is.</ab>
<ab n="21">Forsake me not, O
Lord: O my God, be not farre from me.</ab>
<ab n="22">Make haste to
helpe mee, O Lord my saluation.<note> Heb. for my helpe.</note></ab>



</div>