<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_69" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-68-69.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-69-71.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid complaineth of his
affliction. 13 Hee prayeth for deliuerance. 22 Hee deuoteth his
enemies to destruction. 30 He praiseth God with
thankesgiuing.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician vpon Shoshannim, A Psalme of Dauid.] Saue mee, O God, for
the waters are come in vnto my soule.</ab>
<ab n="2">I sinke in deepe
mire, where there is no standing: I am come into deepe waters,
where the flouds ouerflow me.<note> Heb. the myre of depth. , Heb. depth of waters.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I am weary of my
crying, my throate is dried: mine eyes faile while I waite for my
God.</ab>
<ab n="4">They that hate mee
without a cause, are moe then the haires of mine head: they that
would destroy me, being mineenemies wrongfully, are mightie: then I
restored that which I tooke not away.</ab>
<ab n="5">O God, thou
knowest my foolishnesse; and my sinnes are not hidde from
thee.<note> Heb. guiltinesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Let not them that
waite on thee, O Lord God of hostes, be ashamed for my sake: let
not those that seeke thee, beconfounded for my sake, O God of
Israel.</ab>
<ab n="7">Because for thy
sake I haue borne reproch: shame hath couered my face.</ab>
<ab n="8">I am become a
stranger vnto my brethren, and an aliant vnto my mothers
children.</ab>
<ab n="9">For the zeale of
thine house hath eaten mee vp; and the reproches of them that
reproched thee, are fallen vpon me.<note> Iohn 2.17. , Rom.15.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">When I wept, and
chastened my soule with fasting, that was to my reproch.</ab>
<ab n="11">I made sackecloth
also my garment: &amp; I became a prouerbe to them.</ab>
<ab n="12">They that sit in
the gate, speake against mee; and I was the song of the
drunkards.<note> Heb. drinkers of strong drinke.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids prayer against the
wicked.</fw>
<ab n="13">But as for mee,
my prayer is vnto thee, O Lord, in an acceptable time: O God, in
the multitude of thy mercie heareme, in the trueth of thy
saluation.</ab>
<ab n="14">Deliuer me out of
the mire, and let me not sinke: let me bee deliuered from them that
hate me, and out of thedeepe waters.</ab>
<ab n="15">Let not the water
flood ouerflow me, neither let the deepe swallow mee vp, and let
not the pit shut her mouth vponme.</ab>
<ab n="16">Heare me, O Lord,
for thy louing kindnesse is good: turne vnto mee according to the
multitude of thy tendermercies.</ab>
<ab n="17">And hide not thy
face from thy seruant, for I am in trouble: heare me
speedily.<note> Heb. make haste to heare me.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Draw nigh vnto my
soule, and redeeme it: deliuer me because of mine enemies.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thou hast knowen
my reproch and my shame and my dishonor: mine aduersaries are all
before thee.</ab>
<ab n="20">Reproch hath
broken my heart, and I am full of heauines: and I looked for some
to take pitie, but there was none;and for comforters, but I found
none.<note> Heb. to lament with me.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">They gaue mee
also gall for my meat, and in my thirst they gaue mee vineger to
drinke.<note> Mat.27. 28. mar.15. 23. iohn 19 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Let their table
become a snare before them: and that which should haue bene for
their welfare, let it become atrap.<note> Rom.11.9</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Let their eyes be
darkened that they see not; and make their loines continually to
shake.</ab>
<ab n="24">Powre out thine
indignation vpon them, and let thy wrathfull anger take hold of
them.</ab>
<ab n="25">Let their
habitation be desolate, and let none dwell in their
tents.<note> Hebr. their palace. , Hebr. let there not bee a dweller.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For they
persecute him whō thou hast smitten, and they talke to the
griefe of those whom thou hast wounded.<note> Hebr. thy wounded.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Adde iniquitie
vnto their iniquitie: and let them not come into thy
righteousnesse.<note> Or, punishment of iniquitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Let them bee
blotted out of the booke of the liuing, and not be written with the
righteous.</ab>
<ab n="29">But I am poore,
and sorowfull: let thy saluation (O God) set me vp on high.</ab>
<ab n="30">I will praise the
name of God with a song, and will magnifie him with
thankesgiuing.</ab>

<fw>Dauids prayer against the
wicked.</fw>
<ab n="31">This also shall
please the Lord better then an oxe or bullocke that hath hornes and
hoofes.</ab>
<ab n="32">The humble shall
see this, and be glad: and your heart shall liue that seeke
good.<note> Or, meeke.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">For the Lord
heareth the poore, and despiseth not his prisoners.</ab>
<ab n="34">Let the heauen
and earth praise him, the seas, and euery thing that moueth
therein.<note> Hebr. creepeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">For God will saue
Sion, and will build the cities of Iudah, that they may dwell
there, and haue it in possession.</ab>
<ab n="36">The seede also of
his seruants shall inherit it: and they that loue his name shall
dwell therein.</ab>



</div>