<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_145" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-143-145.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-145-147.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXLV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid praiseth God for his fame, 8
For his goodnes, 11 For his kingdome, 14 For his prouidence, 17 For
his sauing mercie.</head>

<ab n="1">[Dauids Psalme of
praise.] I will extoll thee, my God, O King: and I will blesse thy
name for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="2">Euery day wil I
blesse thee: and I will praise thy Name for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="3">Great is the
Lord, and greatly to be praised: and his greatnes is
vnsearchable.<note> Heb. and of his greatnesse there is no search.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">One generation
shall praise thy works to another, and shal declare thy mightie
actes.</ab>

<fw>Gods goodnesse, and trueth.</fw>
<ab n="5">I will speake of
the glorious honour of thy maiestie: and of thy wonderous
workes.<note> Heb. things or words.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And men shall
speake of the might of thy terrible acts: and I wil declare thy
greatnesse.<note> Heb. declare it.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">They shall
abundantly vtter the memory of thy great goodnesse: and shall sing
of thy righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">The Lord is
gracious and full of compassion: slow to anger, and of great
mercy.<note> Exod.34.6,7. num. 14. 18. psal. 86.5,15. and 103.8. , Heb. great in mercie.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The Lord is good
to all: and his tender mercies are ouer all his workes.</ab>
<ab n="10">All thy workes
shall praise thee, O Lord: and thy Saints shal blesse thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">They shall
speake of the glory of thy kingdome: and talke of thy
power.</ab>
<ab n="12">To make knowen
to the sonnes of men his mightie actes: and the glorious Maiestie
of his kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thy kingdome is
an euerlasting kingdome: and thy dominion endureth throughout all
generations.<note> Hebr. a kingdome of all ages.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord
vpholdeth all that fall: and raiseth vp all those that bee bowed
downe.</ab>
<ab n="15">The eyes of all
waite vpon thee: and thou giuest them their meat in due
season.<note> Or, looke vnto thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Thou openest
thine hand: and satisfiest the desire of euery liuing
thing.</ab>
<ab n="17">The Lord is
righteous in all his wayes: and holy in all his works.<note> Or, mercifull, or bountifull.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord is nigh
vnto all them that call vpon him: to all that call vpon him in
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="19">Hee will fulfill
the desire of them that feare him: he also will heare their cry,
and will saue them.</ab>
<ab n="20">The Lord
preserueth all them that loue him: but all the wicked will he
destroy.</ab>
<ab n="21">My mouth shall
speake the praise of the Lord: and let all flesh blesse his holy
Name for euer and euer.</ab>



</div>