<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-6-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth against the malice
of his enemies, professing his innocency. 10 By faith he seeth his
defence and the destruction of his enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">[Shiggaion of
Dauid; which he sang vnto the Lord concerning the words of Cush the
Beniamite.] O Lord, my God, in thee doe I put my trust: saue me
from all them that persecute me, and deliuer me.</ab>
<ab n="2">Least hee
teare my soule like a lyon, renting it in pieces, while there is
none to deliuer.<note> Heb not a deliuerer.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">O Lord my
God, if I haue done this; if there be iniquitie in my
hands:</ab>
<ab n="4">If I haue
rewarded euill vnto him that was at peace with me: (yea I haue
deliuered him that without cause is mine enemie.)</ab>
<ab n="5">Let the
enemie persecute my soule, and take it, yea let him tread downe my
life vpon the earth, and lay mine honour in the dust.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="6">Arise, O
Lord, in thine anger, lift vp thy selfe, because of the rage of
mine enemies: and awake for me to the iudgement that thou hast
commanded.</ab>
<ab n="7">So shall the
congregation of the people compasse thee about: for their sakes
therefore returne thou on high.</ab>

<fw>Dauids prayer, and confidence.</fw>
<ab n="8">The Lord shal
iudge the people: iudge me, O Lord, according to my righteousnesse,
and according to mine integritie that is in me.<note> Psal.18. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Oh let the
wickednes of the wicked come to an end, but establish the iust: for
the righteous God trieth the hearts and reines.<note> 1. Sam.16. 7.1. Chr.28 9. psal.139. 1. Ierem.11. 20 and 17. 10. and 10. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">My defence is of
God, which saueth the vpright in heart.<note> Heb. my buckler is vpon God.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">God iudgeth the
righteous, and God is angrie with the wicked euery-day.<note> Or, God is a righteous Iudge.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If he turne not,
he will whet his sword; he hath bent his bowe, and made it
ready.</ab>
<ab n="13">He hath also
prepared for him the instruments of death; he ordaineth his arrowes
against the persecutors.</ab>
<ab n="14">Behold, he
trauelleth with iniquitie, and hath conceiued mischiefe, and
brought forth falshood.<note> Iob.15. 35. Esa.59. 4. Iam.1. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">He made a pit and
digged it, and is fallen into the ditch which he made.<note> Heb. hee hath digged a pit. , Psal.9.15. and 10.2. prou.5.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">His mischiefe
shall returne vpon his owne head, and his violent dealing shall
come downe vpon his owne pate.</ab>
<ab n="17">I will praise the
Lord according to his righteousnesse: and will sing praise to the
name of the Lord most high.</ab>



</div>