<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_22" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-22-25.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid complaineth in great
discouragement. 9 Hee prayeth in great distresse. 23 Hee praiseth
God.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician vpon Aijeleth Shahar. A Psalme of Dauid.] My God, my God,
why hast thou forsaken mee? Why art thou so far from helping me,
and from the words of my roaring?<note> Mat.27.46. Marc.15.34. , Heb. from my saluation.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">O my God, I crie
in the day time, but thou hearest not; and in the night season, and
am not silent.<note> Heb. there is no silence to me.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But thou art holy,
O thou that inhabitest the praises of Israel!</ab>
<ab n="4">Our fathers
trusted in thee: they trusted, and thou didst deliuer them.</ab>
<ab n="5">They cryed vnto
thee, and were deliuered: they trusted in thee, and were not
confounded.</ab>
<ab n="6">But I am a worme,
and no man; a reproach of men, and despised of the people.</ab>
<ab n="7">All they that see
me, laugh me to scorne: they shoote out the lippe, they shake the
head, saying,<note> Mat.27. 39. , Heb. open.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He trusted on the
Lord, that he would deliuer him: let him deliuer him, seeing he
delighted in him.<note> Mat.27. 43. , Heb. hee rolled himselfe on the Lord. , Or, if he delight in him.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">But thou art hee
that tooke mee out of the wombe; thou didst make me hope, when I
was vpon my mothers breasts.<note> Or, keptst me in safety.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">I was cast vpon
thee from the wombe: thou art my God from my mothers belly.</ab>
<ab n="11">Be not farre from
me, for trouble is neere; for there is none to helpe.<note> Heb. not a helper.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Many bulles haue
compassed me: strong bulles of Bashan haue beset me round.</ab>
<ab n="13">They gaped vpon
me with their mouthes, as a rauening and a roaring
Lyon.<note> Heb. opened their mouthes against me.</note></ab>

<fw>A prophecie of Christ.</fw>
<ab n="14">I am powred out
like water, and all my bones are out of ioynt: my heart is like
waxe, it is melted in the middest of my bowels.<note> Or, sundred.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">My strength is
dried vp like a potsheard: and my tongue cleaueth to my iawes; and
thou hast brought me into the dust of death.</ab>
<ab n="16">For dogges haue
compassed me: the assembly of the wicked haue inclosed me: they
pierced my hands and my feete.<note> Mat.27. 35. Mar.15. 24. Luc.23. 33. Ioh.19. 23. &amp; 37.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">I may tell all my
bones: they looke and stare vpon me.</ab>
<ab n="18">They part my
garments among them, and cast lots vpon my vesture.</ab>
<ab n="19">But be not thou
farre from mee, O Lord; O my strength, hast thee to helpe
me.</ab>
<ab n="20">Deliuer my soule
from the sword: my darling from the power of the dogge.<note> Heb. my only one. , Heb. from the hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Saue me from the
lyons mouth: for thou hast heard me from the hornes of the
vnicornes.</ab>
<ab n="22">I will declare
thy name vnto my brethren: in the midst of the congregation will I
praise thee.<note> Luc.23. 34. Iohn. 19.24. Heb. 2.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Yee that feare
the Lord, praise him; all yee the seede of Iacob glorifie him, and
feare him all yee the seede of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="24">For he hath not
despised, nor abhorred the affliction of the afflicted; neither
hath he hid his face from him, but when he cried vnto him, he
heard.</ab>
<ab n="25">My praise shalbe
of thee, in the great congregation: I will pay my vowes, before
them that feare him.</ab>
<ab n="26">The meeke shall
eate and be satisfied: they shall praise the Lord that seeke him;
your heart shall liue for euer.</ab>
<ab n="27">All the ends of
the world shall remember, and turne vnto the Lord: and all the
kinreds of the nations shall worship before thee.<note> Psal. 2.8. &amp; 72.11. and 86.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For the kingdome
is the Lords: and he is the gouernour among the nations.</ab>
<ab n="29">All they that be
fat vpon earth shall eate and worship: all they that goe downe to
the dust shall bow before him, and none can keepe aliue his owne
soule.</ab>
<ab n="30">A seed shall
serue him; it shalbe accounted to the Lord for a
generation.</ab>
<ab n="31">They shall come,
and shall declare his righteousnes vnto a people that shalbe borne,
that he hath done this.</ab>



</div>