<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_80" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-79-80.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXX.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist in his prayer
complaineth of the miseries of the Church. 8 Gods former fauours
are turned into iudgements. 14 Hee prayeth for
deliuerance.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician vpon Shoshannim Eduth, A Psalme of Asaph.] Giue eare,
shepheard of Israel, thou that leadest Ioseph like a flocke, thou
that dwellest betweene the Cherubims, shine forth.</ab>

<fw>The troubles of the Church.</fw>
<ab n="2">Before Ephraim and
Beniamin, and Manasseh, stirre vp thy strength: and come and saue
vs.<note> Heb. come for saluation to vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Turne vs againe, O
God: and cause thy face to shine, and we shall bee saued.</ab>
<ab n="4">O Lord God of
hosts, how long wilt thou bee angry against the prayer of thy
people?<note> Hebr. wilt thou smoke?</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou feedest them
with the bread of teares: and giuest them teares to drinke in great
measure.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thou makest vs a
strife vnto our neighbours: and our enemies laugh among
themselues.</ab>
<ab n="7">Turne vs againe, O
God of hosts, and cause thy face to shine, and we shall be
saued.</ab>
<ab n="8">Thou hast brought
a vine out of Egypt: thou hast cast out the heathen, and planted
it.</ab>
<ab n="9">Thou preparedst
roome before it: and didst cause it to take deepe root, and it
filled the land.</ab>
<ab n="10">The hilles were
couered with the shadow of it, and the boughs thereof were like the
goodly cedars.<note> Hebr. the Cedars of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">She sent out her
boughs vnto the Sea: and her branches vnto the riuer.</ab>
<ab n="12">Why hast thou
then broken downe her hedges: so that all they which passe by the
way, doe plucke her?</ab>
<ab n="13">The boare out of
the wood doth waste it: and the wild beast of the field doth
deuoure it.</ab>
<ab n="14">Returne, we
beseech thee, O God of hosts: looke downe from heauen, and behold,
and visit this vine:</ab>
<ab n="15">And the vineyard
which thy right hand hath planted: and the branch that thou madest
strong for thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="16">It is burnt with
fire, it is cut downe: they perish at the rebuke of thy
countenance.</ab>
<ab n="17">Let thy hand be
vpon the man of thy right hand: vpon the sonne of man, whom thou
madest strong for thy selfe.</ab>
<ab n="18">So will not wee
goe backe from thee: quicken vs, and we will call vpon thy
Name.</ab>
<ab n="19">Turne vs againe,
O Lord God of hosts, cause thy face to shine, and wee shall be
saued.</ab>



</div>