<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_30" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-28-30.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayseth God for his
deliuerance. 4 He exhorteth others to praise him by example of Gods
dealing with him.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme, and
song at the dedication of the house of Dauid.] I wil extol thee, O
Lord, for thou hast lifted me vp; and hast not made my foes to
reioyce ouer me.</ab>
<ab n="2">O Lord my God, I
cried vnto thee, and thou hast healed me.</ab>
<ab n="3">O Lord, thou hast
brought vp my soule from the graue: thou hast kept me aliue, that I
should not goe downe to the pit.</ab>
<ab n="4">Sing vnto the
Lord, (O yee Saints of his) and giue thanks at the remembrance of
his holinesse.<note> Or, to the memoriall.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For his anger
endureth but a moment; in his fauour is life: weeping may endure
for a night, but ioy commeth in the morning.<note> Heb. there is but a moment in his anger. , Hebr. in the euening. , Hebr. singing.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And in my
prosperitie I said, I shall neuer be mooued.</ab>
<ab n="7">Lord, by thy
fauour thou hast made my mountaine to stand strong: Thou didst hide
thy face, and I was troubled.<note> Hebr. setled strength for my mountaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">I cried to thee, O
Lord: and vnto the Lord I made supplication.</ab>
<ab n="9">What profit is
there in my blood, when I goe downe to the pit? Shall the dust
praise thee? shall it declare thy trueth?<note> Psal.6.6. and 88.11. and 115. 17.</note></ab>

<fw>A prayer of the faithfull.</fw>
<ab n="10">Heare, O Lord,
and haue mercie vpon me: Lord be thou my helper.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thou hast turned
for mee my mourning into dauncing: thou hast put off my sackecloth,
and girded mee with gladnesse:</ab>
<ab n="12">To the end that
my glory may sing prayse to thee, and not be silent: O Lord my God,
I will giue thankes vnto thee for euer.<note> That is, my tongue, or my soule.</note></ab>



</div>