<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_34" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-32-34.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-34-35.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayseth God, and exhorteth
other thereto by his experience. 8 They are blessed that trust in
God. 11 He exhorteth to the feare of God. 15 The Priuiledges of the
righteous.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid, when he changed his behauiour before Abimelech: who droue
him away &amp; he departed.] I will blesse the Lord at all times:
his prayse shall continually bee in my mouth.</ab>

<fw>To see good dayes.</fw>
<ab n="2">My soule shall
make her boast in the Lord: the humble shall heare thereof, and be
glad.</ab>
<ab n="3">O magnifie the
Lord with me, and let vs exalt his name together.</ab>
<ab n="4">I sought the Lord,
and hee heard me; and deliuered mee from all my feares.</ab>
<ab n="5">They looked vnto
him, and were lightned: and their faces were not
ashamed.<note> Or, they flowed vnto him.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">This poore man
cried, and the Lord heard him; and saued him out of all his
troubles.</ab>
<ab n="7">The Angel of the
Lord encampeth round about them that feare him, and deliuereth
them.</ab>
<ab n="8">O taste and see
that the Lord is good: blessed is the man that trusteth in
him.</ab>
<ab n="9">O feare the Lord
yee his Saints: for there is no want to them that feare
him.</ab>
<ab n="10">The young lyons
doe lacke, and suffer hunger: but they that seeke the Lord, shall
not want any good thing.</ab>
<ab n="11">Come yee
children, hearken vnto me: I will teach you the feare of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">What man is hee
that desireth life; and loueth many dayes, that he may see
good?<note> Pet.3. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Keepe thy tongue
from euill, and thy lippes from speaking guile.</ab>
<ab n="14">Depart from
euill, and doe good: seeke peace and pursue it.</ab>
<ab n="15">The eies of the
Lord are vpon the righteous; and his eares are open vnto their
crie.<note> Iob.36.7. psal.33.18. 1.Pet.3.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The face of the
Lord is against them that doe euill; to cut off the remembrance of
them from the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">The righteous
crie, and the Lord heareth; and deliuereth them out of all their
troubles.</ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord is nigh
vnto them that are of a broken heart: and saueth such as be of a
contrite spirit.<note> Heb. to the broken of heart. , Heb. contrite of spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Many are the
afflictions of the righteous: but the Lord deliuereth him out of
them all.</ab>
<ab n="20">He keepeth all
his bones: not one of them is broken.</ab>
<ab n="21">Euill shall slay
the wicked: and they that hate the righteous shalbe
desolate.<note> Or, shalbe guilty.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">The Lord
redeemech the soule of his seruants: and none of them that trust in
him, shalbe desolate.</ab>



</div>