<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_45" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-44-45.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-45-48.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLV.</head>
<head>1 The maiestie and grace of Christs
kingdome. 10 The duetie of the Church, and the benefits
thereof.</head>


<fw>Christs kingdome.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician vpon Shoshannim, for the sonnes of Korah, Maschil: a song
of loues.] My heart is inditing a good matter: I speake of the
things which I haue made, touching the King: my tongue is the penne
of a ready writer.<note> Hebr. boyleth or bubleth vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thou art fairer
then the children of men: grace is powred into thy lips: therfore
God hath blessed thee for euer.</ab>
<ab n="3">Gird thy sword
vpon thy thigh, O most mightie: with thy glory and thy
maiestie.</ab>
<ab n="4">And in thy
maiestie ride prosperously, because of trueth and meekenes, and
righteousnesse: and thy right hand shall teach thee terrible
things.<note> Hebr. prosper thou, ride thou.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thine arrowes are
sharpe in the heart of the Kings enemies; whereby the people fall
vnder thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thy throne (O God)
is for euer and euer: the scepter of thy kingdome is a right
scepter.<note> Heb. 1.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thou louest
righteousnesse, and hatest wickednesse: therefore God, thy God,
hath anointed thee with the oyle of gladnesse aboue thy
fellowes.</ab>
<ab n="8">All thy garments
smell of myrrhe, and aloes, and cassia: out of the Iuorie palaces,
whereby they haue made thee glad.</ab>
<ab n="9">Kings daughters
were among thy honourable women: vpon thy right hand did stand the
Queene in golde of Ophir.</ab>
<ab n="10">Hearken (O
daughter) and consider, and incline thine eare; forget also thine
owne people, and thy fathers house.</ab>
<ab n="11">So shall the king
greatly desire thy beautie: for he is thy Lord, and worship thou
him.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the daughter
of Tyre shall be there with a gift, euen the rich among the people
shall intreate thy fauour.<note> Heb. thy face.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The kings
daughter is all glorious within; her clothing is of wrought
gold.</ab>
<ab n="14">She shall bee
brought vnto the king in raiment of needle worke: the virgins her
companions that followe her, shall be brought vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="15">With gladnesse
and reioycing shall they be brought: they shall enter into the
kings palace.</ab>

<fw>God our refuge.</fw>
<ab n="16">In stead of thy
fathers shall bee thy children, whom thou mayest make princes in
all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">I will make thy
name to bee remembred in all generations: therefore shall the
people praise thee for euer and euer.</ab>



</div>