<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_91" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-90-92.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XCI.</head>
<head>1 The state of the godly. 3 Their
safety. 9 Their habitation. 11 Their seruants. 14 Their friend,
with the effects of them all.</head>

<ab n="1">He that dwelleth
in the secret place of the most high: shall abide vnder the shadow
of the Almightie.<note> Heb. lodge.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I will say of the
Lord, He is my refuge, and my fortresse: my God, in him will I
trust.</ab>
<ab n="3">Surely he shall
deliuer thee from the snare of the fouler: and from the noisome
pestilence.</ab>
<ab n="4">Hee shall couer
thee with his feathers, and vnder his wings shalt thou trust: his
trueth shall bee thy shield and buckler.</ab>
<ab n="5">Thou shalt not bee
afraid for the terrour by night: nor for the arrow that flieth by
day:</ab>

<fw>Gods prouidence.</fw>
<ab n="6">Nor for the
pestilence that walketh in darknes: nor for the destruction, that
wasteth at noone-day.</ab>
<ab n="7">A thousand shall
fall at thy side, and ten thousand at thy right hand: but it shall
not come nigh thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">Onely with thine
eyes shalt thou behold: &amp; see the reward of the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="9">Because thou hast
made the Lord, which is my refuge, euen the most High, thy
habitation:</ab>
<ab n="10">There shall no
euill befall thee: neither shall any plague come nigh thy
dwelling.</ab>
<ab n="11">For hee shall
giue his Angels charge ouer thee: to keepe thee in all thy
wayes.<note> Matt. 4.6. luke 4.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">They shall beare
thee vp in their hands: lest thou dash thy foot against a
stone.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou shalt tread
vpon the Lion, and adder: the yong Lion and the dragon shalt thou
trample vnder feete.<note> Or, Aspe.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Because he hath
set his loue vpon me, therefore will I deliuer him: I wil set him
on high, because hee hath knowen my Name.</ab>
<ab n="15">He shall call
vpon me, and I will answere him: I will bee with him in trouble, I
will deliuer him, and honour him.</ab>
<ab n="16">With long life
wil I satisfie him: and shew him my saluation.<note> Heb. length of dayes.</note></ab>



</div>