<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_55" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-52-55.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-55-56.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. LV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in his prayer complaineth of
his fearefull case. 9 He prayeth against his enemies, of whose
wickednesse and trecherie he complaineth. 16 He comforteth himselfe
in Gods preseruation of him and confusion of his
enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician on Neginoth, Maschil. A Psalme of Dauid.] Giue eare to my
prayer, O God: and hide not thy selfe from my supplication.</ab>

<fw>Dauids complaint.</fw>
<ab n="2">Attend vnto me,
and heare me: I mourne in my complaint, and make a noise.</ab>
<ab n="3">Because of the
voyce of the enemie, because of the oppression of the wicked: for
they cast iniquitie vpon me, and in wrath they hate me.</ab>
<ab n="4">My heart is sore
pained within me: and the terrours of death are fallen vpon
me.</ab>
<ab n="5">Fearefulnesse and
trembling are come vpon me, and horrour hath ouerwhelmed
me.<note> Heb. couered me.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I said, O that
I had wings like a doue; for then would I flee away and be at
rest.</ab>
<ab n="7">Loe, then would I
wander farre off, and remaine in the wildernesse. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="8">I would hasten my
escape from the windie storme, and tempest.</ab>
<ab n="9">Destroy, O Lord,
and diuide their tongues: for I haue seene violence and strife in
the citie.</ab>
<ab n="10">Day and night
they goe about it vpon the walles thereof: mischiefe also and
sorrow are in the midst of it.</ab>
<ab n="11">Wickednesse is in
the midst thereof: deceite and guile depart not from her
streets.</ab>
<ab n="12">For it was not an
enemie that reproached me, then I could haue borne it, neither was
it hee that hated me, that did magnifie himselfe against me, then I
would haue hid my selfe from him.</ab>
<ab n="13">But it was thou,
a man, mine equal, my guide, and mine acquaintance.<note> Heb. a man according to my ranke.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Wee tooke sweet
counsell together, and walked vnto the house of God in
companie.<note> Heb. who sweetned counsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Let death seaze
vpon them, and let them goe downe quicke into hell: for wickednes
is in their dwellings, and among them.<note> Or, the graue.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">As for me, I will
call vpon God: and the Lord shall saue me.</ab>
<ab n="17">Euening and
morning, and at noone will I pray, and crie aloud: and he shall
heare my voyce.</ab>
<ab n="18">He hath deliuered
my soule in peace from the battell that was against me: for there
were many with me.</ab>
<ab n="19">God shall heare
and afflict them, euen he that abideth of old, Selah: because they
haue no changes, therefore they feare not God.<note> Or, with whom also there be no changes yet they feare not God.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">He hath put
foorth his handes against such as be at peace with him: he hath
broken his couenant.<note> Heb. hee hath profaned.</note></ab>

<fw>His confidence.</fw>
<ab n="21">The words of his
mouth were smoother then butter, but warre was in his heart: his
words were softer then oyle, yet were they drawen swords.</ab>
<ab n="22">Cast thy burden
vpon the Lord, and he shall sustaine thee: hee shall neuer suffer
the righteous to bee moued.<note> Psal.37.8 mat.6.25. luk. 12.22. 1.pet.5.7. , Or, gift.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But thou, O God,
shalt bring them downe into the pit of destruction: Bloody and
deceitfull men shall not liue out halfe their dayes, but I will
trust in thee.<note> Heb. men of bloods and deceit. , Hebr. shal not halfe their dayes.</note></ab>



</div>