<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_78" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-78-78.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-78-79.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXVIII.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation both to learne and
to preach the Law of God. 9 The story of Gods wrath against the
incredulous and disobedient. 67 The Israelites being reiected, God
chose Iudah, Sion, and Dauid.</head>


<fw>Gods wonders in Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="1">Giue eare, O my
people, to my Lawe: incline your eares to the wordes of my
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="2">I will open my
mouth in a parable: I wil vtter darke sayings of old:<note> Psal.49.5. matth. 13. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Which we haue
heard, &amp; knowen: and our fathers haue told vs.</ab>
<ab n="4">We will not hide
them from their children, shewing to the generation to come, the
praises of the Lord: and his strength, and his wonderful works that
he hath done.</ab>
<ab n="5">For he established
a Testimony in Iacob, and appointed a Law in Israel, which he
commaunded our fathers: that they should make them knowen to their
children.<note> Deut.4. 9. and 6.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">That the
generation to come might know them, euen the children which should
be borne: who should arise and declare them to their
children:</ab>
<ab n="7">That they might
set their hope in God, and not forget the works of God: but keepe
his Commandements,</ab>
<ab n="8">And might not bee
as their fathers, a stubborne and rebellious generation, a
generation that set not their heart aright: and whose spirit was
not stedfast with God.<note> Hebr. that prepared not their heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The children of
Ephraim being armed, and carying bowes, turned backe in the day of
battell.<note> Hebr. throwing foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They kept not the
couenant of God: and refused to walke in his Law:</ab>
<ab n="11">And forgat his
workes: and his wonders that he had shewed them.</ab>
<ab n="12">Marueilous things
did he in the sight of their fathers: in the land of Egypt, in the
field of Zoan.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hee diuided the
Sea, and caused them to passe through: and he made the waters to
stand as an heape.<note> Exod. 14. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">In the day time
also he led them with a cloud: and all the night with a light of
fire.<note> Exod. 13. 21. and 14. 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hee claue the
rockes in the wildernes: and gaue them drinke as out of the great
depthes.<note> Exod. 17. 6. num.20. 10. psal. 105.44.1. cor.10.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Hee brought
streames also out of the rocke, and caused waters to runne downe
like riuers.</ab>
<ab n="17">And they sinned
yet more against him: by prouoking the most High in the
wildernes.</ab>

<fw>Gods wonders in Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="18">And they tempted
God in their heart: by asking meat for their lust.</ab>
<ab n="19">Yea, they spake
against God: they said, Can God furnish a table in the
wildernes?<note> Num. 11. 4. , Heb. order.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, he smote
the rocke, that the waters gushed out, &amp; the streames
ouerflowed; can he giue bread also? can he prouide flesh for his
people?<note> Exod. 17. 6. num. 20. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Therefore the
Lord heard this, and was wroth, so a fire was kindled against
Iacob: and anger also came vp against Israel.</ab>
<ab n="22">Because they
beleeued not in God: and trusted not in his saluation:</ab>
<ab n="23">Though he had
commanded the cloudes from aboue: and opened the doores of
heauen:</ab>
<ab n="24">And had rained
downe Manna vpon them to eate, and had giuen them of the corne of
heauen.<note> Exod. 16. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Man did eate
Angels food: hee sent them meat to the full.<note> Iohn 6 31. , Or, euery one did eat the bread of the mighty.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">He caused an East
wind to blow in the heauen: and by his power hee brought in the
South wind.<note> Hebr. to goe.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">He rained flesh
also vpon them as dust: and feathered soules like as the sand of
the sea.<note> Hebr. foule of wing.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And hee let it
fall in the midst of their campe, round about their
habitations.</ab>
<ab n="29">So they did eate,
&amp; were well filled: for he gaue them their owne desire.</ab>
<ab n="30">They were not
estranged from their lust: but while their meate was yet in their
mouthes,<note> Num. 11. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">The wrath of God
came vpon them, and slew the fattest of them: and smote downe the
chosen men of Israel.<note> Heb. made to bow. , Or, yong men.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For all this they
sinned still: and beleeued not for his wondrous works.</ab>
<ab n="33">Therefore their
dayes did he consume in vanitie, and their yeeres in
trouble.</ab>
<ab n="34">When hee slew
them, then they sought him: and they returned, and inquired early
after God.</ab>
<ab n="35">And they
remembred that God was their rocke: and the high God, their
redeemer.</ab>
<ab n="36">Neuerthelesse
they did flatter him with their mouth: and they lyed vnto him with
their tongues.</ab>
<ab n="37">For their heart
was not right with him: neither were they stedfast in his
couenant.</ab>

<fw>Egypt plagued.</fw>
<ab n="38">But hee being
full of compassion, forgaue their iniquity, and destroyed them not;
yea many a time turned he his anger away, and did not stirre vp all
his wrath.</ab>
<ab n="39">For he remembred
that they were but flesh; a wind that passeth away, and commeth not
againe.</ab>
<ab n="40">How oft did they
prouoke him in the wildernesse: and grieue him in the
desert?<note> Or, rebell against him.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">Yea they turned
backe and tempted God: and limited the holy one of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="42">They remembred
not his hand: nor the day when hee deliuered them from the
enemie:<note> Or, from affliction.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">How he had
wrought his signes in Egypt: and his wonders in the field of
Zoan:<note> Heb. set.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And had turned
their riuers into blood: and their flouds, that they could not
drinke.<note> Exod.7. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">Hee sent diuers
sorts of flies among them, which deuoured them: and frogges which
destroyed them.<note> Exod.8. 24. &amp; 8.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">He gaue also
their increase vnto the caterpiller: and their labour vnto the
locust.<note> Exod. 10. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="47">He destroyed
their vines with haile: and their Sycomore trees with
frost.<note> Exod.9. 23. , Heb. killed. , Or, great haile stones.</note></ab>
<ab n="48">He gaue vp their
cattel also to the haile: and their flockes to hot
thunder-bolts.<note> Heb. he shut vp. , Or, lightnings.</note></ab>
<ab n="49">He cast vpon them
the fiercenesse of his anger, wrath and indignation, and trouble:
by sending euill angels among them.</ab>
<ab n="50">He made a way to
his anger, hee spared not their soule from death: but gaue their
life ouer to the pestilence.<note> Heb. he waighed a path. , Or, their beasts, to the murreine, Exod.9.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="51">And smote all the
first borne in Egypt: the chiefe of their strength in the
tabernacles of Ham:<note> Exod.12. 29. &amp; 9.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="52">But made his owne
people to goe forth like sheepe: and guided them in the wildernesse
like a flocke.</ab>
<ab n="53">And he led them
on safely, so that they feared not: but the sea ouerwhelmed their
enemies.<note> Exod.14. 27. &amp; 15. 10. , Heb. couered.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">And he brought
them to the border of his sanctuarie: euen to this mountaine which
his right hand had purchased.</ab>
<ab n="55">He cast out the
heathen also before them, and diuided them an inheritance by line:
and made the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tents.<note> Iosu.13.7.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauid chosen.</fw>
<ab n="56">Yet they tempted
and prouoked the most high God: and kept not his
testimonies:</ab>
<ab n="57">But turned backe,
and dealt vnfaithfully like their fathers: they were turned aside
like a deceitfull bowe.</ab>
<ab n="58">For they prouoked
him to anger with their high places: and moued him to ielousie with
their grauen images.<note> Deut.32. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">When God heard
this, hee was wroth, and greatly abhorred Israel:</ab>
<ab n="60">So that he
forsooke the tabernacle of Shiloh: the tent which he placed among
men,<note> 1.King. 4.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="61">And deliuered his
strength into captiuitie: and his glory into the enemies
hand.</ab>
<ab n="62">He gaue his
people ouer also vnto the sword: and was wroth with his
inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="63">The fire consumed
their young men: and their maidens were not giuen to
mariage.<note> Heb. praised.</note></ab>
<ab n="64">Their priests
fell by the sword: and their widowes made no lamentation.</ab>
<ab n="65">Then the Lord
awaked as one out of sleepe: and like a mighty man that shouteth by
reason of wine.</ab>
<ab n="66">And he smote his
enemies in the hinder parts: he put them to a perpetuall
reproch.</ab>
<ab n="67">Moreouer he
refused the tabernacle of Ioseph: and chose not the tribe of
Ephraim.</ab>
<ab n="68">But chose the
tribe of Iudah: the mount Sion which he loued.</ab>
<ab n="69">And he built his
sanctuarie like high palaces: like the earth which he hath
established for euer.<note> Heb. founded.</note></ab>
<ab n="70">He chose Dauid
also his seruant, and tooke him from the sheepe-folds:<note> 1.Sam.16 11. 2.Sam. 7.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="71">From following
the ewes great with young, hee brought him to feed Iacob his
people, and Israel his inheritance.<note> 2.Sam.5. 2. 1. Chron. 11.2. , Heb. from after.</note></ab>
<ab n="72">So he fed them
according to the integritie of his heart: and guided them by the
skilfulnesse of his hands.</ab>



</div>