<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_72" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-71-72.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-72-73.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid praying for Solomon, sheweth
the goodnesse and glory of his, in type, and in trueth, of Christes
kingdome. 18 Hee blesseth God.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme for
Solomon.] Giue the King thy Iudgements, O God, and thy
Righteousnesse vnto the Kings sonne.</ab>
<ab n="2">Hee shall iudge
thy people with righteousnesse, and thy poore with
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="3">The mountaines
shal bring peace to the people, and the litle hils, by
righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="4">Hee shall iudge
the poore of the people, he shall saue the children of the needie,
and shallbreake in pieces the oppressour.</ab>
<ab n="5">They shall feare
thee as long as the Sunne &amp; Moone indure, throughout all
generations.</ab>
<ab n="6">Hee shall come
downe like raine vpon the mowen grasse: as showres that water the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">In his dayes shall
the righteous flourish: and abundance of peace so long as the Moone
endureth.<note> Hebr. till there be no moone.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He shall haue
dominion also from sea to sea, and from the riuer, vnto the ends of
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="9">They that dwell in
the wildernesse shall bowe before him: and his enemies shall licke
the dust.</ab>
<ab n="10">The kings of
Tarshish and of the Isles shall bring presents: the Kings of Sheba
and Seba shalloffer gifts.</ab>
<ab n="11">Yea, all Kings
shall fall downe before him: all nations shall serue him.</ab>
<ab n="12">For hee shall
deliuer the needy when he crieth: the poore also, and him that hath
no helper.</ab>

<fw>The description of the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="13">He shal spare the
poore and needy, and shall saue the soules of the needy.</ab>
<ab n="14">He shall redeeme
their soule from deceit and violence: and precious shall their
blood be in hissight.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he shall
liue, and to him shalbe giuen of the gold of Sheba; prayer also
shalbe made for himcontinually, and daily shall he be
praised.<note> Heb. one shall giue.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">There shalbe an
handfull of corne in the earth vpon the top of the mountaines; the
fruit thereofshall shake like Lebanon, and they of the citie shall
flourish like grasse of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">His name shall
endure for euer: his name shalbe continued as long as the sunne:
and men shalbeblessed in him; all nations shall call him
blessed.<note> Heb. shall be. , Heb. shalbe as a sonne to continue his fathers name for euer.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Blessed be the
Lord God, the God of Israel, who only doth wonderous
things.</ab>
<ab n="19">And blessed be
his glorious name for euer, and let the whole earth be filled with
his glory. Amen,and Amen.</ab>
<ab n="20">The prayers of
Dauid the sonne of Iesse, are ended.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>