<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_132" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-129-132.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-132-136.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXXXII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in his prayer commendeth
vnto God the religious care he had for the Arke. 8 His prayer at
the remouing of the Arke, 11 with a repetition of Gods
promises.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Song of
degrees.] Lord remember Dauid, and all his afflictions:</ab>
<ab n="2">How he sware vnto
the Lord, and vowed vnto the mightie God of Iacob.</ab>
<ab n="3">Surely I will not
come into the tabernacle of my house: nor goe vp into my
bed.</ab>
<ab n="4">I will not giue
sleepe to mine eyes: or slumber to mine eyelids,</ab>
<ab n="5">Untill I finde
out a place for the Lord: an habitation for the mightie God of
Iacob.<note> Heb. habitations,</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Loe, wee heard of
it at Ephrata: we found it in the fields of the wood.</ab>
<ab n="7">We will goe into
his tabernacles: we will worship at his footstoole.</ab>
<ab n="8">Arise, O Lord,
into thy rest: thou, and the Arke of thy strength.<note> 2. Chron. 6.41. num. 10.35.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Let thy Priestes
be clothed with righteousnesse: and let thy saints shout for
ioy.</ab>
<ab n="10">For thy seruant
Dauids sake: turne not away the face of thine Anointed.</ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord hath
sworne in trueth vnto Dauid, hee will not turne from it; of the
fruit of thy body will I set vpon thy throne.<note> 2. Sam.7. 12. 1. king. 8.25. 2.chr. 6.16. luke 1. 9. acts 2.30. , Heb. thy belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">If thy children
will keepe my couenant and my testimonie, that I shall teach them;
their children also shall sit vpon thy throne for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="13">For the Lord
hath chosen Zion: he hath desired it for his habitation.</ab>
<ab n="14">This is my rest
for euer: here will I dwell, for I haue desired it.</ab>
<ab n="15">I will
abundantly blesse her prouision: I will satisfie her poore with
bread.<note> Or, surely.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">I will also
clothe her priests with saluation: and her Saints shall shout aloud
for ioy.</ab>
<ab n="17">There will I
make the horne of Dauid to budde: I haue ordained a lampe for mine
Anointed.<note> Luc.1.69. , Or, candle.</note></ab>

<fw>Brotherly vnitie.</fw>
<ab n="18">His enemies will
I clothe with shame: but vpon himselfe shall his crowne
flourish.</ab>



</div>