<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_49" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-48-50.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLIX.</head>
<head>1 An earnest perswasion to build the
faith of Resurrection, not on worldly power, but on God. 16 Worldly
prosperity is not to be admired.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, a Psalme for the sonnes of Korah.] Heare this, all yee
people, giue eare all yee inhabitants of the world:</ab>
<ab n="2">Both low, and
high, rich and poore together.</ab>
<ab n="3">My mouth shall
speake of wisedome: and the meditation of my heart shalbe of
vnderstanding.</ab>
<ab n="4">I will incline
mine eare to a parable; I will open my darke saying vpon the
harpe.<note> Mat.13. 35. psal. 78.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Wherefore should I
feare in the daies of euill, when the iniquitie of my heeles shall
compasse me about?</ab>
<ab n="6">They that trust in
their wealth, and boast themselues in the multitude of their
riches:</ab>
<ab n="7">None of them can
by any meanes redeeme his brother, nor giue to God a ransome for
him:</ab>
<ab n="8">(For the
redemption of their soule is precious, and it ceaseth for
euer.)</ab>
<ab n="9">That he should
still liue for euer, and not see corruption.</ab>
<ab n="10">For he seeth that
wise men die, likewise the foole, and the brutish person perish,
and leaue their wealth to others.</ab>
<ab n="11">Their inward
thought is, that their houses shall continue for euer, and their
dwelling places to all generations; they call their lands after
their owne names.<note> Heb. to generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Neuerthelesse man
being in honour abideth not: he is like the beastes that
perish.</ab>
<ab n="13">This their way is
their follie; yet their posteritie approue their sayings.
Selah.<note> Heb. delight in their mouth.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods Maiestie.</fw>
<ab n="14">Like sheepe they
are layd in the graue, death shall feede on them; and the vpright
shall haue dominion ouer them in the morning, and their beauty
shall consume in the graue, from their dwelling.<note> Or, strength , Or, the graue being an habitation to euery one of them.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But God will
redeeme my soule from the power of the graue; for he shall receiue
me. Selah.<note> Heb. from the hand of the graue. , Or, hell.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Be not thou
afraid when one is made rich, when the glory of his house is
increased.</ab>
<ab n="17">For when he
dieth, he shall carry nothing away: his glory shall not descend
after him.<note> Iob.27. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Though whiles he
liued, he blessed his soule: and men will praise thee, when thou
doest well to thy selfe.<note> Heb. in his life.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Hee shall goe to
the generation of his fathers, they shall neuer see
light.<note> Heb. the soule shall goe.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Man that is in
honour and vnderstandeth not, is like the beasts that
perish.</ab>



</div>