<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_90" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-89-90.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-90-92.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XC.</head>
<head>1 Moses setting foorth Gods
prouidence, 3 complaineth, of humane fragility, 7 diuine
chastisements, 10 and breuity of life. 12 He prayeth for the
knowledge and sencible experience of Gods good
prouidence.</head>

<ab n="1">[A prayer of Moses
the man of God.] Lord, thou hast bene our dwelling place in all
generations.<note> Heb. in generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Before the
mountaines were broughtforth, or euer thou hadst formed the earth
and the world: euen from euerlasting to euerlasting thou art
God.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou turnest man
to destruction: and sayest, Returne yee children of men.</ab>
<ab n="4">For a thousand
yeeres in thy sight are but as yesterday when it is past: and as a
watch in the night.<note> 2.Pet.3.8. , Or, when he hath passed them.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Thou carriest them
away as with a flood, they are as a sleepe: in the morning they are
like grasse which groweth vp.<note> Or, is changed.</note></ab>

<fw>Mans life short.</fw>
<ab n="6">In the morning it
flourisheth, and groweth vp: in the euening it is cut downe, and
withereth.</ab>
<ab n="7">For we are
consumed by thine anger: and by thy wrath are we troubled.</ab>
<ab n="8">Thou hast set our
iniquities before thee: our secret sinnes in the light of thy
countenance.</ab>
<ab n="9">For all our dayes
are passed away in thy wrath: we spend our yeeres as a tale that is
told.<note> Hebr. turned away. , Or, as a meditation.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The dayes of our
yeres are threescore yeeres and ten, and if by reason of strength
they be fourescore yeeres, yet is their strength labour and sorrow:
for it is soone cut off, and we flie away.<note> Hebr. as for the dayes of our yeeres, in them are seuentie yeeres.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Who knoweth the
power of thine anger? euen according to thy feare, so is thy
wrath.</ab>
<ab n="12">So teach vs to
number our daies: that wee may apply our hearts vnto
wisedome.<note> Heb. cause to come.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Returne (O Lord)
how long? and let it repent thee concerning thy seruants.</ab>
<ab n="14">O satisfie vs
early with thy mercie: that we may reioyce, and be glad all our
dayes.</ab>
<ab n="15">Make vs glad
according to the dayes wherein thou hast afflicted vs: and the
yeeres wherein we haue seene euil.</ab>
<ab n="16">Let thy worke
appeare vnto thy seruants: and thy glory vnto their
children.</ab>
<ab n="17">And let the
beautie of the Lord our God be vpon vs, and establish thou the
worke of our hands vpon vs: yea, the work of our hands establish
thou it.</ab>



</div>