<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_118" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-115-118.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-118-119.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXVIII.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation to praise God for
his mercie. 5 The Psalmist by his experience sheweth how good it is
to trust in God. 19 Under the type of the Psalmist, the comming of
Christ in his kingdome is expressed.</head>

<ab n="1">O giue thankes
vnto the Lord, for hee is good: because his mercie endureth for
euer.<note> Psal. 106. 1. and 107. 1. &amp; 136. 1. 1.chron.16. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Let Israel now
say: that his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="3">Let the house of
Aaron now say: that his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="4">Let them now that
feare the Lord, say: that his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="5">I called vpon the
Lord in distresse: the Lord answered me, and set me in a large
place.<note> Hebr. out of distresse.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord is on my
side, I will not feare: What can man doe vnto mee?<note> Heb.13.6. psal.56.4, 11. , Hebr. for me.</note></ab>

<fw>The cornerstone.</fw>
<ab n="7">The Lord taketh
my part with them that helpe me: therfore shall I see my desire
vpon them that hate me.</ab>
<ab n="8">It is better to
trust in the Lord: then to put confidence in man.</ab>
<ab n="9">It is better to
trust in the Lord: then to put confidence in Princes.<note> Psal. 146. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">All nations
compassed me about: but in the Name of the Lord, will I destroy
them.<note> Hebr. cut them off.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They compassed
mee about, yea they compassed mee about: but in the Name of the
Lord, I will destroy them.</ab>
<ab n="12">They compassed
mee about like Bees, they are quenched as the fire of thornes: for
in the Name of the Lord I wil destroy them.<note> Hebr. cut downe.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Thou hast thrust
sore at mee that I might fall: but the Lord helped mee.</ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord is my
strength and song: and is become my saluation.<note> Exod. 15. 2.isa. 12. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The voice of
reioycing and saluation is in the tabernacles of the righteous: the
Right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.</ab>
<ab n="16">The Right hand
of the Lord is exalted: the Right hand of the Lord doeth
valiantly.</ab>
<ab n="17">I shall not die,
but liue: and declare the workes of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord hath
chastened me sore: but he hath not giuen me ouer vnto
death.</ab>
<ab n="19">Open to mee the
gates of righteousnesse: I will goe into them, and I will praise
the Lord:</ab>
<ab n="20">This gate of the
Lord: into which the righteous shall enter.</ab>
<ab n="21">I will praise
thee, for thou hast heard mee: and art become my saluation.</ab>
<ab n="22">The stone which
the builders refused: is become the head stone of the
corner.<note> Mat.21.42 mar. 12. 10. luk. 20. 17. acts 4. 11. 1.pet. 2.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">This is the
Lords doing: it is marueilous in our eyes.<note> Heb. this is from the LORD.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">This is the day
which the Lord hath made: we will reioyce, and be glad in
it.</ab>
<ab n="25">Saue now, I
beseech thee, O Lord: O Lord, I beseech thee, send now
prosperitie.</ab>
<ab n="26">Blessed be he
that commeth in the Name of the Lord: wee haue blessed you out of
the house of the Lord.<note> Mat. 21,9.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">God is the Lord,
which hath shewed vs light, bind the sacrifice with cords: euen
vnto the horns of the Altar.</ab>

<fw>Who are blessed.</fw>
<ab n="28">Thou art my God,
and I will praise thee: thou art my God, I will exalt thee.</ab>
<ab n="29">O giue thanks
vnto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for
euer.</ab>



</div>