<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-32-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 God is to be praysed for his
goodnesse, 6 for his power, 12 and for his prouidence. 20
Confidence is to be placed in God.</head>

<ab n="1">Reioyce in the
Lord, O yee righteous: for prayse is comely for the
vpright.</ab>
<ab n="2">Praise the Lord
with harp: sing vnto him with the Psalterie, and an instrument of
ten strings.</ab>
<ab n="3">Sing vnto him a
new song; play skilfully with a loud noise.</ab>
<ab n="4">For the word of
the Lord is right: and all his workes are done in trueth.</ab>
<ab n="5">Hee loueth
righteousnesse and iudgement: the earth is ful of the goodnesse of
the Lord.<note> Psal. 119. 64. , Or, mercy.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">By the word of the
Lord were the heauens made: and all the host of them, by the breath
of his mouth.<note> Gen. 1.6. &amp; 7.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods prouidence.</fw>
<ab n="7">He gathereth the
waters of the sea together, as an heape: he layeth vp the depth in
storehouses.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let all the earth
feare the Lord: let all the inhabitants of the world stand in awe
of him.</ab>
<ab n="9">For he spake, and
it was done: he commanded, and it stood fast.</ab>
<ab n="10">The Lord bringeth
the counsell of the heathen to nought: he maketh the deuices of the
people, of none effect.<note> Esa. 19. 3. , Heb. maketh frustrate.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">The counsaile of
the Lord standeth for euer, the thoughts of his heart to all
generations.<note> Prou. 19. 21. Esa.46.10. , Heb. to generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Blessed is the
nation, whose God is the Lord: and the people, whom he hath chosen
for his owne inheritance.<note> Psal.65.4 &amp; 144. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The Lord looketh
from heauen: he beholdeth all the sonnes of men.</ab>
<ab n="14">From the place of
his habitation, he looketh vpon all the inhabitants of the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="15">He fashioneth
their hearts alike: he considereth all their workes.</ab>
<ab n="16">There is no king
saued by the multitude of an hoste: a mightie man is not deliuered
by much strength.</ab>
<ab n="17">An horse is a
vaine thing for safetie: neither shall he deliuer any by his great
strength.</ab>
<ab n="18">Behold, the eye
of the Lord is vpon them that feare him: vpon them that hope in his
mercy:<note> Iob.36.7. &amp; 34.14. 1.Pet.3.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">To deliuer their
soule from death, and to keepe them aliue in famine.</ab>
<ab n="20">Our soule waiteth
for the Lord: he is our helpe, and our shield.</ab>
<ab n="21">For our heart
shall reioyce in him: because we haue trusted in his holy
name.</ab>
<ab n="22">Let thy mercy (O
Lord) be vpon vs: according as we hope in thee.</ab>



</div>