<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_143" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-140-143.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-143-145.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXLIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth for fauour in
Iudgment. 3 He complaineth of his griefes. 5 He strengthneth his
faith by meditation and prayer. 7 Hee prayeth for grace, 9 for
deliuerance, 10 for sanctification, 12 for destruction of his
enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid.] Heare my prayer, O Lord, giue eare to my supplications: in
thy faithfulnesse answere me, and in thy righteousnes.</ab>

<fw>Mans life is but vanitie.</fw>
<ab n="2">And enter not
into iudgement with thy seruant: for in thy sight shall no man
liuing be iustified.<note> Exod. 34. 7. rom.3.20 galat.2.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For the enemie
hath persecuted my soule, he hath smitten my life downe to the
ground: hee hath made mee to dwell in darkenesse, as those that
haue bene long dead.</ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore is my
spirit ouerwhelmed within me: my heart within me is
desolate.</ab>
<ab n="5">I remember the
dayes of old, I meditate on all thy workes: I muse on the worke of
thy hands.</ab>
<ab n="6">I stretch forth
my hands vnto thee: my soule thirsteth after thee, as a thirstie
land, Selah.</ab>
<ab n="7">Heare me
speedily, O Lord, my spirit faileth, hide not thy face from mee:
lest I be like vnto them that goe downe into the pit.<note> Or, for I am become like. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Cause mee to
heare thy louing kindnesse in the morning, for in thee doe I trust,
cause mee to knowe the way wherein I should walke: for I lift vp my
soule vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">Deliuer mee, O
Lord, from mine enemies: I flie vnto thee to hide me.<note> Heb. hid me with thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Teach me to doe
thy will, for thou art my God, thy spirit is good: leade me into
the land of vprightnesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">Quicken me, O
Lord, for thy names sake: for thy righteousnesse sake bring my
soule out of trouble.</ab>
<ab n="12">And of thy mercy
cut off mine enemies, and destroy all them that afflict my soule:
for I am thy seruant.</ab>



</div>