<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_32" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-32-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXII.</head>
<head>1 Blessednesse consisteth in
remission of sinnes. 3 Confession of sinnes giueth ease to the
conscience. 8 Gods promises bring ioy.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid, Maschil.] Blessed is he whose transgression is forgiuen,
whose sinne is couered.<note> Rom.4.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Blessed is the man
vnto whom the Lord imputeth not iniquitie: and in whose spirit
there is no guile.</ab>

<fw>Dauids confession.</fw>
<ab n="3">When I kept
silence, my bones waxed old; through my roaring all the day
long.</ab>
<ab n="4">For day and night
thy hand was heauy vpon me: my moisture is turned into the drought
of summer. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="5">I acknowledged my
sin vnto thee, and mine iniquitie haue I not hid: I said, I will
confesse my transgressions vnto the Lord; and thou forgauest the
iniquitie of my sinne. Selah.<note> Prou.28. 13. Esa.95.24. I.Iohn.1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For this shall
euery one that is godly pray vnto thee, in a time when thou mayest
bee found: surely in the floods of great waters, they shall not
come nigh vnto him.<note> Heb. in a time of finding.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thou art my hiding
place, thou shalt preserue mee from trouble: thou shalt compasse me
about with songs of deliuerance. Selah.<note> Psal.9.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">I will instruct
thee, and teach thee in the way which thou shalt goe: I will guide
thee with mine eye.<note> Heb. I will counsel thee, mine eye shall be vpon thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Be yee not as the
horse, or as the mule which haue no vnderstanding: whose mouth must
be held in with bit and bridle, least they come neere vnto
thee.<note> Pro.26.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Many sorrowes
shall be to the wicked: but he that trusteth in the Lord, mercy
shall compasse him about.</ab>
<ab n="11">Be glad in the
Lord, and reioyce yee righteous: and shout for ioy all ye that are
vpright in heart.</ab>



</div>