<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-19-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 The creatures shew Gods glory. 7
The word his Grace. 12 Dauid prayeth for Grace.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, A Psalme of Dauid.] The heauens declare the glory of God:
and the firmament sheweth his handy worke.<note> Gen.1.6.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods works.</fw>
<ab n="2">Day vnto day
vttereth speach, and night vnto night sheweth knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="3">There is no speach
nor language, where their voyce is not heard.<note> Or, without these their voyce is heard.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Their line is gone
out through all the earth, and their words to the end of the world:
In them hath he set a tabernacle for the Sunne.<note> Hebr. without their voyce heard. , Rom. 10. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Which is as a
bridegrome comming out of his chamber, and reioyceth as a strong
man to runne a race.</ab>
<ab n="6">His going forth is
from the end of the heauen, and his circuite vnto the ends of it:
and there is nothing hidde from the heat thereof.</ab>
<ab n="7">The Law of the
Lord is perfect, conuerting the soule: the testimonie of the Lord
is sure, making wise the simple.<note> Or, doctrine. , Or, restoring.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The Statutes of
the Lord are right, reioycing the heart: the Commandement of the
Lord is pure, inlightning the eyes.</ab>
<ab n="9">The feare of the
Lord is cleane, enduring for euer: the Iudgements of the Lord are
true, and righteous altogether.<note> Hebr. trueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">More to bee
desired are they then gold, yea, then much fine gold: sweeter also
then hony, and the hony combe.<note> Psal.119. 72. &amp; 127 and 103. prou. 8.19. , Hebr. the dropping of hony combes.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Moreouer by them
is thy seruant warned: and in keeping of them there is great
reward.</ab>
<ab n="12">Who can
vnderstand his errours? cleanse thou me from secret faults.</ab>
<ab n="13">Keepe back thy
seruant also from presumptuous sinnes, let them not haue dominion
ouer me: then shall I be vpright, and I shalbe innocent from the
great transgression.<note> Or, much.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Let the words of
my mouth, and the meditation of my heart, bee acceptable in thy
sight, O Lord my strength, and my redeemer.<note> Hebr. my rocke.</note></ab>



</div>