<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_105" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-104-105.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-105-106.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. CV.</head>
<head>1 An exhortation to praise God, and
to seeke out his workes. 7 The story of Gods prouidence ouer
Abraham, 16 Ouer Ioseph, 23 Ouer Iacob in Egypt, 26 Ouer Moses
deliuering the Israelites, 37 Ouer the Israelites brought out of
Egypt, fed in the wildernesse, and planted in Canaan.</head>


<fw>Gods wisedome, and prouidence.</fw>
<ab n="1">O giue thankes
vnto the Lord, call vpon his name: make knowen his deeds among the
people.<note> 1. Chron. 16.8. Esay. 12.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Sing vnto him;
sing Psalmes vnto him: talke yee of all his wondrous
workes.</ab>
<ab n="3">Glory yee in his
holy name: let the heart of them reioyce, that seeke the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">Seeke the Lord,
and his strength: seeke his face euermore.</ab>
<ab n="5">Remember his
maruellous workes, that hee hath done: his wonders, and the
iudgements of his mouth,</ab>
<ab n="6">O yee seede of
Abraham his seruant: yee children of Iacob his chosen.</ab>
<ab n="7">He is the Lord
our God: his iudgements are in all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="8">He hath remembred
his couenant for euer: the word which he commanded to a thousand
generations.</ab>
<ab n="9">Which couenant he
made with Abraham, and his oath vnto Isaac:<note> Gen.17. 2. &amp; 22. 16. and 26. 3. &amp; 28. 13. &amp; 35.11. Luc.1.7,73 Heb.6.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And confirmed
the same vnto Iacob for a law: and to Israel for an euerlasting
couenant:</ab>
<ab n="11">Saying, Unto
thee will I giue the land of Canaan: the lot of your
inheritance.<note> Gen.13. 15. &amp; 15. 10. , Heb. the corde.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">When they were
but a few men in number: yea very few, &amp; strangers in
it.</ab>
<ab n="13">When they went
from one nation to another: from one kingdome to another
people.</ab>
<ab n="14">He suffred no
man to doe them wrong: yea he reproued kings for their
sakes:</ab>
<ab n="15">Saying, Touch
not mine anointed; and doe my Prophets no harme.</ab>
<ab n="16">Moreouer hee
called for a famine vpon the land: he brake the whole staffe of
bread.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hee sent a man
before them: euen Ioseph, who was sold for a seruant.<note> Gen.37. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Whose feete they
hurt with fetters: he was layd in iron.<note> Gen.39. 20. , Heb. his soule came into yron.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Untill the time
that his word came: the word of the Lord tried him.</ab>
<ab n="20">The king sent
and loosed him: euen the ruler of the people, and let him goe
free.<note> Gen.41. 14.</note></ab>

<fw>Plagues of Egypt.</fw>
<ab n="21">Hee made him
lord of his house: and ruler of all his substance:<note> Gen.41. 40. , Hebr. possession.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">To binde his
princes at his pleasure: and teach his Senatours wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="23">Israel also came
into Egypt: and Iacob soiourned in the land of Ham.<note> Gene. 46. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And hee
increased his people greatly: and made them stronger then their
enemies.</ab>
<ab n="25">He turned their
heart to hate his people: to deale subtilly with his
seruants.<note> Exod. 1. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Hee sent Moses
his seruant: and Aaron whom he had chosen.<note> Exod. 3. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">They shewed his
signes among them: and wonders in the land of Ham.<note> Exod. 7. 9. , Heb. words of his signes.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Hee sent
darknesse, and made it darke: and they rebelled not against his
word.<note> Exod. 10. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Hee turned their
waters into blood: and slew their fish.<note> Exod. 7. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">The land brought
foorth frogs in abundance: in the chambers of their
kings.<note> Exod.8.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">He spake, and
there came diuers sorts of flies: and lice in all their
coasts.<note> Exod.8. 17. and 24.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Hee gaue them
haile for raine: and flaming fire in their laud.<note> Exod. 9. 23. , Hebr. he gaue their raine, haile.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">Hee smote their
Uines also, and their figge trees: and brake the trees of their
coastes.</ab>
<ab n="34">He spake, and
the locusts came: and catterpillers, and that without
number,<note> Exod. 10. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">And did eate vp
all the herbes in their land: and deuoured the fruite of their
ground.</ab>
<ab n="36">Hee smote also
all the first borne in their land: the chiefe of all their
strength.<note> Exod. 12. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Hee brought them
foorth also with siluer and gold: and there was not one feeble
person among their tribes.<note> Exod. 12. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="38">Egypt was glad
when they departed: for the feare of them fell vpon
them.<note> Exod.12. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="39">He spread a
cloud for a couering: and fire to giue light in the
night.<note> Exod.13. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="40">The people
asked, and he brought quailes: and satisfied them with the bread of
heauen.<note> Exod. 16. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="41">He opened the
rocke, and the waters gushed out: they ranne in the dry places like
a riuer.<note> Exod.17. 6. num.20. 11. 1.cor. 10.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="42">For he remembred
his holy promise: and Abraham his seruant.</ab>

<fw>Confession of sinnes.</fw>
<ab n="43">And he brought
forth his people with ioy: and his chosen with
gladnesse:<note> Heb. singing.</note></ab>
<ab n="44">And gaue them
the lands of the heathen: and they inherited the labour of the
people:<note> Iosh.13. 17. deut.6. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="45">That they might
obserue his statutes, and keepe his Lawes, Praise ye the
Lord.</ab>



</div>