<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_109" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-107-109.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-109-112.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CIX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid complayning of his
slanderous enemies, vnder the person of Iudas deuoteth them. 16 He
sheweth their sinne. 21 Complayning of his owne misery, hee prayeth
for helpe. 29 He promiseth thankfulnesse.</head>


<fw>Dauids prayers.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, A Psalme of Dauid.] Hold not thy peace, O God of my
praise.</ab>
<ab n="2">For the mouth of
the wicked, and the mouth of the deceitfull are opened against mee:
they haue spoken against me with a lying tongue.<note> Hebr. mouth of deceit. , Hebr. haue opened themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">They compassed
mee about also with wordes of hatred: and fought against me without
a cause.</ab>
<ab n="4">For my loue, they
are my aduersaries: but I giue my selfe vnto prayer.</ab>
<ab n="5">And they haue
rewarded me euill for good: and hatred for my loue.</ab>
<ab n="6">Set thou a wicked
man ouer him: and let Satan stand at his right hand.<note> Or an aduersary.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">When he shall be
iudged, let him be condemned: and let his prayer become
sinne.<note> Hebr. goe out guiltie, or wicked.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Let his dayes be
few: and let another take his office.<note> Act.1.20. , Or, charge.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Let his children
bee fatherlesse: and his wife a widow.</ab>
<ab n="10">Let his children
bee continually vagabonds, &amp; begge: let them seeke their bread
also out of their desolate places.</ab>
<ab n="11">Let the
extortioner catch all that he hath: and let the strangers spoile
his labour.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let there be
none to extend mercy vnto him: neither let there be any to fauour
his fatherlesse children.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let his
posteritie be cut off: and in the generation folowing let their
name be blotted out.</ab>
<ab n="14">Let the
iniquitie of his fathers be remembred with the Lord: and let not
the sinne of his mother be blotted out.</ab>
<ab n="15">Let them be
before the Lord continually: that he may cut off the memory of them
from the earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">Because that he
remembred not to shew mercy, but persecuted the poore and needy
man: that he might euen slay the broken in heart.</ab>
<ab n="17">As he loued
cursing, so let it come vnto him: as hee delighted not in blessing,
so let it be farre from him.</ab>
<ab n="18">As he clothed
himselfe with cursing like as with his garment: so let it come into
his bowels like water, and like oyle into his bones.<note> Heb. within him.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Let it be vnto
him as the garment which couereth him: and for a girdle wherewith
he is girded continually.</ab>

<fw>Christs Priesthood.</fw>
<ab n="20">Let this be the
reward of mine aduersaries from the Lord: and of them that speake
euill against my soule.</ab>
<ab n="21">But do thou for
me, O God the Lord, for thy Names sake: because thy mercie is good:
deliuer thou me.</ab>
<ab n="22">For I am poore
and needie: and my heart is wounded within me.</ab>
<ab n="23">I am gone like
the shadow, when it declineth: I am tossed vp and downe as the
locust.</ab>
<ab n="24">My knees are
weake through fasting: and my flesh faileth of fatnesse.</ab>
<ab n="25">I became also a
reproch vnto them: when they looked vpon me, they shaked their
heads.</ab>
<ab n="26">Helpe me, O Lord
my God: O saue me according to thy mercie.</ab>
<ab n="27">That they may
know, that this is thy hand: that thou, Lord, hast done it.</ab>
<ab n="28">Let them curse,
but blesse thou: when they arise, let them be ashamed, but let thy
seruant reioyce.</ab>
<ab n="29">Let mine
aduersaries be clothed with shame: and let them couer them selues
with their owne confusion, as with a mantle.</ab>
<ab n="30">I will greatly
praise the Lord with my mouth: yea I will praise him among the
multitude.</ab>
<ab n="31">For he shal
stand at the right hand of the poore: to saue him from those that
condemne his soule.<note> Heb. from the iudges of his soule.</note></ab>



</div>