<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_51" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-50-51.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. LI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth for remission of
sinnes, whereof he maketh a deepe confession. 6 Hee prayeth for
sanctification. 16 God delighteth not in sacrifice, but in
sinceritie. 18 Hee prayeth for the Church.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician. A Psalme of Dauid, when Nathan the Prophet came vnto him,
after hee had gone in to Bath-sheba.] Haue mercie vpon mee, O God,
according to thy louing kindnesse: according vnto the multitude of
thy tender mercies blot out my transgressions.</ab>
<ab n="2">Wash mee throughly
from mine iniquitie, and clense me from my sinne.</ab>

<fw>A contrite heart.</fw>
<ab n="3">For I acknowledge
my transgressions: and my sinne is euer before mee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Against thee, thee
onely haue I sinned, and done this euill in thy sight: that thou
mightest bee iustified when thou speakest, and be cleare when thou
iudgest.<note> Rom. 3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Behold, I was
shapen in iniquitie: and in sinne did my mother conceiue
me.<note> Hebr. warme me.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Behold, thou
desirest trueth in the inward parts: and in the hidden part thou
shalt make me to know wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="7">Purge me with
hyssope, and I shalbe cleane: wash me, and I shall be whiter then
snow.<note> Leuit.14. 6. num.19. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Make mee to heare
ioy and gladnesse: that the bones which thou hast broken, may
reioyce.</ab>
<ab n="9">Hide thy face from
my sinnes; and blot out all mine iniquities.</ab>
<ab n="10">Create in mee a
cleane heart, O God; and renew a right spirit within
mee.<note> Or, a constant spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Cast mee not away
from thy presence; and take not thy holy Spirit from me.</ab>
<ab n="12">Restore vnto me
the ioy of thy saluation: and vphold mee with thy free
Spirit.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then will I teach
transgressours thy wayes, and sinners shalbe conuerted vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="14">Deliuer mee from
blood-guiltinesse, O God, thou God of my saluation: and my tongue
shall sing alowd of thy righteousnesse.<note> Hebr. bloods.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">O Lord open thou
my lips, and my mouth shall shew foorth thy praise.</ab>
<ab n="16">For thou desirest
not sacrifice: else would I giue it: thou delightest not in burnt
offering.<note> Or, that I should giue it.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The sacrifices of
God are a broken spirit: a broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou
wilt not despise.<note> Isa.57.15. and 66.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Doe good in thy
good pleasure vnto Sion: build thou the walles of
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="19">Then shalt thou
be pleased with the sacrifices of righteousnesse, with burnt
offering and whole burnt offering: then shall they offer bullockes
vpon thine altar.</ab>



</div>