<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_84" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-83-85.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXXIV.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet longing for the
communion of the Sanctuarie, 4 sheweth how blessed they are that
dwell therein. 8 Hee prayeth to be restored vnto it.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician vpon Gittith, a Psalme for the sonnes of Korah.] How
amiable are thy tabernacles, O Lord of hostes!</ab>
<ab n="2">My soule longeth,
yea euen fainteth for the courts of the Lord: my heart and my flesh
cryeth out for the liuing God.</ab>
<ab n="3">Yea the sparrowe
hath found an house, and the swallow a nest for her selfe, where
she may lay her young, euen thine altars, O Lord of hostes, my king
and my God.</ab>
<ab n="4">Blessed are they
that dwell in thy house: they wilbe still praysing thee.
Selah.</ab>
<ab n="5">Blessed is the man
whose strength is in thee: in whose heart are the wayes of
them:</ab>
<ab n="6">Who passing
through the valley of Baca, make it a well: the raine also filleth
the pooles.<note> Or, of mulbery-trees make him a well &amp;c. , Heb. couereth.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">They goe from
strength to strength: euery one of them in Zion appeareth before
God.<note> Or, from companie to companie.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">O Lord God of
hostes, heare my prayer: giue eare, O God of Iacob. Selah.</ab>

<fw>The desire of the godly.</fw>
<ab n="9">Behold, O God our
shield: and looke vpon the face of thine anointed.</ab>
<ab n="10">For a day in thy
courts, is better then a thousand: I had rather be a doore keeper
in the house of my God, then to dwell in the tents of
wickednesse.<note> Heb. I would choose rather to sit at the threshold.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For the Lord God
is a sunne and shield: the Lord will giue grace and glory: no good
thing will he withhold from them that walke vprightly.<note> Psal. 2.12. &amp; 34.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">O Lord of hostes:
blessed is the man that trusteth in thee.</ab>



</div>