<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid in confidence of his
integrity, craueth defence of God against his enemies. 10 He
sheweth their pride, craft and eagernes. 13 Hee prayeth against
them in confidence of his hope.</head>


<fw>Dauids prayer.</fw>
<ab n="1">[A prayer of
Dauid.] Heare the right, O Lord, attend vnto my crie, giue eare
vnto my prayer, that goeth not out of fained lips.<note> Heb. iustice. , Heb. without lips of deceit.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Let my sentence
come forth from thy presence: let thine eyes beholde the things
that are equall.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou hast prooued
mine heart, thou hast visited me in the night, thou hast tried me,
and shalt find nothing: I am purposed that my mouth shall not
transgresse.</ab>
<ab n="4">Concerning the
workes of men, by the word of thy lips, I haue kept me from the
paths of the destroyer.</ab>
<ab n="5">Hold vp my goings
in thy paths, that my footsteps slip not.<note> Heb. be not moued.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I haue called vpon
thee, for thou wilt heare me, O God: incline thine eare vnto me,
and heare my speach.</ab>
<ab n="7">Shewe thy
marueilous louing kindnesse, O thou that sauest by thy right hand,
them which put their trust in thee, frō those that rise vp
against them.<note> Or, that sauest them which trust in thee from these that rise vp against thy right hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Keepe me as the
apple of the eye: hide mee vnder the shadowe of thy wings,</ab>
<ab n="9">From the wicked
that oppresse me, from my deadly enemies, who compasse me
about.<note> Heb. that waste me. , Heb. my enemies against the soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">They are inclosed
in their owne fat: with their mouth they speake proudly.</ab>
<ab n="11">They haue now
compassed vs in our steps: they haue set their eyes bowing downe to
the earth:</ab>
<ab n="12">Like as a lyon
that is greedie of his pray, and as it were a yong lyon lurking in
secret places.<note> Heb. the likeness of him (i. of euery one of them) is as a lion that desireth to rauin. , Heb. sitting.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Arise, O Lord,
disappoint him, cast him downe: deliuer my soule from the wicked,
which is thy sword:<note> Heb. preuent his face. , Or, by thy sword.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">From men which
are thy hand, O Lord, from men of the world, which haue their
portion in this life, and whose belly thou fillest with thy hid
treasure: They are full of children, and leaue the rest of their
substance to their babes.<note> Or, from by thine hand. , Or, their children are full.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">As for me, I will
behold thy face in righteousnesse: I shall bee satisfied, when I
awake, with thy likenesse.</ab>



</div>