<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_119" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-118-119.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-119-119.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-119-119b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-119-119c.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-119-120.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXIX.</head>
<head>This Psalme conteineth sundry
prayers, praises, and professions of obedience.</head>

<ab n="1">[ALEPH.] Blessed
are the vndefiled in the way: who walke in the Law of the
Lord.<note> Or, perfect, or sincere.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Blessed are they
that keepe his testimonies: and that seeke him with the whole
heart.</ab>
<ab n="3">They also doe no
iniquitie: they walke in his wayes.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou hast
commaunded vs to keepe thy precepts diligently.</ab>
<ab n="5">O that my wayes
were directed to keepe thy statutes!</ab>
<ab n="6">Then shall I not
bee ashamed: when I haue respect vnto all thy
commandements.</ab>
<ab n="7">I will praise
thee with vprightnesse of heart: when I shall haue learned thy
righteous iudgements.<note> Hebr. iudgments of thy righteousnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">I will keepe thy
statutes: O forsake me not vtterly.</ab>
<ab n="9">[BETH.]
Wherewithall shall a yong man cleanse his way? by taking heede
thereto according to thy word.</ab>
<ab n="10">With my whole
heart haue I sought thee: O let me not wander from thy
Commandements.</ab>
<ab n="11">Thy word haue I
hidde in mine heart: that I might not sinne against thee.</ab>
<ab n="12">Blessed art
thou, O Lord: teach me thy statutes.</ab>
<ab n="13">With my lips
haue I declared all the iudgements of thy mouth.</ab>
<ab n="14">I haue reioyced
in the way of thy testimonies: as much as in all riches.</ab>
<ab n="15">I will meditate
in thy precepts: and haue respect vnto thy wayes.</ab>
<ab n="16">I will delight
my selfe in thy statutes: I will not forget thy word.</ab>
<ab n="17">[GIMEL.] Deale
bountifully with thy seruant; that I may liue, and keepe thy
word.</ab>

<fw>Dauids meditations.</fw>
<ab n="18">Open thou mine
eyes, that I may behold wonderous things out of thy
Law.<note> Heb. reueale.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">I am a stranger
in the earth: hide not thy commandements from me.<note> Gen.47.9 1.chro. 29. 15. psal.39. 12. heb.11. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">My soule
breaketh for the longing: that it hath vnto thy iudgements at all
times.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thou hast
rebuked the proud that are cursed: which doe erre from thy
Commandements.</ab>
<ab n="22">Remooue from me
reproch and contempt: for I haue kept thy testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="23">Princes also did
sit and speake against me: but thy seruant did meditate in thy
statutes.</ab>
<ab n="24">Thy testimonies
also are my delight: and my counsellers.<note> Heb. men of my counsell.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">[DALETH.] My
soule cleaueth vnto the dust: quicken thou mee according to thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="26">I haue declared
my wayes, and thou heardest me: teach me thy Statutes.<note> Psal.25.4. and 27. 11. and 86. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Make me to
vnderstand the way of thy precepts: so shall I talke of thy
wonderous workes.</ab>
<ab n="28">My soule melteth
for heauines: strengthen thou me according vnto thy
word.<note> Heb. droppeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Remoue from mee
the way of lying: and grant me thy Law graciously.</ab>
<ab n="30">I haue chosen
the way of trueth: thy iudgements haue I laid before me.</ab>
<ab n="31">I haue stucke
vnto thy Testimonies: O Lord put me not to shame.</ab>
<ab n="32">I will runne the
way of thy Commandements: when thou shalt enlarge my heart.</ab>
<ab n="33">[HE.] Teach me,
O Lord, the way of thy Statutes: and I shall keepe it vnto the
end.</ab>
<ab n="34">Giue me
vnderstanding, and I shall keepe thy Law: yea I shall obserue it
with my whole heart.</ab>
<ab n="35">Make me to goe
in the path of thy commandements: for therein doe I
delight.</ab>
<ab n="36">Incline my heart
vnto thy testimonies: and not to couetousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="37">Turne away mine
eyes from beholding vanitie: and quicken thou me in thy
way.<note> Heb. make to passe.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods promise.</fw>
<ab n="38">Stablish thy
word vnto thy seruant: who is deuoted to thy feare.</ab>
<ab n="39">Turne away my
reproch which I feare: for thy iudgements are good.</ab>
<ab n="40">Behold, I haue
longed after thy precepts: quicken me in thy
righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="41">[VAV.] Let thy
mercies come also vnto me, O Lord: euen thy saluation, according to
thy word.</ab>
<ab n="42">So shall I haue
wherewith to answere him that reprocheth me: for I trust in thy
word.<note> Or, so shall I answere him that reproueth me in a thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="43">And take not the
word of trueth vtterly out of my mouth: for I haue hoped in thy
iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="44">So shall I keepe
thy Law continually: for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="45">And I wil walke
at libertie: for I seeke thy precepts.<note> Hebr. at large.</note></ab>
<ab n="46">I will speake of
thy testimonies also before kings, &amp; wil not be
ashamed.</ab>
<ab n="47">And I will
delight my selfe in thy commandements, which I haue loued.</ab>
<ab n="48">My hands also
will I lift vp vnto thy commandements, which I haue loued: and I
will meditate in thy statutes.</ab>
<ab n="49">[ZAIN.] Remember
the word vnto thy seruant: vpon which thou hast caused me to
hope.</ab>
<ab n="50">This is my
comfort in my affliction: for thy word hath quickened me.</ab>
<ab n="51">The proud haue
had mee greatly in derision: yet haue I not declined from thy
Law.</ab>
<ab n="52">I remembred thy
iudgements of old, O Lord: and haue comforted my selfe.</ab>
<ab n="53">Horrour hath
taken holde vpon me, because of the wicked that forsake thy
Law.</ab>
<ab n="54">Thy statutes
haue bin my songs in the house of my pilgrimage.</ab>
<ab n="55">I haue remembred
thy name, O Lord, in the night, and haue kept thy Law.</ab>
<ab n="56">This I had:
because I kept thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="57">[CHETH.] Thou
art my portion, O Lord, I haue said, that I would keepe thy
words.</ab>
<ab n="58">I intreated thy
fauour with my whole heart: be mercifull vnto mee according to thy
word.<note> Heb. face.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids delight in Gods law.</fw>
<ab n="59">I thought on my
wayes: and turned my feete vnto thy Testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="60">I made haste;
and delayed not to keepe thy commandements.</ab>
<ab n="61">The bands of the
wicked haue robbed me: but I haue not forgotten thy
lawe.<note> Or, companies.</note></ab>
<ab n="62">At mid-night I
will rise to giue thankes vnto thee: because of thy righteous
iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="63">I am a companion
of all them that feare thee: and of them that keepe thy
precepts.</ab>
<ab n="64">The earth, O
Lord, is full of thy mercy: teach me thy statutes.</ab>
<ab n="65">[TETH.] Thou
hast dealt well with thy seruant, Oh Lord, according vnto thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="66">Teach me good
iudgement and knowledge: for I haue beleeued thy
commandements.</ab>
<ab n="67">Before I was
afflicted, I went astray: but now haue I kept thy word.</ab>
<ab n="68">Thou art good,
and doest good; teach me thy statutes.</ab>
<ab n="69">The proud haue
forged a lie against me: but I will keepe thy precepts with my
whole heart.</ab>
<ab n="70">Their heart is
as fat as grease: but I delight in thy law.</ab>
<ab n="71">It is good for
me that I haue bene afflicted: that I might learne thy
statutes.</ab>
<ab n="72">The law of thy
mouth is better vnto me: then thousands of gold and
siluer.<note> Psal.19. 9. Prou.8. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="73">[IOD.] Thy hands
haue made me and fashioned me: giue me vnderstanding, that I may
learne thy commandements.</ab>
<ab n="74">They that feare
thee will bee glad when they see mee: because I haue hoped in thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="75">I knowe, O Lord,
that thy iudgements are right: and that thou in faithfulnesse hast
afflicted me.<note> Heb. righteousnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="76">Let, I pray
thee, thy mercifull kindnesse be for my comfort; according to thy
word vnto thy seruant.<note> Heb. to comfort me.</note></ab>
<ab n="77">Let thy tender
mercies come vnto me, that I may liue: for thy lawe is my
delight.</ab>
<ab n="78">Let the proud be
ashamed, for they dealt peruersly with me without a cause: but I
will meditate in thy precepts.</ab>

<fw>Dauids delight in Gods law.</fw>
<ab n="79">Let those that
feare thee turne vnto me: and those that haue knowen thy
testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="80">Let my heart be
sound in thy statutes; that I be not ashamed.</ab>
<ab n="81">[CAPH.] My soule
fainteth for thy saluation: but I hope in thy word.</ab>
<ab n="82">Mine eyes faile
for thy word: saying, When wilt thou comfort me?</ab>
<ab n="83">For I am become
like a bottle in the smoke: yet doe I not forget thy
statutes.</ab>
<ab n="84">How many are the
dayes of thy seruant? when wilt thou execute iudgement on them that
persecute me?</ab>
<ab n="85">The proud haue
digged pittes for me: which are not after thy law.</ab>
<ab n="86">All thy
commaundements are faithfull: they persecute me wrongfully; helpe
thou me.<note> Heb. faithfulnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="87">They had almost
consumed mee vpon earth: but I forsooke not thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="88">Quicken mee
after thy louing kindnesse: so shall I keepe the testimonie of thy
mouth.</ab>
<ab n="89">[LAMED.]
Foreuer, O Lord, thy word is setled, in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="90">Thy
faithfulnesse is vnto all generations: thou hast established the
earth, and it abideth.<note> Heb. to generation and generation. , Heb. standeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="91">They continue
this day according to thine ordinances: for all are thy
seruants.</ab>
<ab n="92">Unlesse thy lawe
had bene my delights: I should then haue perished in mine
affliction.</ab>
<ab n="93">I will neuer
forget thy precepts: for with them thou hast quickened me.</ab>
<ab n="94">I am thine, saue
me: for I haue sought thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="95">The wicked haue
waited for me to destroy me: but I will consider thy
testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="96">I haue seene an
end of all perfection: but thy commandement is exceeding
broad.</ab>
<ab n="97">[MEM.] O How
loue I thy Law! it is my meditation all the day.</ab>
<ab n="98">Thou through thy
Commandements hast made me wiser then mine enemies: for they are
euer with mee.<note> Heb. it is euer with me.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods word a light.</fw>
<ab n="99">I haue more
vnderstanding then all my teachers: for thy Testimonies are my
meditation.</ab>
<ab n="100">I vnderstand
more then the ancients: because I keepe thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="101">I haue
refrained my feete from euery euill way: that I may keepe thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="102">I haue not
departed from thy Iudgements: for thou hast taught me.</ab>
<ab n="103">How sweet are
thy words vnto my taste! yea, sweeter then hony to my
mouth.<note> Psal.19.9. , Hebr. palat.</note></ab>
<ab n="104">Through thy
precepts I get vnderstanding: therefore I hate euery false
way.</ab>
<ab n="105">[NVN.] Thy word
is a lampe vnto my feete: and a light vnto my path.<note> Or, candle.</note></ab>
<ab n="106">I haue sworne,
and I will performe it: that I will keepe thy righteous
iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="107">I am afflicted
very much: quicken mee, O Lord, according vnto thy word.</ab>
<ab n="108">Accept, I
beseech thee, the freewil offrings of my mouth, O Lord: and teach
me thy iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="109">My soule is
continually in my hand: yet doe I not forget thy Law.</ab>
<ab n="110">The wicked haue
layde a snare for mee: yet I erred not from thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="111">Thy Testimonies
haue I taken as an heritage for euer: for they are the reioycing of
my heart.</ab>
<ab n="112">I haue inclined
mine heart to performe thy Statutes, alway, euen vnto the
end.<note> Hebr. to do.</note></ab>
<ab n="113">[SAMECH.] I
hate vaine thoughts: but thy Law doe I loue.</ab>
<ab n="114">Thou art my
hiding place, and my shield: I hope in thy word.</ab>
<ab n="115">Depart from me,
ye euil doers: for I will keepe the Commandements of my
God.<note> Matth. 7. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="116">Uphold mee
according vnto thy word, that I may liue: and let mee not be
ashamed of my hope.</ab>
<ab n="117">Hold thou me
vp, and I shall be safe: and I will haue respect vnto thy Statutes
continually.</ab>
<ab n="118">Thou hast
troden downe all them that erre from thy Statutes: for their deceit
is falshood.</ab>

<fw>Dauids zeale.</fw>
<ab n="119">Thou puttest
away all the wicked of the earth like drosse: therefore I loue thy
Testimonies.<note> Hebr. causest to cease.</note></ab>
<ab n="120">My flesh
trembleth for feare of thee: and I am afraide of thy
Iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="121">[AIN.] I Haue
done Iudgement and iustice: leaue mee not to mine
oppressours.</ab>
<ab n="122">Bee suretie for
thy seruant for good: let not the proud oppresse me.</ab>
<ab n="123">Mine eyes faile
for thy saluation: and for the word of thy righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="124">Deale with thy
seruant according vnto thy mercie: and teach me thy
Statutes.</ab>
<ab n="125">I am thy
seruant, giue me vnderstanding: that I may know thy
Testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="126">It is time for
thee, Lord, to worke: for they haue made voyde thy Law.</ab>
<ab n="127">Therefore I
loue thy Commandements: aboue gold, yea aboue fine
gold.<note> Prou.8. 11. psal.19. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="128">Therefore I
esteeme all thy precepts concerning all things to be right: and I
hate euery false way.</ab>
<ab n="129">[PE.] Thy
Testimonies are wonderfull: therefore doeth my soule keepe
them.</ab>
<ab n="130">The entrance of
thy wordes giueth light: it giueth vnderstanding vnto the
simple.</ab>
<ab n="131">I opened my
mouth, and panted: for I longed for thy Commandements.</ab>
<ab n="132">Looke thou vpon
mee, and be mercifull vnto me: as thou vsest to do vnto those that
loue thy Name.<note> Hebr according to the custome towards those, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="133">Order my steps
in thy word: and let not any iniquitie haue dominion ouer
me.</ab>
<ab n="134">Deliuer me from
the oppression of man: so will I keepe thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="135">Make thy face
to shine vpon thy seruant: and teach me thy Statutes.</ab>
<ab n="136">Riuers of
waters runne downe mine eyes: because they keepe not thy
Law.</ab>
<ab n="137">[TSADDI.]
Righteous art thou, O Lord: and vpright are thy iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="138">Thy testimonies
that thou hast commaunded, are righteous: and very
faithfull.<note> Hebr. righteousnesse. , Heb. faithfulnesse.</note></ab>

<fw>Dauids griefe: His hope.</fw>
<ab n="139">My zeale hath
consumed me: because mine enemies haue forgotten thy
words.<note> Psal.69.8. ioh.2. 17. , Heb. cut me off.</note></ab>
<ab n="140">Thy word is
very pure: therefore thy seruant loueth it.<note> Heb. tried or refined.</note></ab>
<ab n="141">I am small and
despised: yet doe not I forget thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="142">Thy
righteousnesse is an euerlasting righteousnesse: and thy law is the
trueth.</ab>
<ab n="143">Trouble and
anguish haue taken hold on me: yet thy commaundements are my
delights.<note> Hebr. found me.</note></ab>
<ab n="144">The
righteousnesse of thy Testimonies is euerlasting: giue me
vnderstanding, and I shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="145">[KOPH.] I Cried
with my whole heart: heare me, O Lord, I will keepe thy
statutes.</ab>
<ab n="146">I cried vnto
thee, saue me: and I shall keepe thy testimonies.<note> Or, that I may keepe.</note></ab>
<ab n="147">I preuented the
dawning of the morning, and cried: I hoped in thy word.</ab>
<ab n="148">Mine eyes
preuent the night watches: that I might meditate in thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="149">Heare my voice
according vnto thy louing kindnesse: O Lord quicken me according to
thy iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="150">They draw nigh
that follow after mischiefe: they are farre from thy Law.</ab>
<ab n="151">Thou art neere,
O Lord: and all thy commandements are trueth.</ab>
<ab n="152">Concerning thy
testimonies, I haue knowen of old: that thou hast founded them for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="153">[RESH.]
Consider mine affliction, and deliuer me: for I doe not forget thy
Law.</ab>
<ab n="154">Plead my cause,
and deliuer me: quicken me according to thy word.</ab>
<ab n="155">Saluation is
farre from the wicked: for they seeke not thy statutes.</ab>
<ab n="156">Great are thy
tender mercies, O Lord: quicken me according to thy
iudgements.<note> Or, many.</note></ab>
<ab n="157">Many are my
persecutors, and mine enemies: yet doe I not decline from thy
testimonies.</ab>
<ab n="158">I beheld the
transgressours, and was grieued: because they kept not thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="159">Consider how I
loue thy precepts: quicken me, O Lord, according to thy louing
kindnesse.</ab>

<fw>Dauids griefe: His hope.</fw>
<ab n="160">Thy word is
true from the beginning: and euery one of thy righteous iudgements
endureth for euer.<note> Heb. the beginning of thy word is true.</note></ab>
<ab n="161">[SCHIN.]
Princes haue persecuted mee without a cause: but my heart standeth
in awe of thy word.</ab>
<ab n="162">I reioyce at
thy word: as one that findeth great spoile.</ab>
<ab n="163">I hate and
abhorre lying: but thy Law doe I loue.</ab>
<ab n="164">Seuen times a
day doe I praise thee: because of thy righteous iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="165">Great peace
haue they which loue thy law: &amp; nothing shall offend
them.<note> Heb. they shall haue no stumbling blocke</note></ab>
<ab n="166">Lord, I haue
hoped for thy saluation: and done thy commandements.</ab>
<ab n="167">My soule hath
kept thy testimonies: and I loue them exceedingly.</ab>
<ab n="168">I haue kept thy
precepts and thy testimonies: for all my wayes are before
thee.</ab>
<ab n="169">[TAV.] Let my
crie come neere before thee, O Lord: giue mee vnderstanding
according to thy worde.</ab>
<ab n="170">Let my
supplication come before thee: deliuer me according to thy
word.</ab>
<ab n="171">My lips shall
vtter praise: when thou hast taught me thy Statutes.</ab>
<ab n="172">My tongue shall
speake of thy word: for all thy commandements are
righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="173">Let thine hand
helpe me: for I haue chosen thy precepts.</ab>
<ab n="174">I haue longed
for thy saluation, O Lord: and thy Lawe is my delight.</ab>
<ab n="175">Let my soule
liue, and it shall praise thee: and let thy iudgments helpe
me.</ab>
<ab n="176">I haue gone
astray like a lost sheepe, seeke thy seruant: for I doe not forget
thy commandements.</ab>



</div>