<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-8-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-10-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 Dauid complaineth to God of the
outrage of the wicked. 12 He prayeth for remedie. 16 He professeth
his confidence.</head>

<ab n="1">Why standest thou
afarre off, O Lord? why hidest thou thy selfe in times of
trouble?</ab>
<ab n="2">The wicked in his
pride doeth persecute the poore: let them be taken in the deuices
that they haue imagined.<note> Heb. in the pride of the wicked be doth persecute. , Psal.7.16 and 9.16. prou.5.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For the wicked
boasteth of his hearts desire, and blesseth the couetous, whom the
Lord abhorreth.<note> Heb. soules , Or, the covetous blesseth himself, he abhorreth the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">The wicked through
the pride of his countenance will not seeke after God: God is not
in all his thoughts.<note> Or, all his thoughts are there is no God. , Psal.14.1. and 53.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">His wayes are
alwayes grieuous, thy iudgements are farre aboue out of his sight:
as for all his enemies, he puffeth at them.</ab>
<ab n="6">He hath said in
his heart, I shall not be moued: for I shall neuer be in
aduersitie.<note> Hebr. vnto generation and generation.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">His mouth is full
of cursing, and deceit, and fraud: vnder his tongue is mischiefe
and vanitie.<note> Rom. 3. 14 , Heb. deceits. , Or, iniquitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">He sitteth in the
lurking places of the villages: in the secret places doeth he
murder the innocent: his eyes are priuily set against the
poore.<note> Heb. hide themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">He lieth in waite
secretly as a lyon in his denne, he lieth in wait to catch the
poore: he doth catch the poore when he draweth him into his
net.<note> Heb. in the secret place</note></ab>
<ab n="10">He croucheth, and
humbleth himselfe, that the poore may fall by his strong
ones.<note> Heb. hee breaketh himselfe. , Or, into his strong parts.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods iudgments on the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="11">Hee hath said in
his heart, God hath forgotten: he hideth his face, hee will neuer
see it.<note> Psal.94.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Arise, O Lord, O
God lift vp thine hand: forget not the humble.<note> Or, afflicted.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Wherefore doeth
the wicked contemne God? he hath said in his heart, Thou wilt not
require it.</ab>
<ab n="14">Thou hast seene
it, for thou beholdest mischiefe and spite to requite it with thy
hand: the poore committeth himselfe vnto thee, thou art the helper
of the fatherlesse.<note> Hebr. leaueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Breake thou the
arme of the wicked, and the euill man: seeke out his wickednes,
till thou finde none.</ab>
<ab n="16">The Lord is King
for euer and euer: the heathen are perished out of his
land.<note> Psal,29.9. and 145.13. and 146.10. iere.16.10. lam.5.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Lord, thou hast
heard the desire of the humble: thou wilt prepare their heart, thou
wilt cause thine eare to heare,<note> Or, establish.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">To iudge the
fatherlesse and the oppressed, that the man of the earth may no
more oppresse.<note> Or, terrifie.</note></ab>



</div>