<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_66" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-64-66.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-66-68.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXVI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid exhorteth to praise God, 5
To obserue his great workes, 8 To blesse him for his gracious
benefits. 12 He voweth for himselfe religious seruice to God. 16 He
declareth Gods speciall goodnesse to himselfe.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician, a song or Psalme.] Make a ioyfull noise vnto God, all yee
lands.<note> Heb. all the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Sing forth the
honour of his name: make his praise glorious.</ab>
<ab n="3">Say vnto God, How
terrible art thou in thy workes? through the greatnesse of thy
power shall thine enemies submit themselues vnto thee.<note> Or, yeild fained obedience. Heb. lie.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">All the earth
shall worship thee; and shall sing vnto thee, they shall sing to
thy name; Selah.</ab>
<ab n="5">Come and see the
workes of God: he is terrible in his doing toward the children of
men.</ab>
<ab n="6">He turned the sea
into dry land: they went through the flood on foote, there did we
reioyce in him.</ab>
<ab n="7">He ruleth by his
power for euer, his eyes behold the nations: let not the rebellious
exalt themselues. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="8">O blesse our God,
yee people, and make the voice of his praise to be heard.</ab>
<ab n="9">Which holdeth our
soule in life, and suffereth not our feete to be moued.<note> Heb. putteth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For thou, O God,
hast proued vs: thou hast tried vs, as siluer is tryed.</ab>

<fw>The reioycing of the iust.</fw>
<ab n="11">Thou broughtest
vs into the net; thou layedst affliction vpon our loynes.</ab>
<ab n="12">Thou hast caused
men to ride ouer our heads, we went through fire, and through
water: but thou broughtest vs out into a wealthy place.<note> Heb. moist.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">I will goe into
thy house, with burnt offerings: I will pay thee my vowes,</ab>
<ab n="14">Which my lips
haue vttered, and my mouth hath spoken, when I was in
trouble.<note> Hebr. opened.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">I will offer vnto
thee burnt sacrifices of fatlings, with the incense of rammes: I
will offer bullockes with goates. Selah.<note> Hebr. marrow.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Come and heare
all ye that feare God, and I will declare what he hath done for my
soule.</ab>
<ab n="17">I cried vnto him
with my mouth: and he was extolled with my tongue.</ab>
<ab n="18">If I regard
iniquitie in my heart: the Lord will not heare me.</ab>
<ab n="19">But verily God
hath heard mee; hee hath attended to the voice of my
prayer.</ab>
<ab n="20">Blessed bee God,
which hath not turned away my prayer, nor his mercie from
me.</ab>



</div>