<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_60" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-59-61.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. LX.</head>
<head>1 Dauid complayning to God of former
iudgement, 4 now vpon better hope prayeth for deliuerance. 6
Comforting himselfe in Gods promises, he craueth that helpe whereon
he trusteth.</head>


<fw>Dauids confidence.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician vpon Shushan-Eduth Michtam of Dauid, to teach. When hee
stroue with Aram Naharaim, and with Aram Zobah, when Ioab returned,
and smote of Edom in the valley of salt, twelue thousand.] O God,
thou hast cast vs off; thou hast scattered vs, thou hast bene
displeased, O turne thy selfe to vs againe.<note> Psal.44. 10. , Hebr. broken.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Thou hast made the
earth to tremble; thou hast broken it: heale the breaches thereof,
for it shaketh.</ab>
<ab n="3">Thou hast shewed
thy people hard things: thou hast made vs to drinke the wine of
astonishment.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thou hast giuen a
banner to them that feare thee: that it may be displayed because of
the trueth. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="5">That thy beloued
may be deliuered; saue with thy right hand, and heare
mee.<note> Psal.108. 6. &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">God hath spoken in
his holinesse, I wil reioyce: I will diuide Shechem, and mete out
the valley of Succoth.</ab>
<ab n="7">Gilead is mine,
and Manasseh is mine; Ephraim also is the strength of mine head;
Iudah is my Lawgiuer.</ab>
<ab n="8">Moab is my
wash-pot, ouer Edom wil I cast out my shooe: Philistia, triumph
thou because of me.<note> Or, triumph thou ouer me. [by an ironie].</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Who wil bring me
into the strong citie? who will lead me into Edom?<note> Hebr. city of strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Wilt not thou, O
God, which hadst cast vs off? and thou, O God, which didst not goe
out with our armies.<note> Psal.44. 10. and 108 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Giue vs helpe
from trouble: for vaine is the helpe of man.<note> Hebr. saluation.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Through God wee
shall doe valiantly: for he it is that shall tread downe our
enemies.</ab>



</div>