<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_104" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-103-104.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-104-105.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CIV.</head>
<head>1 A meditation vpon the mighty
power, 7 and wonderfull prouidence of God. 31 Gods glory is
eternall. 33 The Prophet voweth perpetually to praise
God.</head>

<ab n="1">Blesse the Lord,
O my soule, O Lord my God, thou art very great: thou art clothed
with honour and maiestie.</ab>
<ab n="2">Who couerest thy
selfe with light, as with a garment: who stretchest out the heauens
like a curtaine.</ab>
<ab n="3">Who layeth the
beames of his chambers in the waters, who maketh the cloudes his
charet: who walketh vpon the wings of the wind.</ab>
<ab n="4">Who maketh his
Angels spirits: his ministers a flaming fire.<note> Heb. 1.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Who laid the
foundations of the earth: that it should not be remoued for
euer.<note> Hebr. he hath founded the earth vpon her bases.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Thou coueredst it
with the deepe as with a garment: the waters stood aboue the
mountaines.</ab>
<ab n="7">At thy rebuke
they fled: at the voice of thy thunder they hasted away.</ab>
<ab n="8">They go vp by the
mountaines: they goe downe by the valleys vnto the place which thou
hast founded for them.<note> Or, the mountaines ascend, the valleys descend.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thou hast set a
bound that they may not passe ouer: that they turne not againe to
couer the earth.</ab>
<ab n="10">He sendeth the
springs into the valleys: which runne among the hilles.<note> Hebr. who sendeth. , Heb. walke</note></ab>
<ab n="11">They giue drinke
to euery beast of the field: the wild asses quench their
thirst.<note> Heb. break</note></ab>
<ab n="12">By them shall
the foules of the heauen haue their habitation: which sing among
the branches.<note> Heb. giue a voyce.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">He watereth the
hilles from his chambers: the earth is satisfied with the fruit of
thy workes.</ab>
<ab n="14">He causeth the
grasse to grow for the cattell, and herbe for the seruice of man:
that he may bring forth food out of the earth:<note> Iosh.9.13</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And wine that
maketh glad the heart of man, and oile to make his face to shine:
and bread which strengtheneth mans heart.<note> Hebr. to make his face shine with oyle, or more then oyle.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The trees of the
Lord are full of sappe: the cedars of Lebanon which he hath
planted.</ab>
<ab n="17">Where the birds
make their nests: as for the Storke, the firre trees are her
house.</ab>

<fw>Gods wisedome, and prouidence.</fw>
<ab n="18">The hie hilles
are a refuge for the wilde goates: and the rockes for the
conies.</ab>
<ab n="19">He appointed the
moone for seasons; the sunne knoweth his going downe.</ab>
<ab n="20">Thou makest
darknesse, and it is night: wherein all the beasts of the forrest
doe creepe forth.<note> Heb. all the beasts thereof doe trample on the forrest.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The young lyons
roare after their pray: and seeke their meate from God.</ab>
<ab n="22">The sunne
ariseth, they gather themselues together: and lay them downe in
their dennes.</ab>
<ab n="23">Man goeth forth
vnto his worke: and to his labour, vntill the euening.</ab>
<ab n="24">O Lord, how
manifold are thy workes! in wisedome hast thou made them all: the
earth is full of thy riches.</ab>
<ab n="25">So is this great
and wide Sea, wherein are things creeping innumerable: both small
and great beasts.</ab>
<ab n="26">There goe the
shippes; there is that Leuiathan, whom thou hast made to play
therein.<note> Heb. formed.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">These waite all
vpon thee: that thou mayest giue them their meate in due
season.<note> Psal. 145. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">That thou giuest
them, they gather: thou openest thine hand, they are filled with
good.</ab>
<ab n="29">Thou hidest thy
face, they are troubled, thou takest away their breath, they die:
and returne to their dust.</ab>
<ab n="30">Thou sendest
forth thy spirit, they are created: and thou renewest the face of
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="31">The glory of the
Lord shall endure for euer: the Lord shall reioyce in his
workes.<note> Heb. shalbe.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Hee looketh on
the earth, and it trembleth; he toucheth the hilles, and they
smoke.</ab>
<ab n="33">I will sing vnto
the Lord as long as I liue: I will sing praise to my God, while I
haue my being.</ab>
<ab n="34">My meditation of
him shalbe sweete: I will be glad in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="35">Let the sinners
be consumed out of the earth, and let the wicked bee no more:
blesse thou the Lord, O my soule. Praise yee the Lord.</ab>



</div>