<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_33" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-32-33.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-33-34.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXIII.</head>
<head>1 The kindnesse of Iacob and Esau at
their meeting. 17 Iacob commeth to Succoth. 18 At Salem he buyeth a
field, and buildeth an Altar called Elohe Israel.</head>

<ab n="1">And Iacob lifted
vp his eyes, and looked, and behold, Esau came, and with him foure
hundreth men: and hee diuided the children vnto Leah, and vnto
Rachel, and vnto the two handmaids.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he put the
handmaides, and their chidren foremost, and Leah and her children
after, and Rachel and Ioseph hindermost.</ab>
<ab n="3">And hee passed
ouer before them, and bowed himselfe to the ground seuen times,
vntill hee came neere to his brother.</ab>
<ab n="4">And Esau ran to
meete him, and imbraced him, and fell on his necke, and kissed him,
and they wept.</ab>
<ab n="5">And he lift vp
his eyes, and sawe the women, and the children, and said, who are
those with thee? And he said, The children which God hath
graciously giuen thy seruant.<note> Heb. To thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Then the
handmaidens came neere; they and their children, and they bowed
themselues.</ab>

<fw>Iacob and Esau.</fw>
<ab n="7">And Leah also
with her children came neere, and bowed themselues: and after came
Ioseph neere and Rachel, and they bowed themselues.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he said, What
meanest thou by all this droue, which I met? And he said, These are
to find grace in the sight of my lord.<note> Heb. what is all this band to thee?</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Esau said, I
haue enough: my brother, keepe that thou hast vnto thy
selfe.<note> Heb. bee that to thee that is thine.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Iacob saide,
Nay, I pray thee: if now I haue found grace in thy sight, then
receiue my present at my hand: for therefore I haue seene thy face,
as though I had seene the face of God; and thou wast pleased with
me.</ab>
<ab n="11">Take, I pray
thee, my blessing that is brought to thee; because God hath dealt
graciously with mee, and because I haue enough: and hee vrged him,
and he tooke it.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he said, Let
vs take our iourney, and let vs goe, and I will goe before
thee.</ab>
<ab n="13">And hee said
vnto him, My lord knoweth, that the children are tender, and the
flockes and heards with yong are with mee: and if men should
ouer-driue them one day, all the flocke will die.</ab>
<ab n="14">Let my lord, I
pray thee, passe ouer before his seruant, and I will leade on
softly, according as the cattell that goeth before me, and the
children be able to endure, vntill I come vnto my lord vnto
Seir.<note> Heb. according to the foote of the worke, &amp;c. &amp; according to the foot of the children.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And Esau said,
Let me now leaue with thee some of the folke that are with me: And
hee said, What needeth it? let me finde grace in the sight of my
lord.<note> Heb. Set, or place. , Heb. wherfore is this?</note></ab>
<ab n="16">¶ So Esau
returned that day, on his way vnto Seir.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Iacob
iourneyed to Succoth, and built him an house, and made boothes for
his cattell: therefore the name of the place is called
Succoth.<note> That is, boothes.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And Iacob
came to Shalem, a citie of Shechem, which is the land of Canaan,
when he came from Padan Aram, and pitched his tent before the
Citie.<note> Called Acts. 7. 16. Sychem.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And he bought a
parcell of a field where hee had spread his tent, at the hand of
the children of Hamor Shechems father, for an hundred pieces of
money.<note> Called Acts. 7. 16. Emor. , Or, lambes.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And hee erected
there an Altar, and called it El-Elohe-Israel.<note> That is, God, the God of Israel.</note></ab>



</div>