<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_41" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-41-44.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLI.</head>
<head>1 Gods care of the poore. 4 Dauid
complaineth of his enemies trecherie. 10 He flyeth to God for
succour.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician. A Psalme of Dauid.] Blessed is he that considereth the
poore; the Lord will deliuer him in time of trouble.<note> Or, the weake, or sicke. , Heb. in the day of euill.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord will
preserue him, and keepe him aliue, and he shall be blessed vpon the
earth; and thou wilt not deliuer him vnto the will of his
enemies.<note> Or, doe not thou deliuer.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The Lord will
strengthen him vpon the bed of languishing: thou wilt make all his
bed in his sicknesse.<note> Heb. turne.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I sayd, Lord be
mercifull vnto me, heale my soule, for I haue sinned against
thee.</ab>
<ab n="5">Mine enemies
speake euill of me: when shall hee die, and his name
perish?</ab>
<ab n="6">And if hee come to
see me, he speaketh vanity: his heart gathereth iniquitie to it
selfe, when he goeth abroad, he telleth it.</ab>
<ab n="7">All that hate me,
whisper together against me; against me doe they deuise my
hurt.<note> Heb. euill to me.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">An euill disease,
say they, cleaueth fast vnto him; and now that he lyeth, he shall
rise vp no more.<note> Heb. a thing of Belial.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Yea mine owne
familiar friend in whom I trusted, which did eate of my bread, hath
lift vp his heele against me.<note> Ioh.13.18 , Heb. the man of my peace. , Heb. magnified.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But thou, O Lord,
be mercifull vnto mee, and raise me up vp that I may requite
them.</ab>

<fw>Dauids hope in trouble.</fw>
<ab n="11">By this I know
that thou fauourest me: because mine enemie doeth not triumph ouer
me.</ab>
<ab n="12">And as for me,
thou vpholdest me in mine integritie; and settest me before thy
face for euer.</ab>
<ab n="13">Blessed bee the
Lord God of Israel, from euerlasting, and to euerlasting. Amen, and
Amen.</ab>



</div>