<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_83" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-81-83.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-83-85.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXXIII.</head>
<head>1 A complaint to God of the enemies
conspiracies. 9 A prayer against them that oppresse the
Church.</head>

<ab n="1">[A song or Psalme
of Asaph.] Keepe not thou silence, O God: hold not thy peace, and
be not still, O God.</ab>
<ab n="2">For loe, thine
enemies make a tumult: and they that hate thee, haue lift vp the
head.</ab>
<ab n="3">They haue taken
craftie counsell against thy people, and consulted against thy
hidden ones.</ab>
<ab n="4">They haue said,
Come, and let vs cut them off from being a nation: that the name of
Israel may bee no more in remembrance.</ab>
<ab n="5">For they haue
consulted together with one consent: they are confederate against
thee.<note> Heb. heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The tabernacles of
Edom, and the Ishmaelites: of Moab, and the Hagarens.</ab>
<ab n="7">Gebal and Ammon,
and Amalek: the Philistines, with the inhabitants of Tyre.</ab>
<ab n="8">Assur also is
ioyned with them: they haue holpen the children of Lot.
Selah.<note> Hebr. they haue bene an arme to the children of Lot.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Doe vnto them as
vnto the Midianites: as to Sisera, as to Iabin, at the brooke of
Kison:<note> Iudg. 7. 22. , Iudg.4. 15. and 24.</note></ab>

<fw>The desire of the godly.</fw>
<ab n="10">Which perished at
En-dor: they became as dung for the earth.</ab>
<ab n="11">Make their nobles
like Oreb, and like Zeeb: yea all their princes as Zebah, and as
Zalmunna:<note> Iudg.7. 25. &amp; 8.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Who sayd, Let vs
take to our selues, the houses of God in possession.</ab>
<ab n="13">O my God, make
them like a wheele: as the stubble before the wind.</ab>
<ab n="14">As the fire
burneth a wood: and as the flame setteth the mountaines on
fire:</ab>
<ab n="15">So persecute them
with thy tempest: and make them afraid with thy storme.</ab>
<ab n="16">Fill their faces
with shame: that they may seeke thy name, O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="17">Let them be
confounded and troubled for euer: yea let them be put to shame, and
perish:</ab>
<ab n="18">That men may
knowe, that thou, whose name alone is IEHOVAH: art the most High
ouer all the earth.</ab>



</div>