<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_58" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-56-59.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LVIII.</head>
<head>1 Dauid reprooueth wicked Iudges, 3
Describeth the nature of the wicked, 6 Deuoteth them to Gods
iudgements, 10 whereat the righteous shall reioyce.</head>


<fw>The wicked.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician Al-taschith, Michtam of Dauid.] Doe yee indeed speake
righteousnesse, O congregation? doe ye iudge vprightly, O ye sonnes
of men?</ab>
<ab n="2">Yea, in heart you
worke wickednesse; you waigh the violence of your hands in the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="3">The wicked are
estranged from the wombe, they goe astray as soone as they be
borne, speaking lies.<note> Heb. from the belly.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Their poison is
like the poyson of a serpent; they are like the deafe adder that
stoppeth her eare:<note> Heb. according to the likenesse. , Or, aspe.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Which will not
hearken to the voyce of charmers, charming neuer so
wisely.<note> Or, be the charmest neuer so cunning.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Breake their
teeth, O God, in their mouth: breake out the great teeth of the
young lyons, O Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">Let them melt away
as waters, which runne continually: When he bendeth his bow to
shoote his arrowes, let them be as cut in pieces.</ab>
<ab n="8">As a snaile which
melteth, let euery one of them passe away: like the vntimely birth
of a woman, that they may not see the sunne.</ab>
<ab n="9">Before your pots
can feele the thornes, he shall take them away as with a
whirlewind, both liuing, and in his wrath.<note> Heb. as liuing, as wrath.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">The righteous
shall reioyce when he seeth the vengeance: he shall wash his feete
in the blood of the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="11">So that a man
shall say, Uerily there is a reward for the righteous: verily hee
is a God that iudgeth in the earth.<note> Heb. fruite of the &amp;c.</note></ab>



</div>