<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_136" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-132-136.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-136-138.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXXXVI.</head>
<head>An exhortation to giue thankes to
God for particular mercies.</head>

<ab n="1">O giue thankes
vnto the Lord, for hee is good: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Psa.106.1. and 107. 1. and 118. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">O giue thankes
vnto the God of gods: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>

<fw>Gods mercie.</fw>
<ab n="3">O giue thankes to
the Lord of lords: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="4">To him who alone
doth great wonders: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="5">To him that by
wisedome made the heauens: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Gen.1. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">To him that
stretched out the earth aboue the waters: for his mercy endureth
for euer.<note> Gen.1.6. ier.10.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">To him that made
great lights: for his mercy endureth for euer.<note> Gen.1.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">The sunne to rule
by day: for his mercy endureth for euer.<note> Heb. for the rulings by day.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The moone and
starres to rule by night: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="10">To him that
smote Egypt in their first borne: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Exod.12. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And brought out
Israel from among them: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Exod. 13. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">With a strong
hand and with a stretched out arme: for his mercy endureth for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="13">To him which
diuided the red sea into parts: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Exod. 14. 21.22.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And made Israel
to passe through the midst of it: for his mercy endureth for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="15">But ouerthrewe
Pharaoh and his hoste in the red sea: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Exod.14. 28. , Heb. shaked off.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">To him which led
his people through the wildernesse: for his mercy endureth for
euer.<note> Exod. 15. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">To him which
smote great kings: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="18">And slue famous
kings: for his mercy endureth for euer.<note> Deut. 29 7. psal. 135. 10, &amp; 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Sihon king of
the Amorites: for his mercy endureth for euer.<note> Num.21. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And Og the king
of Bashan: for his mercy endureth for euer.<note> Num.21. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And gaue their
land for an heritage: for his mercy endureth for euer.<note> Iosh.12.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Euen an heritage
vnto Israel his seruant: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="23">Who remembred vs
in our lowe estate: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="24">And hath
redeemed vs from our enemies: for his mercy endureth for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="25">Who giueth foode
to all flesh: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="26">O giue thankes
vnto the God of heauen: for his mercy endureth for euer.</ab>



</div>