<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_116" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-115-118.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXVI.</head>
<head>1 The Psalmist professeth his loue
and duetie to God, for his deliuerance. 12 Hee studieth to be
thankfull.</head>

<ab n="1">I loue the Lord:
because hee hath heard my voice, &amp; my supplications.</ab>
<ab n="2">Because hee hath
inclined his eare vnto mee: therefore will I call vpon him as long
as I liue.<note> Hebr. in my dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The sorrowes of
death compassed me, and the paines of hell gate hold vpon me: I
found trouble and sorrow.<note> Psal.18. 5.6. , Hebr. found me.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then called I
vpon the Name of the Lord: O Lord, I beseech thee deliuer my
soule.</ab>
<ab n="5">Gracious is the
Lord, and righteous: yea our God is mercifull.</ab>
<ab n="6">The Lord
preserueth the simple: I was brought low, and hee helped
me.</ab>
<ab n="7">Returne vnto thy
rest, O my soule: for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="8">For thou hast
deliuered my soule from death, mine eyes from teares, and my feete
from falling.</ab>
<ab n="9">I wil walke
before the Lord: in the land of the liuing.</ab>
<ab n="10">I beleeued,
therfore haue I spoken: I was greatly afflicted.<note> 2. Cor. 4. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">I said in my
haste: All men are lyers.<note> Rom. 3.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">What shall I
render vnto the Lord: for all his benefits towards mee?</ab>

<fw>The Saints death.</fw>
<ab n="13">I will take the
cup of saluation: and call vpon the Name of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">I will pay my
vowes vnto the Lord: now in the presence of all his people.</ab>
<ab n="15">Precious in
þe sight of the Lord: is the death of his
Saints.</ab>
<ab n="16">Oh Lord, truely
I am thy seruant, I am thy seruant, and the sonne of thy handmayde:
thou hast loosed my bonds.</ab>
<ab n="17">I will offer to
thee the sacrifice of thankes-giuing: and will call vpon the Name
of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">I will pay my
vowes vnto the Lord: now in the presence of all his people:</ab>
<ab n="19">In the Courts of
the Lords house, in the middes of thee, O Ierusalem. Praise ye the
Lord.</ab>



</div>