<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_74" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-74-75.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXIV.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet complaineth of the
desolation of the Sanctuarie. 10 Hee moueth God to helpe in
consideration of his power. 18 Of his reprochfull enemies, of his
children, and of his Couenant.</head>


<fw>Prayers of the Church
afflicted.</fw>
<ab n="1">[Maschil of
Asaph.] O God, why hast thou cast vs off for euer? why doeth thine
anger smoke against the sheepe of thy pasture?</ab>
<ab n="2">Remember thy
Congregation which thou hast purchased of olde: the rod of thine
inheritance which thou hast redeemed, this mount Sion, wherein thou
hast dwelt.<note> Or, tribe.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Lift vp thy feete
vnto the perpetuall desolations: euen all that the enemie hath done
wickedly in the Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thine enemies
roare in the midst of thy congregations: they set vp their ensignes
for signes.</ab>
<ab n="5">A man was famous
according as he had lifted vp axes vpon the thicke trees.</ab>
<ab n="6">But now they
breake downe the carued worke thereof at once, with axes and
hammers.</ab>
<ab n="7">They haue cast
fire into thy Sanctuary, they haue defiled by casting downe, the
dwelling place of thy Nawe to the ground.<note> Hebr. they bene sent thy Sanctuarie into the fire.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">They said in their
hearts, Let vs destroy them together: they haue burnt vp all the
Synagogues of God in the land.<note> Hebr. breake.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">We see not our
signes, there is no more any prophet, neither is there among vs any
that knoweth howe long.</ab>
<ab n="10">O God, how long
shall the aduersarie reproach? shall the enemie blaspheme thy Name
for euer?</ab>
<ab n="11">Why withdrawest
thou thy hand, euen thy right hand? plucke it out of thy
bosome.</ab>
<ab n="12">For God is my
King of old working saluation in the midst of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou didst diuide
the sea by thy strength: thou brakest the heads of the dragons in
the waters.<note> Exod. 14. 21. , Hebr breake. , Or, whales</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Thou brakest the
heads of Leuiathan in pieces, and gauest him to bee meat to the
people inhabiting the wildernesse.</ab>
<ab n="15">Thou didst cleaue
the fountaine and the flood: thou driedst vp mightie
riuers.<note> Exo. 17.5 num.20.11 iosh.3.13. , Heb. riuers of strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">The day is thine,
the night also is thine: thou hast prepared the light and the
sunne.</ab>

<fw>Prayers of the Church
afflicted.</fw>
<ab n="17">Thou hast set all
the borders of the earth: Thou hast made Summer and
Winter.<note> Heb. made them.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Remember this,
that the enemie hath reproached, O Lord, and that the foolish
people haue blasphemed thy Name.</ab>
<ab n="19">O deliuer not the
soule of thy turtle doue vnto the multitude of the wicked forget
not the Congregation of thy poore for euer.</ab>
<ab n="20">Haue respect vnto
the couenant: for the darke places of the earth are full of the
habitations of crueltie.</ab>
<ab n="21">O let not the
oppressed returne ashamed: let the poore and needie praise thy
name.</ab>
<ab n="22">Arise, O God,
plead thine owne cause: remember how the foolish man reprocheth
thee daily.</ab>
<ab n="23">Forget not the
voyce of thine enemies: the tumult of those that rise vp against
thee, increaseth continually.<note> Heb. ascendeth.</note></ab>



</div>