<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_92" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-90-92.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-92-94.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XCII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet exhorteth to praise
God, 4 for his great workes, 6 for his iudgements on the wicked, 10
and for his goodnesse to the godly.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme or song
for the Sabbath day.] It is a good thing to giue thanks vnto the
Lord, and to sing praises vnto thy Name, O most High:</ab>
<ab n="2">To shew foorth thy
louing kindnesse in the morning: and thy faithfulnesse euery
night:<note> Hebr. in the nights.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Upon an instrument
of tenne strings, and vpon the psalterie: vpon the harpe with a
solemne sound.<note> Or, vpon the solemne sound with the harpe. Hebr. Higgaion.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For thou, Lord,
hast made me glad through thy worke: I will triumph in the workes
of thy hands.</ab>
<ab n="5">O Lord, how great
are thy workes! and thy thoughts are very deepe.</ab>
<ab n="6">A brutish man
knoweth not: neither doeth a foole vnderstand this.</ab>

<fw>Gods power.</fw>
<ab n="7">When the wicked
spring as the grasse, and when all the workers of iniquitie doe
flourish: it is that they shall be destroyed for euer.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ But thou,
Lord, art most high for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="9">For loe, thine
enemies, O Lord, for loe, thine enemies shall perish: all the
workers of iniquity shalbe scattred.</ab>
<ab n="10">But my horne
shalt thou exalt like the horne of an vnicorne: I shalbe anointed
with fresh oyle.</ab>
<ab n="11">Mine eye also
shall see my desire on mine enemies: and mine eares shall heare my
desire of the wicked that rise vp against me.</ab>
<ab n="12">The righteous
shal flourish like the palme tree: hee shall growe like a cedar in
Lebanon.<note> Hose. 14.5</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Those that be
planted in the house of the Lord, shall flourish in the courts of
our God.</ab>
<ab n="14">They shal still
bring forth fruit in old age: they shalbe fat, &amp;
flourishing:<note> Heb. greene</note></ab>
<ab n="15">To shew that the
Lord is vpright: hee is my rocke, and there is no vnrighteousnesse
in him.</ab>



</div>