<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_68" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-66-68.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-68-69.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXVIII.</head>
<head>1 A prayer at the remoouing of the
Arke. 4 An exhortation to praise God for his mercies, 7 for his
care of the Church, 19 for his great workes.</head>


<fw>The reioycing of the iust.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician. A Psalme or song of Dauid.] Let God arise, let his
enemies be scattered: let them also that hate him, flee before
him.<note> Num.10. 36. , Hebr. from his face.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">As smoke is driuen
away, so driue them away: as waxe melteth before the fire, so let
the wicked perish at the presence of God.</ab>
<ab n="3">But let the
righteous be glad: let them reioyce before God, yea let them
exceedingly reioyce.<note> Hebr. reioyce with gladnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Sing vnto God,
sing praises to his Name: extoll him that rideth vpon the heauens,
by his Name Iah, and reioyce before him.</ab>
<ab n="5">A father of the
fatherlesse, and a iudge of the widowes, is God in his holy
habitation.</ab>
<ab n="6">God setteth the
solitary in a families: hee bringeth out those which are bound with
chaines, but the rebellious dwell in a dry land.<note> Hebr. in a house.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">O God, when thou
wentest forth before thy people; when thou didst march through the
wildernes, Selah.</ab>
<ab n="8">The earth shooke,
the heauens also dropped at the presence of God: euen Sinai it
selfe was mooued at the presence of God, the God of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="9">Thou, O God, didst
send a plentifull raine, whereby thou didst confirme thine
inheritance, when it was weary.<note> Hebr. shake out. , Hebr. confirme it.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thy Congregation
hath dwelt therein: thou, O God, hast prepared of thy goodnesse for
the poore.</ab>
<ab n="11">The Lord gaue the
word: great was the company of those that published it.<note> Hebr. armie.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Kings of armies
did flee apace: and she that taried at home, diuided the
spoile.<note> Hebr. did flee, did flee.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Though ye haue
lien among the pots, yet shall yee bee as the wings of a doue,
couered with siluer, and her feathers with yellow gold.</ab>
<ab n="14">When the Almighty
scattered Kings in it, it was white as snow in Salmon.<note> Or, for her, she was.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The hil of God is
as the hill of Bashan, an high hill as the hill of Bashan.</ab>
<ab n="16">Why leape ye, ye
high hilles? this is the Hil which God desireth to dwell in, yea
the Lord will dwel in it for euer.</ab>

<fw>Gods power in his Church.</fw>
<ab n="17">The chariots of
God are twentie thousand, euen thousands of Angels: the Lord is
among them as in Sinai, in the holy place.<note> Or, euen many thousands.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Thou hast
ascended on high, thou hast ledde captiuitie captiue, thou hast
receiued giftes for men; yea, for the rebellious also, that the
Lord God might dwell among them.<note> Eph.4.8. , Heb. in the man.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Blessed be the
Lord, who daily loadeth vs with benefits, euen the God of our
saluation. Selah.</ab>
<ab n="20">Hee that is our
God, is the God of saluation; and vnto God the Lord belong the
issues from death.</ab>
<ab n="21">But God shall
wound the head of his enemies: and the hairy scalpe of such a one
as goeth on still in his trespasses.</ab>
<ab n="22">The Lord said, I
will bring againe from Bashan, I will bring my people againe from
the depthes of the sea:</ab>
<ab n="23">That thy foote
may be dipped in the blood of thine enemies, and the tongue of thy
dogges in the same.<note> Or, red.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">They haue seene
thy goings, O God, euen the goings of my God, my King, in the
Sanctuarie.</ab>
<ab n="25">The singers went
before, the players on instruments followed after; amongst them
were the damosels playing with timbrels.</ab>
<ab n="26">Blesse yee God,
in the Congregations, euen the Lord, from the fountaine of
Israel.<note> Or, ye that are of the fountaine of Israel.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">There is little
Beniamin with their ruler, the princes of Iudah and their Councill,
the princes of Zebulun, and the princes of Naphtali.<note> Or, with their company.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">Thy God hath
commanded thy strength: strengthen, O God, that which thou hast
wrought for vs.</ab>
<ab n="29">Because of thy
Temple at Ierusalem, shall kings bring presents vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="30">Rebuke the
company of spearemen, the multitude of the bulles, with the calues
of the people, till euery one submit himselfe with pieces of
siluer: scatter thou the people that delite in warre.<note> Or, the beast of the reeds. , Or, be scattereth.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Princes shall
come out of Egypt, Ethiopia shall soone stretch out her hands vnto
God.</ab>
<ab n="32">Sing vnto God,
yee kingdomes of the earth: O sing praises vnto the Lord,
Selah:</ab>

<fw>Gods power in his Church.</fw>
<ab n="33">To him that
rideth vpon the heauens of heauens, which were of olde: loe, hee
doeth send out his voice, and that a mightie voice.<note> Heb. giue.</note></ab>
<ab n="34">Ascribe yee
strength vnto God: his excellencie is ouer Israel, and his strength
is in the cloudes.<note> Or, heauens.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">O God, thou art
terrible out of thy holy places: the God of Israel is he that
giueth strength, and power vnto his people: blessed be God.</ab>



</div>