<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_73" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-72-73.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXXIII.</head>
<head>1 The Prophet preuailing in a
Temptation, 2 sheweth the occasion thereof, the prosperitie of the
wicked: 13 The wound giuen thereby, diffidence. 15 The victory ouer
it, knowledge of Gods purpose, in destroying of the wicked and
sustaining the righteous.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Asaph.] Truely God is good to Israel, euen to such as are of a
cleane heart.<note> Or, yet. , Heb. cleane of heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But as for mee, my
feete were almost gone: my steps had well-nigh slipt.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I was enuious
at the foolish, when I sawe the prosperity of the
wicked.<note> Iob. 21.7. psal.37.1. Ierem.12.1</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For there are no
bands in their death: but their strength is firme.<note> Heb. fat.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">They are not in
trouble as other men: neither are they plagued like other
men.<note> Heb. in the trouble of other men. , Heb. with.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore pride
compasseth them about as a chaine: violence couereth them as a
garment.</ab>
<ab n="7">Their eies stand
out with fatnes: they haue more then heart could wish.<note> Heb. they passe the thoughts of the heart.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">They are corrupt,
and speake wickedly concerning oppression: they speake
loftily.</ab>
<ab n="9">They set their
mouth against the heauens; and their tongue walketh through the
earth.</ab>

<fw>The description of the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="10">Therefore his
people returne hither: and waters of a full cup are wrung out to
them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they say, How
doth God know? and is there knowledge in the most High?</ab>
<ab n="12">Behold, these are
the vngodly: who prosper in the world, they increase in
riches.</ab>
<ab n="13">Uerily I haue
cleansed my heart in vaine, and washed my hands in
innocencie.</ab>
<ab n="14">For all the day
long haue I bene plagued, and chastened euery morning.<note> Heb. my chastisement was.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">If I say, I will
speake thus: behold, I should offend against the generation of thy
children.</ab>
<ab n="16">When I thought to
know this, it was too painfull for me,<note> Heb. it was labour in mine eies.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Untill I went
into the Sanctuarie of God; then vnderstood I their end.</ab>
<ab n="18">Surely thou didst
set them in slippery places: thou castedst them downe into
destruction.</ab>
<ab n="19">How are they
brought into desolation as in a moment? they are vtterly consumed
with terrours.</ab>
<ab n="20">As a dreame when
one awaketh; so, O Lord, when thou awakest thou shalt despise their
image.</ab>
<ab n="21">Thus my heart was
greeued, and I was pricked in my reines.</ab>
<ab n="22">So foolish was I,
and ignorant: I was as a beast before thee.<note> Heb. I knew not. , Heb. with thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Neuerthelesse I
am continually with thee: thou hast holden me by my right
hand.</ab>
<ab n="24">Thou shalt guide
me with thy counsell; and afterward receiue me to glory.</ab>
<ab n="25">Whom haue I in
heauen but thee? and there is none vpon earth that I desire besides
thee.</ab>
<ab n="26">My flesh and my
heart faileth: but God is the strength of my heart, and my portion
for euer.<note> Heb. rocke.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">For loe, they
that are farre from thee, shall perish: thou hast destroyed all
them that goe awhoring from thee.</ab>
<ab n="28">But it is good
for me, to drawe neere to God: I haue put my trust in the Lord God,
that I maydeclare all thy workes.</ab>



</div>