<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_37" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-35-37.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-37-38.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXVII.</head>
<head>Dauid perswadeth to patience and
confidence in God, by the different estate of the godly and the
wicked.</head>

<ab n="1">[A Psalme of
Dauid.] Fret not thy selfe because of euill doers, neither bee thou
enuious against the workers of iniquitie.<note> Prou.23. 17. &amp; 24.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For they shall
soone be cut downe like the grasse; and wither as the greene
herbe.</ab>
<ab n="3">Trust in the Lord,
and do good, so shalt thou dwell in the land, and verely thou shalt
be fed.<note> Hebr. in trueth and stablenesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Delight thy selfe
also in the Lord; and he shall giue thee the desires of thine
heart.</ab>
<ab n="5">Commit thy way
vnto the Lord: trust also in him, and he shall bring it to
passe.<note> Heb. rolle thy way vpon the Lord. , Prou.16.3 mat.6.25. 1.Pet.5.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he shall bring
forth thy righteousnes as the light, and thy iudgement as the noone
day.</ab>

<fw>The prosperitie of the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="7">Rest in the Lord,
and wait patiently for him: fret not thy selfe because of him who
prospereth in his way, because of the man who bringeth wicked
deuices to passe.<note> Hebr. be silent to the LORD.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Cease from anger,
and forsake wrath: fret not thy selfe in any wise to doe
euill.</ab>
<ab n="9">For euil doers
shall be cut off: but those that waite vpon the Lord, they shall
inherite the earth.</ab>
<ab n="10">For yet a little
while, and the wicked shall not bee: yea, thou shalt diligently
consider his place, and it shall not be.</ab>
<ab n="11">But the meeke
shall inherite the earth: and shall delight themselues in the
abundance of peace.<note> Matt.5.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">The wicked
plotteth against the iust, and gnasheth vpon him with his
teeth.<note> Or, practiseth.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The Lord shall
laugh at him: for he seeth that his day is comming.<note> Psal.2.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The wicked haue
drawen out the sword, and haue bent their bow to cast downe the
poore and needy, and to slay such as be of vpright
conuersation.<note> Heb. the vpright of way.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Their sword shall
enter into their owne heart, and their bowes shall be
broken.</ab>
<ab n="16">A little that a
righteous man hath, is better then the riches of many
wicked.</ab>
<ab n="17">For the armes of
the wicked shall be broken: but the Lord vpholdeth the
righteous.</ab>
<ab n="18">The Lord knoweth
the dayes of the vpright: and their inheritance shall be for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="19">They shall not be
ashamed in the euill time: and in the dayes of famine they shalbe
satisfied.</ab>
<ab n="20">But the wicked
shall perish, and the enemies of the Lord shall be as the fat of
lambes: they shall consume: into smoke shall they consume
away.<note> Hebr. the preciousnes of Lambes.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">The wicked
borroweth, and payeth not againe: but the righteous sheweth mercy,
and giueth.</ab>
<ab n="22">For such as be
blessed of him, shall inherite the earth: and they that be cursed
of him, shalbe cut off.</ab>
<ab n="23">The steps of a
good man are ordered by the Lord: and he delighteth in his
way.<note> Or, established.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Though hee fall,
he shall not be vtterly cast downe: for the Lord vpholdeth him with
his hand.</ab>

<fw>The prosperitie of the wicked.</fw>
<ab n="25">I haue bene yong,
and now am old; yet haue I not seene the righteous forsaken, nor
his seede begging bread.</ab>
<ab n="26">He is euer
mercifull, and lendeth: and his seede is blessed.<note> Hebr. all the day.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Depart from
euill, and doe good; and dwell for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="28">For the Lord
loueth iudgement, and forsaketh not his Saints, they are preserued
for euer: but the seed of the wicked shall be cut off.</ab>
<ab n="29">The righteous
shall inherite the land, and dwell therein for euer.</ab>
<ab n="30">The mouth of the
righteous speaketh wisedome; and his tongue talketh of
iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="31">The Law of his
God is in his heart: none of his steps shall slide.<note> Or, going.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">The wicked
watcheth the righteous, and seeketh to slay him.</ab>
<ab n="33">The Lord will not
leaue him in his hand, nor condemne him when he is iudged.</ab>
<ab n="34">Wait on the Lord,
and keepe his way, and he shall exalt thee to inherit the land:
when the wicked are cut off, thou shalt see it.</ab>
<ab n="35">I haue seene the
wicked in great power: and spreading himselfe like a greene bay
tree.<note> Or, a greeve tree, that groweth him owne soyle.</note></ab>
<ab n="36">Yet he passed
away, and loe he was not: yea, I sought him, but hee could not be
found.</ab>
<ab n="37">Marke the perfect
man, and behold the vpright: for the end of that man is
peace.</ab>
<ab n="38">But the
transgressours shall be destroyed together: the end of the wicked
shalbe cut off.</ab>
<ab n="39">But the saluation
of the righteous is of the Lord: he is their strength in the time
of trouble.</ab>
<ab n="40">And the Lord
shall helpe them and deliuer them: he shall deliuer them from the
wicked, and saue them because they trust in him.</ab>



</div>