<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_115" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-112-115.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-115-118.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
CXV.</head>
<head>1 Because God is truly glorious, 4
and Idols are vanity, 9 He exhorteth to confidence in God. 12 God
is to be blessed for his blessings.</head>

<ab n="1">Not vnto vs, O
Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue glory: for thy mercy, and
for thy truthes sake.</ab>
<ab n="2">Wherefore should
the heathen say: Where is now their God?<note> Psal.42. 10 &amp; 79. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But our God is in
the heauens: he hath done whatsoeuer he pleased.<note> Psal.135.6</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Their idoles are
siluer and gold: the worke of mens hands.<note> Psal.135. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">They haue mouths,
but they speake not; eies haue they, but they see not.</ab>
<ab n="6">They haue eares,
but they heare not: noses haue they, but they smell not.</ab>
<ab n="7">They haue hands,
but they handle not, feete haue they, but they walke not: neither
speake they through their throat.</ab>
<ab n="8">They that make
them are like vnto them: so is euery one that trusteth in
them.</ab>
<ab n="9">O Israel, trust
thou in the Lord: he is their helpe and their shield.</ab>
<ab n="10">O house of
Aaron, trust in the Lord: he is their helpe &amp; their
shield.</ab>

<fw>Gods mercie.</fw>
<ab n="11">Ye that feare
the Lord trust in the Lord: he is their helpe and their
shield.</ab>
<ab n="12">The Lord hath
bene mindfull of vs, he will blesse vs, he will blesse the house of
Israel: he will blesse the house of Aaron.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hee will blesse
them that feare the Lord: both small and great.<note> Hebr. with.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The Lord shall
increase you more and more: you and your children.</ab>
<ab n="15">You are blessed
of the Lord: which made heauen and earth.</ab>
<ab n="16">The heauen, euen
the heauens are the Lords: but the earth hath hee giuen to the
children of men.</ab>
<ab n="17">The dead praise
not the Lord: neither any that go downe into silence.</ab>
<ab n="18">But we will
blesse the Lord, from this time foorth and for euermore. Praise the
Lord.<note> Dan.2. 20.</note></ab>



</div>