<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_65" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-64-66.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
LXV.</head>
<head>1 Dauid prayeth God for his grace. 4
The blessednesse of Gods chosen, by reason of
benefits.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
musician, a Psalme and song of Dauid.] Praise waiteth for thee, O
God, in Sion: and vnto thee shall the vowe be
performed.<note> Heb. is silent.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">O thou that
hearest prayer, vnto thee shall all flesh come.</ab>
<ab n="3">Iniquities
preuaile against me: as for our transgressions, thou shalt purge
them away.<note> Heb. words or matters of iniquities.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Blessed is the man
whom thou choosest and causest to approach vnto thee, that hee may
dwell in thy Courts: we shalbe satisfied with the goodnesse of thy
house, euen of thy holy temple.</ab>
<ab n="5">By terrible things
in righteousnesse, wilt thou answere vs, O God of our saluation:
who art the confidence of all the ends of the earth, and of them
that are a farre off vpon the sea.</ab>
<ab n="6">Which by his
strength setteth fast the mountaines; being girded with
power.</ab>
<ab n="7">Which stilleth the
noise of the seas; the noise of their waues, and the tumult of the
people.</ab>

<fw>Gods chosen: Their benefits.</fw>
<ab n="8">They also that
dwell in the vttermost parts are afraid at thy tokens: thou makest
the outgoings of the morning, and euening to reioyce.<note> Or, to sing.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Thou visitest the
earth and waterest it: thou greatly inrichest it with the riuer of
God which is full of water; thou preparest them corne, when thou
hast so prouided for it.<note> Or, after thou hadst made it to desire raine.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Thou waterest the
ridges thereof abundantly: thou settlest the furrowes thereof: thou
makest it soft with showres, thou blessest the springing
thereof.<note> Or, thou causest raine to descend into the furrowes thereof. , Heb. thou dissoluest it.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Thou crownest the
yeere with thy goodnesse; and thy paths drop fatnesse.<note> Heb. the yeere of thy goodnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">They drop vpon
the pastures of the wildernesse; and the little hilles reioyce on
euery side.<note> Heb. are girded with ioy.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The pastures are
cloathed with flockes; the valleis also are couered ouer with
corne; they shout for ioy, they also sing.</ab>



</div>