<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_31" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-30-32.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXXI.</head>
<head>1 Dauid shewing his confidence in
God, craueth his helpe. 7 He reioyceth in his mercy. 9 He prayeth
in his calamitie. 19 He prayseth God for his
goodnesse.</head>

<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, A Psalme of Dauid.] In thee, O Lord, doe I put my trust,
let me neuer be ashamed: deliuer me in thy
righteousnesse.<note> Psal. 22. 5. Esa.49. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Bowe downe thine
eare to me, deliuer me speedily: be thou my strong rocke, for an
house of defence to saue me.<note> Heb. to me for a rocke of strength.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For thou art my
rocke and my fortresse: therfore for thy names sake lead me, and
guide me.</ab>
<ab n="4">Pull me out of the
net, that they haue layd priuily for me: for thou art my
strength.</ab>
<ab n="5">Into thine hand I
commit my spirit: thou hast redeemed mee, O Lord God of
trueth.<note> Luc.23. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I haue hated them
that regard lying vanities: but I trust in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="7">I will be glad,
and reioyce in thy mercie: for thou hast considered my trouble;
thou hast knowen my soule in aduersities;</ab>
<ab n="8">And hast not shut
me vp into the hand of the enemie: thou hast set my feete in a
large roome.</ab>
<ab n="9">Haue mercy vpon
me, O Lord, for I am in trouble; mine eie is consumed with griefe,
yea my soule and my belly.</ab>
<ab n="10">For my life is
spent with griefe, and my yeeres with sighing: my strength faileth,
because of mine iniquitie, and my bones are consumed.</ab>
<ab n="11">I was a reproch
among all mine enemies, but especially among my neighbours, and a
feare to mine acquaintance: they that did see me without, fled from
me.</ab>

<fw>A prayer of the faithfull.</fw>
<ab n="12">I am forgotten as
a dead man out of minde: I am like a broken vessell.<note> Heb. a vessell that perisheth.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For I haue heard
the slaunder of many, feare was on euery side: while they tooke
counsell together against me, they deuised to take away my
life.</ab>
<ab n="14">But I trusted in
thee, O Lord: I sayd, Thou art my God.</ab>
<ab n="15">My times are in
thy hand: deliuer me from the hand of mine enemies, and from them
that persecute me.</ab>
<ab n="16">Make thy face to
shine vpon thy seruant: saue me for thy mercies sake.</ab>
<ab n="17">Let mee not be
ashamed, O Lord, for I haue called vpon thee: let the wicked be
ashamed, and let them be silent in the graue.<note> Or, let them be cast off for the graue.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Let the lying
lippes be put to silence: which speake grieuous things proudly and
contemptuously against the righteous.<note> Heb. a hard thing.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">O how great is
thy goodnesse, which thou hast layd vp for them that feare thee:
which thou hast wrought for them that trust in thee, before the
sonnes of men!<note> Esa.64. 4. 1.Cor. 2. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Thou shalt hide
them in the secret of thy presence, from the pride of man: thou
shalt keepe them secretly in a pauilion, from the strife of
tongues.</ab>
<ab n="21">Blessed be the
Lord; for hee hath shewed me his maruellous kindnesse, in a strong
citie.<note> Or, fensed city.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">For I sayd in my
haste, I am cut off from before thine eies: Neuerthelesse thou
heardest the voice of my supplications, when I cryed vnto
thee.</ab>
<ab n="23">O loue the Lord,
all yee his Saints: for the Lord preserueth the faithfull, and
plentifully rewardeth the proud doer.</ab>
<ab n="24">Be of good
courage, and hee shall strenghten your heart: all ye that hope in
the Lord.<note> Psal. 27. 14.</note></ab>



</div>