<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_40" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Psalms-Chapter-40-41.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XL.</head>
<head>1 The benefite of confidence in God.
6 Obedience is the best sacrifice. 11 The sence of Dauids euils
inflameth his prayer.</head>


<fw>Sacrifice refused.</fw>
<ab n="1">[To the chiefe
Musician, A Psalme of Dauid.] I waited patiently for the Lord, and
he inclined vnto me, and heard my crie.<note> Heb. in waiting I waited.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">He brought me vp
also out of an horrible pit, out of the mirie clay, and set my
feete vpon a rock, and established my goings.<note> Heb. a pit of noise.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And he hath put a
new song in my mouth, euen praise vnto our God: many shall see it,
and feare, and shall trust in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="4">Blessed is that
man that maketh the Lord his truste: and respecteth not the proud,
nor such as turne aside to lies.</ab>
<ab n="5">Many, O Lord my
God; are thy wonderfull workes which thou hast done, and thy
thoughts, which are to vs ward: they cannot be reckoned vp in order
vnto thee: if I would declare and speake of them, they are moe then
can be numbred.<note> Or, none can order them vnto thee.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Sacrifice and
offering thou didst not desire, mine eares hast thou opened: burnt
offering and sinne-offering hast thou not required.<note> Psal.51. 16. Esa.1. 11. &amp; 66. 3. Hos.6. 6 Heb. 10. 5. Mat.12.7 , Heb. digged.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Then sayd I, Loe,
I come: in the volume of the booke it is written of me:</ab>
<ab n="8">I delight to doe
thy will, O my God: yea thy lawe is within my heart.<note> Heb. in the midst of my bowels.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">I haue preached
righteousnesse in the great congregation: loe, I haue not refrained
my lippes, O Lord, thou knowest.</ab>
<ab n="10">I haue not hid
thy righteousnesse within my heart, I haue declared thy
faithfulnesse and thy saluation: I haue not concealed thy louing
kindnesse, and thy truth, from the great congregation.</ab>
<ab n="11">With-hold not
thou thy tender mercies from me, O Lord: let thy louing kindnesse,
and thy trueth continually preserue me.</ab>
<ab n="12">For innumerable
euils haue compassed me about, mine iniquities haue taken hold vpon
me, so that I am not able to looke vp: they are moe then the haires
of mine head, therefore my heart faileth me.<note> Heb. forsaketh.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Be pleased, O
Lord, to deliuer me: O Lord, make haste to helpe me.</ab>

<fw>Of flatterers.</fw>
<ab n="14">Let them be
ashamed and confounded together, that seeke after my soule to
destroy it: let them be driuen backward, and put to shame, that
wish me euill.<note> Psal.34. 5. &amp; 70.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Let them be
desolate, for a reward on their shame, that say vnto me, Aha,
aha!</ab>
<ab n="16">Let all those
that seeke thee, reioyce and bee glad in thee: let such as loue thy
saluation, say continually, The Lord be magnified.</ab>
<ab n="17">But I am poore
and needy, yet the Lord thinketh vpon me: thou art my helpe and my
deliuerer, make no tarrying, O my God.</ab>



</div>