<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CPsalms_42" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-41-42.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-42-42.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XLII.</head>
<head>1 Iacob sendeth his ten sonnes to
buy corne in Egypt. 6 They are imprisoned by Ioseph for spies. 18
They are set at libertie, on condition to bring Beniamin. 21 They
haue remorse for Ioseph. 24 Simeon is kept for a pledge. 25 They
returne with corne, and their money. 29 Their relation to Iacob. 36
Iacob refuseth to send Beniamin.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when Iacob
saw that there was corne in Egypt, Iacob said vnto his sonnes, Why
doe ye looke one vpon an other?<note> Acts.7. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And hee said,
Beholde, I haue heard that there is corne in Egypt: get you downe
thither and buy for vs from thence, that we may liue, and not
die.</ab>
<ab n="3">¶ And
Iosephs ten brethren went downe to buy corne in Egypt.</ab>
<ab n="4">But Beniamin
Iosephs brother, Iacob sent not with his brethren: for he said,
Lest peraduenture mischiefe befall him.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the sonnes of
Israel came to buy corne among those that came: for the famine was
in the land of Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="6">And Ioseph was
the gouernour ouer the land, and hee it was that sold to all the
people of the land: and Iosephs brethren came, &amp; bowed downe
themselues before him, with their faces to the earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">And Ioseph saw
his brethren, and he knew them, but made himselfe strange vnto
them, and spake roughly vnto them; and hee saide vnto them, Whence
come ye? And they said, From the land of Canaan, to buy
food.<note> Hebr. hard things with them.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And Ioseph knew
his brethren, but they knew not him.</ab>
<ab n="9">And Ioseph
remembred the dreames which hee dreamed of them, and said vnto
them, Ye are spies: to see the nakednes of the land you are
come.<note> Chap.37. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And they said
vnto him, Nay, my lord, but to buy food are thy seruants
come.</ab>
<ab n="11">We are all one
mans sonnes, we are true men: thy seruants are no spies.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he said vnto
them, Nay: but to see the nakednesse of the land, you are
come.</ab>

<fw>Ioseph talketh with his
brethren.</fw>
<ab n="13">And they said,
Thy seruants are twelue brethren, the sonnes of one man in the land
of Canaan: and behold, the yongest is this day with our father, and
one is not.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Ioseph said
vnto them, That is it that I spake vnto you, saying, Ye are
spies.</ab>
<ab n="15">Hereby ye shall
be proued: by the life of Pharaoh ye shall not goe foorth hence,
except your yongest brother come hither.</ab>
<ab n="16">Send one of you,
and let him fetch your brother, and ye shalbe kept in prison, that
your wordes may be proued, whether there be any trueth in you: or
els by the life of Pharaoh surely ye are spies.<note> Heb. bound</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And he put them
all together into warde, three dayes.<note> Hebr. gathered.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And Ioseph said
vnto them the third day, This doe, and liue: for I feare
God.</ab>
<ab n="19">If ye be true
men, let one of your brethren be bound in the house of your prison:
goe ye, carry corne for the famine of your houses.</ab>
<ab n="20">But bring your
yongest brother vnto mee, so shall your wordes be verified, and yee
shall not die: and they did so.<note> Chap. 43. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">¶ And they
said one to another, We are verily guiltie concerning our brother,
in that we saw the anguish of his soule, when he besought vs, and
we would not heare: therefore is this distresse come vpon
vs.</ab>
<ab n="22">And Reuben
answered them, saying, Spake I not vnto you, saying, Doe not sinne
against the childe, and ye would not heare? therefore behold also,
his blood is required.<note> Chap.37. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And they knew
not that Ioseph vnderstood them: for hee spake vnto them by an
interpreter.<note> Hebr. an interpreter was betweene them.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And hee turned
himselfe about from them and wept, and returned to them againe, and
communed with them, and tooke from them Simeon, and bound him
before their eyes.</ab>
<ab n="25">¶ Then
Ioseph commanded to fill their sackes with corne, and to restore
euery mans money into his sacke, and to giue them prouision for the
way: and thus did he vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="26">And they laded
their asses with the corne, and departed thence.</ab>

<fw>Ioseph talketh with his
brethren.</fw>
<ab n="27">And as one of
them opened his sacke, to giue his asse prouender in the Inne, he
espied his money: for behold, it was in his sackes mouth.</ab>
<ab n="28">And he said vnto
his brethren, My money is restored, and loe, it is euen in my
sacke: and their heart failed them, and they were afraid, saying
one to an other, What is this that God hath done vnto
vs?<note> Hebr. went foorth.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">¶ And they
came vnto Iacob their father, vnto the land of Canaan, and told him
all that befell vnto them, saying;</ab>
<ab n="30">The man who is
the lord of the land, spake roughly to vs, and tooke vs for spies
of the countrey.<note> Hebr. with vs hard things.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">And we said vnto
him, We are true men; we are no spies.</ab>
<ab n="32">We be twelue
brethren, sonnes of our father: one is not, and the yongest is this
day with our father, in the land of Canaan.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the man the
lord of the countrey said vnto vs, Hereby shall I know that ye are
true men: leaue one of your brethren here with me, and take foode
for the famine of your housholds, and be gone.</ab>
<ab n="34">And bring your
yongest brother vnto me: then shall I know that you are no spies,
but that you are true men: so will I deliuer you your brother, and
ye shall traffique in the land.</ab>
<ab n="35">¶ And it
came to passe as they emptied their sacks, that behold, euery mans
bundle of money was in his sacke: and when both they and their
father saw the bundels of money, they were afraid.</ab>
<ab n="36">And Iacob their
father said vnto them, We haue ye bereaued of my children: Ioseph
is not, and Simeon is not, and ye wil take Beniamin away: all these
things are against me.</ab>
<ab n="37">And Reuben spake
vnto his father, saying; Slay my two sonnes, if I bring him not to
thee: deliuer him into my hand, and I will bring him to thee
againe.</ab>
<ab n="38">And he said, My
sonne shall not goe downe with you, for his brother is dead, and he
is left alone: if mischiefe befall him by the way in the which yee
goe, then shall ye bring downe my gray haires with sorrow to the
graue.</ab>



</div>