<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 The Lambe standing on mount Sion
with his company. 6 An Angel preacheth the Gospel. 8 The fall of
Babylon. 15 The haruest of the world, and putting in of the sickle.
20 The vintage and winepresse of the wrath of God.</head>


<fw>A new song.</fw>
<ab n="1">And I looked,
and loe, a Lambe stood on the mount Sion, and with him an hundreth
fourty and foure thousand, hauing his Fathers Name written in their
foreheads.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I heard a
voice from heauen, as the voice of many waters, and as the voyce of
a great thunder: and I heard the voyce of harpers, harping with
their harpes.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they sung
as it were a new song before the throne, and before the foure
beasts, and the Elders, and no man could learne that song, but the
hundreth and fourtie and foure thousand, which were redeemed from
the earth.</ab>
<ab n="4">These are they
which were not defiled with women: for they are virgines: These are
they which follow the Lambe whithersoeuer hee goeth: These were
redeemed from among men, being the first fruits vnto God, and to
the Lambe.<note> Gr. were bought.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And in their
mouth was found no guile: for they are without fault before the
throne of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I saw
another Angel flie in the midst of heauen, hauing the euerlasting
Gospel, to preach vnto them that dwel on the earth, and to euery
nation, and kinred, and tongue, and people,</ab>
<ab n="7">Saying with a
loud voice, Feare God, and giue glory to him, for the houre of his
iudgement is come: and worshippe him that made heauen and earth,
and the sea, and the fountains of waters.<note> Psa.146.5 acts 14.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And there
followed another Angel, saying, Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that
great citie, because she made all nations drinke of the wine of the
wrath of her fornication.<note> Esa.21.9. iere.51.8. chap.18.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And the third
Angel followed them, saying with a lowd voice, If any man worship
the beast and his image, and receiue his marke in his forehead, or
in his hand,</ab>
<ab n="10">The same
shall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God, which is powred out
without mixture into the cup of his indignation, and hee shall be
tormented with fire and brimstone, in the presence of the holy
Angels, and in the presence of the Lambe:</ab>

<fw>The earth reaped.</fw>
<ab n="11">And the smoke
of their torment ascendeth vp for euer and euer. And they haue no
rest day nor night, who worship the beast and his image, and
whosoeuer receyueth the marke of his name.</ab>
<ab n="12">Here is the
patience of the Saints: Here are they that keepe the Commandements
of God, and the faith of Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="13">And I heard a
voyce from heauen, saying vnto me, Write, Blessed are the dead
which die in the Lord, from hencefoorth, yea, saith the Spirit,
that they may rest from their labours, and their workes doe follow
them.<note> Or, from henceforth saith the Spirit, yea</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I looked,
and beholde, a white cloud, and vpon the cloude one sate like vnto
the sonne of man, hauing on his head a golden crowne, and in his
hand a sharpe sickle.</ab>
<ab n="15">And another
Angel came out of the Temple crying with a loude voice to him that
sate on the cloud: Thrust in thy sickle and reape, for the time is
come for thee to reape, for the haruest of the earth is
ripe.<note> Ioel 3.13. , Or, dryed.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And hee that
sate on the cloude thrust in his sickle on the earth, and the earth
was reaped.</ab>
<ab n="17">And another
Angel came out of the Temple which is in heauen, he also hauing a
sharpe sickle.</ab>
<ab n="18">And another
Angel came out from the Altar, which had power ouer fire, and cryed
with a loud cry to him, that had the sharpe sickle, saying, Thrust
in thy sharpe sickle, and gather the clusters of the vine of the
earth, for her grapes are fully ripe.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the Angel
thrust in his sickle into the earth, and gathered the vine of the
earth, &amp; cast it into the great winepresse of the wrath of
God.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the
winepresse was troden without the citie, and blood came out of the
winepresse, euen vnto the horse bridles, by the space of a thousand
and sixe hundred furlongs.</ab>



</div>