<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The booke sealed with seuen
seales: 9 which only the lamb that was slain is worthy to opē.
12 Therfore the Elders praise him, 9 and confesse that he redeemed
them with his blood.</head>

<ab n="1">And I saw in
þe right hand of him that sate on the Throne, a
booke written within, &amp; on the backeside, sealed with seuen
seales.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I saw a
strong Angel proclaiming with a loude voice; Who is worthy to open
the booke, and to loose the seales thereof?</ab>
<ab n="3">And no man in
heauen, nor in earth, neither vnder the earth, was able to open the
booke, neither to looke thereon.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I wept
much, because no man was found worthy to open, and to reade the
booke, neither to looke thereon.</ab>

<fw>A new song.</fw>
<ab n="5">And one of the
Elders saith vnto me, Weepe not: beholde, the Lion of the tribe of
Iuda, the roote of Dauid, hath preuailed to open the booke, and to
loose the seuen seales thereof.<note> Gen.49.9</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I beheld,
and loe, in the middest of the Throne, and of the foure beastes,
and in the midst of the Elders stood a Lambe as it had beene
slaine, hauing seuen hornes and seuen eyes, which are the seuen
Spirits of God, sent foorth into all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">And he came,
and tooke the booke out of the right hand of him that sate vpon the
Throne.</ab>
<ab n="8">And when he had
taken the booke, the foure Beasts, and foure and twenty Elders fel
down before the Lambe, hauing euery one of them harps, and golden
vials full of odours, which are the prayers of Saints.<note> Or, incense.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And they sung a
new song, saying, Thou art worthy to take the Booke, and to open
the seales thereof: for thou wast slaine, and hast redeemed vs to
God by thy blood, out of euery kinred, and tongue, and people, and
nation:</ab>
<ab n="10">And hast made
vs vnto our God Kings and Priests, and we shall reigne on the
earth.<note> 1.Pet.2.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I beheld,
and I heard the voyce of many Angels, round about the Throne, and
the beasts and the Elders, and the number of them was ten thousand
times tenne thousand, and thousands of thousands,</ab>
<ab n="12">Saying with a
lowd voice, Worthy is the Lambe that was slaine, to receiue power,
and riches, and wisedome, and strength, and honour, and glory, and
blessing.</ab>
<ab n="13">And euery
creature which is in heauen, and on the earth, and vnder the earth,
and such as are in the sea, and all that are in them, heard I,
saying, Blessing, honour, glory, and power bee vnto him that
sitteth vpon the Throne, and vnto the Lambe for euer and
euer.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the foure
beasts said, Amen. And the foure and twenty Elders fell downe and
worshipped him that liueth for euer and euer.</ab>



</div>