<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The opening of the seales in
order, and what followed thereupon, conteining a prophesie to the
end of the world.</head>


<fw>Seales opened.</fw>
<ab n="1">And I sawe when
the Lambe opened one of the seales, and I heard as it were the
noise of thunder, one of the foure beastes, saying, Come and
see.</ab>
<ab n="2">And I saw, and
behold, a white horse, and hee that sate on him had a bowe, and a
crowne was giuen vnto him, and hee went foorth conquering, and to
conquere.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when hee
had opened the second seale, I heard the second beast say, Come and
see.</ab>
<ab n="4">And there went
out another horse that was red: and power was giuen to him that
sate thereon to take peace from the earth, and that they should
kill one another: and there was giuen vnto him a great
sword.</ab>
<ab n="5">And when hee
had opened the third seale, I heard the third beast say, Come and
see. And I beheld, and loe, a blacke horse: and hee that sate on
him had a paire of balances in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I heard a
voice in the midst of the foure beastes say, A measure of wheate
for a penie, and three measures of barley for a penie, and see thou
hurt not the oyle and the wine.<note> The word chænix signifieth a measure containing one wine quart, and the twelfth part of a quart.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And when hee
had opened the fourth seale, I heard the voice of the fourth beast
say, Come and see.</ab>
<ab n="8">And I looked,
and behold, a pale horse, &amp; his name that sate on him was
Death, and hell followed with him: and power was giuen vnto them,
ouer the fourth part of the earth to kill with sword, &amp; with
hunger, and with death, and with the beastes of the
earth.<note> Or, to him.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And when hee
had opened the fift seale, I saw vnder the altar, the soules of
them that were slaine for the word of God, and for the testimony
which they held.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they cried
with a lowd voice, saying, How long, O Lord, holy and true, doest
thou not iudge and auenge our blood on them that dwell on the
earth?</ab>
<ab n="11">And white
robes were giuen vnto euery one of them, and it was sayd vnto them,
that they should rest yet for a little season, vntill their fellow
seruants also, and their brethren that should be killed as they
were, should be fulfilled.</ab>

<fw>The number of the sealed.</fw>
<ab n="12">And I beheld
when he had opened the sixt seale, and loe, there was a great
earthquake, and the Sunne became blacke as sackecloth of haire, and
the Moone became as blood.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the
starres of heauen fell vnto the earth, euen as a figge tree casteth
her vntimely figs when she is shaken of a mighty winde.<note> Or.greene figs.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the heauen
departed as a scrowle when it is rolled together, and euery
mountaine and Island were moued out of their places.<note> Esa.34.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And the kings
of the earth, and the great men, and the rich men, and the chiefe
captaines, and the mighty men, and euery bondman, and euery free
man, hid themselues in the dennes, and in the rockes of the
mountaines,</ab>
<ab n="16">And said to
the mountaines and rockes, Fall on vs, and hide vs from the face of
him that sitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the
Lambe:<note> Luk.23. 30.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For the great
day of his wrath is come, and who shall be able to stand?</ab>



</div>