<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 A beast riseth out of the sea with
seuen heads and ten hornes, to whom the dragon giueth his power. 11
Another beast commeth vp out of the earth: 14 causeth an image to
be made of the former beast, 15 and that men should worship it, 16
and receiue his marke.</head>

<ab n="1">And I stoode
vpon the sand of the sea: and saw a beast rise vp out of the sea,
hauing seuen heads, and tenne hornes, and vpon his hornes tenne
crownes, and vpon his heads, the name of blasphemie.<note> Or, names.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the beast
which I saw, was like vnto a Leopard, and his feet were as the feet
of a Beare, and his mouth as the mouth of a Lion: and the dragon
gaue him his power, and his seat, and great authoritie.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I saw one
of his heads as it were wounded to death, and his deadly wound was
healed: and al the world wondered after the beast.<note> Gr. slaine.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And they
worshipped the dragon which gaue power vnto the beast, and they
worshipped the beast, saying, Who is like vnto the beast? Who is
able to make warre with him?</ab>
<ab n="5">And there was
giuen vnto him a mouth, speaking great things, and blasphemies, and
power was giuen vnto him to continue fortie and two
moneths.<note> Or, to make warre.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he opened
his mouth in blasphemie against God, to blaspheme his Name, and his
Tabernacle, and them that dwelt in heauen.</ab>

<fw>The Lambe slaine.</fw>
<ab n="7">And it was
giuen vnto him to make warre with the Saints, and to ouercome them:
And power was giuen him ouer all kinreds, and tongues, and
nations.</ab>
<ab n="8">And all that
dwel vpon the earth, shall worship him, whose names are not written
in the booke of life of the Lambe, slaine from the foundation of
the world.</ab>
<ab n="9">If any man
haue an eare, let him heare:</ab>
<ab n="10">Hee that
leadeth into captiuitie, shall goe into captiuitie: Hee that
killeth with the sword, must be killed with the sword. Here is the
patience and the faith of the Saints.<note> Matth.26. 52.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I beheld
another beast comming vp out of the earth, and hee had two hornes
like a lambe, and hee spake as a dragon.</ab>
<ab n="12">And he
exerciseth all the power of the first beast before him, and causeth
the earth and them which dwell therein, to worship the first beast,
whose deadly wound was healed.</ab>
<ab n="13">And hee doeth
great wonders, so that hee maketh fire come downe from heauen on
the earth in the sight of men,</ab>
<ab n="14">And deceiueth
them that dwel on the earth, by the meanes of those miracles which
he had power to do in the sight of the beast, saying to them that
dwell on the earth, that they should make an Image to the beast
which had the wound by a sword, and did liue.</ab>
<ab n="15">And he had
power to giue life vnto the Image of the beast, that the Image of
the beast should both speake, and cause that as many as would not
worship the Image of the beast, should be killed.<note> Gr. breath.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And he
causeth all, both smal and great rich and poore, free and bond, to
receiue a marke in their right hand, or in their
foreheads:<note> Gr. to giue.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And that no
man might buy or sell, saue he that had the marke, or the name of
the beast, or the number of his name.</ab>
<ab n="18">Here is
wisedome. Let him that hath vnderstanding, count the number of the
beast: for it is the number of a man, and his number is, sixe
hundred threescore and sixe.</ab>



</div>