<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 God is praised in heauen for
iudging the great whore, and auenging the blood of his Saints. 7
The marriage of the Lambe. 20 The Angel will not be worshipped. 17
The foules called to the great slaughter.</head>

<ab n="1">And after
these things I heard a great voyce of much people in heauen,
saying, Alleluia: saluation, and glorie, and honour, and power vnto
the Lord our God:</ab>
<ab n="2">For true and
righteous are his iudgements, for hee hath iudged the great whore
which did corrupt the earth with her fornication, and hath auenged
the blood of his seruants at her hand.</ab>
<ab n="3">And againe
they sayd, Alleluia: and her smoke rose vp for euer &amp;
euer.</ab>
<ab n="4">And the foure
and twentie Elders, and the foure beasts fell downe, and worshipped
God that sate on the throne, saying, Amen, Alleluia.</ab>
<ab n="5">And a voice
came out of the throne, saying, Praise our God all yee his
seruants, and ye that feare him, both small and great.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I heard as
it were the voice of a great multitude, and as the voice of many
waters, and as the voice of mightie thundrings, saying, Alleluia:
for the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.</ab>
<ab n="7">Let vs bee
glad and reioyce, and giue honour to him: for the mariage of the
Lambe is come, and his wife hath made herselfe readie.</ab>
<ab n="8">And to her was
granted, that she should bee arayed in fine linnen, cleane and
white: for the fine linnen is the righteousnesse of Saints.</ab>
<ab n="9">And hee saith
vnto mee, Write, Blessed are they which are called vnto the
marriage supper of the Lambe. And he saith vnto mee, These are the
true sayings of God.<note> Mat.22.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And I fell at
his feete to worship him: And he said vnto me, See thou doe it not:
I am thy fellow seruant, and of thy brethren, that haue the
testimonie of Iesus, Worship God: for the testimony of Iesus, is
the spirit of prophecie.<note> Cha.22.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And I sawe
heauen opened, and behold a white horse, and hee that sate vpon him
was called faithful and true, and in righteousnes hee doth iudge
and make warre.</ab>

<fw>The sharpesword.</fw>
<ab n="12">His eyes were
as a flame of fire, and on his head were many crownes, and hee had
a name written, that no man knew but he himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="13">And hee was
clothed with a vesture dipt in blood, and his name is called, The
word of God.<note> Esa. 63.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the
armies which were in heauen followed him vpon white horses, clothed
in fine linnen, white and cleane.</ab>
<ab n="15">And out of
his mouth goeth a sharpe sword, that with it hee should smite the
nations: and he shal rule them with a rod of yron: and he treadeth
the winepresse of the fiercenesse and wrath of Almighty
God.</ab>
<ab n="16">And he hath
on his vesture, and on his thigh a name written, King Of Kings, And
Lord Of Lords.<note> Chap.17. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And I saw an
Angel standing in the Sunne, and hee cried with a lowd voyce,
saying to all the foules that flie in the midst of heauen, Come and
gather your selues together vnto the supper of the great
God:</ab>
<ab n="18">That yee may
eate the flesh of Kings, and the flesh of Captaines, and the flesh
of mighty men, and the flesh of horses, and of them that sit on
them, and the flesh of all men both free and bond, both small and
great.</ab>
<ab n="19">And I saw the
beast, &amp; the Kings of the earth, and their armies gathered
together to make warre against him that sate on the horse, and
against his armie.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the beast
was taken, &amp; with him the false prophet, that wrought miracles
before him, with which he deceiued them that had receiued the marke
of the beast, and them that worshipped his image. These both were
cast aliue into a lake of fire burning with brimstone.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
remnant were slain with the sword of him that sate vpon the horse,
which sword proceeded out of his mouth: and all the foules were
filled with their flesh.</ab>



</div>