<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>3 The two witnesses Prophesie. 6
They haue power to shut heauen, that it raine not. 7 The beast
shall fight against them, and kill them. 8 They lie vnburied, 11
and after three dayes and a halfe rise againe. 14 The second woe is
past. 15 The seuenth trumpet soundeth.</head>

<ab n="1">And there was
giuen me a reede like vnto a rod, and the Angel stood, saying,
Rise, and measure the Temple of God, and the Altar, and them that
worship therein.</ab>
<ab n="2">But the Court
which is without the Temple leaue out, and measure it not: for it
is giuen vnto the Gentiles, and the holy citie shall they tread
vnder foote fourty and two moneths.<note> Gr. cast out</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And I will
giue power vnto my two witnesses, and they shall prophesie a
thousand two hundred and threescore dayes clothed in
sackcloth.<note> Or, I will giue vnto my two witnesses that they may prophesie.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">These are the
two oliue trees, and the two candlestickes, standing before the God
of the earth.<note> Zach.4.3. &amp; 11.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And if any man
will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and deuoureth
their enemies: and if any man will hurt them, hee must in this
maner be killed.</ab>
<ab n="6">These haue
power to shut heauen, that it raine not in the dayes of their
prophesie: and haue power ouer waters to turne them to blood, and
to smite the earth with all plagues, as often as they will.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when they
shall haue finished their testimonie, the beast that ascendeth out
of the bottomlesse pit, shall make warre against them, and shall
ouercome them, and kill them.</ab>
<ab n="8">And their dead
bodies shall lie in the street of the great citie, which
spiritually is called Sodome and Egypt, where also our Lord was
crucified.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they of
the people, and kinreds, and tongues, and nations, shal see their
dead bodies three dayes and an halfe, and shall not suffer their
dead bodies to be put in graues.</ab>
<ab n="10">And they that
dwell vpon the earth shall reioyce ouer them, and make merry, and
shall send gifts one to another, because these two Prophets
tormented them that dwelt on the earth.</ab>

<fw>An earthquake.</fw>
<ab n="11">And after
three dayes and an halfe the Spirit of life from God, entred into
them: and they stood vpon their feete, and great feare fell vpon
them which saw them.</ab>
<ab n="12">And they
heard a great voyce from heauen, saying vnto them, Come vp hither.
And they ascended vp to heauen in a cloud, and their enemies beheld
them.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the same
houre was there a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the city
fell, and in the earthquake were slaine of men seuen thousand: and
the remnant were affrighted, and gaue glory to the God of
heauen.<note> Gr names of men.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The second
woe is past, and behold, the third woe commeth quickly.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
seuenth Angel sounded, and there were great voyces in heauen,
saying, The kingdomes of this world are become the kingdomes of our
Lord, and of his Christ, and he shall reigne for euer and
euer.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the foure
and twentie Elders which sate before God on their seates, fell vpon
their faces, and worshipped God,</ab>
<ab n="17">Saying, Wee
giue thee thankes, O Lord God Almightie, which art, and wast, and
art to come; because thou hast taken to thee thy great power, and
hast reigned.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
nations were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead
that they should bee iudged, and that thou shouldest giue reward
vnto thy seruants the Prophets, and to the Saints, &amp; them that
feare thy Name, small and great, and shouldest destroy them which
destroy the earth.<note> Or, corrupt</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And the
Temple of God was opened in heauen, and there was seene in his
Temple the Arke of his Testament, and there were lightnings, and
voyces, and thundrings, and an earthquake, and great haile.</ab>



</div>