<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>2 Iohn seeth the throne of God in
heauen. 4 The foure and twentie Elders. 6 The foure beasts full of
eyes before and behinde. 10 The Elders lay downe their crownes, and
worship him that sate on the Throne.</head>

<ab n="1">After this I
looked, and beholde, a doore was opened in heauen: and the first
voice which I heard, was as it were of a trumpet, talking with me,
which said, Come vp hither, and I will shew thee things which must
be hereafter.</ab>
<ab n="2">And immediatly
I was in the spirit: and beholde, a Throne was set in heauen, and
one sate on the Throne.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he that
sate was to looke vpon like a Iasper, and a Sardine stone: and
there was a rainebow round about the Throne, in sight like vnto an
Emeralde.</ab>

<fw>The foure beasts.</fw>
<ab n="4">And round about
the Throne were foure and twentie seates, and vpon the seates I saw
foure and twentie Elders sitting, clothed in white rayment, and
they had on their heades crownes of golde.</ab>
<ab n="5">And out of the
Throne proceeded lightnings, and thundrings, and voyces: and there
were seuen lampes of fire burning before the Throne, which are the
seuen Spirits of God.</ab>
<ab n="6">And before the
Throne there was a sea of glasse like vnto Chrystall: and in the
middest of the throne, and round about the Throne, were foure
beastes full of eyes before and behinde.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the first
beast was like a Lion, and the second beast like a Calfe, and the
third beast had a face as a man, and the fourth beast was like a
flying Egle.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the foure
beasts had each of them sixe wings about him, and they were full of
eyes within, and they rest not day and night, saying, Holy, holy,
holy, Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and is to
come.<note> Gr. they haue no rest. , Esai.6.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And when those
beasts giue glory, and honour, and thankes to him that sate on the
Throne, who liueth for euer and euer,</ab>
<ab n="10">The foure and
twentie Elders fall downe before him that sate on the Throne, and
worship him that liueth for euer and euer, and cast their crownes
before the Throne, saying,</ab>
<ab n="11">Thou art
worthy, O Lord, to receiue glorie, and honour, and power: for thou
hast created all things, and for thy pleasure they are, and were
created.<note> Chap.5. 12.</note></ab>



</div>