<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>4 Iohn writeth his reuelation to the
seuen Churches of Asia, signified by the seuen golden
Candlestickes. 7 The comming of Christ. 14 His glorious power and
maiestie.</head>

<ab n="1">The Reuelation
of Iesus Christ, which God gaue vnto him, to shewe vnto his
seruants things which must shortly come to passe; and he sent and
signified it by his Angel vnto his seruant Iohn,</ab>
<ab n="2">Who bare record
of the word of God, and of the testimonie of Iesus Christ, and of
all things that he saw.</ab>
<ab n="3">Blessed is hee
that readeth, and they that heare the words of this prophesie, and
keepe those things which are written therein: for the time is at
hand.</ab>
<ab n="4">Iohn to the
seuen Churches in Asia, Grace be vnto you, &amp; peace, from him
which is, and which was, and which is to come, and from the seuen
spirits which are before his throne:<note> Exo.3.14.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And from Iesus
Christ, who is the faithful witnesse, and the first begotten of the
dead, and the Prince of the kings of the earth: vnto him that loued
vs, and washed vs from our sinnes in his owne blood,<note> 1.Cor. 15. 21. coloss. 1.18. , Heb.9.14</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And hath made
vs Kings and Priests vnto God and his Father: to him be glory and
dominion for euer and euer, Amen.<note> 1. Pet.2.5</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Behold he
commeth with clouds, and euery eye shal see him, and they also
which pearced him: and all kinreds of the earth shall waile because
of him: euen so. Amen.<note> Matt. 24. 30.</note></ab>

<fw>First and last.</fw>
<ab n="8">I am Alpha and
Omega, the beginning and the ending, saith the Lord, which is, and
which was, and which is to come, the Almighty.</ab>
<ab n="9">I Iohn, who
also am your brother, and companion in tribulation, and in the
kingdome and patience of Iesus Christ, was in the Isle that is
called Patmos, for the word of God, and for the testimonie of Iesus
Christ.</ab>
<ab n="10">I was in the
spirit on the Lords day, and heard behind me a great voice, as of a
trumpet,</ab>
<ab n="11">Saying, I am
Alpha and Omega, the first and the last: and what thou seest, write
in a booke, and send it vnto the seuen Churches which are in Asia,
vnto Ephesus, and vnto Smyrna, and vnto Pergamos, and vnto
Thyatira, and vnto Sardis, and Philadelphia, and vnto
Laodicea.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I turned
to see the voice that spake with mee. And being turned, I saw seuen
golden Candlesticks,</ab>
<ab n="13">And in the
midst of the seuen candlestickes, one like vnto the Sonne of man,
clothed with a garment downe to the foot, and girt about the paps
with a golden girdle.</ab>
<ab n="14">His head, and
his haires were white like wooll as white as snow, and his eyes
were as a flame of fire,</ab>
<ab n="15">And his feet
like vnto fine brasse, as if they burned in a furnace: and his
voice as the sound of many waters.</ab>
<ab n="16">And hee had in
his right hand seuen starres: and out of his mouth went a sharpe
two edged sword: and his countenance was as the Sunne shineth in
his strength.</ab>
<ab n="17">And when I
sawe him, I fell at his feete as dead: and hee laid his right hand
vpon me, saying vnto mee, Feare not, I am the first, and the
last.<note> Esay. 41. 4.and 44.6</note></ab>

<fw>Seuen candlesticks.</fw>
<ab n="18">I am hee that
liueth, and was dead: and behold, I am aliue for euermore, Amen,
and haue the keyes of hell and of death.</ab>
<ab n="19">Write the
things which thou hast seene, and the things which are, and the
things which shall be hereafter,</ab>
<ab n="20">The mysterie
of the seuen starres which thou sawest in my right hand, and the
seuen golden Candlestickes. The seuen Starres are the Angels of the
seuen Churches: and the seuen candlestickes which thou sawest, are
the seuen Churches.</ab>



</div>