<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_20" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-19-20.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XX.</head>
<head>2 Satan bound for a thousand yeeres.
6 The first resurrection: they blessed that haue part therein. 7
Satan let loose againe. 8 Gog and Magog. 10 The deuil cast into the
lake of fire and brimstone. 12 The last and generall
resurrection.</head>


<fw>Satan loosed.</fw>
<ab n="1">And I saw an
Angel come down from heauen, hauing the key of the bottomles pit,
&amp; a great chaine in his hand.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee laid
hold on the dragon that old serpent, which is the deuill and Satan,
and bound him a thousand yeres,</ab>
<ab n="3">And cast him
into the bottomlesse pit, and shut him vp, and set a seale vpon
him, that he should deceiue the nations no more, till the thousand
yeeres should bee fulfilled: and after that hee must be loosed a
little season.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I saw
thrones, and they sate vpon them, and iudgement was giuen vnto
them: &amp; I saw the soules of them that were beheaded for the
witnesse of Iesus, and for the word of God, and which had not
worshipped the beast, neither his image, neither had receiued his
marke vpon their foreheads, or in their hands; and they liued and
reigned with Christ a thousand yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="5">But the rest
of the dead liued not againe vntill the thousand yeeres were
finished. This is the first resurrection.</ab>
<ab n="6">Blessed &amp;
holy is he that hath part in þe first resurrection:
on such the second death hath no power, but they shall be Priests
of God, and of Christ, and shall reigne with him a thousand
yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when the
thousand yeeres are expired, Satan shall be loosed out of his
prison,</ab>
<ab n="8">And shall goe
out to deceiue the nations which are in the foure quarters of the
earth, Gog &amp; Magog, to gather them together to battell: the
number of whom is as the sand of the sea.<note> Ezek.38. 2.and 39.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And they went
vp on the breadth of the earth, and compassed the campe of the
Saints about, and the beloued citie: and fire came downe from God
out of heauen, and deuoured them.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the deuil
that deceiued them, was cast into the lake of fire and brimstone,
where the beast and the false prophet are, and shall be tormented
day and night, for euer and euer.</ab>
<ab n="11">And I saw a
great white throne, and him that sate on it, from whose face the
earth and the heauen fled away, and there was found no place for
them.</ab>

<fw>A new heauen.</fw>
<ab n="12">And I sawe
the dead, small and great, stand before God: and the books were
opened: &amp; another booke was opened, which is the booke of life:
and the dead were iudged out of those things which were written in
the books, according to their works.<note> Chap.3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the sea
gaue vp the dead which were in it: and death and hell deliuered vp
the dead which were in them: and they were iudged euery man
according to their works.<note> Or, hell.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And death and
hell were cast into the lake of fire: this is the second
death.</ab>
<ab n="15">And whosoeuer
was not found written in the booke of life, was cast into the lake
of fire.</ab>



</div>