<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>2 Babylon is fallen. 4 The people of
God commanded to depart out of her. 9 The Kings of the earth, 11
with the Merchants and Mariners, lament ouer her. 20 The Saints
reioyce for the iudgements of God vpon her.</head>


<fw>Babylon is fallen.</fw>
<ab n="1">And after
these things, I saw another Angel come downe from heauen, hauing
great power, and the earth was lightened with his glory.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he cryed
mightily with a strōg voyce, saying, Babylon the great is
fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of deuils, and the
hold of euery foule spirit, and a cage of euery vncleane and
hatefull bird:<note> Chap.14. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For all
nations haue drunke of the wine of the wrath of her fornication,
and the Kings of the earth haue committed fornication with her,
&amp; the Merchants of the earth are waxed rich thorow the
abundance of her delicacies.<note> Or, power.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And I heard
another voice from heauen, saying, Come out of her, my people, that
yee be not partakers of her sinnes, and that yee receiue not of her
plagues:</ab>
<ab n="5">For her sinnes
haue reached vnto heauen, and God hath remembred her
iniquities.</ab>
<ab n="6">Reward her
euen as she rewarded you, and double vnto her double according to
her works: in the cup which she hath filled, fill to her
double.</ab>
<ab n="7">How much she
hath glorified her selfe, and liued deliciously, so much torment
and sorrow giue her: for she saith in her heart, I sit a Queene,
and am no widow, and shall see no sorrow.<note> Esay.47. 8.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore
shall her plagues come in one day, death, and mourning, and famine,
and she shall bee vtterly burnt with fire, for strong is the Lord
God, who iudgeth her.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the Kings
of the earth, who haue committed fornication, and liued deliciously
with her, shall bewaile her and lament for her, when they shall see
the smoke of her burning:</ab>
<ab n="10">Standing
afarre off for the feare of her torment, saying, Alas, alas, that
great citie Babylon, that mighty citie: for in one houre is thy
iudgement come.</ab>
<ab n="11">And the
Merchants of the earth shall weepe and mourne ouer her, for no man
buyeth their merchandise any more.</ab>

<fw>Babylon destroyed.</fw>
<ab n="12">The
merchandise of gold, and siluer, and pretious stones, and of
pearles, and fine linnen, and purple, and silke, and scarlet, and
all Thine wood, and all maner vessels of Yuorie, and all maner
vessels of most precious wood, and of brasse, and iron, and
marble,<note> Or, sweet.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And Cynamome,
and odours, and ointments, and frankincense, &amp; wine, and oile,
and fine floure, and wheat, and beasts, and sheepe, and horses, and
chariots, and slaues, and soules of men.<note> Or, bodies.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And the
fruits that thy soule lusted after, are departed from thee, and all
things which were daintie, and goodly, are departed from thee, and
thou shalt finde them no more at all.</ab>
<ab n="15">The Merchants
of these things which were made riche by her, shall stand afarre
off for the feare of her torment, weeping and wailing.</ab>
<ab n="16">And saying,
Alas, alas, that great city, that was clothed in fine linnen, and
purple and scarlet, and decked with gold, and pretious stones, and
pearles:</ab>
<ab n="17">For in one
houre so great riches is come to nought. And euery shipmaster, and
all the company in ships, and sailers, and as many as trade by sea,
stood a farre off,</ab>
<ab n="18">And cryed
when they saw the smoke of her burning, saying, What city is like
vnto this great citie?</ab>
<ab n="19">And they cast
dust on their heads, and cried, weeping, and wailing, saying, Alas,
alas, that great citie, wherein were made rich all that had ships
in the sea, by reason of her costlinesse, for in one houre is she
made desolate.</ab>
<ab n="20">Reioyce ouer
her thou heauen, and ye holy Apostles and Prophets, for God hath
auenged you on her.</ab>
<ab n="21">And a mightie
Angel tooke vp a stone like a great milstone, and cast it into the
sea, saying, Thus with violence shall that great citie Babylon bee
throwen downe, and shall bee found no more at all.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the voyce
of harpers and musitions, and of pipers, and trumpetters, shall bee
heard no more at all in thee: and no craftsman, of whatsoeuer craft
hee be, shall be found any more in thee: and the sound of a
milstone shalbe heard no more at all in thee:</ab>
<ab n="23">And the light
of a candle shall shine no more at all in thee: and the voice of
the bridegrome and of the bride shalbe heard no more at all in
thee: for thy Merchants were the great men of the earth: for by thy
sorceries were all nations deceiued.</ab>
<ab n="24">And in her
was found the blood of Prophets, and of Saints, and of all that
were slaine vpon the earth.</ab>



</div>