<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-14-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>2 The Angels powre out their Vials
full of wrath. 6 The plagues that follow thereupon. 15 Christ
commeth as a thiefe. Blessed are they that watch.</head>

<ab n="1">And I heard a
great voyce out of the Temple, saying to the seuen Angels, Goe your
wayes, and powre out the vials of the wrath of God vpō the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="2">And the first
went, and powred out his viall vpon the earth, and there fell a
noysome and grieuous sore vpon the men which had the marke of the
beast, and vpon them which worshipped his image.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the second
Angel powred out his viall vpon the sea, and it became as the blood
of a dead man: and euery liuing soule died in the sea.</ab>

<fw>Blood to drinke.</fw>
<ab n="4">And the third
Angel powred out his viall vpon the riuers and fountaines of
waters, &amp; they became blood.</ab>
<ab n="5">And I heard
the Angel of the waters say, Thou art righteous, O Lord, which art,
and wast, and shalt be, because thou hast iudged thus:</ab>
<ab n="6">For they haue
shedde the blood of Saints and Prophets, and thou hast giuen them
blood to drinke: for they are worthy.</ab>
<ab n="7">And I heard
another out of the altar say, Euen so, Lord God Almightie, true and
righteous are thy iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the fourth
Angel powred out his viall vpon the Sunne, and power was giuen vnto
him to scorch men with fire.</ab>
<ab n="9">And men were
scorched with great heat, and blasphemed the Name of God, which
hath power ouer these plagues: and they repented not, to giue him
glory.<note> Or, burned</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And the fift
Angel powred out his viall vpon the seat of the beast, and his
kingdome was full of darkenesse, and they gnawed their tongues for
paine,</ab>
<ab n="11">And
blasphemed the God of heauen, because of their paines, and their
sores, and repented not of their deeds.</ab>
<ab n="12">And the sixt
Angel powred out his viall vpon the great riuer Euphrates, and the
water thereof was dried vp, that the way of the Kings of the East
might be prepared.</ab>
<ab n="13">And I saw
three vncleane spirits like frogs come out of the mouth of the
dragon, &amp; out of the mouth of the beast, &amp; out of the mouth
of the false prophet.</ab>
<ab n="14">For they are
the spirits of deuils working miracles, which goe forth vnto the
Kings of the earth, and of the whole world, to gather them to the
battell of that great day of God Almighty.</ab>
<ab n="15">Behold, I
come as a thiefe. Blessed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his
garments, least hee walke naked, and they see his
shame.<note> Mat.24 44.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And hee
gathered them together into a place, called in the Hebrewe tongue,
Armageddon.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the
seuenth Angel powred out his viall into the ayre, and there came a
great voyce out of the Temple of heauen, from the throne, saying,
It is done.</ab>

<fw>Great Babylon.</fw>
<ab n="18">And there
were voices and thunders, and lightnings: and there was a great
earthquake, such as was not since men were vpon the earth, so
mighty an earthquake, and so great.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the great
Citie was diuided into three parts, and the Cities of the nations
fell: and great Babylon came in remembrance before God, to giue
vnto her the cup of the wine of the fiercenesse of his
wrath.<note> Ier.25.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And euery
yland fled away, and the mountaines were not found.</ab>
<ab n="21">And there
fell vpon men a great haile out of heauen, euery stone about the
weight of a talent, and men blasphemed God, because of the plague
of the hayle: for the plague thereof was exceeding great.</ab>



</div>