<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>What is commaunded to bee written to
the Angels, that is, the Ministers of the Churches of 1 Ephesus, 8
Smyrna, 12 Pergamus, 18 Thyatira: and what is commended, or found
wanting in them.</head>

<ab n="1">Vnto the Angel
of the church of Ephesus, write, These things saith he that holdeth
the seuen starres in his right hand, who walketh in the midst of
the seuen golden Candlesticks:</ab>
<ab n="2">I know thy
workes, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canst not
beare them which are euil, and thou hast tried them which say they
are Apostles, and are not, and hast found them lyers:</ab>
<ab n="3">And hast borne,
and hast patience, and for my Names sake hast laboured, and hast
not fainted.</ab>
<ab n="4">Neuerthelesse,
I haue somewhat against thee, because thou hast left thy first
loue.</ab>
<ab n="5">Remember
therfore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe the first
workes, or else I will come vnto thee quickly, and will remoue thy
Candlesticke out of his place, except thou repent.</ab>
<ab n="6">But this thou
hast, that thou hatest the deeds of the Nicolaitans, which I also
hate.</ab>
<ab n="7">Hee that hath
an eare, let him heare what the Spirit saith vnto the Churches: To
him that ouercommeth will I giue to eate of the tree of life, which
is in the middest of the Paradise of God.</ab>
<ab n="8">And vnto the
Angel of the Church in Smyrna, write, These things saith the first
and the last, which was dead, and is aliue,</ab>

<fw>Balaams doctrine.</fw>
<ab n="9">I know thy
works, and tribulation, and pouertie, but thou art rich, and I know
the blasphemie of them which say they are Iewes and are not, but
are the Synagogue of Satan.</ab>
<ab n="10">Feare none of
those things which thou shalt suffer: behold, the deuill shal cast
some of you into prison, that ye may be tried, and yee shall haue
tribulation tenne dayes: bee thou faithfull vnto death, and I will
giue thee a crowne of life.</ab>
<ab n="11">He that hath
an eare, let him heare what the spirit saith vnto the churches. He
that ouercommeth, shall not be hurt of the second death.</ab>
<ab n="12">And to the
Angel of the Church in Pergamos, write, These things saith hee,
which hath the sharpe sword with two edges:</ab>
<ab n="13">I know thy
workes, and where thou dwellest, euen where Satans seat is, and
thou holdest fast my Name, and hast not denied my faith, euen in
those daies, wherein Antipas was my faithful Martyr, who was slaine
among you, where Satan dwelleth.</ab>
<ab n="14">But I haue a
fewe things against thee, because thou hast there them that holde
the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balac to cast a stumbling blocke
before the children of Israel, to eate things sacrificed vnto
idoles, and to commit fornication.<note> Num.25.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">So hast thou
also them that hold the doctrine of the Nicolaitans, which thing I
hate.</ab>
<ab n="16">Repent, or
else I will come vnto thee quickly, and wil fight against them with
the sword of my mouth.</ab>
<ab n="17">Hee that hath
an eare, let him heare what the Spirit saith vnto the Churches. To
him that ouercommeth will I giue to eate of the hidden Manna, and
will giue him a white stone, and in the stone a new name written,
which no man knoweth, sauing hee that receiueth it.</ab>
<ab n="18">And vnto the
Angel of the church in Thyatira, write, These things saith the
Sonne of God, who hath his eyes like vnto a flame of fire, and his
feete are like fine brasse:</ab>
<ab n="19">I know thy
works, and charitie, and seruice, and faith, and thy patience, and
thy workes, and the last to bee more then the first.</ab>

<fw>To hold fast.</fw>
<ab n="20">Notwithstanding,
I haue a few things against thee, because thou sufferest that woman
Iezebel, which calleth herselfe a Prophetesse, to teach and to
seduce my seruants to commit fornication, and to eat things
sacrificed vnto idoles.<note> 1. Kin.16. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And I gaue her
space to repent of her fornication, and she repented not.</ab>
<ab n="22">Behold, I will
cast her into a bed, and them that commit adultery with her, into
great tribulation, except they repent of their deeds.</ab>
<ab n="23">And I will
kill her children with death, and all the Churches shall know that
I am hee which searcheth the reines and hearts: and I will giue
vnto euery one of you according to your workes.<note> Iere. 11. 20.and 17. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">But vnto you I
say, and vnto the rest in Thyatira, as many as haue not this
doctrine, and which haue not knowen the depthes of Satan, as they
speake, I will put vpon you none other burden:</ab>
<ab n="25">But that which
ye haue already, hold fast till I come.</ab>
<ab n="26">And hee that
ouercommeth, and keepeth my workes vnto the ende, to him will I
giue power ouer the nations:</ab>
<ab n="27">(And he shall
rule them with a rod of yron: as the vessels of a potter shall they
be broken to shiuers:) euen as I receiued of my Father.<note> Psal.2.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And I will
giue him the morning starre.</ab>
<ab n="29">He that hath
an eare, let him heare what the Spirit saith vnto the
Churches.</ab>



</div>