<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_21" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-20-21.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-21-22.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XXI.</head>
<head>1 A new heauen and a new earth. 10
The heauenly Ierusalem, with a full description thereof. 23 She
needeth no Sunne, the glory of God is her light. 24 The kings of
the earth bring their riches vnto her.</head>

<ab n="1">And I saw a
new heauen, and a new earth: for the first heauen, and the first
earth were passed away, and there was no more sea.<note> Esa.65.17 2.pet.3.13</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And I Iohn saw
the holy City, new Hierusalem comming down from God out of heauen,
prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.</ab>
<ab n="3">And I heard a
great voice out of heauen, saying, Behold, the Tabernacle of God is
with men, and he wil dwell with them, and they shall be his people,
and God himselfe shalbe with them, and be their God.</ab>
<ab n="4">And God shall
wipe away all teares from their eyes: and there shall bee no more
death, neither sorrow, nor crying, neither shall there bee any more
paine: for the former things are passed away.<note> Chap.7.17</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And he that
sate vpon the throne, said, Behold, I make all things new. And hee
said vnto me, Write: for these words are true and
faithfull.<note> 2.Cor.5. 17.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And he said
vnto mee, It is done: I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the
end. I will giue vnto him that is athirst, of the fountaine of the
water of life, freely.<note> Chap.1.8. and 22. 13. , Esa.55.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">He that
ouercommeth, shall inherite all things, and I will bee his God, and
he shall be my sonne.</ab>
<ab n="8">But the
fearefull, and vnbeleeuing, and the abominable, and murderers, and
whore mongers, and sorcerers, and idolaters, and all lyars, shall
haue their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone:
which is the second death.</ab>

<fw>Holy Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="9">And there came
vnto me one of the seuen Angels, which had the seuen vials full of
the seuen last plagues, and talked with me, saying, Come hither, I
will shew thee the Bride, the Lambes wife.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he caried
me away in the spirit to a great and high mountaine, and shewed me
that great citie, the holy Hierusalem, descending out of heauen
from God,</ab>
<ab n="11">Hauing the
glory of God: and her light was like vnto a stone most precious;
euen like a iasper stone, cleare as christal,</ab>
<ab n="12">And had a
wall great and high, and had twelue gates, and at the gates twelue
Angels, &amp; names written thereon, which are the names of the
twelue tribes of the children of Israel.</ab>
<ab n="13">On the East
three gates, on the North three gates, on the South three gates,
and on the West three gates.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the wall
of the citie had twelue foundations, and in them the names of the
twelue Apostles of the Lambe.</ab>
<ab n="15">And hee that
talked with mee, had a golden reede to measure the citie, and the
gates thereof, and the wall thereof.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the city
lieth foure square, and the length is as large as the breadth: and
he measured the city with the reed, twelue thousand furlongs: the
length, and the breadth, and the height of it are equall.</ab>
<ab n="17">And he
measured the wall thereof, an hundred, and fourtie, and foure
cubites, according to the measure of a man, that is, of the
Angel.</ab>
<ab n="18">And the
building of the wall of it was of Iasper, and the city was pure
gold, like vnto cleare glasse.</ab>
<ab n="19">And the
foundations of the wall of the city were garnished with all maner
of precious stones. The first foundation was Iasper, the second
Saphir, the third a Chalcedony, the fourth an Emerald,</ab>
<ab n="20">The fift
Sardonix, the sixt Sardius, the seuenth Chrysolite, the eight
Beryl, the ninth a Topas, the tenth a Chrysoprasus, the eleuenth a
Iacinct, the twelfth an Amethyst.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
twelue gates were twelue pearles, euery seuerall gate was of one
pearle, and the streete of the city was pure golde, as it were
transparent glasse.</ab>

<fw>The water of life is offered
freely.</fw>
<ab n="22">And I saw no
Temple therein: For the Lord God Almightie, and the Lambe, are the
Temple of it.</ab>
<ab n="23">And the citie
had no need of the Sunne, neither of the Moone to shine in it: for
the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lambe is the light
thereof.<note> Esai. 60. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">And the
nations of them which are saued, shall walke in the light of it:
and the kings of the earth doe bring their glory and honour into
it.<note> Esai.60.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">And the gates
of it shall not bee shut at all by day: for there shall bee no
night there.<note> Esai.60.11</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And they
shall bring the glorie and honour of the nations into it.</ab>
<ab n="27">And there
shall in no wise enter into it any thing that defileth, neither
whatsoeuer worketh abomination, or maketh a lie: but they which are
written in the Lambes booke of life.</ab>



</div>