<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>2 The Angel of the Church of Sardis
is reproued, 3 exhorted to repent, and threatned if hee doe not
repent. 8 The Angel of the Church of Philadelphia 10 is approoued
for his diligence and patience. 15 The Angel of Laodicea rebuked,
for being neither hote nor colde, 19 and admonished to be more
zealous. 20 Christ standeth at the doore, and
knocketh.</head>

<ab n="1">And vnto the
Angel of the Church in Sardis write, These things saith he that
hath the seuen Spirits of God, &amp; the seuen starres; I know thy
workes, that thou hast a name that thou liuest, and art
dead.</ab>
<ab n="2">Be watchfull,
and strengthen the things which remaine, that are ready to die: for
I haue not found thy works perfect before God.</ab>

<fw>The key of Dauid.</fw>
<ab n="3">Remember
therefore, how thou hast receiued and heard, and hold fast, and
repent. If therefore thou shalt not watch, I will come on thee as a
thiefe, and thou shalt not know what houre I will come vpon
thee.<note> 1.Thess.5. 2. 2.pet.3. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Thou hast a few
names euen in Sardis, which haue not defiled their garments, and
they shall walke with me in white: for they are worthy.</ab>
<ab n="5">Hee that
ouercommeth, the same shalbe clothed in white raiment, and I will
not blot out his name out of the booke of life, but I will confesse
his name before my Father, and before his Angels.<note> Chap. 20. 12. phil.4. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Hee that hath
an eare, let him heare what the Spirit saith vnto the
Churches.</ab>
<ab n="7">And to the
Angel of the Church in Philadelphia write, These things saith he
that is Holy, he that is true, he that hath the key of Dauid, he
that openeth, and no man shutteth, and shutteth, and no man
openeth;</ab>
<ab n="8">I know thy
workes: behold, I haue set before thee an open doore, and no man
can shut it: for thou hast a little strength, and hast kept my
word, and hast not denied my Name.</ab>
<ab n="9">Behold, I will
make them of the synagogue of Satan, which say they are Iewes, and
are not, but doe lie: behold, I will make them to come and worship
before thy feete, and to know that I haue loued thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">Because thou
hast kept the word of my patience, I also will keepe thee from the
houre of temptation, which shall come vpon all the world, to try
them that dwell vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="11">Beholde, I
come quickly, hold that fast which thou hast, that no man take thy
crowne.</ab>
<ab n="12">Him that
ouercommeth, will I make a pillar in the Temple of my God, and he
shall goe no more out: and I wil write vpon him the Name of my God,
and the name of the Citie of my God, which is new Hierusalem, which
commeth downe out of heauen from my God: And I will write vpon him
my New name.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hee that hath
an eare, let him heare what the Spirit saith vnto the
Churches.</ab>
<ab n="14">And vnto the
Angel of the Church of the Laodiceans, write, These things saith
the Amen, the faithfull and true witnesse, the beginning of the
creation of God:<note> Or, in Laodicea.</note></ab>

<fw>Lukewarme. The foure beasts.</fw>
<ab n="15">I know thy
workes, that thou art neither cold nor hot, I would thou wert cold
or hot.</ab>
<ab n="16">So then
because thou art lukewarme, and neither cold nor hot, I wil spew
thee out of my mouth:</ab>
<ab n="17">Because thou
sayest, I am rich, and increased with goods, and haue need of
nothing: and knowest not that thou art wretched, and miserable, and
poore, and blinde, and naked.</ab>
<ab n="18">I counsell
thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire, that thou mayest bee
rich, and white raiment, that thou mayest be clothed, and that the
shame of thy nakednesse doe not appeare, and anoint thine eyes with
eye salue, that thou mayest see.</ab>
<ab n="19">As many as I
loue, I rebuke and chasten, be zealous therefore, and
repent.<note> Prou.3.11. hebr. 12. 5.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, I
stand at the doore, and knocke: if any man heare my voyce, and open
the doore, I will come in to him, and will sup with him, and he
with me.</ab>
<ab n="21">To him that
ouercommeth, will I graunt to sit with mee in my throne, euen as I
also ouercame, and am set downe with my Father in his
throne.</ab>
<ab n="22">Hee that hath
an eare, let him heare what the Spirit saith vnto the
Churches.</ab>



</div>