<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>A mightie strong Angel appeareth
with a booke open in his hand. 6 Hee sweareth by him that liueth
for euer, that there shalbe no more time. 9 Iohn is commaunded to
take and eate the booke.</head>


<fw>The booke eaten.</fw>
<ab n="1">And I saw
another mighty Angel come down from heauen, clothed with a cloud,
and a rainebow was vpon his head, and his face was as it were the
Sunne, and his feet as pillars of fire.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee had in
his hand a little booke open: and hee set his right foote vpon the
sea, and his left foote on the earth,</ab>
<ab n="3">And cryed with
a loude voice, as when a Lion roareth: and when hee had cried,
seuen thunders vttered their voices.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when the
seuen thunders had vttered their voices, I was about to write: and
I heard a voice from heauen, saying vnto mee, Seale vp those things
which the seuen thunders vttered, and write them not.</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Angel
which I saw stand vpon the sea, and vpon the earth, lifted vp his
hand to heauen,</ab>
<ab n="6">And sware by
him that liueth for euer and euer, who created heauen, and the
things that therein are, and the earth, and the things that therein
are, and the sea, and the things which are therein, that there
should bee time no longer.</ab>
<ab n="7">But in the
dayes of the voice of the seuenth Angel, when he shall begin to
sound, the mysterie of God should be finished, as hee hath declared
to his seruants the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the voice
which I heard from heauen spake vnto me againe, and said, Go, and
take the litle booke which is open in the hand of the Angel which
standeth vpon the sea, and vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I went
vnto the Angel, and said vnto him, Giue me the little booke. And he
sayd vnto me, Take it, and eat it vp, and it shall make thy belly
bitter, but it shall bee in thy mouth sweete as hony.<note> Ezek.2.8. and 3.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And I tooke
the little booke out of the Angels hand, and ate it vp, and it was
in my mouth sweet as honie: and as soone as I had eaten it, my
belly was bitter.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he sayd
vnto me, Thou must prophesie againe before many peoples, and
nations, and tongues, and kings.</ab>



</div>