<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRevelation_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-10-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Revelation-Chapter-12-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 A woman clothed with the Sunne
trauaileth. 4 The great red dragon standeth before her, ready to
deuoure her child: 6 when she was deliuered she fleeth into the
wildernes. 7 Michael and his Angels fight with the dragon, and
preuaile. 13 The dragon being cast down into the earth, persecuteth
the woman.</head>


<fw>Satan cast out.</fw>
<ab n="1">And there
appeared a great wonder in heauen, a woman clothed with the Sunne,
&amp; the Moone vnder her feete, and vpon her head a Crowne of
twelue starres:<note> Or, signe.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And shee being
with childe, cried, trauailing in birth, and pained to be
deliuered.</ab>
<ab n="3">And there
appeared another wonder in heauen, and behold a great red dragon,
hauing seuen heads, and ten hornes, and seuen crownes vpon his
heads.<note> Or, signe.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And his taile
drew the third part of the starres of heauen, and did cast them to
the earth: And the dragon stood before the woman which was ready to
be deliuered, for to deuoure her childe as soone as it was
borne.</ab>
<ab n="5">And shee
brought foorth a man child, who was to rule all nations with a rod
of yron: and her child was caught vp vnto God, and to his
Throne.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the woman
fled into the wildernesse, where shee hath a place prepared of God,
that they should feed her there a thousand, two hundred, and
threescore dayes.</ab>
<ab n="7">And there was
warre in heauen, Michael and his Angels fought against the dragon,
&amp; the dragon fought and his angels,</ab>
<ab n="8">And preuailed
not, neither was their place found any more in heauen.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the great
dragon was cast out, that old serpent, called the deuill and Satan,
which deceiueth the whole world: hee was cast out into the earth,
and his angels were cast out with him.</ab>
<ab n="10">And I heard a
lowd voyce saying in heauen, Now is come saluation, and strength,
and the kingdome of our God, and the power of his Christ: for the
accuser of our brethren is cast down, which accused them before our
God day and night.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they
ouercame him by the blood of the Lambe, and by the word of their
Testimony, and they loued not their liues vnto the death.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore
reioyce, yee heauens, and yee that dwell in them; Woe to the
inhabiters of the earth, and of the sea: for the deuill is come
downe vnto you, hauing great wrath, because he knoweth that he hath
but a short time.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when the
dragon saw that he was cast vnto the earth, hee persecuted the
woman which brought foorth the man childe.</ab>

<fw>Satans rage.</fw>
<ab n="14">And to the
woman were giuen two wings of a great Eagle, that shee might flee
into the wildernesse into her place, where she is nourished for a
time, and times, and halfe a time, from the face of the
serpent.</ab>
<ab n="15">And the
serpent cast out of his mouth water as a flood, after the woman:
that he might cause her to bee caried away of the flood.</ab>
<ab n="16">And the earth
helped the woman, and the earth opened her mouth, and swallowed vp
the flood which the dragon cast out of his mouth.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the
dragon was wroth with the woman, and went to make warre with the
remnant of her seed, which keepe the Commaundements of God, and
haue the testimony of Iesus Christ.</ab>



</div>