<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>1 Gods mercies must mooue vs to
please God. 3 No man must thinke too well of himselfe, 6 But attend
euerie one, on that calling, wherein he is placed. 9 Loue, and many
other dueties are required of vs. 19 Reuenge is specially
forbidden.</head>

<ab n="1">I beseech you
therefore brethren, by the mercies of God, that yee present your
bodies a liuing sacrifice, holy, acceptable vnto God, which is your
reasonable seruice.</ab>
<ab n="2">And bee not
conformed to this world: but be ye transformed by the renuing of
your minde, that ye may proue what is that good, that acceptable
and perfect will of God.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I say, through
the grace giuen vnto mee, to euery man that is among you, not to
thinke of himselfe more highly then hee ought to thinke, but to
thinke soberly, according as God hath dealt to euery man the
measure of faith.<note> Gr. to sobrietie.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For as we haue
many members in one body, and all members haue not the same
office:</ab>
<ab n="5">So we being many
are one bodie in Christ, and euery one members one of
another.</ab>
<ab n="6">Hauing then gifts,
differing according to the grace that is giuen to vs, whether
prophecie, let vs prophecie according to the proportion of
faith.</ab>
<ab n="7">Or ministery, let
vs wait, on our ministring: or hee that teacheth, on
teaching:</ab>
<ab n="8">Or he that
exhorteth, on exhortation: he that giueth, let him doe it with
simplicitie: hee that ruleth, with diligence: hee that sheweth
mercy, with cheerefulnesse.<note> Or, imparteth. , Or, liberally.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Let loue bee
without dissimulation: abhorre that which is euill, cleaue to that
which is good.</ab>
<ab n="10">Bee kindly
affectioned one to another with brotherly loue, in honour
preferring one another.<note> Or, in the loue of the brethren.</note></ab>

<fw>Exhortations to seuerall
dueties.</fw>
<ab n="11">Not slouthfull in
busines: feruent in spirit, seruing the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">Reioycing in
hope, patient in tribulation, continuing instant in prayer.</ab>
<ab n="13">Distributing to
the necessitie of Saints; giuen to hospitalitie.</ab>
<ab n="14">Blesse them which
persecute you, blesse, and curse not.</ab>
<ab n="15">Reioyce with them
that doe reioice, and weepe with them that weepe.</ab>
<ab n="16">Be of the same
mind one towards another. Minde not high things, but condescend to
men of low estate. Bee not wise in your owne conceits.<note> Or, be contented with meane things.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Recompence to no
man euill for euill. Prouide things honest in the sight of all
men.</ab>
<ab n="18">If it be
possible, as much as lyeth in you, liue peaceably with all
men.</ab>
<ab n="19">Dearely beloued,
auenge not your selues, but rather giue place vnto wrath: for it is
written, Uengeance is mine, I will repay, saith the
Lord.<note> Deut. 32. 35.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore if
thine enemie hunger, feed him: if he thirst, giue him drink. For in
so doing thou shalt heape coales of fire on his head.<note> Pro.25.21</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Be not ouercome
of euill, but ouercome euill with good.</ab>



</div>