<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 Subiection, and many other dueties
wee owe to the Magistrates. 8 Loue is the fulfilling of the Law. 11
Gluttonie and drunkennes, and the workes of darkenesse, are out of
season in the time of the Gospel.</head>

<ab n="1">Let euery soule
bee subiect vnto the higher powers: For there is no power but of
God. The powers that be, are ordeined of God.<note> Or, ordered.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Whosoeuer
therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God: and
they that resist, shall receiue to themselues damnation.</ab>
<ab n="3">For rulers are not
a terrour to good works, but to the euill. Wilt thou then not bee
afraide of the power? doe that which is good, and thou shalt haue
praise of the same.</ab>
<ab n="4">For hee is the
minister of God to thee for good: but if thou do that which is
euill, be afraid: for he beareth not the sword in vaine: for he is
the minister of God, a reuenger to execute wrath vpon him that
doeth euill.</ab>
<ab n="5">Wherfore ye must
needs be subiect, not onely for wrath, but also for conscience
sake.</ab>

<fw>Of loue.</fw>
<ab n="6">For, for this
cause pay you tribute also: for they are Gods ministers, attending
continually vpon this very thing.</ab>
<ab n="7">Render therfore to
all their dues, tribute to whom tribute is due, custome to whome
custome, feare to whome feare, honour to whom honour.</ab>
<ab n="8">Owe no man any
thing, but to loue one another: for hee that loueth another hath
fulfilled the Law.</ab>
<ab n="9">For this, Thou
shalt not commit adulterie, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not
steale, Thou shalt not beare false witnesse, Thou shalt not couet:
and if there be any other commandement, it is briefly comprehended
in this saying, namely, Thou shalt loue thy neighbour as thy
selfe.</ab>
<ab n="10">Loue worketh no
ill to his neighbour, therefore loue is the fulfilling of the
Law.</ab>
<ab n="11">And that, knowing
the time, that now it is high time to awake out of sleepe: for now
is our saluation neerer then when we beleeued.</ab>
<ab n="12">The night is
farre spent, the day is at hand: let vs therefore cast off the
workes of darkenesse, and let vs put on the armour of
light.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let vs walke
honestly as in the day, not in rioting and drunkennesse, not in
chambring and wantonnes, not in strife and enuying.<note> Or, decently.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But put yee on
the Lord Iesus Christ, and make not prouision for the flesh, to
fulfill the lusts thereof.</ab>



</div>