<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-8-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 They that are in Christ, and liue
according to the Spirit, are free from condemnation. 5. 13 What
harme commeth of the flesh, 6.14 and what good of the Spirit: 17
and what of being Gods childe, 19 whose glorious deliuerance all
things long for, 29 was before hand decreed from God. 38 What can
seuer vs from his loue?</head>

<ab n="1">There is
therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Christ Iesus,
who walke not after the flesh, but after the spirit.</ab>
<ab n="2">For the law
of the spirit of life, in Christ Iesus, hath made me free from the
law of sinne and death.</ab>
<ab n="3">For what the
law could not doe, in that it was weake through the flesh, God
sending his owne Sonne, in the likenesse of sinnefull flesh, and
for sinne condemned sinne in the flesh:<note> Or, by a sacrifice for sin.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">That the
righteousnesse of the law might be fulfilled in vs, who walke not
after the flesh, but after the spirit.</ab>
<ab n="5">For they that
are after the flesh, doe minde the things of the flesh: but they
that are after the spirit, the things of the spirit.</ab>
<ab n="6">For to be
carnally minded, is death: but to be spiritually minded, is life
and peace:<note> Gr. the minding of the flesh. , Gr. the minding of the spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Because the
carnall minde is enmitie against God: for it is not subiect to the
law of God, neither indeed can be.<note> Gr. the minding of the flesh.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">So then they
that are in the flesh, cannot please God.</ab>

<fw>Saued by hope.</fw>
<ab n="9">But ye are
not in the flesh, but in the spirit, if so be that the spirit of
God dwell in you. Now if any man haue not the spirit of Christ, he
is none of his.</ab>
<ab n="10">And if Christ in
you, the body is dead because of sinne: but the spirit is life,
because of righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="11">But if the spirit
of him that raised vp Iesus from the dead, dwell in you: he that
raised vp Christ from the dead, shall also quicken your mortall
bodies, by his spirit that dwelleth in you.<note> Or, because of his spirit.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Therfore brethren,
we are detters, not to the flesh, to liue after the flesh.</ab>
<ab n="13">For if ye liue
after the flesh, ye shall die: but if ye through the spirit doe
mortifie the deeds of the body, ye shall liue.</ab>
<ab n="14">For as many as are
led by the spirit of God, they are the sonnes of God.</ab>
<ab n="15">For ye haue not
receiued the spirit of bondage againe to feare: but ye haue
receiued the spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba,
father.</ab>
<ab n="16">The spirit it
selfe beareth witnes with our spirit, that we are the children of
God.</ab>
<ab n="17">And if children,
then heires, heires of God, and ioynt heires with Christ: if so be
that we suffer with him, that wee may be also glorified
together.</ab>
<ab n="18">For I reckon, that
the sufferings of this present time, are not worthy to be compared
with the glory which shall be reuealed in vs.</ab>
<ab n="19">For the earnest
expectation of the creature, waiteth for the manifestation of the
sonnes of God.</ab>
<ab n="20">For the creature
was made subiect to vanitie, not willingly, but by reason of him
who hath subiected the same in hope:</ab>
<ab n="21">Because the
creature it selfe also shall bee deliuered from the bondage of
corruption, into the glorious libertie of the children of
God.</ab>
<ab n="22">For wee know that
the whole creation groaneth, and trauaileth in paine together
vntill now.<note> Or, euery creature.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And not only they,
but our selues also which haue the first fruites of the spirit,
euen we our selues groane within our selues, waiting for the
adoption, to wit, the redemption of our body.<note> Luke 21. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For wee are saued
by hope: but hope that is seene, is not hope: for what a man seeth,
why doth he yet hope for?</ab>
<ab n="25">But if wee hope
for that wee see not, then doe wee with patience waite for
it.</ab>

<fw>Predestination.</fw>
<ab n="26">Likewise the
spirit also helpeth our infirmities: for we know not what wee
should pray for as wee ought: but the spirit it selfe maketh
intercession for vs with groanings, which cannot bee
vttered.</ab>
<ab n="27">And he that
searcheth the hearts, knoweth what is the minde of the spirit,
because he maketh intercession for the Saints, according to the
will of God.<note> Or, that</note></ab>
<ab n="28">And wee know that
all things worke together for good, to them that loue God, to them
who are the called according to his purpose.</ab>
<ab n="29">For whom he did
foreknow, he also did predestinate to be conformed to the image of
his sonne, that hee might bee the first borne amongst many
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="30">Moreouer, whom he
did predestinate, them he also called: and whom he called, them he
also iustified: and whom he iustified, them he also
glorified.</ab>
<ab n="31">What shall wee
then say to these things? If God be for vs, who can bee against
vs?</ab>
<ab n="32">He that spared not
his owne son, but deliuered him vp for vs all: how shall hee not
with him also freely giue vs all things?</ab>
<ab n="33">Who shall lay any
thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that
iustifieth:</ab>
<ab n="34">Who is he that
condemneth? It is Christ that died, yea rather that is risen
againe, who is euen at the right hand of God, who also maketh
intercession for vs.</ab>
<ab n="35">Who shall separate
vs from the loue of Christ? shall tribulation, or distresse, or
persecution, or famine, or nakednesse, or perill, or sword?</ab>
<ab n="36">(As it is written,
for thy sake we are killed all the day long, wee are accounted as
sheepe for the slaughter.)<note> Psal.44. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="37">Nay in all these
things wee are more then conquerours, through him that loued
vs.</ab>
<ab n="38">For I am
perswaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor
principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to
come,</ab>
<ab n="39">Nor height, nor
depth, nor any other creature, shalbe able to separate vs from the
loue of God, which is in Christ Iesus our Lord.</ab>



</div>