<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Abrahams faith was imputed to him
for righteousnesse, 10 before hee was circumcised. 13 By faith only
he and his seed receiued the promise. 16 Abraham is the father of
all that beleeue. 24 Our faith also shall be imputed to vs for
righteousnes.</head>

<ab n="1">What shall we
say then, that Abraham our father, as perteining to the flesh, hath
found?</ab>
<ab n="2">For if
Abraham were iustified by workes, hee hath whereof to glory, but
not before God.</ab>
<ab n="3">For what
saith the Scripture? Abraham beleeued God, and it was counted vnto
him for righteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="4">Now to him
that worketh, is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of
debt.</ab>

<fw>Iustification by faith.</fw>
<ab n="5">But to him
that worketh not, but beleeueth on him that iustifieth the vngodly;
his faith is counted for righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">Euen as Dauid
also describeth the blessednesse of the man, vnto whom God imputeth
righteousnesse without works:</ab>
<ab n="7">Saying,
Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiuen, and whose sinnes
are couered.</ab>
<ab n="8">Blessed is
the man to whome the Lord will not impute sinne.</ab>
<ab n="9">Commeth this
blessednes then vpon the circumcision onely, or vpon the
vncircumcision also? for wee say that faith was reckoned to Abraham
for righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="10">How was it then
reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in vncircumcision? not in
circumcision, but in vncircumcision.</ab>
<ab n="11">And hee receiued
the signe of circumcision, a seale of the righteousnesse of the
faith, which hee had yet being vncircumcised: that he might be the
father of all them that beleeue, though they be not circumcised;
that righteousnesse might be imputed vnto them also:</ab>
<ab n="12">And the father of
circumcision, to them who are not of the circumcision onely, but
also walke in the steppes of that faith of our father Abraham,
which he had being yet vncircumcised.</ab>
<ab n="13">For the promise
that he should be the heire of the world, was not to Abraham, or to
his seed through the Lawe, but through the righteousnesse of
faith.</ab>
<ab n="14">For if they which
are of the law be heires, faith is made voide, and the promise made
of none effect.</ab>
<ab n="15">Because the law
worketh wrath: for where no Lawe is, there is no
transgression.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore it is of
faith, that it might bee by grace; to the ende the promise might be
sure to all the seede, not to that onely which is of the Law, but
to that also which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of
vs all,</ab>
<ab n="17">(As it is written,
I haue made thee a father of many nations) before him whom he
beleeued, euen God who quickeneth the dead, and calleth those
things which bee not, as though they were,<note> Gen.17.5. , Or, like vnto him.</note></ab>

<fw>Iustification.</fw>
<ab n="18">Who against hope,
beleeued in hope, that hee might become the father of many nations:
according to that which was spoken, So shall thy seede
bee.<note> Gen.15.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And being not
weake in faith, hee considered not his owne body now dead, when hee
was about an hundred yere old, neither yet the deadnes of Saraes
wombe.</ab>
<ab n="20">Hee staggered not
at the promise of God through vnbeliefe: but was strong in faith,
giuing glory to God:</ab>
<ab n="21">And being fully
perswaded, that what he had promised, he was able also to
performe.</ab>
<ab n="22">And therefore it
was imputed to him for righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="23">Now it was not
written for his sake alone, that it was imputed to him:</ab>
<ab n="24">But for vs also,
to whome it shall bee imputed, if wee beleeue on him that raised vp
Iesus our Lord from the dead,</ab>
<ab n="25">Who was deliuered
for our offences, and was raised againe for our
iustification.</ab>



</div>