<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-9-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-9-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 Paul is sory for the Iewes. 7 All
the seed of Abraham were not the children of the promise. 18 God
hath mercy vpon whom hee will. 21 The potter may doe with his clay
what he list. 25 The calling of the Gentiles, and reiecting of the
Iewes were foretold. 32 The cause why so few Iewes embraced the
righteousnesse of faith.</head>


<fw>Pauls zeale.</fw>
<ab n="1">I say the
trueth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing mee
witnesse in the holy Ghost,</ab>
<ab n="2">That I haue
great heauinesse, and continuall sorrow in my heart.</ab>
<ab n="3">For I could
wish that my selfe were accursed from Christ, for my brethren my
kinsemen according to the flesh:<note> Or, separated.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Who are
Israelites: to whom perteineth the adoption, and the glory, and the
couenants, and the giuing of the Law, and the seruice of God, and
the promises:<note> Or, testaments.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Whose are the
fathers, and of whom as concerning the flesh Christ came, who is
ouer all, God blessed for euer, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="6">Not as though
the word of God hath taken none effect. For they are not all Israel
which are of Israel:</ab>
<ab n="7">Neither
because they are the seed of Abraham are they all children: but in
Isaac shall thy seed be called.<note> Gen.21. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">That is, They
which are the children of the flesh, these are not the children of
God: but the children of the promise are counted for the
seed.</ab>
<ab n="9">For this is
the word of promise, At this time will I come, and Sara shall haue
a sonne.<note> Gen.18. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And not onely
this, but when Rebecca also had conceiued by one, euen by our
father Isaac,</ab>
<ab n="11">(For the children
being not yet borne, neither hauing done any good or euil, that the
purpose of God according to election might stand, not of workes,
but of him that calleth.)</ab>
<ab n="12">It was said vnto
her, The elder shall serue the yonger.<note> Gene.25. 23. , Or, greater. , Or, lesser.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">As it is written,
Iacob haue I loued, but Esau haue I hated.<note> Mala. 1.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">What shall we say
then? Is there vnrighteousnes with God? God forbid.</ab>
<ab n="15">For hee saith to
Moses, I will haue mercy on whom I wil haue mercie, and I will haue
compassion on whom I will haue compassion.<note> Exod. 33. 19.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods will.</fw>
<ab n="16">So then it is not
of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that
sheweth mercy.</ab>
<ab n="17">For the Scripture
saith vnto Pharaoh, Euen for this same purpose haue I raised thee
vp, that I might shew my power in thee, and that my Name might bee
declared throughout all the earth.<note> Exod 9. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Therefore hath hee
mercie on whom hee will haue mercy, and whom he will, he
hardeneth.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thou wilt say then
vnto mee; Why doeth he yet find fault? For who hath resisted his
will?</ab>
<ab n="20">Nay but O man, who
art thou that repliest against God? Shall the thing formed say to
him that formed it, Why hast thou made me thus?<note> Or, answerest againe, or disputest with God? , Esay 45. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Hath not the
potter power ouer the clay, of the same lumpe, to make one vessell
vnto honour, and another vnto dishonour?<note> Iere.18.6. wisd.15.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">What if God,
willing to shew his wrath, &amp; to make his power knowen, indured
with much long suffering the vessels of wrath fitted to
destruction:<note> Or, made vp.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">And that he might
make knowen the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which
hee had afore prepared vnto glorie?</ab>
<ab n="24">Euen vs whom hee
hath called, not of the Iewes onely, but also of the
Gentiles.</ab>
<ab n="25">As he saith also
in Osee, I will call them my people, which were not my people: and
her, beloued, which was not beloued.<note> Ose.2.23. 1.pet.2.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And it shall come
to passe, that in the place where it was saide vnto them, Ye are
not my people, there shall they bee called the children of the
liuing God.<note> Ose.1.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Esaias also crieth
concerning Israel, Though the number of the children of Israel be
as the sand of the sea, a remnant shalbe saued.<note> Esay 10. 22,23.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For he will finish
the worke, and cut it short in righteousnesse: because a short
worke will the Lord make vpon the earth.<note> Or, the account. , Or, the account.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">And as Esaias said
before, Except the Lord of Sabboth had left vs a seed, we had bene
as Sodoma, and bene made like vnto Gomorrha.<note> Esay 1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="30">What shall wee say
then? That the Gentiles which followed not after righteousnesse,
haue attained to righteousnesse, euen the righteousnesse which is
of faith:</ab>

<fw>Ignorant zeale.</fw>
<ab n="31">But Israel which
followed after the Law of righteousnesse, hath not attained to the
Law of righteousnes.</ab>
<ab n="32">Wherefore? because
they sought it, not by faith, but as it were by the works of the
Law: for they stumbled at that stumbling stone,</ab>
<ab n="33">As it is written,
Beholde, I lay in Sion a stumbling stone, and rocke of offence: and
whosoeuer beleeueth on him, shall not be ashamed.<note> Esay 8.14 and 28.16. 1.pet.2.6. , Or, confounded.</note></ab>



</div>