<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-14-15.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>3 Men may not contemne nor condemne
one the other for things indifferent: 13 But take heed that they
giue no offence in them: 15 For that the Apostle prooueth vnlawfull
by many reasons.</head>

<ab n="1">Him that is weake
in the faith receiue you, but not to doubtfull
disputations.<note> Or, not to iudge his doubtfull thoughts.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For one beleeueth
that he may eat all things: another who is weake, eateth
herbes.</ab>
<ab n="3">Let not him that
eateth, despise him that eateth not: and let not him which eateth
not, iudge him that eateth. For God hath receiued him.</ab>
<ab n="4">Who art thou that
iudgest an other mans seruant? to his owne master he standeth or
falleth; Yea he shall bee holden vp: for God is able to make him
stand.</ab>

<fw>Gods iudgment.</fw>
<ab n="5">One man esteemeth
one day aboue another: another esteemeth euery day alike. Let euery
man bee fully perswaded in his owne minde.<note> Or, fully assured.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">He that regardeth
a day, regardeth it vnto the Lord; and hee that regardeth not the
day, to the Lord hee doeth not regard it. He that eateth, eateth to
the Lord, for hee giueth God thankes: and hee that eateth not, to
the Lord hee eateth not, and giueth God thankes.<note> Or, obserueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For none of vs
liueth to himselfe, and no man dieth to himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="8">For whether we
liue, we liue vnto the Lord: and whether wee die, we die vnto the
Lord: whether wee liue therefore or die, we are the Lords.</ab>
<ab n="9">For to this ende
Christ both died, and rose, and reuiued, that hee might be Lord
both of the dead and liuing.</ab>
<ab n="10">But why doest
thou iudge thy brother? or why dost thou set at nought thy brother?
wee shall all stand before the Iudgement seat of
Christ.<note> 2.Cor.5. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For it is
written, As I liue, saith the Lord, euery knee shall bow to mee,
and euery tongue shall confesse to God.<note> Esay 45. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So then euery one
of vs shall giue accompt of himselfe to God.</ab>
<ab n="13">Let vs not
therefore iudge one another any more: but iudge this rather, that
no man put a stumbling blocke, or an occasion to fall in his
brothers way.</ab>
<ab n="14">I know, and am
perswaded by the Lord Iesus, that there is nothing vncleane of it
selfe: but to him that esteemeth any thing to bee vncleane, to him
it is vncleane.<note> Gr. common. , Gr. common.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But if thy
brother be grieued with thy meate: now walkest thou not charitably.
Destroy not him with thy meat, for whom Christ died.<note> Gr. according to charitie. 1.Cor. 8.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Let not then your
good be euill spoken of.</ab>
<ab n="17">For the kingdome
of God is not meat and drinke; but righteousnes, and peace, and ioy
in the holy Ghost.</ab>
<ab n="18">For hee that in
these things serueth Christ, is acceptable to God, and approued of
men.</ab>
<ab n="19">Let vs therefore
follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith
one may edifie an other.</ab>
<ab n="20">For meat, destroy
not the worke of God: all things indeed are pure; but it is euill
for that man who eateth with offence.<note> Tit.1.15.</note></ab>

<fw>Brotherly loue.</fw>
<ab n="21">It is good
neither to eate flesh, nor to drinke wine, nor any thing whereby
thy brother stumbleth, or is offended, or is made
weake.<note> 1.Cor.8. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Hast thou faith?
haue it to thy selfe before God. Happie is he that condemneth not
himselfe in that thing which hee alloweth.</ab>
<ab n="23">And hee that
doubteth, is damned if hee eate, because hee eateth not of faith:
For whatsoeuer is not of faith, is sinne.<note> Or, discerneth, &amp; putteth a difference between meats</note></ab>



</div>