<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The wickednesse of the world,
which prouoked Gods wrath, and caused the Flood. 8 Noah findeth
grace. 13 The order, forme, and end of the Arke.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe, when men began to multiply on the face of the earth, and
daughters were borne vnto them:</ab>
<ab n="2">That the sonnes of
God saw the daughters of men, that they were faire, and they took
them wiues, of all which they chose.</ab>
<ab n="3">And the LORD said,
My Spirit shall not alwayes striue with man; for that hee also is
flesh: yet his dayes shalbe an hundred and twenty yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="4">There were Giants
in the earth in those daies: and also after that, when the sonnes
of God came in vnto the daughters of men, &amp; they bare children
to them; the same became mightie men, which were of old, men of
renowme.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And God
saw, that the wickednes of man was great in the earth, and that
euery imagination of the thoughts of his heart was onely euill
continually.<note> Or, the whole imagination. The Hebr. word signifieth not onely the imagination, but also the purposes and desires. , Chap. 8. 21. mat.15. 19. , Hebr. euery day.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And it repented
the LORD that he had made man on the earth, and it grieued him at
his heart.</ab>

<fw>Noahs Arke.</fw>
<ab n="7">And the LORD said,
I will destroy man, whom I haue created, from the face of the
earth: both man and beast, and the creeping thing, and the foules
of the aire: for it repenteth me that I haue made them.<note> Hebr. from man vnto beast.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But Noah found
grace in the eyes of the LORD.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ These are
the generations of Noah: Noah was a iust man, and perfect in his
generations, and Noah walked with God.<note> Ecclus. 44 17. 2.pet. 2.5. , Or, vpright.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And Noah begate
three sonnes: Sem, Ham, and Iapheth.</ab>
<ab n="11">The earth also
was corrupt before God; and the earth was filled with
violence.</ab>
<ab n="12">And God looked
vpon the earth, and behold, it was corrupt: for all flesh had
corrupted his way vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And God said vnto
Noah, The end of all flesh is come before mee; for the earth is
filled with violence through them; and behold, I will destroy them
with the earth.<note> Or, from the earth.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Make thee
an Arke of Gopher-wood: roomes shalt thou make in the arke, and
shalt pitch it within and without with pitch.<note> Heb. nests.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And this is the
fashion, which thou shalt make it of: the length of the arke shalbe
three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the
height of it thirtie cubits.</ab>
<ab n="16">A window shalt
thou make to the arke, and in a cubite shalt thou finish it aboue;
and the doore of the arke shalt thou set in the side thereof: With
lower, second, and third stories shalt thou make it.</ab>
<ab n="17">And behold, I,
euen I doe bring a flood of waters vpon the earth, to destroy all
flesh, wherein is the breath of life from vnder heauen, and euery
thing that is in the earth shall die.</ab>
<ab n="18">But with thee wil
I establish my Couenant: and thou shalt come into the Arke, thou,
and thy sonnes, and thy wife, and thy sonnes wiues with
thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">And of euery
liuing thing of all flesh, two of euery sort shalt thou bring into
the Arke, to keepe them aliue with thee: they shall be male and
female.</ab>
<ab n="20">Of fowles after
their kinde, and of cattel after their kinde: of euery creeping
thing of the earth after his kinde, two of euery sort shall come
vnto thee, to keepe them aliue.</ab>

<fw>Noah entreth into the Arke.</fw>
<ab n="21">And take thou
vnto thee of all food that is eaten, and thou shalt gather it to
thee; and it shall be for food, for thee, and for them.</ab>
<ab n="22">Thus did Noah;
according to all that God commanded him, so did he.<note> Heb.11. 7.</note></ab>



</div>