<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Paul commendeth his calling to the
Romanes, 9 and his desire to come to them. 16 What his Gospel is,
and the righteousnesse which it sheweth. 18 God is angry with all
maner of sin. 21 What were the sinnes of the Gentiles.</head>

<ab n="1">Paul a
seruant of Iesus Christ, called to bee an Apostle, separated vnto
the Gospel of God,<note> Acts.13. 1.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">(Which he had
promised afore by his Prophets in the holy Scriptures,)</ab>
<ab n="3">Concerning
his Sonne Iesus Christ our Lord, which was made of the seed of
Dauid according to the flesh,</ab>
<ab n="4">And declared
to be the Sonne of God, with power, according to the Spirit of
holinesse, by the resurrection from the dead.<note> Gr. determined.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">By whom we
haue receiued grace and Apostleship for obedience to the faith
among all nations for his Name,<note> Or, to the obedience of faith.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Among whom
are ye also the called of Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="7">To all that
be in Rome, beloued of God, called to be Saints: Grace to you and
peace from God our Father, and the Lord Iesus Christ.</ab>
<ab n="8">First I
thanke my God through Iesus Christ for you all, that your faith is
spoken of throughout the whole world.</ab>
<ab n="9">For God is my
witnesse, whom I serue with my spirit in the Gospel of his Sonne,
that without ceasing I make mention of you, alwayes in my
prayers,<note> Or, in my spirit.</note></ab>

<fw>Pauls zeale for the Gospel.</fw>
<ab n="10">Making request,
(if by any meanes now at length I might haue a prosperous iourney
by the will of God) to come vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="11">For I long to see
you, that I may impart vnto you some spirituall gift, to the end
you may be established,</ab>
<ab n="12">That is, that I
may be comforted together with you, by the mutual faith both of you
and me.<note> Or, in you.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Now I would not
haue you ignorant, brethren, that oftentimes I purposed to come
vnto you, (but was let hitherto) that I might haue some fruit among
you also, euen as among other Gentiles.<note> Or, in you.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">I am debter both
to the Greeks, and to the Barbarians, both to the wise, and to the
vnwise.</ab>
<ab n="15">So, as much as in
mee is, I am ready to preach the Gospel to you that are at Rome
also.</ab>
<ab n="16">For I am not
ashamed of the Gopel of Christ: for it is the power of God vnto
saluation, to euery one that beleeueth, to the Iew first, and also
to the Greeke.</ab>
<ab n="17">For therein is the
righteousnesse of God reueiled from faith to faith: as it is
written, The iust shall liue by faith.<note> Abac.2.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For the wrath of
God is reueiled from heauen against all vngodlinesse, and
vnrighteousnesse of men, who hold the trueth in
vnrighteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="19">Because that which
may bee knowen of God, is manifest in them, for God hath shewed it
vnto them.<note> Or, to them.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For the inuisible
things of him from the Creation of the world, are clearely seene,
being vnderstood by the things that are made, euen his eternall
Power and Godhead, so that they are without excuse:<note> Or, that they may be.</note></ab>

<fw>Gods iudgement.</fw>
<ab n="21">Because that when
they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were
thankefull, but became vaine in their imaginations, and their
foolish heart was darkened:</ab>
<ab n="22">Professing
themselues to be wise, they became fooles:</ab>
<ab n="23">And changed the
glory of the vncorruptible God, into an image made like to
corruptible man, and to birdes, and foure footed beasts, and
creeping things:<note> Psal.106. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Wherefore God also
gaue them vp to vncleannesse, through the lusts of their owne
hearts, to dishonour their owne bodies betweene themselues:</ab>
<ab n="25">Who changed the
trueth of God into a lye, and worshipped and serued the creature
more then the Creatour, who is blessed for euer. Amen.</ab>
<ab n="26">For this cause God
gaue them vp vnto vile affections: for euen their women did change
the naturall vse into that which is against nature:</ab>
<ab n="27">And likewise also
the men, leauing the naturall vse of the woman, burned in their
lust one towards another, men with men working that which is
vnseemely, and receiuing in themselues that recompense of their
errour which was meet.</ab>
<ab n="28">And euen as they
did not like to retaine God in their knowledge, God gaue them ouer
to a reprobate minde, to doe those things which are not
conuenient:<note> Or, to acknowledge. , Or, a minde voyde of iudgement.</note></ab>
<ab n="29">Being filled with
all vnrighteousnes, fornication, wickednesse, couetousnes,
maliciousnes, full of enuie, murther, debate, deceit, malignitie,
whisperers,</ab>
<ab n="30">Backbiters, haters
of God, despitefull, proude, boasters, inuenters of euill things,
disobedient to parents;</ab>
<ab n="31">Without
vnderstanding, couenant breakers, without naturall affection,
implacable, vnmercifull;<note> Or, vnsociable.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">Who knowing the
iudgement of God, (that they which commit such things, are worthy
of death) not onely do the same, but haue pleasure in them that doe
them.<note> Or, consent with them.</note></ab>



</div>