<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-9-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>5 The Scripture sheweth the
difference betwixt the righteousnes of the Law, and this of faith,
11 and that all both Iew and Gentile that beleeue, shal not be
cōfounded, 18 and that the Gentiles shall receiue the word and
beleeue. 19 Israel was not ignorant of these things.</head>

<ab n="1">Brethren, my
hearts desire and prayer to God for Israel is, that they might be
saued.</ab>
<ab n="2">For I beare them
record, that they haue a zeale of God, but not according to
knowledge.</ab>
<ab n="3">For they being
ignorant of Gods righteousnesse, and going about to establish their
owne righteousnesse, haue not submitted themselues vnto the
righteousnesse of God.</ab>
<ab n="4">For Christ is the
end of the Law for righteousnes to euery one that
beleeueth.</ab>
<ab n="5">For Moses
describeth the righteousnesse which is of the Law, that the man
which doeth those things shall liue by them.<note> Leu.18.5 ezek.20.11 gal.3.12.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But the
righteousnesse which is of faith, speaketh on this wise: Say not in
thine heart, Who shall ascend into heauen? That is to bring Christ
down from aboue.<note> Deut.30. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Or, Who shall
descend into the deepe? That is to bring vp Christ againe from the
dead.</ab>
<ab n="8">But what saith it?
The word is nigh thee, euen in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is
the word of faith which we preach,<note> Deut.30. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">That if thou shalt
confesse with thy mouth the Lord Iesus, and shalt beleeue in thine
heart, that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be
saued.</ab>
<ab n="10">For with the
heart man beleeueth vnto righteousnesse, and with the mouth
confession is made vnto saluation.</ab>

<fw>Faith by hearing.</fw>
<ab n="11">For the Scripture
saith, Whosoeuer beleeueth on him, shall not bee
ashamed.<note> Esa.28.16</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For there is no
difference betweene the Iew and the Greeke: for the same Lord ouer
all, is rich vnto all, that call vpon him.</ab>
<ab n="13">For whosoeuer
shall call vpon the Name of the Lord, shall be saued.<note> Ioel 2.32. acts 2.21.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">How then shall
they call on him in whom they haue not beleeued? and how shal they
beleeue in him, of whom they haue not heard? and how shall they
heare without a Preacher?</ab>
<ab n="15">And how shall
they preach, except they be sent? as it is written: How beautifull
are the feete of them that preach the Gospel of peace, and bring
glad tidings of good things!<note> Esa.52.7. naum.1.15 , Esa.52.7. naum.1.15</note></ab>
<ab n="16">But they haue not
all obeyed the Gospel. For Esaias saith, Lord, who hath beleeued
our report?<note> Esa.53.1. iohn 12.38 , Or, preaching. , Gr. the hearing of vs.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">So then, faith
commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</ab>
<ab n="18">But I say, haue
they not heard? yes verely, their sound went into all the earth,
and their words vnto the ends of the world.<note> Psal.19.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">But I say, Did
not Israel know? First Moses saith, I will prouoke you to iealousie
by them that are no people, &amp; by a foolish nation I will anger
you.<note> Deut.32. 21.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">But Esaias is
very bold, and saith, I was found of them that sought me not: I was
made manifest vnto them, that asked not after me.<note> Esa.65.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">But to Israel he
sayth, All day long I haue stretched foorth my hands vnto a
disobedient and gainesaying people.<note> Esa.65.2.</note></ab>



</div>