<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The Iewes prerogatiue: 3 which
they haue not lost: 9 Howbeit the Law conuinceth them also of
sinne: 20 Therefore no flesh is iustified by the Law, 28 but all,
without difference, by faith onely: 31 And yet the Law is not
abolished.</head>

<ab n="1">What
aduantage then hath the Iew? or what profit is there of
Circumcision?</ab>

<fw>None righteous.</fw>
<ab n="2">Much euery
way: chiefly, because that vnto them were committed the Oracles of
God.</ab>
<ab n="3">For what if
some did not beleeue? shall their vnbeliefe make the faith of God
without effect?</ab>
<ab n="4">God forbid:
yea, let God be true, but euery man a lier, as it is written, That
thou mightest be iustified in thy sayings, and mightest ouercome
when thou art iudged.<note> Psal.51.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But if our
vnrighteousnesse commend the righteousnesse of God, what shall we
say? is God vnrighteous who taketh vengeance? (I speake as a
man)</ab>
<ab n="6">God forbid:
for then how shall God iudge the world?</ab>
<ab n="7">For if the
trueth of God hath more abounded through my lye vnto his glory; why
yet am I also iudged as a sinner?</ab>
<ab n="8">And not
rather as wee be slanderously reported, and as some affirme that we
say, Let vs doe euill, that good may come: whose damnation is
iust.</ab>
<ab n="9">What then?
are wee better then they? No in no wise: for we haue before proued
both Iewes, and Gentiles, that they are all vnder
sinne,<note> Gr. charged.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">As it is written,
There is none righteous, no not one:</ab>
<ab n="11">There is none that
vnderstandeth, there is none that seeketh after God.</ab>
<ab n="12">They are all gone
out of the way, they are together become vnprofitable, there is
none that doeth good, no not one.</ab>
<ab n="13">Their throat is an
open sepulchre, with their tongues they haue vsed deceit, the
poyson of Aspes is vnder their lippes:</ab>
<ab n="14">Whose mouth is
full of cursing and bitternesse:</ab>
<ab n="15">Their feet are
swift to shed blood.</ab>
<ab n="16">Destruction &amp;
misery are in their wayes:</ab>
<ab n="17">And the way of
peace haue they not knowen.</ab>
<ab n="18">There is no feare
of God before their eyes.</ab>
<ab n="19">Now we know that
what things soeuer the Law saith, it saith to them who are vnder
the Law: that euery mouth may bee stopped, and all the world may
become guilty before God.<note> Or, subiect to the iudgement of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore by the
deedes of the Law, there shall no flesh be iustified in his sight:
for by the Law is the knowledge of sinne.</ab>

<fw>Iustification by faith.</fw>
<ab n="21">But nowe the
righteousnesse of God without the Lawe is manifested, being
witnessed by the Lawe and the Prophets.</ab>
<ab n="22">Euen the
righteousnesse of God, which is by faith of Iesus Christ vnto all,
and vpon all them that beleeue: for there is no difference:</ab>
<ab n="23">For all haue
sinned, and come short of the glory of God,</ab>
<ab n="24">Being iustified
freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Iesus
Christ:</ab>
<ab n="25">Whom God hath set
forth to bee a propitiation, through faith in his blood, to declare
his righteousnesse for the remission of sinnes, that are past,
through the forbearance of God.<note> Or, foreordeined. , Or, passing ouer.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">To declare, I say,
at this time his righteousnesse: that hee might bee iust, and the
iustifier of him which beleeueth in Iesus.</ab>
<ab n="27">Where is boasting
then? It is excluded. By what Law? Of works? Nay: but by the Law of
faith.</ab>
<ab n="28">Therefore wee
conclude, that a man is iustified by faith, without the deeds of
the Law.</ab>
<ab n="29">Is he the God of
the Iewes only? Is he not also of the Gentiles? Yes, of the
Gentiles also:</ab>
<ab n="30">Seeing it is one
God which shal iustifie the circumcision by faith, and
vncircumcision through faith.</ab>
<ab n="31">Doe we then make
void the lawe through faith? God forbid: yea, we establish the
Law.</ab>



</div>