<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-9-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-11-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-11-13.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 God hath not cast off all Israel.
7 Some were elected, though the rest were hardened. 16 There is
hope of their conuersion. 18 The Gentiles may not insult vpon them:
26 For there is a promise of their saluation. 33 Gods iudgements
are vnsearchable.</head>

<ab n="1">I say then, Hath
God cast away his people? God forbidde. For I also am an Israelite
of the seede of Abraham, of the tribe of Beniamin.</ab>
<ab n="2">God hath not cast
away his people which hee foreknew. Wote yee not what the Scripture
saieth of Elias? how hee maketh intercession to God against Israel,
saying,</ab>

<fw>The true, and wilde Oliue.</fw>
<ab n="3">Lord, they haue
killed thy Prophets, and digged downe thine Altars, and I am left
alone, and they seeke my life.<note> 1.Reg.19. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">But what saieth
the answere of God vnto him? I haue reserued to my selfe seuen
thousand men, who haue not bowed the knee to the image of
Baal.<note> 1.Reg.19. 18.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Euen so then at
this present time also there is a remnant according to the election
of grace.</ab>
<ab n="6">And if by grace,
then is it no more of workes: otherwise grace is no more grace. But
if it bee of workes, then is it no more grace, otherwise worke is
no more worke.</ab>
<ab n="7">What then? Israel
hath not obtained that which he seeketh for, but the election hath
obtained it, and the rest were blinded,<note> Or, hardened.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">According as it is
written, God hath giuen them the spirit of slumber: eyes that they
should not see, and eares that they should not heare vnto this
day.<note> Esa.29.10 , Or, remorse , Esa.6.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And Dauid sayth,
Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, and a stumbling
blocke, and a recompense vnto them.<note> Psa.69.22</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Let their eyes be
darkened, that they may not see, and bow downe their backe
alway.<note> Psa.69.23</note></ab>
<ab n="11">I say then; Haue
they stumbled that they should fall? God forbid. But rather through
their fall, saluation is come vnto the Gentiles, for to prouoke
them to ielousie.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now if the fall
of them be the riches of the world, and the diminishing of them,
the riches of the Gentiles: how much more their
fulnesse?<note> Or, decay, or losse.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For I speake to
you Gentiles, in as much as I am the Apostle of the Gentiles, I
magnifie mine office:</ab>
<ab n="14">If by any means I
may prouoke to emulation them which are my flesh, and might saue
some of them.</ab>
<ab n="15">For if the
casting away of them be the reconciling of the world: what shal the
receiuing of them be, but life from the dead?</ab>
<ab n="16">For if the first
fruite bee holy, the lumpe is also holy: and if the root be holy,
so are the branches.</ab>
<ab n="17">And if some of
the branches bee broken off, and thou being a wilde oliue tree wert
graffed in amongst them, and with them partakest of the roote and
fatnesse of the Oliue tree:<note> Or, for them.</note></ab>

<fw>The true, and wilde Oliue.</fw>
<ab n="18">Boast not against
the branches: but if thou boast, thou bearest not the root, but the
root thee.</ab>
<ab n="19">Thou wilt say
then, The branches were broken off, that I might bee graffed
in.</ab>
<ab n="20">Well: because of
vnbeliefe they were broken off, and thou standest by fayth. Be not
high minded, but feare.</ab>
<ab n="21">For if God spared
not the natural branches, take heede least hee also spare not
thee.</ab>
<ab n="22">Beholde therefore
the goodnesse and seueritie of God: on them which fell, seueritie;
but towards thee, goodnesse, if thou continue in his goodnesse:
otherwise thou also shalt be cut off.</ab>
<ab n="23">And they also, if
they bide not still in vnbeliefe, shall be graffed in: for God is
able to graffe them in againe.</ab>
<ab n="24">For if thou wert
cut out of the Oliue tree which is wilde by nature, and wert
graffed contrary to nature into a good Oliue tree: how much more
shall these which be the naturall branches, bee graffed into their
owne Oliue tree?</ab>
<ab n="25">For I would not,
brethren, that ye should bee ignorant of this mysterie (least yee
should bee wise in your owne conceits) that blindnesse in part is
happened to Israel, vntill the fulnes of the Gentiles be come
in.<note> Or, hardnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">And so all Israel
shall be saued, as it is written, There shall come out of Sion the
Deliuerer, and shall turne away vngodlinesse from
Iacob.<note> Esa.59.20</note></ab>
<ab n="27">For this is my
couenant vnto them, when I shall take away their sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="28">As concerning the
Gospel, they are enemies for your sake: but as touching the
election, they are beloued for the fathers sakes.</ab>
<ab n="29">For the gifts and
calling of God are without repentance.</ab>
<ab n="30">For as yee in
times past haue not beleeued God, yet haue now obtained mercy
through their vnbeliefe:<note> Or, obeyed.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">Euen so haue
these also now not beleeued, that through your mercy they also may
obtaine mercy.<note> Or, obeyed.</note></ab>
<ab n="32">For God hath
concluded them all in vnbeliefe, that he might haue mercy vpon
all.<note> Or, shut them all vp together.</note></ab>
<ab n="33">O the depth of
the riches both of the wisedome and knowledge of God! how
vnsearchable are his iudgements, and his wayes past finding
out!</ab>

<fw>Exhortations to seuerall
dueties.</fw>
<ab n="34">For who hath
knowen the mind of the Lord, or who hath bene his
counseller?<note> Esa.40.13 wisd.9.13. 1.cor.2.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">Or who hath first
giuen to him, and it shall bee recompensed vnto him againe?</ab>
<ab n="36">For of him, and
through him, and to him are all things: to whom be glory for euer.
Amen.</ab>



</div>