<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 They that sinne, though they
condemne it in others, cannot excuse themselues, 6 and much lesse
escape the iudgement of God, 9 whether they be Iewes or Gentiles.
14 The Gentiles cannot escape, 17 nor yet the Iewes, 25 whom their
Circumcision shall not profit, if they keepe not the
Law.</head>


<fw>Who are iustified.</fw>
<ab n="1">Therefore,
thou art inexcusable, O man, whosoeuer thou art that iudgest: for
wherein thou iudgest another, thou condemnest thy selfe, for thou
that iudgest doest the same things.</ab>
<ab n="2">But wee are
sure that the iudgement of God is according to trueth, against them
which commit such things.</ab>
<ab n="3">And thinkest
thou this, O man, that iudgest them which doe such things, and
doest the same, that thou shalt escape the iudgement of
God?</ab>
<ab n="4">Or despisest
thou the riches of his goodnesse, and forbearance, and long
suffering, not knowing that the goodnes of God leadeth thee to
repentance?</ab>
<ab n="5">But after thy
hardnesse, and impenitent heart, treasurest vp vnto thy selfe
wrath, against the day of wrath, and reuelation of the righteous
iudgement of God:<note> Iames 5. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Who will
render to euery man according to his deedes:<note> Psal.62. 12. matth. 16. 27. reuel. 22. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">To them, who
by patient continuance in well doing, seeke for glorie, and honour,
and immortalitie, eternall life:</ab>
<ab n="8">But vnto them
that are contentious, &amp; doe not obey the trueth, but obey
vnrighteousnes, indignation, &amp; wrath,</ab>
<ab n="9">Tribulation,
and anguish vpon euery soule of man that doeth euill, of the Iew
first, and also of the Gentile.<note> Gr. Greeke</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But glory, honour,
and peace, to euery man that worketh good, to the Iew first, and
also to the Gentile.<note> Gr. Greeke</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For there is no
respect of persons with God.</ab>
<ab n="12">For as many as
haue sinned without Law, shall also perish without Law: and as many
as haue sinned in the Law, shalbe iudged by the Law.</ab>
<ab n="13">(For not the
hearers of the Law are iust before God, but the doers of the Law
shalbe iustified;</ab>
<ab n="14">For when the
Gentiles which haue not the Law, doe by nature the things contained
in the Law: these hauing not the Law, are a Law vnto
themselues,</ab>
<ab n="15">Which shew the
worke of the Law written in their hearts, their conscience also
bearing witnesse, and their thoughts the meane while accusing, or
else excusing one another:<note> Or, the conscience witnessing with them. , Or, between themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">In the day when
God shall iudge the secrets of men by Iesus Christ, according to my
Gospel.</ab>

<fw>The true Iewe.</fw>
<ab n="17">Behold, thou art
called a Iew, and restest in the Law, and makest thy boast of
God:</ab>
<ab n="18">And knowest his
will, and approuest the things that are more excellent, being
instructed out of the Law,<note> Or, triest the things that differ.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And art confident
that thou thy selfe art a guide of the blinde, a light of them
which are in darkenesse:</ab>
<ab n="20">An instructour of
the foolish, a teacher of babes: which hast the forme of knowledge
and of the trueth in the Law:</ab>
<ab n="21">Thou therefore
which teachest another, teachest thou not thy selfe? thou that
preachest a man should not steale, doest thou steale?</ab>
<ab n="22">Thou that sayest a
man should not commit adulterie, doest thou commit adulterie? thou
that abhorrest idols, doest thou commit sacriledge?</ab>
<ab n="23">Thou that makest
thy boast of the Law, through breaking the Law dishonourest thou
God?</ab>
<ab n="24">For the Name of
God is blasphemed among the Gentiles, through you, as it is
written:<note> Esay 52. 5. ezech. 36.20,23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">For Circumcision
verily profiteth if thou keepe the Law: but if thou be a breaker of
the Law, thy Circumcision is made vncircumcision.</ab>
<ab n="26">Therefore, if the
vncircumcision keepe the righteousnesse of the Law, shall not his
vncircumcision be counted for Circumcision?</ab>
<ab n="27">And shall not
vncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfill the Law, iudge
thee, who by the letter, and Circumcision, doest transgresse the
Law?</ab>
<ab n="28">For hee is not a
Iew, which is one outwardly, neither is that Circumcision, which is
outward in the flesh:</ab>
<ab n="29">But he is a Iew
which is one inwardly, and Circumcision is, that of the heart, in
the spirit, and not in the letter, whose praise is not of men, but
of God.</ab>



</div>