<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRomans_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Romans-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Wee may not liue in sinne, 2 for
wee are dead vnto it, 3 as appeareth by our baptisme. 12 Let not
sinne raigne any more, 18 because wee haue yeelded our selues to
the seruice of righteousnesse, 23 and for that death is the wages
of sinne.</head>

<ab n="1">What shall we
say then? shall wee continue in sinne: that grace may
abound?</ab>
<ab n="2">God forbid:
how shall wee that are dead to sinne, liue any longer
therein?</ab>
<ab n="3">Know ye not,
that so many of vs as were baptized into Iesus Christ, were
baptized into his death?<note> Or, are.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore wee
are buryed with him by baptisme into death, that like as Christ was
raised vp from the dead by the glorie of the Father: euen so wee
also should walke in newnesse of life.</ab>
<ab n="5">For if we
haue bene planted together in the likenesse of his death: wee
shalbe also in the likenesse of his resurrection:</ab>
<ab n="6">Knowing this,
that our old man is crucified with him, that the bodie of sinne
might bee destroyed, that hencefoorth we should not serue
sinne.</ab>
<ab n="7">For he that
is dead, is freed from sinne.<note> Gr. iustified</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Now if we be
dead with Christ, we beleeue that we shal also liue with
him:</ab>
<ab n="9">Knowing that
Christ being raysed from the dead, dieth no more, death hath no
more dominion ouer him.</ab>
<ab n="10">For in that he
dyed, he dyed vnto sinne once: but in that hee liueth, hee liueth
vnto God.</ab>
<ab n="11">Likewise reckon
yee also your selues to be dead indeed vnto sinne: but aliue vnto
God, through Iesus Christ our Lord.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let not sinne
reigne therfore in your mortall body, that ye should obey it in the
lusts thereof.</ab>
<ab n="13">Neither yeeld yee
your members as instruments of vnrighteousnes vnto sinne: but
yeelde your selues vnto God, as those that are aliue from the dead,
and your members as instruments of righteousnesse vnto
God.<note> Gr. armes, or weapons.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For sinne shall
not haue dominion ouer you, for yee are not vnder the Law, but
vnder Grace.</ab>
<ab n="15">What then? shal we
sinne, because wee are not vnder the Law, but vnder Grace? God
forbid.</ab>

<fw>Wages of sinne.</fw>
<ab n="16">Know ye not, that
to whom yee yeeld your selues seruants to obey, his seruants ye are
to whom ye obey: whether of sinne vnto death, or of obedience vnto
righteousnesse?</ab>
<ab n="17">But God bee
thanked, that yee were the seruants of sinne: but ye haue obeyed
from the heart that fourme of doctrine, which was deliuered
you.<note> Gr. whereto ye were deliuered.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Being then made
free from sinne, yee became the seruants of righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="19">I speake after the
maner of men, because of the infirmitie of your flesh: for as yee
haue yeelded your members seruants to vncleannesse and to
iniquitie, vnto iniquitie: euen so now yeelde your members seruants
to righteousnesse, vnto holinesse.</ab>
<ab n="20">For when yee were
the seruants of sinne ye were free from righteousnesse.<note> Gr. to righteousnesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">What fruit had yee
then in those things, whereof ye are now ashamed? for the end of
those things is death.</ab>
<ab n="22">But now being made
free from sinne, and become seruants to God, yee haue your fruit
vnto holinesse, and the end euerlasting life.</ab>
<ab n="23">For the wages of
sinne is death: but the gift of God is eternall life, through Iesus
Christ our Lord.</ab>



</div>