<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRuth_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ruth-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ruth-Chapter-4-4-1-Samuel.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 Boz calleth into iudgment the next
kinseman. 6 He refuseth the redemption according to the maner in
Israel. 9 Boaz buyeth the inheritance. 11 He marrieth Ruth. 13 She
beareth Obed the grandfather of Dauid. 18 The generation of
Pharez.</head>

<ab n="1">Then went Boaz
vp to the gate, and sate him downe there: and beholde, the kinseman
of whome Boaz spake, came by, vnto whom he said, Ho, such a one:
turne aside, sit downe here. And hee turned aside, and sate
downe.</ab>

<fw>Boaz talketh with Ruths
kinsman.</fw>
<ab n="2">And hee tooke
ten men of the Elders of the citie, and said, Sit ye downe here.
And they sate downe.</ab>
<ab n="3">And he said
vnto the kinseman: Naomi that is come againe out of the countrey of
Moab, selleth a parcell of land, which was our brother
Elimelechs.</ab>
<ab n="4">And I thought
to aduertise thee, saying, Buy it before the inhabitants, and
before the Elders of my people. If thou wilt redeeme it, redeeme
it, but if thou wilt not redeeme it, then tell mee, that I may
know: for there is none to redeeme it, besides thee, and I am after
thee. And he said, I will redeeme it.<note> Heb. I said I wil reueale in thine eare.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Then said Boaz,
What day thou buyest the field of the hand of Naomi, thou must buy
it also of Ruth the Moabitesse, the wife of the dead, to raise vp
the name of the dead vpon his inheritance.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And the
kinseman said, I cannot redeeme it for my selfe, lest I marre mine
owne inheritance: redeeme thou my right to thy selfe, for I cannot
redeeme it.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now this was
the maner in former time in Israel, concerning redeeming and
concerning changing, for to confirme all things: a man plucked off
his shooe, and gaue it to his neighbour: and this was a testimonie
in Israel.<note> Deut. 25. 7,9.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Therfore the
kinseman said vnto Boaz, Buy it for thee: so he drew off his
shooe.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And Boaz
saide vnto the Elders, and vnto all the people, Ye are witnesses
this day, that I haue bought all that was Elimelechs, and all that
was Chilions, and Mahlons, of the hande of Naomi.</ab>
<ab n="10">Moreouer, Ruth
the Moabitesse, the wife of Mahlon, haue I purchased to be my wife,
to raise vp the name of the dead vpon his inheritance, that the
name of the dead be not cut off from among his brethren, and from
the gate of his place: ye are witnesses this day.</ab>
<ab n="11">And all the
people that were in the gate, and the Elders said, Wee are
witnesses: The Lord make the woman that is come into thine house,
like Rachel and like Leah, which two did build the house of Israel:
and do thou worthily in Ephratah, and bee famous in
Bethlehem.<note> Or, get thee riches or power. , Hebr. proclaime thy name.</note></ab>

<fw>Elkanah, and his two wiues.</fw>
<ab n="12">And let thy
house be like the house of Pharez, ( whom Tamar bare vnto to Iudah)
of the seed which the Lord shall giue thee of this yong
woman.<note> Gen.38. 29. 1. chro. 2.4. matt. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">¶ So Boaz
tooke Ruth, and she was his wife: and when he went in vnto her, the
Lord gaue her conception, and she bare a sonne.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the women
said vnto Naomi, Blessed be the Lord which hath not left thee this
day without a kinseman, that his name may bee famous in
Israel:<note> Hebr. caused to cease vnto thee. , Or, redeemer.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And he shalbe
vnto thee a restorer of thy life, and a nourisher of thine old age:
for thy daughter in law which loueth thee, which is better to thee
then seuen sonnes, hath borne him.<note> Hebr. to nourish. , Heb. thy gray haires.</note></ab>

<fw>Elkanah, and his two wiues.</fw>
<ab n="16">And Naomi
tooke the childe, and laid it in her bosome, and became nurse vnto
it.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the women
her neighbours gaue it a name, saying, There is a sonne borne to
Naomi, and they called his name Obed: hee is the father of Iesse
the father of Dauid.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Now
these are the generations of Pharez: Pharez begate
Hezron,<note> 1. Chron 2.4 matt. 1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Hezron
begate Ram, and Ram begate Amminadab,</ab>
<ab n="20">And Amminadab
begate Nahshon, and Nahshon begate Salmon,<note> Or, Salmah.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And Salmon
begate Boaz, and Boaz begate Obed,</ab>
<ab n="22">And Obed begat
Iesse, and Iesse begate Dauid.</ab>



</div>