<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CRuth_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ruth-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Ruth-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 By Naomi her instruction, 5 Ruth
lieth at Boaz his feete. 8 Boaz acknowledgeth the right of a
kinseman. 14 He sendeth her away with sixe measures of
barley.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Naomi her
mother in law said vnto her, My daughter, shal I not seeke rest for
thee, that it may be well with thee?</ab>
<ab n="2">And now is not
Boaz of our kinred, with whose maidens thou wast? Behold, he
winnoweth barley to night in the threshing floore.</ab>
<ab n="3">Wash thy selfe
therefore, and annoint thee, and put thy raiment vpon thee, and get
thee downe to the floore: but make not thy selfe knowen vnto the
man, vntill hee shall haue done eating and drinking.</ab>
<ab n="4">And it shall be
when hee lieth downe, that thou shalt marke the place where hee
shall lie, and thou shalt goe in, and vncouer his feete, and lay
thee downe, and he will tell thee what thou shalt doe.<note> Or, lift vp the clothes that are on his feete.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And shee said
vnto her, All that thou sayest vnto me, I will doe.</ab>
<ab n="6">¶ And she
went downe vnto the floore, and did according to all that her
mother in law bade her.</ab>
<ab n="7">And when Boaz
had eaten and drunke, and his heart was merrie, hee went to lie
downe at the ende of the heape of corne: and she came softly, and
vncouered his feet, and laid her downe.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And it
came to passe at midnight, that the man was afraid, and turned
himselfe: and behold, a woman lay at his feete.<note> Or, tooke holde on.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">And hee said,
Who art thou? And she answered, I am Ruth thine handmaid: spread
therefore thy skirt ouer thine handmaid, for thou art a neare
kinseman.<note> Or, one that hath right to redeeme.</note></ab>

<fw>Boaz talketh with Ruths
kinsman.</fw>
<ab n="10">And hee said,
Blessed be thou of the Lord, my daughter: for thou hast shewed more
kindnesse in the latter ende, then at the beginning, in as much as
thou followedst not yong men, whether poore, or rich.</ab>
<ab n="11">And now my
daughter, feare not, I will doe to thee all that thou requirest:
for all the citie of my people doeth know, that thou art a vertuous
woman.<note> Heb. gate.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And now it is
true, that I am thy neare kinseman: howbeit there is a kinseman
nearer then I.</ab>
<ab n="13">Tary this
night, and it shall be in the morning, that if hee will performe
vnto thee the part of a kinseman, well, let him doe the kinsemans
part; but if hee will not doe the part of a kinseman to thee, then
will I doe the part of a kinseman to thee, as the Lord liueth: lie
downe vntill the morning.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ And
shee lay at his feete vntill the morning: and she rose vp before
one could know another. And he said, Let it not be knowen, that a
woman came into the floore.</ab>
<ab n="15">Also he said,
Bring the vaile that thou hast vpon thee, and holde it. And when
she helde it, he measured sixe measures of barley, and laide it on
her: and he went into the citie.<note> Or, sheete, or, apron.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And when shee
came to her mother in law, she said, Who art thou, my daughter? and
she tolde her all that the man had done to her.</ab>
<ab n="17">And she said,
These sixe measures of barley gaue he me, for he said to me, Go not
emptie vnto thy mother in law.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then said she,
Sit still, my daughter, vntill thou know how the matter will fall:
for the man will not be in rest, vntil he haue finished the thing
this day.</ab>



</div>