<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CSong-of-the-three-children_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Prayer-of-Azariah-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Prayer-of-Azariah-Chapter-1-1b.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Prayer-of-Azariah-Chapter-1-1c-Susanna.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Azarias his praier and confession
in the flame, 24 wherewith the Chaldeans about the ouen were
consumed, but the three children within it were not hurt. 28 The
Song of the three children in the ouen.</head>

<ab n="1">[And
they walked in the midst of the fire, praising God, and blessing
the Lord. ] Then Azarias stood vp &amp; prayed on this manner, and
opening his mouth in the midst of the fire, said,</ab>
<ab n="2">Blessed
art thou, O Lord God of our fathers: thy Name is worthy to be
praised, and glorified for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="3">For thou
art righteous in all the things that thou hast done to vs: yea,
true are all thy workes: thy wayes are right, and all thy
iudgements trueth.<note> Psal.25. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">In all
the things that thou hast brought vpon vs, and vpon the holy citie
of our fathers, euen Ierusalem, thou hast executed true iudgement:
for according to trueth and iudgement, didst thou bring all these
things vpon vs, because of our sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="5">For wee
haue sinned and committed iniquitie, departing from thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">In all
things haue we trespassed, and not obeyed thy Commandements, nor
kept them, neither done as thou hast commanded vs, that it might
goe well with vs.</ab>
<ab n="7">Wherefore
all that thou hast brought vpon vs, and euery thing that thou hast
done to vs, thou hast done in true iudgement.</ab>
<ab n="8">And thou
didst deliuer vs into the hands of lawlesse enemies, most hatefull
forsakers [of God] and to an vniust King, and the most wicked in
all the world.</ab>
<ab n="9">And now
wee can not open our mouthes, we are become a shame, and reproch to
thy seruants, and to them that worship thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">Yet
deliuer vs not vp wholy for thy Names sake, neither disanull thou
thy Couenant:</ab>
<ab n="11">And
cause not thy mercy to depart from vs: for thy beloued Abrahams
sake: for thy seruant Isaacs sake, and for thy holy Israels
sake.</ab>
<ab n="12">To whom
thou hast spoken and promised, That thou wouldest multiply their
seed as the starres of heauen, and as the sand that lyeth vpon the
sea shore.</ab>
<ab n="13">For we,
O Lord, are become lesse then any nation, and bee kept vnder this
day in all the world, because of our sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="14">Neither
is there at this time, Prince, or Prophet, or leader, or burnt
offering, or sacrifice, or oblation, or incense, or place to
sacrifice before thee, and to finde mercie.</ab>
<ab n="15">Neuerthelesse
in a contrite heart, and an humble spirit, let vs be
accepted.</ab>
<ab n="16">Like as
in the burnt offering of rammes and bullockes, and like as in ten
thousands of fat lambes: so let our sacrifice bee in thy sight this
day, and [grant] that wee may wholy goe after thee: for they shall
not bee confounded that put their trust in thee.</ab>
<ab n="17">And now
wee follow thee, with all our heart, wee feare thee, and seeke thy
face.</ab>
<ab n="18">Put vs
not to shame: but deale with vs after thy louing kindenesse, and
according to the multitude of thy mercies.</ab>
<ab n="19">Deliuer
vs also according to thy marueilous workes, and giue glory to thy
Name, O Lord, and let all them that doe thy seruants hurt be
ashamed.</ab>
<ab n="20">And let
them be confounded in all their power and might, and let their
strength be broken.<note> Or, by thy power and might.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">And let
them know that thou art Lord, the onely God, and glorious ouer the
whole world.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the
kings seruants that put them in, ceased not to make the ouen hote
with rosin, pitch, towe, and small wood.<note> Or, Naptha, which is a certaine kind of fat and chalke clay. Plin. lib.2.6.105.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">So that
the flame streamed forth aboue the fornace, fourtie and nine
cubites:</ab>
<ab n="24">And it
passed through, and burnt those Caldeans it found about the
fornace.</ab>
<ab n="25">But the
Angel of the Lord came downe into the ouen, together with Azarias
and his fellowes, and smote the flame of the fire out of the
ouen:</ab>
<ab n="26">And
made the mids of the fornace, as it had bene a moist whistling
wind, so that the fire touched them not at all, neither hurt nor
troubled them.<note> Or, coels.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">Then
the three, as out of one mouth, praised, glorified, and blessed God
in the fornace, saying;</ab>
<ab n="28">Blessed
art thou, O Lord God of our fathers: and to be praised and exalted
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="29">And
blessed is thy glorious and holy Name: and to be praised and
exalted aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="30">Blessed
art thou in the Temple of thine holy glory: and to be praised and
glorified aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="31">Blessed
art thou that beholdest the depths, and sittest vpon the Cherubims,
and to be praised and exalted aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="32">Blessed
art thou on the glorious Throne of thy kingdome: and to bee praised
and glorified aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="33">Blessed
art thou in the firmament of heauen: and aboue all to be praised
and glorified for euer.</ab>
<ab n="34">O all
yee workes of the Lorde, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.<note> Or, highly exalt: and so in the rest.</note></ab>
<ab n="35">O ye
heauens, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all for
euer.<note> Psal.148.4</note></ab>
<ab n="36">O yee
Angels of the Lord, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue
all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="37">O all
ye waters that be aboue the heauen, blesse yee the Lord: praise and
exalt him aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="38">O all
yee powers of the Lord, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="39">O yee
Sunne and Moone, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="40">O ye
starres of heauen, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue
all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="41">O euery
showre and dew, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="42">O all
ye windes, blesse yee the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="43">O yee
fire and heate, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="44">O yee
Winter and Summer, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue
all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="45">O ye
dewes and stormes of snow, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="46">O ye
nights and dayes, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue
all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="47">O ye
light and darkenesse, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="48">O yee
yce and colde, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="49">O ye
frost and snow, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="50">O ye
lightnings and clouds, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="51">O let
the earth blesse the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="52">O ye
mountaines and little hils, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt
him aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="53">O all
ye things that grow on the earth, blesse ye the Lord: praise and
exalt him aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="54">O yee
fountaines, blesse yee the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="55">O ye
seas and riuers, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all
for euer.</ab>
<ab n="56">O ye
whales and all that mooue in the waters, blesse ye the Lord: praise
and exalt him aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="57">O all
ye foules of the aire, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.<note> Gr. heauen.</note></ab>
<ab n="58">O all
ye beasts and cattell, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="59">O ye
children of men, blesse yee the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue
all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="60">O
Israel blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue all for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="61">O ye
priests of the Lord, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him aboue
all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="62">O ye
seruants of the Lord, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt him
aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="63">O ye
spirits and soules of the righteous, blesse ye the Lord, praise and
exalt him aboue all for euer.</ab>
<ab n="64">O ye
holy and humble men of heart, blesse ye the Lord: praise and exalt
him aboue all for euer.<note> Or, Saints</note></ab>
<ab n="65">O
Ananias, Azarias, and Misael, blesse ye the Lord, praise and exalt
him aboue all for euer: for hee hath deliuered vs from hell, and
saued vs from the hand of death, and deliuered vs out of the mids
of the furnace, [and] burning flame: euen out of the mids of the
fire hath he deliuered vs.<note> Or, graue.</note></ab>
<ab n="66">O giue
thanks vnto the Lord, because he is gracious: for his mercie
endureth for euer.</ab>
<ab n="67">O all
ye that worship the Lord, blesse the God of gods, praise him, and
giue him thankes: for his mercie endureth for euer.</ab>



</div>