<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CSong-of-Solomon_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Song-of-Solomon-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The loue of the Church to Christ.
6 The vehemencie of loue. 8 The calling of the Gentiles. 14 The
Church prayeth for Christes comming.</head>

<ab n="1">O that
thou wert as my brother that sucked the brests of my mother, when I
should find thee without, I would kisse thee, yet I should not be
despised.<note> Hebr. they should not despise me.</note></ab>

<fw>Spirituall loue.</fw>
<ab n="2">I would
leade thee, and bring thee into my mothers house, who would
instruct me: I would cause thee to drinke of spiced wine, of the
iuice of my pomegranate.<note> Prou.9.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">His left
hand should be vnder my head, and his right hand should embrace
me.<note> Chap.2.6</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I charge
you, O daughters of Ierusalem, that ye stirre not vp, nor awake my
loue vntill he please.<note> Chap.3.5. and 2.7. , Heb. why should yee stirre vp, or why,&amp;c?</note></ab>
<ab n="5">(Who is
this that commeth vp from the wildernesse, leaning vpon her
beloued?) I raised thee vp vnder the apple tree: there thy mother
brought thee forth, there she brought thee forth, that bare
thee.<note> Chap.3.6</note></ab>
<ab n="6">¶ Set
mee as a seale vpon thine heart, as a seale vpon thine arme: for
loue is strong as death, iealousie is cruel as the graue: the
coales thereof are coales of fire, which hath a most vehement
flame.<note> Heb. hard.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Many
waters cannot quench loue, neither can the floods drowne it: if a
man would giue all the substance of his house for loue, it would
vtterly be contemned.</ab>
<ab n="8">¶ We
haue a litle sister, and shee hath no breasts: what shall we doe
for our sister, in the day when she shall bee spoken for?</ab>
<ab n="9">If she be
a wall, we will build vpon her a palace of siluer: and if she bee a
dore, we will inclose her with boards of Cedar.</ab>
<ab n="10">I am a
wall, and my breasts like towers: then was I in his eyes as one
that found fauour.<note> Heb. peace</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Solomon
had a vineyard at Baalhamon, hee let out the vineyard vnto keepers:
euery one for the fruit thereof was to bring a thousand pieces of
siluer.</ab>
<ab n="12">My
vineyard which is mine, is before me: thou (O Solomon) must haue a
thousand, and those that keepe the fruit thereof, two
hundred.</ab>
<ab n="13">Thou that
dwellest in the gardens, the companions hearken to thy voice: cause
me to heare it.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶
Make haste, my beloued, and be thou like to a Roe, or to a yong
Hart vpon the mountaines of spices.<note> Heb. flee away.</note></ab>



</div>