<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CSong-of-Solomon_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Song-of-Solomon-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Song-of-Solomon-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 Christ awaketh the Church with his
calling. 2 The Church hauing a taste of Christes loue, is sicke of
loue. 9 A description of Christ by his graces.</head>

<ab n="1">I am come
into my garden, my sister, my spouse, I haue gathered my Myrrhe
with my spice, I haue eaten my honie combe with my hony, I haue
drunke my wine with my milke: eate, O friends, drinke, yea drinke
abundantly, O beloued!<note> Or, and be drunken with loues.</note></ab>

<fw>Ill watchmen.</fw>
<ab n="2">¶ I
sleepe, but my heart waketh: it is the voyce of my beloued that
knocketh, saying, Open to me, my sister, my loue, my doue, my
vndefiled: for my head is filled with dewe, and my lockes with the
drops of the night.</ab>
<ab n="3">I haue put
off my coate, how shall I put it on? I haue washed my feete, how
shall I defile them?</ab>
<ab n="4">My beloued
put in his hand by the hole of the dore, and my bowels were moued
for him.<note> Or, (as some read) in me.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">I rose vp
to open to my beloued, and my hands dropped with myrrhe, and my
fingers with sweete smelling myrrhe, vpon the handles of the
locke.<note> Heb. passing, or running about.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I opened
to my beloued, but my beloued had with drawen himselfe, and was
gone: my soule failed when hee spake: I sought him, but I could not
find him: I called him, but he gaue me no answere.</ab>
<ab n="7">The
watchmen that went about the citie, found me, they smote me, they
wounded me, the keepers of the walles tooke away my vaile from
me.</ab>
<ab n="8">I charge
you, O daughters of Ierusalem, if ye find my beloued, that yee tell
him, that I am sicke of loue.<note> Heb. what.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">¶
What is thy beloued more then another beloued, O thou fairest among
women? what is thy beloued more then another beloued, that thou
doest so charge vs?</ab>
<ab n="10">My
beloued is white and ruddy, the chiefest among tenne
thousand.<note> Heb. astandard bearer</note></ab>
<ab n="11">His head
is as the most fine gold, his locks are bushy, and blacke as a
Rauen.<note> Or, curled.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">His eyes
are as the eyes of doues by the riuers of water, washed with milk,
and fitly set.<note> Chap. 1.15. &amp; 4.1. , Heb sitting in fulnesse, that is fitly placed, and set as a precious stone in the foile of a ring.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">His
cheekes are as a bed of spices, as sweete flowers: his lippes like
lillies, dropping sweete smelling myrrhe.<note> Or, towers of perfumes.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">His hands
are as gold rings set with the Berill: His belly is as bright
iuorie, ouerlayd with Saphires.</ab>
<ab n="15">His
legges are as pillars of marble, set vpon sockets of fine gold: his
countenance is as Lebanon, excellent as the Cedars.</ab>
<ab n="16">His mouth
is most sweete, yea he is altogether louely. This is my beloued,
and this is my friend, O daughters of Ierusalem.<note> Heb. his palate.</note></ab>



</div>