<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CSong-of-Solomon_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Song-of-Solomon-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The mutuall loue of Christ and his
Church. 8 The hope, 10 and calling of the Church. 14 Christs care
of the Church. 16 The profession of the Church, her faith and
hope.</head>

<ab n="1">I Am the
rose of Sharon, and the lillie of the valleys.</ab>
<ab n="2">As the
lillie among thornes, so is my loue among the daughters.</ab>
<ab n="3">As the
apple tree among the trees of the wood, so is my beloued among the
sonnes. I sate downe vnder his shadow with great delight, and his
fruit was sweete to my taste.<note> Heb. I delighted and sate downe, &amp;c. , Heb. palate</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Hee
brought me to the banketting house, and his banner ouer mee, was
loue.<note> Heb. house of wine.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Stay me
with flagons, comfort me with apples, for I am sicke of
loue.<note> Heb. straw me with apples.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">His left
hand is vnder my head, and his right hand doeth imbrace
me.<note> Chap.8.3.</note></ab>

<fw>Christ, and his Church.</fw>
<ab n="7">I charge
you, O ye daughters of Ierusalem, by the Roes, and by the hindes of
the field, that ye stirre not vp, nor awake my loue, till she
please.<note> Heb. I adiure you. , Chap.3.5. and 8.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ The
voice of my beloued! behold! hee commeth leaping vpon the
mountaines, skipping vpon the hils.</ab>
<ab n="9">My beloued
is like a Roe, or a yong Hart: behold, he standeth behind our wall,
he looketh foorth at the windowe, shewing himselfe through the
lattesse.<note> Verse 17. , Heb. flourishing.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">My
beloued spake, and said vnto me, Rise vp, my Loue, my faire one,
and come away.</ab>
<ab n="11">For loe,
the winter is past, the raine is ouer, and gone.</ab>
<ab n="12">The
flowers appeare on the earth, the time of the singing of birds is
come, and the voice of the turtle is heard in our land.</ab>
<ab n="13">The fig
tree putteth foorth her greene figs, and the vines with the tender
grape giue a good smell. Arise, my loue, my faire one, and come
away.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ O
my doue! that art in the clefts of the rocke, in the secret places
of the staires: let me see thy countenance, let me heare thy voice,
for sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.</ab>
<ab n="15">Take vs
the foxes, the litle foxes, that spoile the vines: for our vines
haue tender grapes.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ My
beloued is mine, and I am his: he feedeth among the
lillies.<note> Chap.6.3. and 7.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Untill
the day breake, and the shadowes flee away: turne my beloued and be
thou like a Roe, or a yong Hart, vpon the mountaines of
Bether.<note> Chap.4.6 , Chap.8. 14. , Or, of diuision.</note></ab>



</div>