<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CSong-of-Solomon_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Song-of-Solomon-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Song-of-Solomon-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 A further description of the
Church her graces. 10 The Church professeth her faith and
desire.</head>

<ab n="1">Howe
beautifull are thy feete with shooes, O princes daughter! the
ioynts of thy thighs are like iewels, the worke of the hands of a
cunning workman.</ab>

<fw>The beautie of the church.</fw>
<ab n="2">Thy nauell
is like a round goblet, which wanteth not licour: thy belly is like
an heape of wheate, set about with lillies.<note> Heb. mixture.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thy two
breasts are like two yong Roes that are twinnes.<note> Chap. 4.5</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Thy necke
is as a towre of yuory: thine eyes like the fish pooles in Heshbon,
by the gate of Bathrabbim: thy nose is as the towre of Lebanon,
which looketh toward Damascus.</ab>
<ab n="5">Thine head
vpon thee is like Carmel, and the haire of thine head like purple,
the king is held in the galleries.<note> Or, crimson , Heb. bound</note></ab>
<ab n="6">How faire,
and how pleasant art thou, O Loue, for delights!</ab>
<ab n="7">This thy
stature is like to a palme tree, and thy breasts to clusters of
grapes.</ab>
<ab n="8">I said, I
will goe vp to the palme tree, I will take hold of the boughes
thereof: now also thy breasts shall be as clusters of the vine, and
the smell of thy nose, like apples.</ab>
<ab n="9">And the
roofe of thy mouth like the best wine, for my beloued, that goeth
downe sweetely, causing the lippes of those that are asleepe, to
speake.<note> Hebr. streightly. , Or, of the ancient.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ I
am my beloueds, and his desire is towards me.<note> Chap.2. 16. and 6.3</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Come, my
beloued, let vs goe forth into the field: let vs lodge in the
villages.</ab>
<ab n="12">Let vs
get vp earely to the vineyards, let vs see if the vine flourish,
whether the tender grape appeare, and the pomegranates bud forth:
there will I giue thee my loues.<note> Heb. open.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">The
mandrakes giue a smell, and at our gates are all maner of pleasant
fruits, new and olde, which I haue laid vp for thee, O my
beloued.<note> Gen. 30. 14.</note></ab>



</div>