<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CSusanna_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Prayer-of-Azariah-Chapter-1-1c-Susanna.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Susanna-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Susanna-Chapter-1-1b-Bel-and-the-Dragon.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>16 Two Iudges hide themselues in the
garden of Susanna to haue their pleasure of her: 28 which when they
could not obteine, they accuse and cause her to be condemned for
adulterie, 46 but Daniel examineth the matter againe, and findeth
the two iudges false.</head>

<ab n="1">There dwelt a man
in Babylon, called Ioacim.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee tooke a
wife, whose name was Susanna, the daughter of Chelcias, a very
faire woman, and one that feared the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">Her parents also
were righteous, and taught their daughter according to the Law of
Moses.</ab>
<ab n="4">Now Ioacim was a
great rich man, and had a faire garden ioyning vnto his house, and
to him resorted the Iewes: because he was more honourable then all
others.</ab>
<ab n="5">The same yeere
were appointed two of the Ancients of the people to be iudges, such
as the Lord spake of, that wickednesse came from Babylon from
ancient iudges, who seemed to gouerne the people.</ab>
<ab n="6">These kept much at
Ioacims house: and all that had any suits in lawe, came vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="7">Now when the
people departed away at noone, Susanna went into her husbands
garden to walke.</ab>
<ab n="8">And the two Elders
saw her going in euery day and walking: so that their lust was
inflamed toward her.</ab>
<ab n="9">And they peruerted
their owne mind, and turned away their eyes, that they might not
looke vnto heauen, nor remember iust iudgements.</ab>
<ab n="10">And albeit they
both were wounded with her loue: yet durst not one shew another his
griefe.</ab>
<ab n="11">For they were
ashamed to declare their lust, that they desired to haue to doe
with her.</ab>
<ab n="12">Yet they watched
diligently from day to day to see her.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the one said
to the other, Let vs now goe home: for it is dinner time.</ab>
<ab n="14">So when they were
gone out, they parted the one from the other, and turning backe
againe they came to the same place, and after that they had asked
one another the cause, they acknowledged their lust: then appointed
they a time both together, when they might find her alone.</ab>
<ab n="15">And it fell out
as they watched a fit time, she went in as before, with two maids
onely, and she was desirous to wash her selfe in the garden: for it
was hot.<note> Gr. as yesterday and the day before.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And there was no
body there saue the two Elders, that had hid themselues, and
watched her.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then she said to
her maids, Bring me oile and washing bals, and shut the garden
doores, that I may wash me.</ab>
<ab n="18">And they did as
she bad them, and shut the garden doores, and went out themselues
at priuie doores to fetch the things that she had commaunded them:
but they saw not the Elders, because they were hid.<note> Or, side doores.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Now when the
maids were gone forth, the two Elders rose vp, and ran vnto her,
saying,</ab>
<ab n="20">Behold, the
garden doores are shut, that no man can see vs, and we are in loue
with thee: therefore consent vnto vs, and lie with vs.</ab>
<ab n="21">If thou wilt not,
we will beare witnesse against thee, that a young man was with
thee: and therefore thou didst send away thy maides from
thee.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then Susanna
sighed and said, I am straited on euery side: for if I doe this
thing, it is death vnto me: and if I doe it not, I cannot escape
your hands.</ab>
<ab n="23">It is better for
me to fall into your hands, and not doe it: then to sinne in the
sight of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="24">With that Susanna
cried with a loud voice: and the two Elders cried out against
her.</ab>
<ab n="25">Then ranne the
one, and opened the garden doore.</ab>
<ab n="26">So when the
seruants of the house heard the crie in the garden, they rushed in
at a priuie doore to see what was done vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="27">But when the
Elders had declared their matter, the seruants were greatly
ashamed: for there was neuer such a report made of Susanna.</ab>
<ab n="28">And it came to
passe the next day, when the people were assembled to her husband
Ioacim, the two Elders came also full of mischieuous imagination
against Susanna to put her to death,</ab>
<ab n="29">And said before
the people, Send for Susanna, the daughter of Chelcias, Ioacims
wife. And so they sent.</ab>
<ab n="30">So she came with
her father and mother, her children and all her kinred.</ab>
<ab n="31">Now Susanna was a
very delicate woman and beauteous to behold.</ab>
<ab n="32">And these wicked
men commanded to vncouer her face (for she was couered) that they
might be filled with her beautie.</ab>
<ab n="33">Therefore her
friends, and all that saw her, wept.</ab>
<ab n="34">Then the two
Elders stood vp in the mids of the people, and laid their hands
vpon her head.</ab>
<ab n="35">And she weeping
looked vp towards heauen: for her heart trusted in the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="36">And the Elders
said, As we walked in the garden alone, this woman came in, with
two maides, and shut the garden doores, &amp; sent the maides
away.</ab>
<ab n="37">Then a young man
who there was hid, came vnto her &amp; lay with her.</ab>
<ab n="38">Then we that
stood in a corner of the garden, seeing this wickednesse, ran vnto
them.</ab>
<ab n="39">And when we saw
them together, the man we could not hold: for he was stronger then
we, and opened the doore, and leaped out.</ab>
<ab n="40">But hauing taken
this woman, we asked who the young man was: but she would not tell
vs: these things doe we testifie.</ab>
<ab n="41">Then the assembly
beleeued them, as those that were the Elders and Iudges of the
people: so they condemned her to death.</ab>
<ab n="42">Then Susanna
cried out with a loud voice and said: O euerlasting God that
knowest the secrets, and knowest all things before they be:</ab>
<ab n="43">Thou knowest that
they haue borne false witnesse against me, and behold I must die:
whereas I neuer did such things, as these men haue maliciously
inuented against me.</ab>
<ab n="44">And the Lord
heard her voice.</ab>
<ab n="45">Therefore when
she was led to be put to death: the Lord raised vp the holy spirit
of a young youth, whose name was Daniel,</ab>
<ab n="46">Who cried with a
loud voice: I am cleare frō the blood of this woman.</ab>
<ab n="47">Then all the
people turned them towards him, &amp; said: what meane these words
that thou hast spoken?</ab>
<ab n="48">So he standing in
the mids of them, said, Are ye such fooles ye sonnes of Israel,
that without examination or knowledge of the truth, ye haue
condemned a daughter of Israel?</ab>
<ab n="49">Returne againe to
the place of iudgement: for they haue borne false witnesse against
her</ab>
<ab n="50">Wherefore all the
people turned againe in hast, and the Elders said vnto him, Come
sit downe among vs, and shew it vs, seeing God hath giuen thee the
honour of an Elder.</ab>
<ab n="51">Then said Daniel
vnto them, Put these two aside one farre from another, and I will
examine them.</ab>
<ab n="52">So when they were
put asunder one from another, hee called one of them, and said vnto
him, O thou that art waxen old in wickednesse: now thy sinnes which
thou hast committed aforetime, are come [to light.]</ab>
<ab n="53">For thou hast
pronounced false iudgement, and hast condemned the innocent, and
hast let the guiltie goe free, albeit the Lord saith, The innocent
and righteous shalt thou not slay.<note> Exod. 23. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="54">Now then if thou
hast seene her: tell me, Under what tree sawest thou them
companying together? who answered, Under a masticke
tree.<note> Gr. lentiske tree.</note></ab>
<ab n="55">And Daniel said,
Uery wel; Thou hast lied against thine owne head: for euen now the
Angel of God hath receiued the sentence of God, to cut thee in
two.</ab>
<ab n="56">So hee put him
aside, and commanded to bring the other, &amp; said vnto him, O
thou seed of Chanaan, and not of Iuda, beauty hath deceiued thee,
and lust hath peruerted thine heart.</ab>
<ab n="57">Thus haue yee
dealt with the daughters of Israel, and they for feare companied
with you: but the daughter of Iuda would not abide your
wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="58">Now therefore
tell mee, Under what tree didst thou take them companying together?
who answered, Under a holme tree.<note> Or, kinde of oake.</note></ab>
<ab n="59">Then said Daniel
vnto him, Well: thou hast also lied against thine owne head: for
the Angel of God waiteth with the sword to cut thee in two, that he
may destroy you.</ab>
<ab n="60">With that all the
assembly cried out with a lowd voice, and praised God who saueth
them that trust in him.</ab>
<ab n="61">And they arose
against the two Elders, (for Daniel had conuicted them of false
witnesse by their owne mouth)</ab>
<ab n="62">And according to
the Law of Moses, they did vnto them in such sort as they
malitiously intended to doe to their neighbour: And they put them
to death. Thus the innocent blood was saued the same
day.<note> Deut. 19. 19. prou. 19.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="63">Therefore
Chelcias and his wife praised God for their daughter Susanna, with
Ioacim her husband, and all the kinred: because there was no
dishonestie found in her.</ab>
<ab n="64">From that day
foorth was Daniel had in great reputation in the sight of the
people.</ab>



</div>