<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>11 Raguel telleth Tobias what had
happened to his daughter: 12 and giueth her in marriage vnto him.
17 She is conueyed to her chamber, and weepeth. 18 Her mother
cōforteth her.</head>

<ab n="1">And when they
were come to Ecbatane, they came to the house of Raguel; and Sara
met them: and after that they had saluted one another, shee brought
them into the house.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then sayd
Raguel to Edna his wife, How like is this yong man to Tobit my
cousin?</ab>
<ab n="3">And Raguel
asked them, From whence are you, brethren? To whom they said, We
are of the sonnes of Nephthali, which are captiues in
Nineue.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then hee said
to them, Doe yee know Tobit our kinseman? And they said, We know
him. Then said hee, Is he in good health?</ab>
<ab n="5">And they said,
Hee is both aliue, and in good health: And Tobias sayd, He is my
father.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then Raguel
leaped vp, and kissed him, and wept,</ab>
<ab n="7">And blessed
him; and said vnto him, Thou art the sonne of an honest and good
man: but when he had heard that Tobit was blinde, he was sorowfull,
and wept.</ab>
<ab n="8">And likewise
Edna his wife, and Sara his daughter wept. Moreouer, they
entertained them cheerefully, and after that they had killed a
ramme of the flocke, they set store of meat on the table. Then said
Tobias to Raphael, Brother Azarias, speak of those things, of which
thou diddest talke in the way, and let this businesse be
dispatched.<note> A sucking ramme or lambe. Iunius.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">So he
communicated the matter with Raguel, and Raguel said to Tobias,
Eate and drink, and make merry:</ab>
<ab n="10">For it is meet that
thou shouldest marry my daughter: neuerthelesse I will declare vnto
thee the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="11">I haue giuen my
daughter in mariage to seuen men, who died that night they came in
vnto her: neuerthelesse for the present be merry: But Tobias said,
I will eate nothing here, till we agree and sweare one to
another.</ab>
<ab n="12">Raguel said, Then
take her from hencefoorth according to the manner, for thou art her
cousin, and she is thine, and the mercifull God giue you good
successe in all things.<note> Or, Law.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Then he called his
daughter Sara, and she came to her father, and hee tooke her by the
hand, and gaue her to be wife to Tobias, saying, Behold, take her
after the Law of Moses, and leade her away to thy father: And he
blessed them,<note> Num.36.6</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And called Edna his
wife, &amp; tooke paper, and did write an instrument of couenants,
and sealed it.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then they began to
eate.</ab>
<ab n="16">After Raguel called
his wife Edna, and said vnto her, Sister, prepare another chamber,
&amp; bring her in thither.</ab>
<ab n="17">Which when she had
done as hee had bidden her, she brought her thither, and she wept,
&amp; she receiued the teares of her daughter, and said vnto
her,<note> Or, licked.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Be of good comfort,
my daughter, the Lord of heauen and earth giue thee ioy for this
thy sorow: be of good comfort, my daughter.</ab>



</div>