<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-7-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>3 Tobias driueth the wicked spirit
away, as hee was taught. 4 He and his wife rise vp to pray. 10
Raguel thought he was dead: 15 But finding him aliue, praiseth God,
12 and maketh a wedding feast.</head>

<ab n="1">And when they
had supped, they brought Tobias in vnto her.</ab>
<ab n="2">And as he
went, he remembred the wordes of Raphael, and tooke the ashes of
the perfumes, and put the heart, and the liuer of the fish
thereupon, and made a smoke therewith.<note> Or, imbers</note></ab>
<ab n="3">The which
smell, when the euill spirit had smelled, hee fled into the outmost
parts of Egypt, and the Angel bound him.</ab>
<ab n="4">And after that
they were both shut in together, Tobias rose out of the bed and
said, Sister, arise, and let vs pray, that God would haue pitie on
vs.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then began
Tobias to say, Blessed art thou, O God of our fathers, and blessed
is thy holy and glorious Name for euer, let the heauens blesse
thee, and all thy creatures.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thou madest
Adam, and gauest him Eue his wife for an helper &amp; stay: of them
came mankind: thou hast said, It is not good that man should bee
alone, let vs make vnto him an aide like to himselfe.<note> Gen. 2.7, 18, 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And now, O
Lord, I take not this my sister for lust, but vprightly: therefore
mercifully ordeine, that wee may become aged together.</ab>
<ab n="8">And she said
with him, Amen.</ab>
<ab n="9">So they slept
both that night, and Raguel arose, and went &amp; made a
graue</ab>
<ab n="10">Saying, I feare
lest he be dead.</ab>
<ab n="11">But when Raguel was
come into his house,</ab>
<ab n="12">He said vnto his
wife Edna, Send one of the maids, and let her see, whether he be
aliue: if he be not, that we may bury him, and no man know
it.</ab>
<ab n="13">So the maid opened
the doore and went in, and found them both asleepe,</ab>
<ab n="14">And came forth, and
told them, that he was aliue.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then Raguel praised
God, and said, O God, thou art worthy to be praised with all pure
and holy praise: therefore let thy Saints praise thee with all thy
creatures, and let all thine Angels and thine elect praise thee for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thou art to be
praised, for thou hast made mee ioyfull, and that is not come to
me, which I suspected: but thou hast dealt with vs according to thy
great mercie.</ab>
<ab n="17">Thou art to be
praised, because thou hast had mercie of two, that were the onely
begotten children of their fathers, grant them mercy, O Lord, and
finish their life in health, with ioy and mercie.</ab>
<ab n="18">Then Raguel bade
his seruants to fill the graue.</ab>
<ab n="19">And hee kept the
wedding feast fourteene dayes.</ab>
<ab n="20">For before the
dayes of the mariage were finished, Raguel had said vnto him by an
othe, that he should not depart, till the fourteene dayes of the
mariage were expired,</ab>
<ab n="21">And then he should
take the halfe of his goods, and goe in safetie to his father, and
should haue the rest when I and my wife be dead.</ab>



</div>