<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>The thankesgiuing vnto God, which
Tobit wrote.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Tobit
wrote a prayer of reioycing, and said, Blessed be God that liueth
for euer, and blessed be his kingdome:</ab>
<ab n="2">For he doeth
scourge, and hath mercy: hee leadeth downe to hell, and bringeth vp
againe: neither is there any that can auoid his hand.<note> Deut. 32. 39. 1.sam. 2.6. wisd. 16, 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Confesse him
before the Gentiles, ye children of Israel: for he hath scattered
vs among them.</ab>
<ab n="4">There declare
his greatnesse, and extoll him before all the liuing, for he is our
Lord, and he is the God our father for euer:</ab>
<ab n="5">And he wil
scourge vs for our iniquities, and will haue mercy againe, and will
gather vs out of all nations, among whom he hath scattered
vs.</ab>
<ab n="6">If you turne
to him with your whole heart, and with your whole minde, and deale
vprightly before him, then will hee turne vnto you, and will not
hide his face from you: Therefore see what he will doe with you,
and confesse him with your whole mouth, and praise the Lord of
might, and extoll the euerlasting King: in the land of my
captiuitie doe I praise him, and declare his might and maiesty to a
sinnefull nation: O yee sinners turne, and doe iustice before him:
who can tell if he will accept you, and haue mercy on you?</ab>
<ab n="7">I wil extoll
my God, and my soule shal praise the King of heauen, and shal
reioyce in his greatnesse.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let all men
speake, and let all praise him for his righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="9">O Ierusalem
the holy Citie, he will scourge thee for thy childrens workes, and
will haue mercy againe on the sonnes of the righteous.<note> Or, he will lay a scourge vpon the workes of thy children.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Giue praise to the
Lord, for hee is good: and praise the euerlasting King, that his
Tabernacle may bee builded in thee againe with ioy: and let him
make ioyfull there in thee, those that are captiues, and loue in
thee for euer those that are miserable.<note> Or, to make.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Many nations shall
come from farre to the Name of the Lord God, with gifts in their
hands, euen giftes to the King of heauen: all generations shall
praise thee with great ioy.</ab>
<ab n="12">Cursed are all
they which hate thee, and blessed shall all be, which loue thee for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="13">Reioyce &amp; be
glad for the children of the iust: for they shall be gathered
together, &amp; shall blesse the Lord of the iust.</ab>
<ab n="14">O blessed are they
which loue thee, for they shall reioyce in thy peace: blessed are
they which haue been sorowfull for all thy scourges, for they shal
reioyce for thee, when they haue seene all thy glory, and shalbe
glad for euer.<note> Or, prosperitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Let my soule
blesse God the great King.</ab>
<ab n="16">For Ierusalem
shall be built vp with Saphires, and Emerauds, and precious stone:
thy walles and towres, and battlements with pure golde.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the streets of
Ierusalem shal be paued with Berill, and Carbuncle, and stones of
Ophir.</ab>
<ab n="18">And all her
streets shall say, Halleluiah, and they shall praise him, saying,
Blessed be God which hath extolled it for euer.</ab>



</div>