<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>3 Tobit giueth instructions to his
sonne Tobias, 20 and telleth him of money left with Gabael in
Media.</head>

<ab n="1">In that day
Tobit remembred the money, which he had committed to Gabael in
Rages of Media,</ab>
<ab n="2">And said with
himselfe, I haue wished for death, wherefore doe I not call for my
sonne Tobias, that I may signifie to him of the money before I
die.</ab>
<ab n="3">And when he
had called him, he said; My sonne, when I am dead, bury me, and
despise not thy mother, but honour her all the dayes of thy life,
and doe that which shall please her, and greiue her
not.<note> Exod.20. 12. ecclus.7 27.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Remember, my
sonne, that shee saw many dangers for thee, when thou wast in her
wombe, and when shee is dead, bury her by me in one graue.</ab>
<ab n="5">My sonne, be
mindfull of the Lord our God all thy dayes, and let not thy will be
set to sinne, or to transgresse his Commandements: doe vprightly
all thy life long, and follow not the wayes of
vnrighteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="6">For if thou
deale truely, thy doings shall prosperously succeed to thee, and to
all them that liue iustly.</ab>
<ab n="7">Giue almes of
thy substance, and when thou giuest almes, let not thine eye be
enuious, neither turne thy face from any poore, and the face of God
shall not be turned away from thee.<note> Prou.3.9. eccle.4.1. and 14.13. luke 14.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">If thou hast
abundance, giue almes accordingly: if thou haue but a litle, be not
afraid to giue according to that litle.<note> Ecclu.35. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For thou
layest vp a good treasure for thy selfe against the day of
necessitie.</ab>
<ab n="10">Because that almes
doth deliuer from death, and suffereth not to come into
darknesse.<note> Ecclu.29. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For almes is a good
gift vnto all that giue it, in the sight of the most High.</ab>
<ab n="12">Beware of all
whoredome, my sonne, and chiefely take a wife of the seed of thy
fathers, and take not a strange woman to wife, which is not of thy
fathers tribe: for we are the children of the Prophets, Noe,
Abraham, Isaak, and Iacob: remember, my sonne, that our fathers
from the beginning, euen that they all maried wiues of their owne
kinred, and were blessed in their children, and their seede shall
inherite the land.<note> 1.Thess.4. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Now therefore my
sonne, loue thy brethren, and despise not in thy heart thy
brethren, the sonnes and daughters of thy people, in not taking a
wife of them: for in pride is destruction and much trouble, and in
lewdnesse is decay, and great want: for lewdnesse is the mother of
famine.</ab>
<ab n="14">Let not the wages
of any man, which hath wrought for thee, tary with thee, but giue
him it out of hand: for if thou serue God he will also repay thee:
be circumspect, my sonne, in all things thou doest, and be wise in
all thy conuersation.<note> Leuit. 19. 13. deut. 24.14.15.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Doe that to no man
which thou hatest: drinke not wine to make thee drunken; neither
let drunkennesse goe with thee in thy iourney.<note> Matth.7. 12. luc.6. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">Giue of thy bread
to the hungry, and of thy garments to them that are naked, and
according to thine abundance giue almes, and let not thine eye be
enuious, when thou giuest almes.<note> Luc.14. 13. , Matth.6.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Powre out thy bread
on the buriall of the iust, but giue nothing to the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="18">Aske counsell of
all that are wise, and despise not any counsell that is
profitable.</ab>
<ab n="19">Blesse the Lord thy
God alway, and desire of him that thy wayes may be directed, and
that all thy pathes, and counsels may prosper: for euery nation
hath not counsell, but the Lord himselfe giueth all good things,
and hee humbleth whom he will, as he will; now therefore my sonne,
remember my commandements, neither let them be put out of thy
minde.</ab>
<ab n="20">And now I signifie
this to thee, that I committed tenne talents to Gabael the sonne of
Gabrias at Rages in Media.</ab>
<ab n="21">And feare not my
sonne, that we are made poore, for thou hast much wealth, if thou
feare God, and depart from all sinne, and doe that which is
pleasing in his sight.</ab>



</div>