<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-14-14-Judith.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>3 Tobit giueth instructions to his
sonne, 8 Specially to leaue Nineue. 11 Hee and his wife die, and
are buried. 12 Tobias remoueth to Ecbatane, 14 and there died,
after hee had heard of the destruction of Nineue.</head>

<ab n="1">So Tobit made
an ende of praising God.</ab>
<ab n="2">And he was
eight and fifty yeeres olde when hee lost his sight, which was
restored to him after eight yeeres, and he gaue almes, and he
increased in the feare of the Lord God, and praised
him.<note> Or, did more and more feare.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And when he
was very aged, hee called his sonne, and the sixe sons of his
sonne, and said to him, My sonne, take thy children; for behold, I
am aged, and am ready to depart out of this life.</ab>
<ab n="4">Goe into
Media, my sonne, for I surely beleeue those things which Ionas the
Prophet spake of Nineue, that it shall be ouerthrowen, and that for
a time peace shal rather be in Media, and that our brethren shall
lie scattered in the earth from that good land, and Ierusalem shall
be desolate, and the house of God in it shalbe burned, and shall be
desolate for a time:</ab>
<ab n="5">And that
againe God will haue mercie on them, and bring them againe into the
land where they shall build a Temple, but not like to the first,
vntill the time of that age be fulfilled, and afterward they shall
returne from all places of their captiuitie, and build vp Ierusalem
gloriously, and the house of God shall be built in it for euer,
with a glorious building, as the prophets haue spoken
thereof.<note> Ezra 3. 8. and 6. 14. , For euer is not in the Rom. copie.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And all
nations shall turne, and feare the Lord God truely, and shall burie
their idoles.</ab>
<ab n="7">So shall all
nations praise the Lord, and his people shal confesse God, and the
Lord shall exalt his people, and all those which loue the Lord God
in trueth and iustice, shall reioyce, shewing mercie to our
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="8">And now, my
sonne, depart out of Nineue, because that those things which the
Prophet Ionas spake, shall surely come to passe.</ab>
<ab n="9">But keepe
thou the Law and the Commandements, and shew thy selfe mercifull
and iust, that it may goe well with thee.</ab>
<ab n="10">And burie me
decently, and thy mother with me, but tarie no longer at Nineue.
Remember, my sonne, how Aman handled Achiacharus þe
brought him vp, how out of light he brought him into darkenes, and
how he rewarded him againe: yet Ahiacharus was saued, but the other
had his reward, for hee went downe into darkenesse. Manasses gaue
almes, and escaped the snares of death which they had set for him:
but Aman fell into the snare and perished.<note> Or, preserued. , Iunius readeth Nasban. , Rom. which he had set.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore now, my
sonne, consider what almes doeth, and how righteousnesse doth
deliuer. When he had said these things, he gaue vp the ghost in the
bed, being an hundred, and eight and fiftie yeeres old, and he
buried him honourably.<note> Or, they.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And when Anna his
mother was dead, he buried her with his father: but Tobias departed
with his wife and children to Ecbatane, to Raguel his father in
law:</ab>
<ab n="13">Where hee became
old with honour, and hee buried his father and mother in lawe
honourably, and hee inherited their substance, and his father
Tobits.<note> Or, possessed.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And he died at
Ecbatane in Media, being an hundred and seuen and twentie yeeres
old.</ab>
<ab n="15">But before he
died, he heard of the destruction of Nineue, which was taken by
Nabuchodonosor &amp; Assuerus: and before his death hee reioyced
ouer Nineue.</ab>



</div>