<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>5 Tobit offereth halfe to the Angel
for his paines; 6 But he calleth them both aside, and exhorteth
them, 15 and telleth them that he was an Angel, 21 and was seene no
more.</head>

<ab n="1">Then Tobit
called his son Tobias, and said vnto him, My sonne, see that the
man haue his wages, which went with thee, and thou must giue him
more.</ab>
<ab n="2">And Tobias
said vnto him, O father, it is no harme to me to giue him halfe of
those things which I haue brought.</ab>
<ab n="3">For he hath
brought me againe to thee in safety, and made whole my wife, and
brought mee the money, and likewise healed thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then the old
man said: It is due vnto him.</ab>
<ab n="5">So he called
the Angell, and he said vnto him, Take halfe of all that yee haue
brought, and goe away in safety.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then he tooke
them both apart, and sayd vnto them, Blesse God, praise him, and
magnifie him, and praise him for the things which he hath done vnto
you in the sight of all that liue. It is good to praise God and
exalt his name, &amp; honorably to shew forth the works of God,
therfore be not slacke to praise him.<note> Or, with honour.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">It is good to
keepe close the secret of a King, but it is honorable to reueale
the works of God: do that which is good, and no euill shall touch
you.</ab>
<ab n="8">Praier is
good with fasting, and almes and righteousnesse: a little with
righteousnes is better then much with vnrighteousnesse: it is
better to giue almes then to lay vp gold.</ab>
<ab n="9">For almes
doth deliuer from death, and shall purge away all sinne. Those that
exercise almes, and righteousnesse, shall be filled with
life.</ab>
<ab n="10">But they that
sinne are enemies to their owne life.</ab>
<ab n="11">Surely I will keep
close nothing from you. For I said, it was good to keepe close the
secret of a King, but that it was honorable to reueale the works of
God.</ab>
<ab n="12">Now therefore,
when thou didst pray, and Sara thy daughter in Law, I did bring the
remembrance of your prayers before the holy one, and when thou
didst bury the dead, I was with thee likewise.</ab>
<ab n="13">And when thou
didst not delay to rise vp, and leaue thy dinner to go and couer
the dead, thy good deede was not hidde from me: but I was with
thee.<note> Greek. to go and bury.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And now God hath
sent mee to heale thee, &amp; Sara thy daughter in law.</ab>
<ab n="15">I am Raphael one
of the seuen holy Angels, which present the prayers of the Saints,
and which go in and out before the glory of the Holy one.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then they were
both troubled, and fel vpon their faces: for they feared.</ab>
<ab n="17">But he said vnto
them, feare not, for it shall go well with you, praise God
therefore.</ab>
<ab n="18">For not of any
fauour of mine, but by the will of our God I came, wherefore praise
him for euer.</ab>
<ab n="19">All these daies I
did appeare vnto you, but I did neither eat nor drinke, but you did
see a vision.<note> Gen.18.8. 19.3. Iudg.13. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Now therefore giue
God thanks: for I go vp to him þe sent me, but
write all things which are done, in a booke.</ab>
<ab n="21">And when they
rose, they saw him no more.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then they
confessed the great and wonderfull workes of God, and how the Angel
of the Lord had appeared vnto them.</ab>



</div>