<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 Tobit leaueth his meate to bury
the dead, 10 and becommeth blinde. 11 His wife taketh in worke to
get her liuing. 14 Her husband and she fall out about a
kidde.</head>

<ab n="1">Now when I was
come home againe, and my wife Anna was restored vnto me, with my
sonne Tobias, in the feast of Pentecost, which is the holy Feast of
the seuen weekes, there was a good dinner prepared me, in the which
I sate down to eate.</ab>
<ab n="2">And when I saw
abundance of meate, I sayd to my sonne, Goe and bring what poore
man soeuer thou shalt finde out of our brethren, who is mindfull of
the Lord, and loe, I tarie for thee.</ab>
<ab n="3">But he came
againe and said, Father, one of our nation is strangled, and is
cast out in the market place.</ab>
<ab n="4">Then before I
had tasted of any meate, I start vp and tooke him vp into a roume,
vntill the going downe of the Sunne.</ab>
<ab n="5">Then I
returned and washed my selfe, and ate my meate in
heauinesse,</ab>
<ab n="6">Remembring
that prophesie of Amos, as hee said; Your feasts shall be turned
into mourning, and all your mirth into lamentation.<note> Amos 8. 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Therefore I
wept: and after the going downe of the Sunne, I went and made a
graue, and buried him.</ab>
<ab n="8">But my
neighbours mocked me, and said, This man is not yet afraide to be
put to death for this matter, who fledde away, and yet loe, he
burieth the dead againe.<note> Cha.1.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">The same night
also I returned from the buriall, and slept by the wall of my court
yard, being polluted, and my face was vncouered:</ab>
<ab n="10">And I knewe not
that there were Sparrowes in the wall, and mine eyes being open,
the Sparrowes muted warme doung into mine eyes, and a whitenesse
came in mine eyes, and I went to the Physicians, but they helped me
not: moreouer Achiacharus did nourish mee, vntill I went into
Elymais.<note> Or, Swallowes. , Or, white filmes.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And my wife Anna
did take womens workes to doe.<note> Or, was hired to spinne in the womens rooms.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And when shee had
sent them home to the owners, they payd her wages, and gaue her
also besides a kid.<note> Or, her worke.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And when it was in
mine house, and beganne to crie, I said vnto her, From whence is
this kidde? is it not stollen? render it to the owners, for it is
not lawfull to eate any thing that is stollen.<note> Deu.22.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But shee replyed
vpon me, It was giuen for a gift more then the wages: Howbeit I did
not beleeue her, but bade her render it to the owners: and I was
abashed at her. But she replyed vpon me, Where are thine almes, and
thy righteous deedes? behold, thou and all thy workes are
knowen.<note> Iob 2.9. , Or, loe all things are knowen to thee.</note></ab>



</div>