<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/2-Esdras-Chapter-16-16c-Tobit.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Tobit his stocke, and deuotion in
his youth, 9 His marriage, 10 And captiuitie, 13 His preferment, 16
Almes and charitie in burying the dead, 19 For which he is accused
and flieth, 22 And after returneth to Niniue.</head>

<ab n="1">The Booke of
the wordes of Tobit, sonne of Tobiel, the son of Ananiel, the sonne
of Aduel, the sonne of Gabael, of the seed of Asael, of the Tribe
of Nephthali,<note> Or, acts.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">Who in the
time of Enemessar king of the Assyrians, was led captiue out of
This be which is at the right hand of that citie, which is called
properly Nephthali in Galile aboue Aser.<note> 2.King.17. 3. , Or, Kedes of Nephthali in Galile, Iudg.4.6.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I Tobit haue
walked all the dayes of my life in the way of trueth, and iustice,
and I did many almes deeds to my brethren, and my nation, who came
with me to Nineue into the land of the Assyrians.</ab>
<ab n="4">And when I was
in mine owne countrey, in the land of Israel, being but yong, all
the tribe of Nephthali my father, fell from the house of Ierusalem,
which was chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, that all the
tribes should sacrifice there where the Temple of the habitation of
the most High was consecrated, and built for all ages.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now all the
tribes which together reuolted, and the house of my father
Nephthali sacrificed vnto the heifer Baal.<note> 1.King.12. 30. Or, to the power of Baal, or the god Baal.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But I alone
went often to Ierusalem at the Feasts, as it was ordeined vnto al
the people of Israel by an euerlasting decree, hauing the first
fruits, and tenths of encrease, with that which was first shorne,
and them gaue I at the Altar to the Priestes the children of
Aaron.<note> Exod. 22. 29. deu.12. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">The first
tenth part of al increase, I gaue to the sonnes of Aaron, who
ministred at Ierusalem: another tenth part I sold away, and went,
and spent it euery yeere at Ierusalem.<note> Or, Levi.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And the third,
I gaue vnto them to whom it was meet, as Debora my fathers mother
had commanded mee, because I was left an orphane by my
father.</ab>
<ab n="9">Furthermore
when I was come to the age of a man, I married Anna of mine owne
kinred, and of her I begate Tobias.<note> Num.36. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And when we were
caried away captiues to Nineue, all my brethren, and those that
were of my kinred, did eate of the bread of the
Gentiles.<note> Gene.43. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But I kept my selfe
from eating<note> Greek, my soule.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Because I remembred
God with all my heart.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the most High
gaue me grace, and fauour before Enemessar, so that I was his
purueyour.<note> Greek. byer.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And I went into
Media, and left in trust with Gabael, the brother of Gabrias at
Rages a citie of Media, ten talents of siluer.<note> Or, in the land or countrey of Media.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Now when Enemessar
was dead, Sennacherib his sonne reigned in his stead, whose estate
was troubled, that I could not goe into Media.<note> Gr, the wayes of whom were vnsetled.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">And in the time of
Enemessar, I gaue many almes to my brethren, and gaue my bread to
the hungry,</ab>
<ab n="17">And my clothes to
the naked: and if I saw any of my nation dead, or cast about the
walles of Nineue, I buried him.<note> Or, behind walles.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And if the king
Sennacherib had slaine any, when hee was come, and fledde from
Iudea, I buried them priuily, (for in his wrath hee killed many)
but the bodies were not found, when they were sought for of the
king.<note> 2. Kin. 19. 35,36. isai. 37.36,37. ecclus.48. 18,12.1. macc.7.41. 2.mac. 8. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And when one of the
Nineuites went, and complained of me to the king that I buried
them, and hid my selfe: vnderstanding that I was sought for to be
put to death, I withdrew my selfe for feare.</ab>
<ab n="20">Then all my goods
were forcibly taken away, neither was there any thing left me,
besides my wife Anna, and my sonne Tobias.</ab>
<ab n="21">And there passed
not fiue and fiftie dayes before two of his sonnes killed him, and
they fled into the mountaines of Ararath, and Sarchedonus his sonne
reigned in his stead, who appointed ouer his fathers accounts, and
ouer all his affaires, Achiacharus my brother Anaels
sonne.<note> 2.King. 19.37. 2. chr.32.21. , Or, Esar-Haddon.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">And Achiacharus
entreating for me, I returned to Nineue: now Achiacharus was
Cup-bearer, and keeper of the Signet, and Steward, and ouerseer of
the accounts: and Sarchedonus appointed him next vnto him: and hee
was my brothers sonne.<note> Or, Esar-Haddon.</note></ab>



</div>