<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-4-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-5-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>4 Yong Tobias seeketh a guide into
Media. 6 The Angel will goe with him, 12 and saith he is his
kinseman. 16 Tobias and the Angel depart together. 17 But his
mother is grieued for her sonnes departing.</head>

<ab n="1">Tobias then
answered and said, Father, I will doe all things, which thou hast
commanded me.</ab>
<ab n="2">But how can I
receiue the money, seeing, I know him not?</ab>
<ab n="3">Then he gaue
him the handwriting, and said vnto him, Seeke thee a man which may
goe with thee whiles I yet liue, and I will giue him wages, and
goe, and receiue the money.</ab>
<ab n="4">Therefore when
he went to seeke a man, he found Raphael that was an
Angell.</ab>
<ab n="5">But he knew
not; and he said vnto him, Canst thou goe with me to Rages? &amp;
knowest thou those places well?</ab>
<ab n="6">To whom the
Angel said, I will goe with thee, and I know the way well: for I
haue lodged with our brother Gabael.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then Tobias
said vnto him, Tary for me till I tell my father.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then he said
vnto him, Goe and tary not; so he went in, and said to his father;
Behold, I haue found one, which wil goe with me. Then he said, Call
him vnto me, that I may know of what tribe he is, and whether hee
be a trustie man to goe with thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">So he called
him, and he came in, and they saluted one another.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then Tobit said
vnto him, Brother, shew me of what tribe and family thou
art.</ab>
<ab n="11">To whom hee said,
Doest thou seeke for a tribe or family, or an hired man to goe with
thy sonne? Then Tobit said vnto him, I would know, brother, thy
kinred, and name.</ab>
<ab n="12">Then he said, I am
Azarias, the sonne of Ananias the great, and of thy
brethren.</ab>
<ab n="13">Then Tobit said,
Thou art welcome brother, be not now angry with mee, because I haue
enquired to know thy tribe, and thy family, for thou art my
brother, of an honest &amp; good stocke: for I know Ananias, and
Ionathas sonnes of that great Samaias: as we went together to
Ierusalem to worship, and offered the first borne, and the tenths
of the fruits, and they were not seduced with the errour of our
brethren: my brother, thou art of a good stocke.</ab>
<ab n="14">But tell me, what
wages shall I giue thee? wilt thou a drachme a day? and things
necessary as to my owne sonne?</ab>
<ab n="15">Yea moreouer, if ye
returne safe, I will adde some thing to the wages.</ab>
<ab n="16">So they were well
pleased. Then said he to Tobias; Prepare thy selfe for the iourney,
and God send you a good iourney. And when his sonne had prepared
all things for the iourney, his father said; Goe thou with this
man, and God which dwelleth in heauen prosper your iourney, &amp;
the Angel of God keepe you company. So they went foorth both, and
the yong mans dogge with them.</ab>
<ab n="17">But Anna his mother
wept, and said to Tobit, Why hast thou sent away our sonne? is hee
not the staffe of our hand, in going in and out before vs?</ab>
<ab n="18">Be not greedy (to
adde) money to money: but let it bee as refuse in respect of our
childe.<note> Let not money be added, but be the off scouring of our sonne.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For that which the
Lord hath giuen vs to liue with, doeth suffice vs.<note> Or, so long as God hath granted vs to liue, this is sufficient.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Then said Tobit to
her, Take no care my sister he shal returne in safety, and thine
eyes shall see him.</ab>
<ab n="21">For the good Angel
will keepe him company, and his iourney shall be prosperous, and he
shall returne safe.</ab>
<ab n="22">Then she made an
end of weeping.</ab>



</div>