<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-9-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>6 Tobits mother spieth her sonne
comming. 10 His father meeteth him at the doore, and recouereth his
sight. 14 Hee praiseth God, 17 And welcommeth his daughter in
Lawe.</head>

<ab n="1">After these
things Tobias went his way, praising God that he had giuen him a
prosperous iourney, and blessed Raguel, and Edna his wife, and went
on his way till they drew neere vnto Nineue.</ab>
<ab n="2">Then Raphael
said to Tobias, Thou knowest brother, how thou didst leaue thy
father.</ab>
<ab n="3">Let vs haste
before thy wife, and prepare the house.</ab>
<ab n="4">And take in
thine hand the gall of the fish: so they went their way, and the
dog went after them.</ab>
<ab n="5">Now Anna sate
looking about towards the way for her sonne.</ab>
<ab n="6">And when she
espied him comming, she said to his father, Behold, thy sonne
commeth, and the man that went with him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Then said
Raphael, I know, Tobias, that thy father will open his
eyes.</ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore
annoint thou his eies with the gall, and being pricked therewith he
shall rub, and the whitenesse shall fall away, and he shall see
thee.</ab>
<ab n="9">Then Anna ran
forth, and fell vpon the necke of her sonne, and said vnto him,
seeing I haue seene thee my sonne, from henceforth, I am content to
die, and they wept both.</ab>
<ab n="10">Tobit also went
forth toward the doore, and stumbled: but his sonne ran vnto
him,</ab>
<ab n="11">And tooke hold of
his father, and he strake of the gall on his fathers eyes, saying,
Be of good hope, my father.</ab>
<ab n="12">And when his eyes
beganne to smart, he rubbed them.</ab>
<ab n="13">And the whitenesse
pilled away from the corners of his eyes, and when he saw his
sonne, he fell vpon his necke.</ab>
<ab n="14">And he wept, and
said, Blessed art thou, O God, and blessed is thy Name for euer,
and blessed are all thine holy Angels:</ab>
<ab n="15">For thou hast
scourged, and hast taken pitie on me: for behold, I see my sonne
Tobias. And his sonne went in reioycing, and told his father the
great things that had happened to him in Media.</ab>
<ab n="16">Then Tobit went
out to meete his daughter in law at the gate of Niniue, reioycing
and praysing God: and they which saw him goe, marueiled because he
had receiued his sight.</ab>
<ab n="17">But Tobit gaue
thankes before them: because God had mercy on him. And when hee
came neere to Sara his daughter in Law, hee blessed her, saying,
Thou art welcome daughter: God be blessed which hath brought thee
vnto vs, and blessed be thy father and thy mother; And there was
ioy amongst all his brethren which were at Nineue.</ab>
<ab n="18">And Achiacharus,
and Nasbas his brothers sonne came.<note> Iunius, who is also called Nasbas.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And Tobias wedding
was kept seuen dayes with great ioy.</ab>



</div>