<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CTobit_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Tobit-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Tobit grieued with his wiues
taunts, prayeth. 11 Sara reproched by her fathers maides, prayeth
also. 17 An Angel is sent to helpe them both.</head>

<ab n="1">Then I being
grieued, did weepe, and in my sorrowe prayed, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">O Lord, thou
art iust and all thy workes, and all thy wayes are mercie and
trueth, and thou iudgest truely &amp; iustly for euer.</ab>
<ab n="3">Remember me,
and looke on me, punish me not for my sinnes and ignorances, and
the sinnes of my fathers, who haue sinned before thee.</ab>
<ab n="4">For they
obeyed not thy commandements, wherefore thou hast deliuered vs for
a spoile, and vnto captiuitie, and vnto death, and for a prouerbe
of reproch to all the nations among whom we are
dispersed.<note> Deut.28. 15,37.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And now thy
iudgments are many and true: Deale with me according to my sinnes,
and my fathers: because we haue not kept thy commandements, neither
haue walked in trueth before thee.</ab>
<ab n="6">Now therefore
deale with me as seemeth best vnto thee, and command my spirit to
be taken from me, that I may be dissolued, and become earth: for it
is profitable for me to die, rather then to liue, because I haue
heard false reproches, and haue much sorow: command therfore that I
may now be deliuered out of this distresse, and goe into the
euerlasting place: turne not thy face away from me.<note> Or, dismissed, or deliuered.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">It came to
passe the same day, that in Ecbatane a citie of Media, Sara the
daughter of Raguel, was also reproched by her fathers
maides,</ab>
<ab n="8">Because that
she had bin maried to seuen husbands, whom Almodeus the euill
spirit had killed, before they had lien with her. Doest thou not
knowe, said they, that thou hast strangled thine husbands? thou
hast had already seuen husbands, neither wast thou named after any
of them.</ab>
<ab n="9">Wherefore
doest thou beate vs for them? If they be dead, goe thy wayes after
them, let vs neuer see of thee either sonne or daughter.</ab>
<ab n="10">When she heard
these things, she was very sorowful, so that she thought to haue
strangled her selfe, and she said, I am the onely daughter of my
father, and if I doe this, it shall bee a reproch vnto him, and I
shall bring his old age with sorow vnto the graue.</ab>
<ab n="11">Then she prayed
toward the window, &amp; said, Blessed art thou, O Lord my God, and
thine holy and glorious Name is blessed, and honourable foreuer,
let al thy works praise thee for euer.</ab>
<ab n="12">And now, O Lord, I
set mine eyes and my face toward thee,</ab>
<ab n="13">And say, take me
out of the earth, that I may heare no more the reproch.</ab>
<ab n="14">Thou knowest, Lord,
that I am pure from all sinne with man,</ab>
<ab n="15">And that I neuer
polluted my name, nor the name of my father in the land of my
captiuitie: I am the onely daughter of my father, neither hath he
any child to bee his heire, neither any neere kinseman, nor any
sonne of his aliue, to whome I may keepe my selfe for a wife: my
seuen husbands are already dead, and why should I liue? but if it
please not thee that I should die, command some regard to be had of
me, and pitie taken of me, that I heare no more
reproch.<note> Or, brother.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">So the prayers of
them both were heard before the Maiesty of the great God.</ab>
<ab n="17">And Raphael was
sent to heale them both, that is, to scale away the whitenesse of
Tobits eyes, and to giue Sara the daughter of Raguel, for a wife to
Tobias the sonne of Tobit, and to bind Asmodeus the euill spirit,
because she belongeth to Tobias by right of inheritance. The selfe
same time came Tobit home, and entred into his house, and Sara, the
daughter of Raguel came downe from her vpper chamber.</ab>



</div>