<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_19" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-19-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIX.</head>
<head>1 Why God shewed no mercie to the
Egyptians. 5 And how wonderfully hee dealt with his people. 14 The
Egyptians were worse then the Sodomites. 18 The wonderfull
agreement of the creatures to serue Gods people.</head>

<ab n="1">As for
the vngodly, wrath came vpon them without mercie vnto the end: for
he knew before what they would doe;</ab>
<ab n="2">Howe
that hauing giuen them leaue to depart, and sent them hastily away,
they would repent and pursue them.</ab>
<ab n="3">For
whilest they were yet mourning, and making lamentation at the
graues of the dead, they added another foolish deuice, and pursued
them as fugitiues, whom they had entreated to be gone.<note> Or, cast out by entreaty.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For the
destiny, whereof they were worthy, drew them vnto this end, and
made them forget the things that had already happened, that they
might fulfill the punishment which was wanting to their
torments,</ab>
<ab n="5">And
that thy people might passe a wonderfull way: but they might find a
strange death.</ab>
<ab n="6">For the
whole creature in his proper kind was fashioned againe anew,
seruing the peculiar commandements that were giuen vnto them, that
thy children might be kept without hurt.</ab>
<ab n="7">As
namely, a cloud shadowing the campe, and where water stood before
drie land appeared, and out of the red Sea a way without
impediment, and out of the violent streame a greene field:</ab>
<ab n="8">Where-thorough
all the people went that were defended with thy hand, seeing thy
marueilous strange wonders.</ab>
<ab n="9">For
they went at large like horses, and leaped like lambes, praising
thee O Lord, who hadst deliuered them.</ab>
<ab n="10">For
they were yet mindefull of the things that were done while they
soiourned in the strange land, how the ground brought forth flies
in stead of cattell, and how the riuer cast vp a multitude of frogs
in stead of fishes.<note> Or, lice.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But
afterwards they saw a new generation of foules, when being led with
their appetite they asked delicate meates.</ab>
<ab n="12">For
quailes came vp vnto them from the Sea, for their
contentment.<note> Or, comfort.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And
punishments came vpon the sinners not without former signes by the
force of thunders: for they suffered iustly, according to their
owne wickednesse, insomuch as they vsed a more hard and hatefull
behauiour towards strangers:</ab>
<ab n="14">For
the Sodomits did not receiue those whom they knew not when they
came: but these brought friends into bondage, that had well
deserued of them.</ab>
<ab n="15">And
not onely so: but peraduenture some respect shall be had of those,
because they vsed strangers not friendly.</ab>
<ab n="16">But
these very grieuously afflicted them, whom they had receiued with
feastings, and were already made partakers of the same lawes with
them.</ab>
<ab n="17">Therefore
euen with blindnesse were these stricken, as those were at the
doores of the righteous man: when being compassed about with
horrible great darknesse, euery one sought the passage of his owne
doores.</ab>
<ab n="18">For
the elements were changed in themselues by a kind of harmonie, like
as in a Psaltery notes change the name of the tune, and yet are
alwayes sounds, which may well be perceiued by the sight of the
things that haue beene done.<note> Gre. by themselues.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For
earthly things were turned into watry, and the things that before
swamme in the water, now went vpon the ground.</ab>
<ab n="20">The
fire had power in the water, forgetting his owne vertue: and the
water forgat his owne quenching nature.</ab>
<ab n="21">On the
other side, the flames wasted not the flesh of the corruptible
liuing things, though they walked therin, neither melted they the
ycie kind of heauenly meate, that was of nature apt to
melt.</ab>
<ab n="22">For in
all things, O Lord, thou didst magnifie thy people, and glorifie
them, neither didst thou lightly regard them: but didst assist them
in euery time and place.</ab>



</div>