<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Additions-to-Esther-Chapter-16-16-Wisdom-of-Solomon.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>2 To whom God sheweth himselfe, 4
and Wisedome herselfe. 6 An euill speaker can not lie hid. 12 We
procure our owne destruction: 13 for God created not
death.</head>

<ab n="1">Loue
righteousnesse, yee that be iudges of the earth: thinke of the Lord
with a good (heart) and in simplicitie of heart seeke
him.<note> 1.King.3. 3 esay. 56.1. 13.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For hee
will bee found of them that tempt him not: and sheweth himselfe
vnto such as doe not distrust him.<note> Deut.4. 29.2. chro.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For
froward thoughts separate from God: and his power when it is tryed,
reprooueth the vnwise.<note> Or, maketh manifest.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For into
a malitious soule wisedome shall not enter: nor dwell in the body
that is subiect vnto sinne.</ab>
<ab n="5">For the
holy spirit of discipline will flie deceit, &amp; remoue from
thoughts that are without vnderstanding: and will not abide when
vnrighteousnesse commeth in.<note> Iere.4.22. , Or, is rebuked, or sheweth it selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For
wisedome is a louing spirit: and will not acquite a blasphemour of
his words: for God is witnesse of his reines, and a true beholder
of his heart, and a hearer of his tongue.<note> Gal. 5. 22. , Or, lippes.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For the
spirit of the Lord filleth the world: and that which containeth all
things hath knowledge of the voice.<note> Or, vpholdeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Therefore
he that speaketh vnrighteous things, cannot be hid: neither shal
vengeance, when it punisheth. passe by him.</ab>
<ab n="9">For
inquisition shall be made into the counsels of the vngodly: and the
sound of his words, shall come vnto the Lord, for the manifestation
of his wicked deedes.<note> Or, reprouing.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For the
eare of iealousie heareth al things: and the noise of murmurings is
not hid.</ab>
<ab n="11">Therefore
beware of murmuring, which is vnprofitable, and refraine your
tongue from backbiting: for there is no word so secret that shall
goe for nought: and the mouth that belieth, slayeth the
soule.<note> Or, slandereth.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Seeke
not death in the errour of your life: and pull not vpon your selues
destruction, with the workes of your hands.<note> Deut.4. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For God
made not death: neither hath he pleasure in the destruction of the
liuing.</ab>
<ab n="14">For he
created all things, that they might haue their being: and the
generations of the world were healthfull: and there is no poyson of
destruction in them: nor the kingdome of death vpon the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="15">For
righteousnesse is immortall.</ab>
<ab n="16">But
vngodly men with their workes, and words called it to them: for
when they thought to haue it their friend, they consumed to nought,
and made a couenant with it, because they are worthy to take part
with it.</ab>



</div>