<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_12" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-12-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XII.</head>
<head>2 God did not destroy those of
Canaan all at once. 12 If he had done so, who could controll him?
19 but by sparing them hee taught vs, 27 they were punished with
their Gods.</head>

<ab n="1">For
thine vncorruptible spirit is in all things.</ab>
<ab n="2">Therefore
chastnest thou them by little, and little, that offend, and warnest
them by putting them in remembrance, wherin they haue offended,
that leauing their wickednesse they may beleeue on thee O
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="3">For it
was thy will to destroy by the handes of our fathers, both those
old inhabitants of thy holy land,<note> Or, ancient.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Whom
thou hatedst for doing most odious workes of witchcrafts, and
wicked sacrifices;<note> Or, sorceries.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And
also those mercilesse murderers of children, &amp; deuourers of
mans flesh, and the feasts of blood;</ab>
<ab n="6">With
their Priests out of the midst of their idolatrous crew, and the
parents that killed with their owne hands, soules destitute of
helpe:</ab>
<ab n="7">That
the land which thou esteemedst aboue all other, might receiue a
worthy colonie of Gods children.<note> Or, new inhabitance.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Neuerthelesse,
euen those thou sparedst as men, and didst send waspes forerunners
of thine hoste, to destroy them by little and little.<note> Exod. 33. 2. deut.2. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Not
that thou wast vnable to bring the vngodly vnder the hand of the
righteous in battell, or to destroy them at once with cruel
beastes, or with one rough word:</ab>
<ab n="10">But
executing thy iudgements vpon them by little and little, thou
gauest them place of repentance, not being ignorant that they were
a naughtie generation, and that their malice, was bred in them, and
that their cogitation would neuer be changed.</ab>
<ab n="11">For it
was a cursed seed, from the beginning, neither didst thou for feare
of any man giue them pardon for those things wherein they
sinned.<note> Gen.9. 25.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For
who shall say, What hast thou done? or who shall withstand thy
iudgement, or who shall accuse thee for the nations that perish
whom thou hast made? or who shall come to stand against thee, to be
reuenged for the vnrighteous men?<note> Rom.9. 20. , Or, in thy presence. , Or, a reuenger.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For
neither is there any God but thou, that careth for all, to whom
thou mightest shew that thy iudgement is not vnright.<note> 1.Pet. 5.7</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Neither
shall king or tyrant bee able to set his face against thee, for any
whom thou hast punished.</ab>
<ab n="15">For so
much then as thou art righteous thy selfe, thou orderest all things
righteously: thinking it not agreeable with thy power to condemne
him þt hath not deserued to be
punished.<note> Iob 10.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For
thy power is the beginning of righteousnesse, and because thou art
the Lord of all, it maketh thee to be gracious vnto all.</ab>
<ab n="17">For
when men will not beleeue, that thou art of a full power, thou
shewest thy strength, and among them that know it, thou makest
their boldnesse manifest.<note> Or, perfect.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">But
thou, mastering thy power, iudgest with equitie, and orderest vs
with great fauour: for thou mayest vse power when thou
wilt.</ab>
<ab n="19">But by
such workes hast thou taught thy people, that the iust man should
be mercifull, and hast made thy children to be of a good hope, that
thou giuest repentance for sinnes.</ab>
<ab n="20">For if
thou didst punish the enemies of thy children, and the condemned to
death with such deliberation, giuing them time and place, wherby
they might be deliuered from their malice.</ab>
<ab n="21">With
how great circumspection diddest thou iudge thine owne sonnes, vnto
whose fathers thou hast sworne, and made couenants of good
promises?</ab>
<ab n="22">Therefore
whereas thou doest chasten vs, thou scourgest our enemies a
thousand times more, to the intent that when wee iudge, wee should
carefully thinke of thy goodnesse, and when we our selues are
iudged, wee should looke for mercy.</ab>
<ab n="23">Wherefore,
whereas men haue liued dissolutely and vnrighteously, thou hast
tormented them with their owne abominations.<note> Or, abominable idoles.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For
they went astray very farre in the wayes of errour, &amp; held them
for gods (which euen amongst the beasts of their enemies were
despised) being deceiued as children of no
vnderstanding.<note> Chap. 11.13. rom.1. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore
vnto them, as to children without the vse of reason, thou didst
send a iudgement to mocke them.</ab>
<ab n="26">But
they that would not bee refourmed by that correction wherein he
dallied with them, shall feele a iudgement worthy of God.</ab>
<ab n="27">For
looke, for what things they grudged when they were punished, (that
is) for them whom they thought to be gods, [now] being punished in
them; when they saw it, they acknowledged him to be the true God,
whome before they denyed to know: and therefore came extreme
damnation vpon them.</ab>



</div>