<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 What wisedome did for Adam, 4 Noe,
5 Abraham, 6 Lot, and against the fiue cities, 10 for Iacob, 13
Ioseph, 16 Moses, 17 and the Israelites.</head>

<ab n="1">She
preserued the first formed father of the world that was created
alone, and brought him out of his fall,</ab>
<ab n="2">And
gaue him power to rule all things.<note> Gen.2.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But
when the vnrighteous went away from her in his anger, he perished
also in the fury wherwith he murdered his brother.<note> Gen.4.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For
whose cause the earth being drowned with the flood, Wisedome againe
preserued it, &amp; directed the course of the righteous, in a
piece of wood, of small value.<note> Gen.7.21</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Moreouer,
the nations in their wicked conspiracie being confounded, she found
out the righteous, and preserued him blamelesse vnto God, and kept
him strong against his tender compassion towards his
sonne.<note> Gen.11.9 , Or, in.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">When
the vngodly perished, shee deliuered the righteous man, who fled
from the fire which fell downe vpon the fiue cities.<note> Gen. 22. 10. gen.19. 16. , Gre. Pentapolis.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Of
whose wickednesse euen to this day the waste land that smoketh, is
a testimonie, and plants bearing fruite that neuer come to
ripenesse: and a standing pillar of salt is a monument of an
vnbeleeuing soule.</ab>
<ab n="8">For
regarding not wisedome, they gate not only this hurt, that they
knew not the things which were good: but also left behind them to
the world a memoriall of their foolishnes: so that in the things
wherein they offended, they could not so much as be hid.</ab>
<ab n="9">But
Wisedome deliuered from paine those that attended vpon her.</ab>
<ab n="10">When
the righteous fled from his brothers wrath, she guided him in right
paths: shewed him the kingdome of God: and gaue him knowledge of
holy things, made him rich in his trauailes, and multiplied the
fruit of his labours.</ab>
<ab n="11">In the
couetousnesse of such as oppressed him, she stood by him, and made
him rich.</ab>
<ab n="12">She
defended him from his enemies, and kept him safe from those that
lay in wait, and in a sore conflict she gaue him the victory, that
he might knowe that godlinesse is stronger then all.</ab>
<ab n="13">When
the righteous was solde, she forsooke him not, but deliuered him
from sinne: she went downe with him into the pit,<note> Gen.37. 38. &amp; 39.7. acts 7.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And
left him not in bonds till she brought him the scepter of the
kingdom and power against those that oppressed him: as for them
that had accused him, she shewed them to be liers, and gaue them
perpetuall glory.<note> Or, the power of them that ruled ouer him.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">She
deliuered the righteous people, and blamelesse seed from the nation
that oppressed them.<note> Exo.1.10. and 12.42. , Or, holy.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">She
entred into the soule of the seruant of the Lord, and withstood
dreadfull kings in wonders and signes,<note> Exod.5.1</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Rendred
to the righteous a reward of their labours, guided them in a
marueilous way, and was vnto them for a couer by day, and a light
of starres in the night season:<note> Or, flame.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Brought
them through the red sea, and led them thorow much
water.<note> Exod. 14. 21,22. psal. 78.13.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">But
she drowned their enemies, and cast them vp out of the bottome of
the deepe.</ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore
the righteous spoiled the vngodly, &amp; praised thy holy Name, O
Lord, and magnified with one accord thine hand that fought for
them.<note> Exo.15.1</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For
wisedome opened the mouth of the dumbe, and made the tongues of
them that cannot speake, eloquent.</ab>



</div>