<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_17" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVII.</head>
<head>1 Why the Egyptians were punished
with darkenesse. 4 The terrours of that darknes. 12 The terrours of
an ill conscience.</head>

<ab n="1">For
great are thy Iudgements, and cannot be expressed: therefore
vnnourtured soules haue erred.<note> Or, soules that will not be reformed.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For
when vnrighteous men thought to oppresse the holy nation: they
being shut vp in their houses, the prisoners of darkenesse, and
fettered with the bondes of a long night, lay [there] exiled from
the eternall prouidence.<note> Or, vnder their roofes. , Or, fugitiues.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">For
while they supposed to lie hid in their secret sinnes, they were
scattered vnder a darke vaile of forgetfulnesse, being horribly
astonished, and troubled with (strange) apparitions.<note> Or, in. , Or, sights.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For
neither might the corner that helde them keepe them from feare: but
noises (as of waters) falling downe, sounded about them, and sadde
visions appeared vnto them with heauie countenances.</ab>
<ab n="5">No
power of the fire might giue them light: neither could the bright
flames of the starres endure to lighten that horrible
night.</ab>
<ab n="6">Onely
there appeared vnto them a fire kindled of it selfe, very
dreadfull: for being much terrified, they thought the things which
they saw to be worse then the sight they saw not.</ab>
<ab n="7">As for
the illusions of arte Magicke, they were put downe, and their
vaunting in wisedome was reprooued with disgrace.<note> Exo.7.12. and 8.7,19.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">For
they that promised to driue away terrours, and troubles from a
sicke soule, were sicke themselues of feare worthy to be laughed
at.</ab>
<ab n="9">For
though no terrible thing did feare them: yet being skared with
beasts that passed by, and hissing of serpents,</ab>
<ab n="10">They
died for feare, denying that they saw the ayre, which could of no
side be auoided.<note> Or refusing to looke vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For
wickednesse condemned by her owne witnesse, is very timorous, and
being pressed with conscience, alwayes forecasteth grieuous
things.</ab>
<ab n="12">For
feare is nothing else, but a betraying of the succours which reason
offereth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And
the expectation from within being lesse, counteth the ignorance
more then the cause which bringeth the torment.</ab>
<ab n="14">But
they sleeping the same sleepe that night which was indeed
intolerable, and which came vpon them out of the bottomes of
ineuitable hell:<note> Or, wherein they could doe nothing.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Were
partly vexed with monstrous apparitions, and partly fainted, their
heart failing them: for a suddaine feare and not looked for, came
vpon them.</ab>
<ab n="16">So
then, whosoeuer there fell downe, was straitly kept, shut vp in a
prison without yron barres.</ab>
<ab n="17">For
whether hee were husbandman, or shepheard, or a labourer in the
field, he was ouertaken, and endured that necessitie, which could
not be auoided: for they were all bound with one chaine of
darkenesse.<note> Or, desert.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Whether
it were a whistling winde, or a melodious noise of birdes among the
spreading branches, or a pleasing fall of water running
violently:</ab>
<ab n="19">Or a
terrible sound of stones cast downe, or a running that could not be
seene of skipping beasts, or a roaring voice of most sauage wilde
beasts, or a rebounding Eccho from the hollow mountaines: these
things made them to swoone for feare.<note> Or, hideous.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">For
the whole world shined with cleare light, and none were hindered in
their labour.</ab>
<ab n="21">Ouer
them onely was spread an heauie night, an image of that darkenesse
which should afterwards receiue them: but yet were they vnto
themselues more grieuous then the darkenesse.</ab>



</div>