<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 All men haue their beginning and
end alike. 6 He preferred wisedome before all things else. 8 God
gaue him all the knowledge, which he had. 22 The praise of
wisedome.</head>

<ab n="1">I my
selfe also am a mortall man, like to all, and the ofspring of him
that was first made of the earth,</ab>
<ab n="2">And in
my mothers wombe was fashioned to be flesh in the time of tenne
moneths being compacted in blood, of the seed of man, and the
pleasure that came with sleepe.<note> Iob.10. 12.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And when
I was borne, I drew in the common aire, and fell vpon the earth
which is of like nature, and the first voice which I vttered, was
crying as all others doe.</ab>
<ab n="4">I was
nursed in swadling clothes, and that with cares.</ab>
<ab n="5">For
there is no king that had any other beginning of birth.</ab>
<ab n="6">For all
men haue one entrance vnto life, and the like going
out.<note> Iob.1.21. 1.Timo.6.7</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Wherefore
I prayed, and vnderstanding was giuen mee: I called vpon God, and
the spirit of wisedome came to me.</ab>
<ab n="8">I
preferred her before scepters, and thrones, and esteemed riches
nothing in comparison of her.</ab>
<ab n="9">Neither
compared I vnto her any precious stone, because all gold in respect
of her is as a little sand, and siluer shalbe counted as clay
before her.<note> Gre. stone of inestimable price.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">I loued
her aboue health and beautie, and chose to haue her in stead of
light: for the light that commeth from her neuer goeth out.</ab>
<ab n="11">All
good things together came to me with her, and innumerable riches in
her hands.<note> 1.King.3. 13. matt.6. 33.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And I
reioyced in them all, because wisedome goeth before them: and I
knew not that shee was the mother of them.</ab>
<ab n="13">I
learned diligently, and doe communicate her liberally: I doe not
hide her riches.<note> Greeke, without guile. , Gr. without enuie.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For
shee is a treasure vnto men that neuer faileth: which they that
vse, become the friends of God: being commended for the gifts that
come from learning.<note> Or, enter friendship with God.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">God
hath granted me to speake as I would, and to conceiue as is meet
for the things that are giuen mee: because it is hee that leadeth
vnto wisedome, and directeth the wise.<note> Or, God grant. , Or, are to be spoken of.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For in
his hand are both we and our wordes: all wisedome also and
knowledge of workemanship.</ab>
<ab n="17">For hee
hath giuen mee certaine knowledge of the things that are, namely to
know how the world was made, &amp; the operation of the
elements:</ab>
<ab n="18">The
beginning, ending, and midst of the times: the alterations of the
turning of the Sunne, and the change of seasons:</ab>
<ab n="19">The
circuits of yeres, and the positions of starres:</ab>
<ab n="20">The
natures of liuing creatures, and the furies of wilde beasts: the
violence of windes, and the reasonings of men: the diuersities of
plants, and the vertues of rootes:</ab>
<ab n="21">And all
such things as are either secret or manifest: them I know.</ab>
<ab n="22">For
wisedome which is the worker of all things, taught mee: for in her
is an vnderstanding spirit holy, one onely, manifold, subtile,
liuely, cleare, vndefiled, plaine, not subiect to hurt, louing the
thing that is good, quicke, which cānot be letted, ready to do
good:<note> Greeke, onely begotten.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">Kinde
to man, stedfast, sure, free from care, hauing all power,
ouerseeing all things, and going through all vnderstanding, pure,
and most subtile spirits.</ab>
<ab n="24">For
wisedome is more moouing then any motion: she passeth and goeth
through all things by reason of her purenesse.</ab>
<ab n="25">For she
is the breath of the power of God, and a pure influence flowing
from the glory of the Almighty: therefore can no vndefiled thing
fall into her.<note> Or, vapour. , Or, streame.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">For
shee is the brightnesse of the euerlasting light: the vnspotted
mirrour of the power of God, and the Image of his
goodnesse.<note> Hebr.1.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">And
being but one she can doe all things: and remayning in her selfe,
she maketh all things new: and in all ages entring into holy
soules, she maketh them friends of God, &amp; Prophets.<note> Or, createth.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For God
loueth none but him, that dwelleth with wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="29">For she
is more beautiful then the Sunne, and aboue all the order of
starres, being compared with the light, she is found before
it.</ab>
<ab n="30">For
after this commeth night: but vice shall not preuaile against
wisdome.</ab>



</div>