<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_15" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XV.</head>
<head>1 We doe acknowledge the true God. 7
The follie of Idole-makers, 14 and of the enemies of Gods people:
15 because besides the idoles of the Gentiles, 18 they worshipped
vile beasts.</head>

<ab n="1">But
thou O God, art gracious and true: long suffering, and in mercy
ordering all things.</ab>
<ab n="2">For if
we sinne we are thine, knowing thy power: but we will not sinne,
knowing that we are counted thine.</ab>
<ab n="3">For to
know thee is perfect righteousnesse: yea to know thy power is the
roote of immortality.</ab>
<ab n="4">For
neither did the mischieuous inuention of men deceiue vs: nor an
image spotted with diuers colours, the painters fruitlesse
labour.</ab>
<ab n="5">The
sight wherof entiseth fooles to lust after it, and so they desire
the forme of a dead image that hath no breath.<note> Or, turneth a reproch to the foolish</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Both
they that make them, they that desire them, and they that worship
them, are louers of euill things, and are worthy to haue such
things to trust vpon.</ab>
<ab n="7">For the
potter tempering soft earth fashioneth, euery vessell with much
labour for our seruice: yea of the same clay hee maketh both the
vessels that serue for cleane vses: and likewise also all such as
serue to the contrary: but what is the vse of either sort, the
potter himselfe is the iudge.<note> Rom.9.11</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And
employing his labours lewdly, he maketh a vaine God of the same
clay, euen he which a little before was made of earth himselfe, and
within a little while after returneth to the same out of the which
he was taken: when his life which was lent him shall be
demanded.<note> Luke 12. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Notwithstanding
his care is, not that hee shall haue much labour, nor that his life
is short: but striueth to excel goldsmiths, and siluersmiths, and
endeuoureth to doe like the workers in brasse, and counteth it his
glory to make counterfeit things.<note> Or, be sicke or die.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">His
heart is ashes, his hope is more vile then earth, and his life of
lesse value then clay:</ab>
<ab n="11">Forasmuch
as hee knew not his maker, and him that inspired into him an actiue
soule, and breathed in a liuing spirit.</ab>
<ab n="12">But
they counted our life a pastime, &amp; our time here a market for
gaine: for, say they, we must be getting euery way, though it be by
euil meanes.<note> Gre. life.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">For
this man that of earthly matter maketh brickle vessels, and grauen
images, knoweth himselfe to offend aboue all others.<note> Or, so.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And
all the enemies of thy people, that hold them in subiection are
most foolish and are more miserable then very babes.</ab>
<ab n="15">For
they counted all the idoles of the heathen to be gods: which
neither haue the vse of eyes to see, nor noses to draw breath, nor
eares to heare, nor fingers of hands to handle, and as for their
feete they are slow to goe.<note> Or, ayre.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">For
man made them, and he that borrowed his owne spirit fashioned them,
but no man can make a god like vnto himselfe.</ab>
<ab n="17">For
being mortall he worketh a dead thing with wicked hands: for hee
himselfe is better then the things which he worshippeth: whereas he
liued once, but they neuer.</ab>
<ab n="18">Yea
they worshipped those beasts also that are most hatefull: for being
compared together, some are worse then others.</ab>
<ab n="19">Neither
are they beautifull, so much, as to bee desired in respect of
beasts, but they went without the praise of God and his
blessing.</ab>
<ab n="KJV">2015 Copyright King James Bible Online |
..</ab>



</div>