<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 The wicked shal wonder at the
godly, 4 and confesse their errour, 5 and the vanitie of their
liues. 15 God will reward the Iust, 17 and warre against the
wicked.</head>

<ab n="1">Then
shal the righteous man stand in great boldnesse, before the face of
such as haue afflicted him, and made no account of his
labours.</ab>
<ab n="2">When
they see it, they shalbe troubled with terrible feare, &amp; shall
be amazed at the strangenesse of his saluation, so farre beyond all
that they looked for.</ab>
<ab n="3">And they
repenting, and groning for anguish of spirit, shall say within
themselues, This was he whom wee had sometimes in derision, and a
prouerbe of reproch.<note> Or, parable</note></ab>
<ab n="4">We
fooles accounted his life madnes, and his end to be without
honour.<note> Chap. 3.2</note></ab>
<ab n="5">How is
hee numbred among the children of God, and his lot is among the
Saints?</ab>
<ab n="6">Therefore
haue wee erred from the way of trueth, and the light of
righteousnesse hath not shined vnto vs, and the Sunne of
righteousnesse rose not vpon vs.</ab>
<ab n="7">We
wearied ourselues in the way of wickednesse, and destruction: yea,
we haue gone through deserts, where there lay no way: but as for
the way of the Lord, we haue not knowen it.<note> Or, filled our selues, or surfeited.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">What
hath pride profited vs? or what good hath riches with our vaunting
brought vs?</ab>
<ab n="9">All
those things are passed away like a shadow, and as a Poste that
hasted by.<note> 1.Chron. 29. 15. and 2.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And as
a ship that passeth ouer the waues of the water, which when it is
gone by, the trace thereof cannot bee found: neither the path way
of the keele in the waues.</ab>
<ab n="11">Or as
when a bird hath flowen thorow the aire, there is no token of her
way to be found, but the light aire being beaten with the stroke of
her wings, and parted with the violent noise and motion of them, is
passed thorow, and therin afterwards no signe where she went, is to
be found.<note> Pro.30.19 , Or, flyeth.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Or like
as when an arrow is shot at a marke, it parteth the aire, which
immediatly commeth together againe: so that a man cannot know where
it went thorow:</ab>
<ab n="13">Euen so
we in like maner, assoone as we were borne, began to draw to our
end, and had no signe of vertue to shew: but were consumed in our
owne wickednesse.</ab>
<ab n="14">For the
hope of the vngodly is like dust that is blowen away with
þe wind, like a thinne froth that is driuen away
with þe storme: like as the smoke which is
dispersed here and there with a tempest, and passeth away as the
remembrance of a guest that tarieth but a day.<note> Iob 8.9. , Gre thistle downe. , Or, chaffe. , Psal. 2.4. &amp; 103.14. pro.10.25. and 11.7. iam.1.10, 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">But
þe righteous liue for euermore, their reward also
is with the Lord, and the care of them is with the most
High.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therfore
shall they receiue a glorious kingdome, &amp; a beautiful crowne
from the Lords hande: for with his right hand shall he couer them,
and with his arme shall he protect them.<note> Or, palace, vnlesse the word betaken vnproperly as 2. Mac.2.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">He
shall take to him his ielousie for cōplete armour, &amp; make
the creature his weapon for the reuenge of his enemies.</ab>
<ab n="18">He shal
put on righteousnesse as a brestplate, and true iudgement in stead
of an helmet.<note> Esa. 59.17</note></ab>
<ab n="19">He
shall take holinesse for an inuincible shield.<note> Or, equity.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">His
seuere wrath shall he sharpen for a sword, and the world shall
fight with him against the vnwise.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then
shal the right-aiming thunder bolts goe abroad, and from the
cloudes, as from a well-drawen bow, shall they flie to the
marke.</ab>
<ab n="22">And
hailestones full of wrath shal be cast as out of a stonebow, and
the water of the Sea shall rage against them, &amp; the floods
shall cruelly drowne them.</ab>
<ab n="23">Yea a
mightie wind shall stand vp against them, &amp; like a storme shall
blow them away: thus iniquity shal lay wast the whole earth, and
ill dealing shall ouerthrow the thrones of the mightie.</ab>



</div>