<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_16" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-15-16.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-16-17.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVI.</head>
<head>2 God gaue strange meate to his
people, to stirre vp their appetite, and vile beasts to their
enemies to take it from them. 5 Hee stung with his serpents, 12 but
soone healed them by his word onely. 17 The creatures altred their
nature to pleasure Gods people, and to offend their
enemies.</head>

<ab n="1">Therefore
by the like were they punished worthily, and by the multitude of
beasts tormented.<note> Num. 21. 6. chap.11. 15,16.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">In
stead of which punishment, dealing graciously with thine owne
people thou preparedst for them meate of a strange taste: euen
quailes to stirre vp their appetite:<note> Num. 11. 31.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">To the
end that they desiring food might for the ougly sight of the beasts
sent among them, loath euen that which they must needs desire: but
these suffering penury for a short space, might be made partakers
of a strange taste.</ab>
<ab n="4">For it
was requisite, that vpon them excercising tyranny should come
penury which they could not auoyde: but to these it should onely be
shewed how their enemies were tormented.</ab>
<ab n="5">For
when the horrible fiercenesse of beasts came vpon these, and they
perished with the stings of crooked serpents, thy wrath endured not
for euer.<note> Or, thy people. , Num. 21. 6. 1.cor.10. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">But
they were troubled for a smal season that they might be admonished,
hauing a signe of saluation, to put them in remembrance of the
commandement of thy Law.<note> Num. 21. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For hee
that turned himselfe towards it, was not saued by the thing that he
saw: but by thee that art the sauiour of all.</ab>
<ab n="8">And in
this thou madest thine enemies confesse, that it is thou who
deliuerest from all euill:</ab>
<ab n="9">For
them the bitings of grassehoppers and flies killed, neither was
there found any remedy for their life: for they were worthy to bee
punished by such.<note> Exod.8. 24 and 10. 4. reuel.9. 7.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But
thy sonnes, not the very teeth of venemous dragons ouercame: for
thy mercy was euer by them, and healed them.</ab>
<ab n="11">For
they were pricked, that they should remember thy words, and were
quickly saued, that not falling into deep forgetfulnesse, they
might be continually mindefull of thy goodnesse.<note> Hebr. stung. , Or, neuer drawen from.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For it
was neither herbe, nor mollifying plaister that restored them to
health: but thy word, O Lord, which healeth all things.</ab>
<ab n="13">For
thou hast power of life and death: thou leadest to the gates of
hell, and bringest vp againe.<note> Psal. 105. deut.32.39. 1.sam.2, 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">A man
indeed killeth through his malice: and the spirit when it is gone
foorth returneth not; neither the soule receiued vp, commeth
againe.</ab>
<ab n="15">But it
is not possible to escape thine hand.</ab>
<ab n="16">For
the vngodly that denied to know thee, were scourged by the strength
of thine arme: with strange raines, hailes, and showers were they
persecuted, that they could not auoyd, and through fire were they
consumed.<note> Exod.9. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For,
which is most to be wondered at, the fire had more force in the
water that quencheth all things: for the world fighteth for the
righteous.<note> Iud.5.20.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">For
sometimes the flame was mitigated, that it might not burne vp the
beasts that were sent against the vngodly: but themselues might see
and perceiue that they were persecuted with the iudgement of
God.</ab>
<ab n="19">And at
another time it burneth euen in the midst of water, aboue the power
of fire, that it might destroy the fruits of an vniust
land.</ab>
<ab n="20">In
stead whereof thou feddest thine owne people, with Angels food, and
didst send them from heauen bread prepared without their labour,
able to content euery mans delight, and agreeing to euery
taste.<note> Exod. 16. 14. num. 11.7. psal. 78.25. ioh. 6.31.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For
thy sustenance declared thy sweetnesse vnto thy children, and
seruing to the appetite of the eater tempered it selfe to euery
mans liking.<note> Iudg.6.4. , Or, Manna. , Or, was tempered.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">But
snow and yce endured the fire and melted not, that they might know
that fire burning the haile, and sparkling in the raine, did
destroy the fruits of the enemies.<note> Chap.19. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But
this againe did euen forget his owne strength, that the righteous
might be nourished.</ab>
<ab n="24">For
the creature that serueth thee who art the maker, encreaseth his
strength against the vnrighteous for their punishment, and abateth
his strength for the benefit of such as put their trust in
thee.</ab>
<ab n="25">Therefore
euen then was it altered into all fashions, and was obedient to thy
grace that nourisheth all things, according to the desire of them
that had need:<note> Or, things. , Or, of them that prayed.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">That
thy children, O Lord, whom thou louest, might know that it is not
the growing of fruits that nourisheth man: but that it is thy word
which preserueth them that put their trust in thee.<note> Deut.8.3. matth.4.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">For
that which was not destroied of the fire, being warmed with a litle
Sunne beame, soone melted away,</ab>
<ab n="28">That
it might bee knowen, that wee must preuent the Sunne, to giue thee
thanks, and at the day-spring pray vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="29">For
the hope of the vnfaithfull, shal melt away as the Winters
hoarefrost, and shall runne away as vnprofitable water.</ab>



</div>