<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 The godly are happie in their
death, 5 and in their troubles; 10 The wicked are not, nor their
children: 15 But they that are pure, are happie, though they haue
no children: 16 For the adulterer and his seed shall
perish.</head>

<ab n="1">But the
soules of the righteous are in the hand of God, and there shall no
torment touch them.<note> Deut. 33. 3.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">In the
sight of the vnwise they seemed to die: and their departure is
taken for misery,<note> Chap.5.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And
their going from vs to be vtter destruction: but they are in
peace.</ab>
<ab n="4">For
though they bee punished in the sight of men: yet is their hope
full of immortalitie.<note> Rom.8. 24. 1.cor.5. 1. 1.pet.1. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And
hauing bene a little chastised, they shalbe greatly rewarded: for
God proued them, and found them worthy for himselfe.<note> Or, benefited. , Exod. 16. 4. deut.8.2. , Or, meet.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">As gold
in the furnace hath hee tried them, and receiued them as a burnt
offering.</ab>
<ab n="7">And in
the time of their visitation, they shall shine and runne to and
fro, like sparkes among the stubble.<note> Matth.13. 43.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">They
shall iudge the nations, and haue dominion ouer the people, and
their Lord shall raigne for euer.<note> Matt. 19. 28. 1.cor.6. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">They
that put their trust in him, shall vnderstand the trueth: and such
as be faithfull in loue, shall abide with him: for grace &amp;
mercy is to his saints, and he hath care for his elect.<note> Or, and such as be faithfull shall remaine with him in loue.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But the
vngodly shalbe punished according to their owne imaginations, which
haue neglected the righteous, and forsaken the Lord.<note> Mat. 25. 41.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">For who
so despiseth wisedome, and nurture, he is miserable, and their hope
is vaine, their labours vnfruitfull, and their works
vnprofitable.</ab>
<ab n="12">Their
wiues are foolish, and their children wicked.<note> Or, light, or vnchaste.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Their
of-spring is cursed: wherefore blessed is the barren that is
vndefiled, which hath not knowen the sinfull bed: she shall haue
fruit in the visitation of soules.<note> Esai. 56.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">And
blessed is the Eunuch which with his hands hath wrought no
iniquitie: nor imagined wicked things against God: for vnto him
shall be giuen the speciall gift of faith, and an inheritance in
the Temple of the Lord more acceptable to his minde.<note> Esai. 56. 4,5. , Gre. the chosen, or amongst the people.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For
glorious is the fruit of good labours: and the root of wisedom
shall neuer fall away.</ab>
<ab n="16">As for
the children of adulterers, they shall not come to their
perfection, and the seed of an vnrighteous bed shal be rooted
out.<note> Or, be partakers of holy things.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">For
though they liue long, yet shall they bee nothing regarded: and
their last age shall be without honour.</ab>
<ab n="18">Or if
they die quickly, they haue no hope, neither comfort in the day of
triall.<note> Or, bearing</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For
horrible is the end of the vnrighteous generation.</ab>



</div>