<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-3-4.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 The chaste man shall be crowned. 3
Bastard slips shall not thriue. 6 They shall witnesse against their
parents. 7 The iust die yong, and are happie. 19 The miserable ende
of the wicked.</head>

<ab n="1">Better
it is to haue no children, and to haue vertue: for the memoriall
thereof is immortal: because it is knowen with God and with
men.<note> Or, approued.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">When it
is present, men take example at it, and when it is gone they desire
it: it weareth a crown, and triumpheth for euer, hauing gotten the
victorie, striuing for vndefiled rewards.</ab>
<ab n="3">But the
multiplying brood of the vngodly shall not thriue, nor take deepe
rooting from bastard slips, nor lay any fast foundation.</ab>
<ab n="4">For
though they flourish in branches for a time: yet standing not fast,
they shall be shaken with the winde: and through the force of
windes they shall be rooted out.<note> Mat.7.19.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The
vnperfect branches shall bee broken off, their fruit vnprofitable,
not ripe to eate: yea meet for nothing.</ab>
<ab n="6">For
children begotten of vnlawfull beds, are witnesses of wickednes
against their parents in their triall.<note> Gre. sleeps.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But
though the righteous be preuented with death: yet shal he be in
rest.</ab>
<ab n="8">For
honourable age is not that which standeth in length of time, nor
that is measured by number of yeeres.</ab>
<ab n="9">But
wisedome is the gray haire vnto men, &amp; an vnspotted life is old
age.</ab>
<ab n="10">He
pleased God, and was beloued of him: so that liuing amongst
sinners, he was translated.<note> Gen. 5.24 heb. 11.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Yea,
speedily was he taken away, lest that wickednes should alter his
vnderstanding, or deceit beguile his soule.</ab>
<ab n="12">For the
bewitching of naughtines doth obscure things that are honest: and
the wandring of concupiscence, doth vndermine the simple
mind.<note> Gre. peruert.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">He
being made perfect in a short time, fulfilled a long
time.<note> Or, sanctified or consummated.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For his
soule pleased the Lord: therefore hasted he to take him away, from
among the wicked.</ab>
<ab n="15">This
the people saw, and vnderstood it not: neither laid they vp this in
their mindes, That his grace and mercie is with his Saints, and
that he hath respect vnto his chosen.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus
the righteous that is dead, shall condemne the vngodly, which are
liuing, and youth that is soone perfected, the many yeeres and old
age of the vnrighteous.</ab>
<ab n="17">For
they shall see the end of the wise, &amp; shall not vnderstand what
God in his counsell hath decreed of him, and to what end the Lord
hath set him in safetie.</ab>
<ab n="18">They
shal see him and despise him, but God shall laugh them to scorne,
and they shal hereafter be a vile carkeis, and a reproch among the
dead for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="19">For he
shall rend them, and cast them downe headlong, that they shalbe
speechles: and he shal shake them from the foundation: and they
shall bee vtterly laid waste, and be in sorow: and their memoriall
shall perish.</ab>
<ab n="20">And
when they cast vp the accounts of their sinnes, they shall come
with feare: and their owne iniquities shall conuince them to their
face.<note> Or, to the casting vp of the account.</note></ab>



</div>