<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_09" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-9-10.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IX.</head>
<head>1 A prayer vnto God for his wisdome,
6 without which the best man is nothing worth, 13 neither can he
tell how to please God.</head>

<ab n="1">O God of
my fathers, and Lord of mercy, who hast made all things with thy
word,</ab>
<ab n="2">And
ordained man through thy wisedome, that he should haue dominion
ouer the creatures, which thou hast made,<note> Gen.1.28.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And
order the world according to equitie and righteousnesse, and
execute iudgement with an vpright heart:</ab>
<ab n="4">Giue me
wisedome that sitteth by thy Throne, and reiect me not from among
thy children:<note> 1.Kin.3.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For I
thy seruant and sonne of thine handmaide, am a feeble person, and
of a short time, and too young for the vnderstanding of iudgement
and lawes.<note> Psal.116. 16.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">For
though a man be neuer so perfect among the children of men, yet if
thy wisedome be not with him, hee shall be nothing
regarded.</ab>
<ab n="7">Thou
hast chosen me to be a king of thy people, and a Iudge of thy sons
and daughters:<note> 1.Chron. 28.5. 2. chro.1.9.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Thou
hast commaunded me to build a Temple vpon thy holy mount, and an
Altar in the city wherein thou dwellest, a resemblance of the holy
Tabernacle which thou hast prepared from the beginning:</ab>
<ab n="9">And
wisedome was with thee: which knoweth thy workes, and was present
when thou madest the world, and knew what was acceptable in thy
sight, and right in thy Commaundements.<note> Pro. 8.22. ioh.1.2,3, 10.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">O send
her out of thy holy heauens, and from the Throne of thy glory, that
being present shee may labour with mee, that I may know what is
pleasing vnto thee.</ab>
<ab n="11">For she
knoweth and vnderstandeth all things, and shee shall leade me
soberly in my doings, and preserue me in her power.<note> Or, by her power or glory.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So
shall my workes be acceptable, and then shall I iudge thy people
righteously, and be worthy to sit in my fathers seate.</ab>
<ab n="13">For
what man is hee that can know the counsell of God? or who can
thinke what the will of the Lord is?<note> Isai 40.13. rom. 11.34 1.cor.2.16.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For the
thoughts of mortall men are miserable, and our deuices are but
vncertaine.<note> Or, feare full.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">For the
corruptible body presseth downe the soule, and the earthy
tabernacle weigheth downe the minde that museth vpon many
things.</ab>
<ab n="16">And
hardly doe we gesse aright at things that are vpon earth, and with
labour doe wee find the things that are before vs: but the things
that are in heauen, who hath searched out?<note> Gre. at hand.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And thy
counsell who hath knowen, except thou giue wisedome, and send thy
holy spirit from aboue?</ab>
<ab n="18">For so
the wayes of them which liued on the earth were reformed, and men
were taught the things that are pleasing vnto thee, and were saued
through wisedome.</ab>



</div>