<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>2 He is in loue with wisedome: 4 For
he that hath it, hath euery good thing. 21 It cannot be had, but
from God.</head>

<ab n="1">Wisdome
reacheth from one ende to another mightily: and sweetly doeth she
order all things.<note> Or, profitably.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">I loued
her and sought her out, from my youth I dedesired to make her my
spouse, and I was a louer of her beautie.<note> Or, to mary her to my selfe.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">In that
she is conuersant with God, she magnifieth her nobilitie: yea, the
Lord of all things himselfe loued her.</ab>
<ab n="4">For she
is priuy to the mysteries of the knowledge of God, and a louer of
his workes.<note> Or, teacher. , Or, chuser.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">If
riches be a possession to be desired in this life: what is richer
then wisedome that worketh all things?</ab>
<ab n="6">And if
prudence worke; who of all that are, is a more cunning workeman
then she?<note> Exod. 31.48.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And if a
man loue righteousnesse, her labours are vertues: for she teacheth
temperance and prudence: iustice and fortitude, which are such
things as men can haue nothing more profitable in their
life.</ab>
<ab n="8">If a man
desire much experience: she knoweth things of old, and coniectureth
aright what is to come: shee knoweth the subtilties of speaches,
and can expound darke sentences: she foreseeth signes and wonders,
and the euents of seasons and times.</ab>
<ab n="9">Therefore
I purposed to take her to me to liue with mee, knowing that shee
would be a counsellour of good things, and a comfort in cares &amp;
griefe.<note> Gr. will.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For her
sake I shall haue estimation among the multitude, and honour with
the Elders, though I be yong.</ab>
<ab n="11">I shall
be found of a quicke conceit in iudgement, and shall be admired in
the sight of great men.</ab>
<ab n="12">When I
hold my tongue they shal bide my leisure, and when I speake they
shall giue good eare vnto me: if I talke much, they shall lay their
handes vpon their mouth.<note> Iob 29.8, 9,10,11.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Moreouer,
by the meanes of her, I shall obtaine immortalitie, and leaue
behind me an euerlasting memoriall to them that come after
me.</ab>
<ab n="14">I shall
set the people in order, and the nations shalbe subiect vnto
me.<note> Or, gouerne.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Horrible
tyrants shall be afraide when they doe but heare of me, I shall be
found good among the multitude, and valiant in warre.<note> Or, appeare.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">After I
am come into mine house, I will repose my selfe with her: for her
conuersation hath no bitternes, and to liue with her, hath no
sorrow, but mirth and ioy.<note> Or, being entred into mine house.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Now
when I considered these things in my selfe, and pondered them in
mine heart, how that to be allyed vnto wisedome, is
immortalitie,<note> Prou.7.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And
great pleasure it is to haue her friendship, and in the workes of
her hands are infinite riches, and in the exercise of conference
with her, prudence: and in talking with her a good report: I went
about seeking how to take her to me.<note> Or, fame. , Or, marry her.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For I
was a wittie child, and had a good spirit.</ab>
<ab n="20">Yea
rather being good, I came into a body vndefiled.</ab>
<ab n="21">Neuerthelesse
when I perceiued that I could not otherwise obtaine her, except God
gaue her me (and that was a point of wisdome also to know whose
gift she was) I prayed vnto the Lord, and besought him, and with my
whole heart I said:<note> Or, went.</note></ab>



</div>