<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>5 The Egyptians were punished, and
the Israelites reserued in the same thing. 15 They were plagued by
the same things, wherein they sinned. 20 God could haue destroyed
them otherwise, 23 but he is mercifull to all.</head>

<ab n="1">She
prospered their works in the hand of the holy Prophet.</ab>
<ab n="2">They
went thorough the wildernesse that was not inhabited, and pitched
tents in places where there lay no way.<note> Exod. 16.1. exod. 17.10,11.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">They
stood against their enemies, and were auenged of their
aduersaries.</ab>
<ab n="4">When
they were thirsty they called vpon thee, and water was giuen them
out of the flinty rocke, and their thirst was quenched out of the
hard stone.</ab>
<ab n="5">For by
what things their enemies were punished, by the same they in their
neede were benefited.</ab>
<ab n="6">For in
stead of a fountaine of a perpetuall running riuer, troubled with
foule blood,</ab>
<ab n="7">For a
manifest reproofe of that commandement, whereby the infants were
slaine, thou gauest vnto them abundance of water by a meanes which
they hoped not for,</ab>
<ab n="8">Declaring
by that thirst then, how thou hadst punished their
aduersaries.<note> Exod. 7. 20.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For
when they were tryed, albeit but in mercy chastised, they knew how
the vngodly were iudged in wrath and tormented thirsting in another
maner then the Iust.</ab>
<ab n="10">For
these thou didst admonish, and trie as a father: but the other as a
seuere king thou didst condemne and punish.</ab>
<ab n="11">Whether
they were absent, or present, they were vexed alike.</ab>
<ab n="12">For a
double griefe came vpon them, and a groaning for the remembrance of
things past.</ab>
<ab n="13">For
when they heard by their owne punishments the other to be
benefited, they had some feeling of the Lord.<note> Or, perceiued.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">For
whom they reiected with scorne when hee was long before throwen out
at the casting forth of the infants, him in the end, when they saw
what came to passe, they admired.</ab>
<ab n="15">But
for the foolish deuises of their wickednesse, wherewith being
deceiued, they worshipped serpents voyd of reason, and vile beasts:
thou didst send a multitude of vnreasonable beasts vpon them for
vengeance,</ab>
<ab n="16">That
they might knowe that wherewithall a man sinneth, by the same also
shall he be punished.</ab>
<ab n="17">For
thy Almighty hand that made the world of matter without forme,
wanted not meanes to send among them a multitude of Beares, or
fierce Lyons,</ab>
<ab n="18">Or
vnknowen wild beasts full of rage newly created, breathing out
either a fiery vapour, or filthy sents of scattered smoake, or
shooting horrible sparkles out of their eyes:</ab>
<ab n="19">Whereof
not onely the harme might dispatch them at once: but also the
terrible sight vtterly destroy them.</ab>
<ab n="20">Yea
and without these might they haue fallen downe with one blast,
being persecuted of vengeance, and scattered abroad thorough the
breath of thy power, but thou hast ordered all things in measure,
and number, and weight.</ab>
<ab n="21">For
thou canst shew thy great strength at all times when thou wilt, and
who may withstand the power of thine arme?</ab>
<ab n="22">For
the whole world before thee is as a litle graine of the ballance,
yea as a drop of the morning dew that falleth downe vpon the
earth.<note> Or, little waight.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">But
thou hast mercy vpon all: for thou canst doe all things, and
winkest at the sinnes of men: because they should amend.</ab>
<ab n="24">For
thou louest all the things that are, and abhorrest nothing which
thou hast made: for neuer wouldest thou haue made any thing, if
thou hadst hated it.</ab>
<ab n="25">And
how could any thing haue endured if it had not beene thy will? or
beene preserued, if not called by thee?</ab>
<ab n="26">But
thou sparest all: for they are thine, O Lord, thou louer of
soules.</ab>



</div>