<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>4 Why Egypt was punished with
darkenesse, 5 and with the death of their children, 18 They
themselues saw the cause thereof. 20 God also plagued his owne
people. 11 By what meanes that plague was stayed.</head>

<ab n="1">Neuerthelesse,
thy Saints had a very great light, whose voice they hearing and not
seeing their shape, because they also had not suffered the same
things, they counted them happy.<note> Exod. 10. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">But for
that they did not hurt them now, of whom they had beene wronged
before, they thanked them, and besought them pardon, for that they
had beene enemies.</ab>
<ab n="3">In
stead whereof thou gauest them a burning pillar of fire, both to be
a guide of the vnknowen iourney, and an harmelesse Sunne to
entertaine them honourably.<note> Exo.13.21 and 14.24. psal.78.14. &amp; 105.29.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">For
they were worthy to be depriued of light, and imprisoned in
darknesse, who had kept thy sonnes shut vp, by whom the vncorrupt
light of the law was to be giuen vnto the world.<note> Or, incorruptible.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And
when they had determined to slay the babes of the Saints, one child
being cast forth, and saued: to reproue them, thou tookest away the
multitude of their children, and destroyedst them altogether in a
mightie water.<note> Exod. 14. 24,25.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Of that
night were our fathers certified afore, that assuredly knowing vnto
what oathes they had giuen credence, they might afterwards bee of
good cheere.<note> Exod. 11. 4.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">So of
thy people was accepted both the saluation of the righteous, and
destruction of the enemies.</ab>
<ab n="8">For
wherewith thou didst punish our aduersaries, by the same thou didst
glorifie vs whom thou hadst called.</ab>
<ab n="9">For the
righteous children of good men did sacrifice secretly, and with one
consent made a holy lawe, that the Saints should bee alike
partakers of the same good and euill, the fathers now singing out
the songs of praise.<note> Exod. 12. , Or, a couenant of God, or league, see Psal. 50.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">But on
the other side there sounded an ill-according crie of the enemies,
and a lamentable noise was caried abroad for children that were
bewailed.</ab>
<ab n="11">The
master and the seruaunt were punished after one maner, and like as
the king, so suffered the common person.<note> Exo. 11. 5. and 12. 29.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">So
they altogether had innumerable dead with one kind of death,
neither were the liuing sufficient to burie them: for in one moment
the noblest ofspring of them was destroyed.</ab>
<ab n="13">For
whereas they would not beleeue any thing by reason of the
enchantments, vpon the destruction of the first borne, they
acknowledged this people to be the sonnes of God.</ab>
<ab n="14">For
while all things were in quiet silence, and that night was in the
midst of her swift course,</ab>
<ab n="15">Thine
almighty word leapt downe from heauen, out of thy royall throne, as
a fierce man of warre into the midst of a land of
destruction,</ab>
<ab n="16">And
brought thine vnfained commandement as a sharpe sword, and standing
vp filled all things with death, and it touched the heauen, but it
stood vpon the earth.</ab>
<ab n="17">Then
suddenly visions of horrible dreames troubled them sore, and
terrours came vpon them vnlooked for.<note> Or, imaginations.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And
one throwen here, another there halfe dead, shewed the cause of his
death.</ab>
<ab n="19">For
the dreames that troubled them, did foreshew this, lest they should
perish, and not know why they were afflicted.</ab>
<ab n="20">Yea,
the tasting of death touched the righteous also, and there was a
destruction of the multitude in the wildernes: but the wrath
endured not long.<note> Num. 16. 46.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">For
then the blamelesse man made haste, and stood foorth to defend
them, and bringing the shield of his proper ministerie, euen prayer
and the propitiation of incense, set himselfe against the wrath,
and so brought the calamity to an end, declaring that hee was thy
seruant.</ab>
<ab n="22">So hee
ouercame the destroyer, not with strength of body, nor force of
armes, but with a word subdued he him that punished, alleaging the
oathes and couenants made with the fathers.</ab>
<ab n="23">For
when the dead were now fallen downe by heaps one vpon another,
standing betweene, he staied the wrath, and parted the way to the
liuing.<note> Or, cut off.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">For in
the long garment was the whole world, &amp; in the foure rowes of
the stones was the glory of the fathers grauen, and thy maiestie
vpon the diademe of his head.<note> Exo.28.6. and 11.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="25">Vnto
these the destroyer gaue place, and was afraid of them: for it was
enough that they onely tasted of the wrath.</ab>



</div>