<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-4-6.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-6-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 Kings must giue eare. 3 They haue
their power from God, 5 Who will not spare them. 12 Wisedome is
soone found. 21 Princes must seeke for it: 24 For a wise Prince is
the stay of his people.</head>

<ab n="1">Heare
therefore, O yee kings, and vnderstand, learne yee that be iudges
of the ends of the earth.</ab>
<ab n="2">Giue
eare you that rule the people, and glory in the multitude of
nations.</ab>
<ab n="3">For
power is giuen you of the Lord, &amp; soueraigntie from the
Highest, who shall try your workes; and search out your
counsels.<note> Rom.13. 1,2.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Because
being Ministers of his kingdome, you haue not iudged aright, nor
kept the law, nor walked after the counsell of God,</ab>
<ab n="5">Horribly
and speedily shall he come vpon you: for a sharpe iudgement shall
be to them that be in high places.</ab>
<ab n="6">For
mercy will soone pardon the meanest: but mighty men shall be
mightily tormented.</ab>
<ab n="7">For he
which is Lord ouer all, shall feare no mans person: neither shall
he stand in awe of any mans greatnesse: for he hath made the small
and great, and careth for all alike.<note> 2.Chro. 19.17. deut. 10.17. iob. 34. 19. ecclesi. 35. 12. 16. act. 10.24. rom. 2.11. gal. 2. 6. ephe 6.9 col.3.25. 1.pet.1.17.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">But a
sore triall shall come vpon the mighty.</ab>
<ab n="9">Unto you
therefore, O kings, doe I speake, that yee may learne wisedome, and
not fall away.</ab>
<ab n="10">For
they that keepe holinesse holily, shall be iudged holy: and they
that haue learned such things, shall find what to
answere.<note> Or, iustified. , Or, a defence.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Wherefore
set your affection vpon my words, desire them, and yee shall be
instructed.</ab>
<ab n="12">Wisedome
is glorious and neuer fadeth away: yea she is easily seene of them
that loue her, and found of such as seeke her.</ab>
<ab n="13">She
preuenteth them that desire her, in making herselfe first knowen
vnto them.</ab>
<ab n="14">Whoso
seeketh her earely, shall haue no great trauaile: for he shall find
her sitting at his doores.</ab>
<ab n="15">To
thinke therefore vpon her is perfection of wisedome: and who so
watcheth for her, shall quickly be without care.</ab>
<ab n="16">For she
goeth about seeking such as are worthy of her, sheweth herselfe
fauourably vnto them in the wayes, and meeteth them in euery
thought.</ab>
<ab n="17">For the
very true beginning of her, is the desire of discipline, and the
care of discipline is loue:<note> Or, nurture</note></ab>
<ab n="18">And
loue is the keeping of her lawes; and the giuing heed vnto her
lawes, is the assurance of incorruption.</ab>
<ab n="19">And
incorruption maketh vs neere vnto God.</ab>
<ab n="20">Therefore
the desire of wisedome bringeth to a kingdome.</ab>
<ab n="21">If your
delight be then in thrones and scepters, O ye kings of the people,
honour wisedome that yee may raigne for euermore.</ab>
<ab n="22">As for
wisedome what she is, and how she came vp, I will tell you, and
will not hide mysteries from you: but will seeke her out from the
beginning of her natiuity, &amp; bring the knowledge of her into
light, and will not passe ouer the trueth.</ab>
<ab n="23">Neither
will I goe with consuming enuy: for such a man shall haue no
fellowship with wisedome.</ab>
<ab n="24">But the
multitude of the wise is the welfare of the world: and a wise king
is the vpholding of the people.</ab>
<ab n="25">Receiue
therefore instruction thorough my words, and it shall doe you
good.</ab>



</div>