<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-14-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 Though men doe not pray to their
shippes, 5 Yet are they saued rather by them then by their Idoles.
8 Idoles are accursed, and so are the makers of them. 14 The
beginning of Idolatrie, 23 And the effects thereof. 30 God wil
punish them that sweare falsely by their Idoles.</head>

<ab n="1">Againe,
one preparing himselfe to saile, and about to passe through the
raging waues, calleth vpon a piece of wood more rotten then the
vesell that carieth him.<note> Or, ship.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For
verely desire of gaine deuised that, and the workeman built it by
his skill:<note> Or, vessell or ship.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">But thy
prouidence, O Father, gouerneth it: for thou hast made a way in the
Sea, and a safe path in the waues:<note> Exod. 14. 22.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Shewing
that thou canst saue from all danger: yea though a man went to Sea
without arte.</ab>
<ab n="5">Neuerthelesse
thou wouldest not that the works of thy wisedome should be idle,
and therefore doe men commit their liues to a small piece of wood,
and passing the rough sea in a weake vessell, are saued.</ab>
<ab n="6">For in
the old time also when the proud gyants perished, the hope of the
world gouerned by thy hand, escaped in a weake vessell, and left to
all ages a seed of generation.<note> Gen.6.4. and 7.10.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">For
blessed is the wood, whereby righteousnesse commeth.</ab>
<ab n="8">But
that which is made with hands, is cursed, aswell it, as hee that
made it: he, because he made it, and it, because being corruptible
it was called God.<note> Psal.115. 8. baruc.6.3</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For the
vngodly and his vngodlines are both alike hatefull vnto
God.<note> Psal.5.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">For
that which is made, shall bee punished together with him that made
it.</ab>
<ab n="11">Therfore
euen vpon the idoles of the Gentiles shall there be a visitation:
because in the creature of God they are become an abomination and
stumbling blocks to the soules of men, and a snare to the feet of
the vnwise.<note> Or, to or by. , Ier.10.8. abac.2. 18. , Gre. scandales. , Or, trap.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">For
the deuising of idoles was the beginning of spiritual fornication,
and the inuention of them the corruption of life.</ab>
<ab n="13">For
neither were they from the beginning, neither shall they be for
euer.</ab>
<ab n="14">For by
the vaine glory of men they entred into the world, and therefore
shall they come shortly to an end.</ab>
<ab n="15">For a
father afflicted with vntimely mourning, when he hath made an image
of his childe soone taken away, now honoured him as a god, which
was then a dead man, and deliuered to those that were vnder him,
ceremonies and sacrifices.</ab>
<ab n="16">Thus
in processe of time an vngodly custome growen strong, was kept as a
law, and grauen images were worshipped by the commandements of
kings,<note> Gre. in time , Or, tyrants</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Whom
men could not honour in presence, because they dwelt farre off,
they tooke the counterfeit of his visage from farre, and made an
expresse image of a king whom they honoured, to the end that by
this their forwardnes, they might flatter him that was absent, as
if he were present.<note> Or, in sight</note></ab>
<ab n="18">Also
the singular diligence of the artificer did helpe to set forward
the ignorant to more superstition.</ab>
<ab n="19">For he
peraduenture willing to please one in authoritie, forced all his
skill to make the resemblance of the best fashion.<note> Gre. to the better.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">And so
the multitude allured by the grace of the worke, tooke him now for
a god, which a litle before was but honoured as a man.</ab>
<ab n="21">And
this was an occasion to deceiue the world: for men seruing either
calamitie or tyrannie, did ascribe vnto stones, and stockes, the
incommunicable Name.<note> Of God.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Moreouer
this was not enough for them, that they erred in the knowledge of
God, but whereas they liued in the great warre of ignorance, those
so great plagues called they peace.</ab>
<ab n="23">For
whilest they slew their children in sacrifices, or vsed secret
ceremonies, or made reuellings of strange rites<note> Deut. 18.10. ier.7.9. and 19.4.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">They
kept neither liues nor mariages any longer vndefiled: but either
one slew another traiterously, or grieued him by adulterie:</ab>
<ab n="25">So
that there reigned in all men without exception, blood,
manslaughter, theft, and dissimulation, corruption,
vnfaithfulnesse, tumults, periurie,<note> Or, confusedly.</note></ab>
<ab n="26">Disquieting
of good men, forgetfulnesse of good turnes, defiling of soules,
changing of kinde, disorder in mariages, adulterie, and shameles
vncleannesse.<note> Or, seke.</note></ab>
<ab n="27">For
the worshipping of idoles not to be named, is the beginning, the
cause, and the end of all euill.<note> Gre. namelesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="28">For
either they are mad when they be merry, or prophesie lies, or liue
vniustly, or else lightly forsweare themselues.</ab>
<ab n="29">For
insomuch as their trust is in idoles which haue no life, though
they sweare falsly, yet they looke not to bee hurt.</ab>
<ab n="30">Howbeit
for both causes shal they be iustly punished: both because they
thought not well of God, giuing heed vnto idols, and also vniustly
swore in deceit, despising holinesse.<note> Or, deuoted.</note></ab>
<ab n="31">For it
is not the power of them by whom they sweare: but it is the iust
vengeance of sinners, that punisheth alwayes the offence of the
vngodly.</ab>



</div>