<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_18" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-17-18.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Genesis-Chapter-18-19.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XVIII.</head>
<head>1 Abraham entertaineth three Angels.
9 Sarah is reproued for laughing at the strange promise. 17 The
destruction of Sodome is reuealed to Abraham. 23 Abraham maketh
intercession for the men thereof.</head>

<ab n="1">And the LORD
appeared vnto him, in the plaines of Mamre: and he sate in the tent
doore, in the heat of the day.<note> Hebr.13. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And he lift vp
his eyes and looked, and loe, three men stood by him: and when he
saw them, hee ranne to meete them from the tent doore, and bowed
himselfe toward the ground,</ab>
<ab n="3">And said, My
Lord, If now I haue found fauour in thy sight, passe not away, I
pray thee, frō thy seruant:</ab>
<ab n="4">Let a little
water, I pray you, be fetched, and wash your feete, and rest your
selues vnder the tree:</ab>
<ab n="5">And I will fetch
a morsell of bread; and comfort ye your hearts, after that you
shall passe on: for therefore are you come to your seruant. And
they said; So doe, as thou hast said.<note> Hebr. stay. , Hebr. you haue passed.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And Abraham
hastened into the tent, vnto Sarah, &amp; said; Make ready quickly
three measures of fine meale, knead it, and make cakes vpon the
hearth.<note> Hebr. Hasten.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And Abraham ranne
vnto the heard, and fetcht a calfe, tender and good, and gaue it
vnto a yong man: and he hasted to dresse it.</ab>
<ab n="8">And he tooke
butter, and milke, and the calfe which he had dressed, and set it
before them; and he stood by them vnder the tree: and they did
eate.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And they
said vnto him, Where is Sarah thy wife? And he said, Behold, in the
tent.</ab>
<ab n="10">And he said, I
will certainly returne vnto thee according to the time of life; and
loe, Sarah thy wife shall haue a sonne. And Sarah heard it in the
tent doore, which was behind him.<note> Chap. 17. 19. and 21. 2.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">Now Abraham and
Sarah were old, and well stricken in age: and it ceased to be with
Sarah after the maner of women.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore Sarah
laughed within her selfe, saying, After I am waxed old, shall I
haue pleasure, my lord being old also?<note> 1.Pet.3. 6.</note></ab>

<fw>Abraham prayeth for the
Sodomites.</fw>
<ab n="13">And the LORD
said vnto Abraham, Wherefore did Sarah laugh, saying; Shall I of a
surety beare a childe, which am old?</ab>
<ab n="14">Is any thing too
hard for the LORD? At the time appointed will I returne vnto thee,
according to the time of life, and Sarah shall haue a
sonne.</ab>
<ab n="15">Then Sarah
denied, saying, I laughed not: for she was afraid. And he said,
Nay, but thou diddest laugh.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And the
men rose vp from thence, and looked toward Sodome: and Abraham went
with them, to bring them on the way.</ab>
<ab n="17">And the LORD
said, Shall I hide from Abraham that thing which I doe;</ab>
<ab n="18">Seeing that
Abraham shall surely become a great and mighty nation, and all the
nations of the earth shall be blessed in him?<note> Chap. 12. 3. and 22. 18. acts. 3. 25. galat. 3.8.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">For I know him,
that hee will command his children, and his household after him,
and they shall keepe the way of the LORD, to doe iustice and
iudgement, that the LORD may bring vpon Abraham, that which hee
hath spoken of him.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the LORD
said, Because the cry of Sodome and Gomorrah is great, and because
their sinne is very grieuous:</ab>
<ab n="21">I will goe downe
now, and see whether they haue done altogether according to the cry
of it, which is come vnto me: and if not, I will know.</ab>
<ab n="22">And the men
turned their faces from thence, and went toward Sodome: but Abraham
stood yet before the LORD.</ab>
<ab n="23">¶ And
Abraham drew neere, and said, Wilt thou also destroy the righteous
with the wicked?</ab>
<ab n="24">Peraduenture
there be fifty righteous within the citie; wilt thou also destroy,
and not spare the place for the fiftie righteous, that are
therein?</ab>
<ab n="25">That be farre
from thee, to do after this maner, to slay the righteous with the
wicked, and that the righteous should be as the wicked, that be
farre from thee: Shall not the Iudge of all the earth doe
right?</ab>
<ab n="26">And the LORD
said, If I find in Sodom fiftie righteous, within the citie, then I
will spare all the place for their sakes.</ab>

<fw>Abraham prayeth for the
Sodomites.</fw>
<ab n="27">And Abraham
answered, and said, Behold now, I haue taken vpon me to speake vnto
the LORD, which am but dust and ashes.</ab>
<ab n="28">Peraduenture
there shall lacke fiue of the fiftie righteous: wilt thou destroy
all the citie for lacke of fiue? And he said, If I find there
fourtie and fiue, I will not destroy it.</ab>
<ab n="29">And hee spake
vnto him yet againe, and said, Peraduenture there shall be fourtie
found there: and he said, I will not doe it for fourties
sake.</ab>
<ab n="30">And he said vnto
him, Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speake: Peraduenture
there shall thirtie bee found there. And he said, I will not doe
it, if I find thirtie there.</ab>
<ab n="31">And he said,
Behold now, I haue taken vpon mee to speake vnto the Lord:
Peraduenture there shall bee twenty found there. And he said, I
will not destroy it for twenties sake.</ab>
<ab n="32">And hee saide,
Oh let not the Lord be angry, and I will speake yet but this once:
Peraduenture ten shall be found there. And he said, I will not
destroy it for tennes sake.</ab>
<ab n="33">And the LORD
went his way, assoone as hee had left communing with Abraham: and
Abraham returned vnto his place.</ab>



</div>