<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_02" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. II.</head>
<head>1 The wicked thinke this life short,
5 and of no other after this. 6 Therefore they will take their
pleasure in this, 10 and conspire against the iust. 21 What that is
which doth blind them.</head>

<ab n="1">For the
vngodly said, reasoning with themselues, but not aright: Our life
is short and tedious, and in the death of a man there is no
remedie: neither was there any man knowen to haue returned from the
graue.<note> Iob.7.1. , Math.22. 23. 1.cor.15 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For wee
are borne at all aduenture: &amp; we shalbe heereafter as though we
had neuer bene: for the breath in our nostrils is as smoke, and a
litle sparke in the mouing of our heart.</ab>
<ab n="3">Which
being extinguished, our body shall be turned into ashes, and our
spirit shall vanish as the soft aire:<note> Or, moist.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">And our
name shalbe forgotten in time, and no man shall haue our works in
remembrance, and our life shall passe away as the trace of a cloud:
and shall be dispersed as a mist that is driuen away with the
beames of the Sunne, and ouercome with the heat
thereof.<note> Or, oppressed.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">For our
time is a very shadow that passeth away: and after our end there is
no returning: for it is fast sealed, so that no man commeth
againe.<note> 1.Chr.29. 15. , Or, he.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">Come on
therefore, let vs enioy the good things that are present: and let
vs speedily vse the creatures like as in youth.<note> Isa.22. 13. and 56. 12. , Or, earnestly. , 1.Cor.15. 32.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Let vs
fill our selues with costly wine, and ointments: and let no flower
of the Spring passe by vs.</ab>
<ab n="8">Let vs
crowne our selues with Rose buds, before they be withered.</ab>
<ab n="9">Let none
of vs goe without his part of our voluptuousnesse: let vs leaue
tokens of our ioyfulnesse in euery place: for this is our portion,
and our lot is this.<note> Or, iolitie.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">Let vs
oppresse the poore righteous man, let vs not spare the widow, nor
reuerence the ancient gray haires of the aged.</ab>
<ab n="11">Let our
strength bee the Lawe of iustice: for that which is feeble is found
to be nothing worth.</ab>
<ab n="12">Therefore
let vs lye in wait for the righteous: because he is not for our
turne, and he is cleane contrary to our doings: he vpbraideth vs
with our offending the Law, and obiecteth to our infamy the
transgressings of our education.</ab>
<ab n="13">Hee
professeth to haue the knowledge of God: and hee calleth himselfe
the childe of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">Hee was
made to reprooue our thoughts.<note> Iohn 7.7. ephes. 5. 13,14.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">Hee is
grieuous vnto vs euen to beholde: for his life is not like other
mens, his waies are of another fashion.<note> Isai.53.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">We are
esteemed of him as counterfeits: he abstaineth from our wayes as
from filthinesse: he pronounceth the end of the iust to be blessed,
and maketh his boast that God is his father.<note> Or, false coine.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Let vs
see if his wordes be true: and let vs proue what shall happen in
the end of him.</ab>
<ab n="18">For if
the iust man be the sonne of God, he will helpe him, and deliuer
him from the hand of his enemies.<note> Psal.22. 8, 9. matth. 27.43.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Let vs
examine him with despitefulnesse and torrture, that we may know his
meekenesse, and prooue his patience.<note> Iere.11. 19.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Let vs
condemne him with a shamefull death: for by his owne saying, he
shall be respected.</ab>
<ab n="21">Such
things they did imagine, and were deceiued: for their owne
wickednesse hath blinded them.</ab>
<ab n="22">As for
the mysteries of God, they knew them not: neither hoped they for
the wages of righteousnesse: nor discerned a reward for blamelesse
soules.<note> Greeke, preferred or esteemed the reward.</note></ab>
<ab n="23">For God
created man to bee immortall, and made him to be an image of his
owne eternitie.<note> Gen.1.26. 27.and 5.1. eccle.17.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="24">Neuerthelesse
through enuie of the deuill came death into the world: and they
that doe holde of his side doe finde it.<note> Gen.3. 12.</note></ab>



</div>