<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CWisedom_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Wisdom-of-Solomon-Chapter-13-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 They were not excused that
worshipped any of Gods workes: 10 But most wretched are they that
worship the works of mens hands.</head>

<ab n="1">Surely
vaine are all men by nature, who are ignorant of God, and could not
out of the good things that are seene, know him that is: neither by
considering the workes, did they acknowledge the
worke-master;</ab>
<ab n="2">But
deemed either fire, or wind, or the swift aire, or the circle of
the stars, or the violent water, or the lights of heauen to be the
gods which gouerne the world:<note> Rom. 1.9. deut. 4.19. and 17.3.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">With
whose beautie, if they being delighted, tooke them to be gods: let
them know how much better the Lord of them is; for the first Author
of beautie hath created them.</ab>
<ab n="4">But if
they were astonished at their power and vertue, let them vnderstand
by them, how much mightier he is that made them.</ab>
<ab n="5">For by
the greatnesse and beautie of the creatures, proportionably the
Maker of them is seene.</ab>
<ab n="6">But yet
for this they are the lesse to bee blamed: for they peraduenture
erre seeking God, and desirous to finde him.</ab>
<ab n="7">For
being conuersant in his workes, they search him diligently, and
beleeue their sight: because the things are beautifull that are
seene.<note> Rom. 1.21 , Or, seeke.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Howbeit,
neither are they to bee pardoned.</ab>
<ab n="9">For if
they were able to know so much, that they could aime at the world;
how did they not sooner finde out the Lord thereof?</ab>
<ab n="10">But
miserable are they, and in dead things is their hope, who called
them gods which are the workes of mens hands, golde and siluer, to
shewe arte in, and resemblances of beasts, or a stone good for
nothing, the worke of an ancient hand.</ab>
<ab n="11">Now a
carpenter that felleth timber, after hee hath sawen downe a tree
meet for the purpose, and taken off all the barke skilfully round
about, and hath wrought it handsomely, &amp; made a vessell thereof
fit for the seruice of mans life:<note> Isai 44.13. , Or, timberwright.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And
after spending the refuse of his worke to dresse his meat, hath
filled himselfe:<note> Or, chips.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And
taking the very refuse among those which serued to no vse (being a
crooked piece of wood, and ful of knots) hath carued it diligently
when hee had nothing else to doe, and formed it by the skill of his
vnderstanding, and fashioned it to the image of a man:</ab>
<ab n="14">Or
made it like some vile beast, laying it ouer with vermilion, and
with paint, colouring it red, and couering euery spot
therein:</ab>
<ab n="15">And
when he had made a conuenient roume for it, set it in a wall, and
made it fast with yron:</ab>
<ab n="16">For he
prouided for it, that it might not fall: knowing that it was vnable
to helpe it selfe, (for it is an image and hath neede of
helpe:)</ab>
<ab n="17">Then
maketh hee prayer for his goods, for his wife and children, and is
not ashamed to speake to that which hath no life.</ab>
<ab n="18">For
health, hee calleth vpon that which is weake: for life, prayeth to
that which is dead: for aide, humbly beseecheth that which hath
least meanes to helpe: and for a good iourney, hee asketh of that
which cannot set a foot forward:<note> Gr. that hath no experience at all.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">And
for gaining and getting, and for good successe of his hands, asketh
abilitie to doe, of him that is most vnable to doe any
thing.</ab>



</div>