<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_06" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. VI.</head>
<head>1 The vision of the foure charets. 9
By the Crownes of Ioshua, is shewed the Temple and Kingdome of
Christ the Branch.</head>

<ab n="1">And I turned,
and lift vp mine eyes, and looked, and beholde, there came foure
charets out from betweene two mountaines, and the mountaines were
mountaines of brasse.</ab>
<ab n="2">In the first
charet were red horses, and in the second charet, blacke
horses.</ab>
<ab n="3">And in the third
charet white horses, and in the fourth charet grisled and bay
horses.<note> Or, strong.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Then I answered,
and said vnto the Angel that talked with mee, What are these, my
Lord ?</ab>
<ab n="5">And the Angel
answered and said vnto me, These are the foure spirits of the
heauens, which go forth from standing before the Lord of all the
earth.<note> Or, winds.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">The blacke
horses which are therin, goe forth into the North countrey, and the
white goe forth after them, and the grisled goe forth toward the
South countrey.</ab>
<ab n="7">And the baye
went foorth, and sought to goe, that they might walke to and fro
through the earth: and he said, Get ye hence, walke to and fro
through the earth. So they walked to and fro through the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="8">Then cried he
vpon me, and spake vnto me, saying, Behold, these that goe toward
the North countrey, haue quieted my spirit, in the North
countrey.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ And the
word of the Lord came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="10">Take of them of
the captiuitie, euen of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Iedaiah, which
are come from Babylon, and come thou the same day, and go into the
house of Iosiah the son of Zephaniah.</ab>

<fw>The Branch.</fw>
<ab n="11">Then take
siluer, and golde, and make crownes, and set them vpon the head of
Ioshua the sonne of Iosedech, the high priest.</ab>
<ab n="12">And speake vnto
him, saying, Thus speaketh the Lord of hostes, saying, Behold, the
man whose name is the Branch, and he shall growe vp out of his
place, and he shall build the Temple of the Lord:<note> Chap.3.4 , Or, branch vp from vnder him.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Euen he shall
build the temple of the Lord, and he shal beare the glory, and
shall sit and rule vpon his throne, and he shall be a priest vpon
his throne, and the counsell of peace shall bee betweene them
both.</ab>
<ab n="14">And the crownes
shall bee to Helem, and to Tobijah, and to Iedaiah, and to Hen the
sonne of Zephaniah for a memoriall, in the Temple of the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="15">And they that
are farre off, shall come and build in the Temple of the Lord, and
ye shall knowe that the Lord of hosts hath sent me vnto you. And
this shall come to passe, if ye will diligently obey the voyce of
the Lord your God.</ab>



</div>