<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 Under the type of Ioshua, the
restauration of the Church. 18 Christ the Branch is
promised.</head>

<ab n="1">And he shewed me
Ioshua the high Priest, standing before the Angel of the Lord, and
Satan standing at his right hand to resist him.<note> That is, an aduersarie. , Heb. to be his aduersarie.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">And the Lord
said vnto Satan; The Lord rebuke thee, O Satan, euen the Lord that
hath chosen Ierusalem rebuke thee. Is not this a brand pluckt out
of the fire?<note> Iude 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Now Ioshua was
clothed with filthie garments, and stood before the Angel.</ab>
<ab n="4">And he answered,
and spake vnto those that stood before him, saying, Take away the
filthie garments from him. And vnto him he said, Behold, I haue
caused thine iniquity to passe from thee, and I wil clothe thee
with change of raiment.</ab>
<ab n="5">And I said, Let
them set a faire mitre vpon his head. So they set a faire mitre
vpon his head, and clothed him with garments, and the Angel of the
Lord stood by.</ab>
<ab n="6">And the Angel of
the Lord protested vnto Ioshua, saying;</ab>
<ab n="7">Thus sayth the
Lord of hosts, If thou wilt walke in my wayes, and if thou wilt
keepe my charge, then thou shalt also iudge my House, and shalt
also keepe my Courts, and I will giue thee places to walke among
these that stand by.<note> Or, ordinance. , Heb. walks.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">Heare now, O
Ioshua the high Priest, thou and thy fellowes that sit before thee:
for they are men wondred at: for behold, I will bring foorth my
seruant the Branch.<note> Heb. men of wonder. , Isai 11.1. iere.23.5. and 33.15. chap. 6.12. luke 1.78.</note></ab>

<fw>Golden candlesticke.</fw>
<ab n="9">For behold the
stone that I haue layd before Ioshua: vpon one stone shall be seuen
eyes, behold, I will engraue the grauing thereof, saith the Lord of
hostes, and I will remoue the iniquitie of that land in one
day.</ab>
<ab n="10">In that day,
saith the Lord of hostes, shal ye call euery man his neighbour
vnder the vine and vnder the figge tree.</ab>



</div>