<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_11" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-9-11.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-11-12.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. XI.</head>
<head>1 The destruction of Ierusalem. 3
The elect being cared for, the rest are reiected. 10 The staues of
beauty and bands broken by the reiection of Christ. 15 The Type and
curse of a foolish Shepheard.</head>

<ab n="1">Open thy
doores, O Lebanon, that the fire may deuoure thy cedars.</ab>
<ab n="2">Howle firre
tree, for the cedar is fallen; because all the mighty are spoiled;
howle O yee okes of Bashan, for the forrest of the vintage is come
downe.<note> Or, gallants. , Or, the defenced forrest.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">¶ There is
a voyce of the howling of the shepheards; for their glory is
spoiled: a voyce of the roaring of young lyons; for the pride of
Iordan is spoiled.</ab>
<ab n="4">Thus saith the
Lord my God; Feede the flocke of the slaughter;</ab>
<ab n="5">Whose
possessours slay them, and hold themselues not guiltie: and they
that sell thē say, Blessed be the Lord; for I am rich: and
their owne shepheards pitie them not.</ab>
<ab n="6">For I will no
more pitie the inhabitants of the land, saith the Lord: but loe, I
will deliuer the men euery one into his neighbours hand, and into
the hand of his King, and they shall smite the land, and out of
their hand I will not deliuer them.<note> Heb. make to be found.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">And I will
feede the flocke of slaughter, euen you, O poore of the flock: and
I tooke vnto me two staues; the one I called Beautie, and the other
I called Bandes, and I fed the flocke.<note> Or, verily the poore. , Or, binders.</note></ab>

<fw>Two staues.</fw>
<ab n="8">Three
shepheards also I cut off in one moneth, and my soule loathed them,
and their soule also abhorred mee.<note> Hebr. was straitened for them.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then said I, I
will not feede you: that that dieth, let it die: and that that is
to be cut off, let it be cut off, and let the rest eate, euery one
the flesh of another.<note> Ier.15.2. , Hebr. of his fellow or neighbour.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">¶ And I
tooke my staffe, euen Beautie, and cut it asunder, that I might
breake my couenant which I had made with all the people.</ab>
<ab n="11">And it was
broken in that day: and so the poore of the flocke that waited vpon
me, knew that it was the word of the Lord.<note> Or, the poore of the flocke, &amp;c. certainly knewe.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">And I said
vnto them, If yee thinke good, giue me my price: and if not,
forbeare: so they weighed for my price thirtie pieces of
siluer.<note> Hebr. if it be good in your eyes. , Matth.26. 15.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord
said vnto mee, Cast it vnto the potter: a goodly price, that I was
prised at of them. And I tooke the thirtie pieces of siluer, and
cast them to the potter in the house of the Lord.<note> Matth.27. 9.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">Then I cut
asunder mine other staffe, euen Bands, that I might break the
brotherhood betweene Iudah and Israel.<note> Or, binders.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">¶ And the
Lord said vnto me, Take vnto thee yet the instruments of a foolish
shepheard.</ab>
<ab n="16">For loe, I wil
raise vp a shepherd in the land, which shall not visit those that
bee cut off, neither shall seeke the yong one, nor heale that that
is broken, nor feed that that standeth still: but he shal eate the
flesh of the fat, and teare their clawes in pieces.<note> Or, hidden. , Or, beare.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">Woe to the
idoll shepheard that leaueth the flocke: the sword shall be vpon
his arme, and vpon his right eye: his arme shall be cleane dryed
vp, and his right eye shall be vtterly darkened.<note> Iere.23.1. ezek.34.2. iohn 10.12.</note></ab>



</div>