<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_14" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-14-14-Malachi.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIV.</head>
<head>1 The destroyers of Ierusalem,
destroied. 4 The comming of Christ, and the graces of his kingdome.
12 The plague of Ierusalems enemies. 16 The remnant shal turne to
the Lord, 20 And their spoiles shalbe holy.</head>

<ab n="1">Beholde, the
day of the Lord commeth, and thy spoile shall be diuided in the
midst of thee.</ab>
<ab n="2">For I wil
gather all nations against Ierusalem to battell, and the citie
shall be taken, &amp; the houses rifeled, and the women rauished,
and halfe of the citie shall goe forth into captiuitie, and the
residue of the people shal not be cut off from the citie.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then shall the
Lord goe forth and fight against those nations, as when he fought
in the day of battel.</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ And his
feet shall stand in that day vpon the mount of Oliues, which is
before Ierusalem on the East, and the mount of Oliues shall cleaue
in the midst thereof toward the East, and toward the West, and
there shall bee a very great valley, and halfe of the Mountaine
shall remoue toward the North, and halfe of it toward the
South.</ab>
<ab n="5">And ye shal
flee to the valley of the mountaines: for the valley of the
mountaines shal reach vnto Azal: yea, ye shall flee like as yee
fled from before the earthquake in the dayes of Uzziah king of
Iudah: and the Lord my God shall come, and all the Saints with
thee.<note> Or, my mountaines. , Or, when he shal touch the valley of the mountaines to the place be separated. , Amos 1.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And it shall
come to passe in that day, that the light shall not be cleare, nor
darke.<note> Hebr. precious. , Hebr. thicknesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">But it shall be
one day, which shalbe knowen to the Lord, not day nor night: but it
shal come to passe that at euening time it shalbe
light.<note> Or, the day shalbe one. , Reuel.20. 25. , Isa.60. 26. reu.21. 23.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And it shal be
in that day, that liuing waters shall goe out from Ierusalem: halfe
of them toward the former Sea, and halfe of them toward the hinder
Sea: in Summer and in winter shall it be.<note> Eze.47. 1. ioel 3.18. reue.22.1. , Eze.47. 1. ioel 3.18. reue.22.1. , Or, Easterns.</note></ab>

<fw>Against the enemies of
Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="9">And the Lord
shall be King ouer all the earth: in that day shal there be one
Lord, and his Name one.</ab>
<ab n="10">All the land
shall be turned as a plaine from Geba to Rimmon, South of
Ierusalem: and it shall be lifted vp and inhabited in her place:
from Beniamins gate vnto the place of the first gate, vnto the
corner gate, and from the towre of Hananiel vnto the Kings
winepresses.<note> Or, compassed. , Or, shall abide.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">And men shall
dwell in it, and there shalbe no more vtter destruction: but
Ierusalem shalbe safely inhabited.<note> Or, shall abide.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">¶ And
this shall be the plague, wherewith the Lord will smite all the
people, that haue fought against Ierusalem: their flesh shall
consume away, while they stand vpon their feete, and their eyes
shall consume away in their holes, and their tongue shall consume
away in their mouth.</ab>
<ab n="13">And it shall
come to passe in that day, that a great tumult from the Lord shalbe
among them, and they shall lay holde euery one on the hand of his
neighbour, and his hand shall rise vp against the hand of his
neighbour.</ab>
<ab n="14">And Iudah also
shall fight at Ierusalem; and the wealth of all the heathen round
about shall be gathered together, golde and siluer, and apparell in
great abundance.<note> Or, thou also O Iudah shalt. , Or, against.</note></ab>

<fw>Against the enemies of
Ierusalem.</fw>
<ab n="15">And so shall
be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camell, and of the
asse, and of all the beasts that shall be in these tents, as this
plague.</ab>
<ab n="16">¶ And it
shall come to passe that euery one that is left of all the nations
which came against Ierusalem, shall euen goe vp from yeere to yeere
to worship the King the Lord of hostes, and to keepe the feast of
Tabernacles.</ab>
<ab n="17">And it shall
be, that who so will not come vp of all the families of the earth
vnto Ierusalem, to worship the King the Lord of hostes, euen vpon
them shall be no raine.</ab>
<ab n="18">And if the
family of Egypt goe not vp, and come not, that haue no raine: there
shall bee the plague wherewith the Lord will smite the heathen that
come not vp to keepe the feast of Tabernacles.<note> Heb. vpon whom there is not.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">This shall be
the punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all nations that
come not vp to keepe the feast of Tabernacles.<note> Or, sinne.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">¶ In that
day shall there be vpon the bels of the horses, Holines Unto The
Lord, and the pots in the Lords house shall bee like the bowles
before the Altar.<note> Or, bridles.</note></ab>
<ab n="21">Yea, euery pot
in Ierusalem and in Iudah shall bee Holinesse vnto the Lord of
hostes, and all they that sacrifice, shall come and take of them,
and seethe therein: and in that day there shall be no more the
Canaanite in the house of the Lord of hostes.<note> Isai 35.8. ioel 3.17. reu. 21.27. and 22.15.</note></ab>



</div>