<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_07" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VII.</head>
<head>1 The captiues enquire of fasting. 4
Zechariah reproueth their fasting. 8 Sinne the cause of their
captiuitie.</head>

<ab n="1">And it came to
passe in the fourth yeere of King Darius, that the word of the Lord
came vnto Zechariah in the fourth day of the ninth moneth, euen in
Chisleu.</ab>
<ab n="2">When they had
sent vnto the house of God, Sherezer and Regem-melech, and their
men to pray before the Lord,<note> Heb. to intreat the face of the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And to speake
vnto the priestes, which were in the house of the Lord of hosts,
and to the prophets, saying, Should I weepe in the fift moneth,
separating my selfe, as I haue done these so many yeeres?</ab>
<ab n="4">¶ Then came
the word of the Lord of hosts vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="5">Speake vnto all
the people of the land, and to the priests, saying, When ye fasted
and mourned in the fift and seuenth moneth, euen those seuenty
yeeres; did ye at all fast vnto me, euen to me?<note> Isa.58.5.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And when ye did
eat, and when ye did drinke, did not ye eat for your selues, and
drinke for your selues?<note> Or, be not ye they that &amp;c.</note></ab>

<fw>Rebellious people.</fw>
<ab n="7">Should yee not
heare the wordes, which the Lord hath cried by the former Prophets,
when Ierusalem was inhabited, and in prosperitie, and the cities
thereof round about her, when men inhabited the South of the
plaine?<note> Or, are not these the wordes. , Hebr. by the hand of, &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">¶ And the
word of the Lord came vnto Zechariah, saying;</ab>
<ab n="9">Thus speaketh
the Lord of hostes, saying, Execute true iudgement, and shew mercie
and compassions euery man to his brother.<note> Heb. iudge iudgement of trueth.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">And oppresse
not the widow, nor the fatherlesse, the stranger, nor the poore,
and let none of you imagine euill against his brother in your
heart.<note> Exod.22. 21. isa.1. 23. iere.5. 28.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But they
refused to hearken, and pulled away the shoulder, and stopped their
eares, that they should not heare.<note> Hebr. they gaue a backsliding shoulder. , Hebr. made heauie.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">Yea, they made
their hearts as an adamant stone, lest they should heare the Law,
and the wordes which the Lord of hostes hath sent in his spirit by
the former Prophets: therefore came a great wrath from the Lord of
hostes.<note> Hebr. by the hand of &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore it is
come to passe, that as he cried, and they would not heare, so they
cried, and I would not heare, saith the Lord of hostes.<note> Pro.1.28. isa.1.15. iere.11.11. and 14.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">But I scattered
them with a whirlewinde among all the nations, whom they knew not:
thus the land was desolate after them, that no man passed through,
nor returned: for they layed the pleasant land
desolate.<note> Heb. land of desire.</note></ab>



</div>