<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-1-1.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-1-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>1 Zechariah exhorteth to repentance.
7 The vision of the horses. 12 At the prayer of the Angel,
comfortable promises are made to Ierusalem. 18 The vision of the
foure hornes, and the foure Carpenters.</head>

<ab n="1">In the eight
moneth, in the seconde yeere of Darius, came the word of the Lord
vnto Zechariah, the sonne of Barachiah, the sonne of Iddo the
Prophet, saying,</ab>
<ab n="2">The Lord hath
bene sore displeased with your fathers.<note> Hebr. with displeasure.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Therefore say
thou vnto them, Thus saith the Lord of hostes; Turne ye vnto me,
saith the Lord of hostes, and I will turne vnto you, saith the Lord
of hostes.<note> Mal.3.7.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Be ye not as
your fathers, vnto whom the former Prophets haue cried, saying,
Thus saith the Lord of hostes, Turne ye now from your euill wayes,
and from your euil doings: but they did not heare, nor hearken vnto
me, saith the Lord.<note> Isa.31.6. iere.3.12. and 18.11. eze.18.30. hose.14.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">Your fathers,
where are they? and the Prophets, doe they liue for euer?</ab>
<ab n="6">But my words and
my statutes, which I commanded my seruants the Prophets, did they
not take holde of your fathers? and they returned and saide; Like
as the Lord of hostes thought to doe vnto vs, according to our
wayes, and according to our doings, so hath he dealt with
vs.<note> Or, ouertake. , Lam.1.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Upon the
foure and twentieth day of the eleuenth moneth, which is the moneth
Sebat, in the second yere of Darius, came the word of the Lord vnto
Zechariah, the sonne of Barachiah, the sonne of Iddo the Prophet,
saying:</ab>

<fw>The vision of horses.</fw>
<ab n="8">I saw by night,
and behold a man riding vpon a red horse, and he stood among the
mirtle trees that were in the bottome, and behinde him were there
red horses, speckled and white.<note> Or, bay.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">Then said I, O
my Lord, what are these? And the Angel that talked with me, said
vnto me, I wil shew thee what these be.</ab>
<ab n="10">And the man
that stood among the myrtle trees answered, and said, These are
they, whom the Lord hath sent to walke to and fro through the
earth.</ab>
<ab n="11">And they
answered the Angel of the Lord that stood among the mirtle trees,
and said, Wee haue walked to and fro through the earth: and behold,
all the earth sitteth still, and is at rest.</ab>
<ab n="12">¶ Then the
Angel of the Lord answered, and said, O Lord of hosts, how long
wilt thou not haue mercie on Ierusalem, and on the cities of Iudah,
against which thou hast had indignation these threescore and ten
yeeres?</ab>
<ab n="13">And the Lord
answered the Angel that talked with me, with good words, and
comfortable words.</ab>
<ab n="14">So the Angel
that communed with me, said vnto me; Cry thou, saying; Thus saith
the Lord of hosts, I am iealous for Ierusalem, and for Zion, with a
great iealousie.<note> Chap.8.2.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">And I am very
sore displeased with the heathen that are at ease: for I was but a
little displeased, and they helped forward the affliction.</ab>
<ab n="16">Therefore thus
saith the Lord, I am returned to Ierusalem with mercies: my house
shall bee built in it, saith the Lord of hostes, and a line shalbe
stretched forth vpon Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="17">Cry yet,
saying, Thus saith the Lord of hostes, My cities through
prosperitie shall yet be spread abroad, and the Lord shall yet
comfort Zion, and shall yet choose Ierusalem.<note> Hebr. good.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">¶ Then
lift I vp mine eyes, and saw, and behold foure hornes.</ab>

<fw>A wall of fire.</fw>
<ab n="19">And I said vnto
the Angel that talked with me; What be these? and he answered mee,
These are the hornes which haue scattered Iudah, Israel, and
Ierusalem.</ab>
<ab n="20">And the Lord
shewed mee foure carpenters.</ab>
<ab n="21">Then said I,
What come these to doe? And hee spake, saying, These are the hornes
which haue scattered Iudah, so that no man did lift vp his head:
but these are come to fray them, to cast out the hornes of the
Gentiles, which lift vp their horne ouer the land of Iudah to
scatter it.</ab>



</div>