<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_10" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-9-11.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. X.</head>
<head>1 God is to be sought vnto, and not
idoles. 5 As he visited his flocke for sinne, so he will saue and
restore them.</head>

<ab n="1">Aske yee of the
Lord raine in the time of the latter raine, so the Lord shal make
bright clouds, and giue them showres of raine, to euery one grasse
in the field.<note> Or, lightnings.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">For the idoles
haue spoken vanitie, and the diuiners haue seene a lye, and haue
told false dreames; they comfort in vaine: therefore they went
their way as a flocke, they were troubled because there was no
shepheard.<note> Ier.10.8. abac.2.18. , Heb. teraphims. , Or, answered that &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Mine anger was
kindled against the shepheards, and I punished the goats: for the
Lord of hostes hath visited his flocke the house of Iudah, and hath
made them as his goodly horse in the battell.<note> Heb. visited vpon.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Out of him came
forth the corner, out of him the naile, out of him the battell bow,
out of him euery oppressour together.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ And they
shall bee as mightie men which tread downe their enemies in the
myre of the streets in the battell, and they shall fight because
the Lord is with them, and the riders on horses shall be
confounded.<note> Or, they shall make the riders on horses ashamed.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And I will
strengthen the house of Iudah, and I will saue the house of Ioseph,
and I will bring them againe to place them, for I haue mercie vpon
them: and they shall be as though I had not cast them off: for I am
the Lord their God, &amp; will heare them.</ab>
<ab n="7">And they of
Ephraim shall be like a mightie man, and their heart shall reioyce
as through wine: yea, their children shall see it, and be glad,
their heart shall reioyce in the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="8">I will hisse
for them and gather them, for I haue redeemed them: and they shall
increase as they haue increased.</ab>

<fw>Two staues.</fw>
<ab n="9">And I will sow
them among the people, and they shall remember me in farre
countries, and they shall liue with their children, and turne
againe.</ab>
<ab n="10">I will bring
them againe also out of the land of Egypt, and gather them out of
Assyria, and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon,
and place shall not be found for them.</ab>
<ab n="11">And he shall
passe through the sea with affliction, &amp; shall smite the waues
in the Sea, and all the deepes of the riuer shall dry vp: and the
pride of Assyria shall be brought downe, and the scepter of Egypt
shall depart away.</ab>
<ab n="12">And I will
strengthen them in the Lord, and they shall walke vp and downe in
his name, saith the Lord.</ab>



</div>