<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_08" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-7-8.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-8-9.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
VIII.</head>
<head>1 The restauration of Ierusalem. 9
They are incouraged to the building by Gods fauour to them. 16 Good
workes are required of them. 18 Ioy and inlargement are
promised.</head>

<ab n="1">Againe the word
of the Lord of hostes came to me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="2">Thus sayeth the
Lord of hostes, I was iealous for Zion, with great iealousie; and I
was iealous for her with great furie.<note> Cha.1. 14.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Thus saith the
Lord, I am returned vnto Zion, and will dwell in the midst of
Ierusalem, and Ierusalem shall be called a Citie of trueth, and the
Mountaine of the Lord of hostes, the holy Mountaine.</ab>

<fw>The Iewes restored.</fw>
<ab n="4">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts; There shall yet old men, and old women, dwell in the
streets of Ierusalem, and euery man with his staffe in his hand for
very age.<note> Hebr. for multitude of dayes.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">And the streets
of the citie shall be full of boyes and girles playing in the
streets thereof.</ab>
<ab n="6">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, If it bee marueilous in the eyes of the remnant of
this people in these dayes, should it also bee marueilous in my
eyes, saith the Lord of hostes?<note> Or, hard or difficult.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, Beholde, I will saue my people from the East
countrey, and from the West countrey.<note> Hebr. the countrey of the going downe of the Sunne.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And I will bring
them, and they shall dwell in the midst of Ierusalem, and they
shalbe my people, and I will bee their God, in Trueth and in
Righteousnesse.</ab>
<ab n="9">¶ Thus
saith the Lord of hostes, Let your handes be strong, ye that heare
in these dayes, these wordes by the mouth of the Prophets, which
were in the day that the foundation of the house of the Lord of
hosts was laied, that the Temple might be built.</ab>
<ab n="10">For before
these daies there was no hire for man, nor any hire for beast,
neither was there any peace to him that went out, or came in,
because of the affliction: for I set all men, euery one against his
neighbour.<note> Or, the hire of men became nothing. &amp;c. , Haggai.1. 6.</note></ab>
<ab n="11">But now I will
not bee vnto the residue of this people, as in the former daies,
saith the Lord of hostes.</ab>
<ab n="12">For the seed
shalbe prosperous: the Uine shall giue her fruit, and the ground
shall giue her increase, and the heauens shall giue their dew, and
I will cause the remnant of this people to possesse all these
things.<note> Hebr. of peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And it shall
come to passe, that as yee were a curse among the heathen, O house
of Iudah, and house of Israel; so will I saue you, and ye shalbe a
blessing: feare not, but let your handes bee strong.</ab>
<ab n="14">For thus saith
the Lord of hostes, As I thought to punish you, when your fathers
prouoked mee to wrath, saith the Lord of hostes, and I repented
not:</ab>
<ab n="15">So againe haue
I thought in these dayes to doe well vnto Ierusalem, and to the
house of Iudah: feare ye not.</ab>

<fw>Gentiles called.</fw>
<ab n="16">¶ These
are the things that yee shall doe; Speake yee euery man the truth
to his neighbor: execute the iudgment of trueth and peace in your
gates.<note> Ephes.4. 25. , Heb. iudge trueth, and the iudgement of peace.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">And let none of
you imagine euill in your hearts against his neighbour, and loue no
false oath: for all these are things that I hate, saith the
Lord.</ab>
<ab n="18">¶ And the
word of the Lord of hostes came vnto me, saying,</ab>
<ab n="19">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts; The fast of the fourth moneth, and the fast of the
fift, and the fast of the seuenth, and the fast of the tenth shall
be to the house of Iudah ioy and gladnesse, and cheerefull feasts:
therefore loue the trueth and peace.<note> Hebr. solemne, or set times.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, It shall yet come to passe, that there shall come
people, and the inhabitants of many cities.</ab>
<ab n="21">And the
inhabitants of one citie shall goe to another, saying, Let vs goe
speedily to pray before the Lord, and to seeke the Lord of hostes:
I will goe also.<note> Isa.2.2. mic.4.12. , Or, continually. Hebr. going. , Hebr. to intreat the face.</note></ab>
<ab n="22">Yea many people
and strong nations shall come to seeke the Lord of hostes in
Ierusalem, and to pray before the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="23">Thus saith the
Lord of hosts, In those daies it shall come to passe, that ten men
shall take holde out of all languages of the nations, euen shall
take hold of the skirt of him that is a Iew, saying, Wee will goe
with you: for we haue heard that God is with you.</ab>



</div>