<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_13" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-12-14.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
XIII.</head>
<head>1 The fountaine of purgation for
Ierusalem, 2 from idolatrie, and false prophecie. 7 The death of
Christ, and the triall of a third part.</head>

<ab n="1">In that day
there shalbe a fountaine opened to the house of Dauid, and to the
inhabitants of Ierusalem, for sinne, and for
vncleannesse.<note> Heb. seperation for vncleannesse.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">¶ And it
shal come to passe in that day, saith the Lord of hostes, that I
will cut off the names of the idoles out of the land: and they shal
no more be remembred: and also I wil cause the prophets, and the
vncleane spirit to passe out of the land.<note> Ezek.30. 13.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And it shal
come to passe that when any shall yet prophecie, then his father
and his mother that begate him, shall say vnto him, Thou shalt not
liue: for thou speakest lies in the Name of the Lord: and his
father and his mother, that begate him, shall thrust him through
when he prophecieth.</ab>
<ab n="4">And it shall
come to passe in that day, that the prophets shalbe ashamed euery
one of his vision, when hee hath prophecied: neither shall they
weare a rough garment to deceiue.<note> Hebr. a garment of haire. , Hebr. to lie.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">But he shal
say, I am no prophet, I am an husbandman: for man taught me to
keepe cattell from my youth.</ab>
<ab n="6">And one shal
say vnto him, What are these wounds in thine hands? Then hee shall
answere: Those with which I was wounded in the house of my
friends.</ab>
<ab n="7">¶ Awake, O
sword, against my shepheard, and against the man that is my fellow,
saith the Lord of hostes: smite the Shepheard, and the sheepe
shalbe scattered: and I wil turne mine hand vpon the litle
ones.<note> Matt.26. 31. mat.14. 27.</note></ab>

<fw>God trieth his.</fw>
<ab n="8">And it shall
come to passe, that in all the land, saith the Lord, two parts
therein shall be cut off, and die, but the third shall be left
therein.</ab>
<ab n="9">And I will
bring the thirde part through the fire, and wil refine them as
siluer is refined, &amp; will try them as gold is tried: they shall
call on my Name, and I wil heare them: I wil say, It is my people:
and they shall say, The Lord is my God.<note> 1.Pet.1. 6, 7.</note></ab>



</div>