<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_04" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. IV.</head>
<head>1 By the golden Candlesticke is
foreshewed the good successe of Zerubbabels foundation. 11 By the
two Oliue trees the two anointed ones.</head>

<ab n="1">And the Angell
that talked with me, came againe and waked me, as a man that is
wakened out of his sleepe:</ab>
<ab n="2">And said vnto
mee, What seest thou? and I said, I haue looked, and behold a
candlesticke all of gold, with a bowle vpon the top of it, and his
seuen lampes thereon, and seuen pipes to the seuen lampes, which
were vpon the top thereof.<note> Heb. with her bowle. , Or, seuen seuerall pipes to the lampes &amp;c.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">And two Oliue
trees by it, one vpon the right side of the bowle, and the other
vpon the left side thereof.</ab>
<ab n="4">So I answered
and spake to the Angell that talked with mee, saying: What are
these, my Lord?</ab>
<ab n="5">Then the Angel
that talked with me, answered and said vnto me; Knowest thou not
what these be? and I said; No, my Lord.</ab>
<ab n="6">Then hee
answered and spake vnto mee, saying; This is the word of the Lord
vnto Zerubbabel, saying; Not by might, nor by power, but by my
spirit, saith the Lord of hostes.<note> Or, armie.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">Who art thou, O
great mountaine? before Zerubbabel thou shalt become a plaine, and
he shall bring forth the head stone thereof with shoutings, crying;
Grace, grace vnto it.</ab>
<ab n="8">Moreouer the
word of the Lord came vnto me, saying;</ab>
<ab n="9">The hands of
Zerubbabel haue layed the foundation of this house: his hands shall
also finish it, and thou shalt know that the Lord of hostes hath
sent me vnto you.</ab>
<ab n="10">For who hath
despised the day of small things? for they shall reioyce and shall
see the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel with those seuen: they
are the eyes of the Lord, which run to and fro through the whole
earth.<note> Or, sith the seuen eyes of the Lord shall reioyce. , Heb. stone of tinne. , Chap.3.9.</note></ab>

<fw>A flying booke.</fw>
<ab n="11">¶ Then
answered I, and said vnto him; What are these two oliue trees vpon
the right side of the candlesticke, and vpon the left side
thereof?</ab>
<ab n="12">And I answered
againe and said vnto him, What be these two oliue branches, which
through the two golden pipes emptie the golden oyle out of
themselues?<note> Heb. by the hand. , Or, emptie out of themselues oyle into the gold. , Heb. the gold,</note></ab>
<ab n="13">And hee
answered mee and said; Knowest thou not what these be? and I said,
No, my Lord.</ab>
<ab n="14">Then said he;
These are the two annointed ones, that stand by the Lord of the
whole earth.<note> Heb. sonnes of oyle.</note></ab>



</div>