<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZechariah_05" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-3-5.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zechariah-Chapter-5-7.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. V.</head>
<head>1 By the flying rowle, is shewed the
curse of Theeues and Swearers. 5 By a woman pressed in an Ephah,
the finall damnation of Babylon.</head>

<ab n="1">Then I turned,
and lift vp mine eyes, and looked, and behold, a flying
roule.</ab>
<ab n="2">And hee said
vnto mee, What seest thou? and I answered, I see a flying roule,
the length thereof is twentie cubites, and the breadth thereof
tenne cubites.</ab>
<ab n="3">Then said hee
vnto mee; This is the curse, that goeth forth ouer the face of the
whole earth: for euery one that stealeth shall be cut off as on
this side, according to it; and euery one that sweareth shall be
cut off as on that side, according to it.<note> Or, euery one of this people that stealeth, holdeth himselfe guiltlesse as it doth.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I will bring it
forth, saith the Lord of hostes, and it shall enter into the house
of the theefe, and into the house of him that sweareth falsely by
my name: and it shall remaine in the midst of his house, and shall
consume it, with the timber thereof, and the stones
thereof.</ab>
<ab n="5">¶ Then the
Angell that talked with me, went forth and said vnto me, Lift vp
now thine eyes, and see what is this that goeth forth.</ab>
<ab n="6">And I said, What
is it? and hee said, This is an Ephah that goeth forth. Hee said
moreouer, This is their resemblance through all the earth.</ab>
<ab n="7">And behold,
there was lift vp a talent of lead: and this is a woman that
sitteth in the midst of the Ephah.<note> Or, weighey piece.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And he said,
This is wickednesse, and he cast it into the midst of the Ephah,
and he cast the weight of lead vpon the mouth thereof.</ab>

<fw>Foure charets.</fw>
<ab n="9">Then lift I vp
mine eyes, and looked, &amp; behold, there came out two women, and
the winde was in their wings (for they had wings like the wings of
a storke) and they lift vp the Ephah betweene the earth and the
heauen.</ab>
<ab n="10">Then saide I to
the Angel that talked with me, Whither do these beare the
Ephah?</ab>
<ab n="11">And he said
vnto mee, To build it an house in the land of Shinar, and it shall
be established, and set there vpon her owne base.</ab>



</div>