<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZephaniah_03" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zephaniah-Chapter-2-3.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP.
III.</head>
<head>1 A sharpe reproofe of Ierusalem for
diuers sinnes. 8 An exhortation to wait for the restauration of
Israel: 14 and to reioyce for their saluation by God.</head>

<ab n="1">Woe to her that
is filthie and polluted, to the oppressing citie.<note> Or, gluttenous. Heb. craw.</note></ab>
<ab n="2">She obeyed not
the voice: she receiued not correction: she trusted not in the
Lord: she drew not neere to her God.<note> Or, instruction.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">Her princes
within her are roaring lyons; her Iudges are euening wolues, they
gnaw not the bones till the morrow.<note> Ezek.22. 27. mic.3. 11.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">Her prophets are
light and treacherous persons: her priests haue polluted the
Sanctuarie, they haue done violence to the Law.<note> Ier.23.11. hose.9.7. , Ezek.22. 26.</note></ab>
<ab n="5">The iust Lord is
in the middest thereof: he will not doe iniquitie: euery morning
doeth hee bring his iudgement to light, he faileth not: but the
vniust knoweth no shame.<note> Heb. morning by morning.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">I haue cut off
the nations: their towres are desolate, I made their streetes
waste, that none passeth by: their cities are destroied, so that
there is no man, that there is none inhabitant.<note> Or, corners.</note></ab>
<ab n="7">I said, Surely
thou wilt feare mee: thou wilt receiue instruction: so their
dwelling should not bee cut off, howsoeuer I punished them: but
they rose early, &amp; corrupted all their doings.</ab>

<fw>Gods loue.</fw>
<ab n="8">¶ Therefore
waite ye vpon mee, sayth the Lord, vntill the day that I rise vp to
the pray: for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may
assemble the kingdomes to powre vpon them mine indignation, euen
all my fierce anger: for all the earth shalbe deuoured with the
fire of my iealousie.<note> Chap.1.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="9">For then will I
turne to the people a pure language, that they may all call vpon
the Name of the Lord, to serue him with one consent.<note> Heb. lip. , Heb. shoulder.</note></ab>
<ab n="10">From beyond the
riuers of Ethiopia, my suppliants, euen the daughter of my
dispersed shal bring mine offring.</ab>
<ab n="11">In that day
shalt thou not be ashamed for all thy doings, wherein thou hast
transgressed against me: for then I will take away out of the midst
of thee them that reioyce in thy pride, and thou shalt no more be
haughty because of mine holy mountaine.<note> Heb. in my holy.</note></ab>
<ab n="12">I will also
leaue in the middest of thee an afflicted and poore people: and
they shall trust in the Name of the Lord.</ab>
<ab n="13">The remnant of
Israel shall not doe iniquitie, nor speake lies: neither shall a
deceitful tongue be found in their mouth: for they shall feede, and
lie downe, and none shall make them afraid.</ab>
<ab n="14">¶ Sing, O
daughter of Zion: shout, O Israel: be glad and reioyce with all the
heart, O daughter of Ierusalem.<note> Isai 12.6. and 54.1.</note></ab>
<ab n="15">The Lord hath
taken away thy iudgements, he hath cast out thine enemy: the King
of Israel, euen the Lord is in the middest of thee: thou shalt not
see euill any more.</ab>
<ab n="16">In that day it
shall be said to Ierusalem, Feare thou not: and to Zion, Let not
thine hands be slacke.<note> Or, faint.</note></ab>
<ab n="17">The Lord thy
God in the midst of thee is mightie: hee will saue, he will reioyce
ouer thee with ioy: hee will rest in his loue, hee will ioy ouer
thee with singing.<note> Heb. he will be silent.</note></ab>
<ab n="18">I will gather
them that are sorrowfull for the solemne assembly, who are of thee,
to whom the reproch of it was a burden.<note> Heb. the burden vpon it was reproch.</note></ab>
<ab n="19">Behold, at that
time I will vndoe all that afflict thee, and I will saue her that
halteth, and gather her that was driuen out, and I will get them
praise and fame in euery land, where they haue beene put to
shame.<note> Mic.4.7. , Heb. I will set them for a praise. , Hebr. of their shame.</note></ab>
<ab n="20">At that time
will I bring you againe euen in the time that I gather you: for I
will make you a name and a praise among all people of the earth,
when I turne backe your captiuitie before your eyes, saith the
Lord.</ab>



</div>