<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CZephaniah_01" type="chapter">








<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Habakkuk-Chapter-3-3-Zephaniah.jpg"/>


<pb facs="http://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611-Bible-KJV/Zephaniah-Chapter-1-2.jpg"/>





<head>CHAP. I.</head>
<head>Gods seuere iudgement against Iudah
for diuers sinnes.</head>

<ab n="1">The worde of the
Lord which came vnto Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of
Gedaliah, the sonne of Amariah, the sonne of Hizkiah, in the dayes
of Iosiah, the sonne of Amon king of Iudah.</ab>
<ab n="2">I will vtterly
consume all things from off the land, saith the Lord.<note> Heb. by taking away I will make an end. , Heb. the face of the land.</note></ab>
<ab n="3">I will consume
man and beast: I will consume the foules of the heauen and the
fishes of the sea, and the stumbling blocks with the wicked, and I
will cut off man from off the land, saith the Lord.<note> Or, Idoles.</note></ab>
<ab n="4">I will also
stretch out mine hand vpon Iudah, and vpon all the inhabitants of
Ierusalem, and I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place,
and the name of the Chemarims with the priests:</ab>
<ab n="5">And them that
worship the hoste of heauen vpon the house tops, &amp; them that
worship, and that sweare by the Lord, and that sweare by
Malcham:<note> Or, to the Lord.</note></ab>
<ab n="6">And them that
are turned backe from the Lord, &amp; those that haue not sought
þ<note/> Lord, nor enquired for him.</ab>
<ab n="7">Hold thy peace
at the presence of the Lord God: for the day of the Lord is at
hand: for the Lord hath prepared a sacrifice: he hath bid his
ghests.<note> Heb. sanctified or prepared.</note></ab>
<ab n="8">And it shall
come to passe in the day of the Lords Sacrifice, that I will punish
the princes, and the kings children, and al such as are clothed
with strange apparell.<note> Heb. visite vpon.</note></ab>

<fw>Setled on the lees.</fw>
<ab n="9">In the same day
also wil I punish all those that leape on the threshold, which fill
their masters houses with violence and deceit.</ab>
<ab n="10">And it shall
come to passe in that day, saith the Lord, that there shall be the
noise of a cry from the fish gate, and an howling from the second,
and a great crashing from the hils.</ab>
<ab n="11">Howle yee
inhabitants of Maktesh, for all the merchant people are cut downe:
all they that beare siluer are cut off.</ab>
<ab n="12">And it shall
come to passe at that time, that I wil search Ierusalem with
candles, and punish the men that are setled on their lees, that say
in their heart, The Lord will not doe good, neither will he doe
euill.<note> Hebr. curded, or thickned.</note></ab>
<ab n="13">Therefore their
goods shall become a booty, and their houses a desolation: they
shall also build houses, but not inhabite them, and they shall
plant Uineyards, but not drinke the wine thereof.<note> Deu.28. 36, 39. amos 5.11.</note></ab>
<ab n="14">The great day
of the Lord is neere, it is neere, and hasteth greatly, euen the
voice of the day of the Lord: the mighty man shall cry there
bitterly.</ab>
<ab n="15">That day is a
day of wrath, a day of trouble and distresse, a day of wastenesse
and desolation, a day of darknesse and gloominesse, a day of
cloudes and thicke darkenesse;<note> Iere.30.7. ioel 2.11. amos 5.18.</note></ab>
<ab n="16">A day of the
trumpet and alarme against the fenced cities, and against the high
towres.</ab>
<ab n="17">And I will
bring distresse vpon men, that they shall walke like blinde men,
because they haue sinned against the Lord, and their blood shall
bee powred out as dust, and their flesh as the doung.</ab>
<ab n="18">Neither their
siluer nor their golde shall be able to deliuer them in the day of
the Lords wrath; but the whole land shall bee deuoured by the fire
of his iealousie: for hee shall make euen a speedy riddance of all
them that dwell in the land.<note> Prou. 11. 4. ezek.7. 19. , Zeph.3.8.</note></ab>



</div>