
<div type="dedication" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    
    <p>To the most high and mightie Prince, James by the grace of God King of Great Britaine,
        France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. The translators of The Bible, wish
        Grace, Mercie, and Peace, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
    
    <p>Great and manifold were the blessings (most dread Soveraigne) which Almighty GOD, the
        Father of all Mercies, bestowed upon us the people of ENGLAND, when first he sent your
        Majesties Royall person to rule and raigne over us. For whereas it was the expectation
        of many, who wished not well unto our ZION, that upon the setting of that bright
        Occidentall Starre Queene ELIZABETH of most happy memory, some thicke and palpable
        cloudes of darkenesse would so have overshadowed this land, that men should have bene in
        doubt which way they were to walke, and that it should hardly be knowen, who was to
        direct the unsetled State: the appearance of your MAJESTIE, as of the Sunne in his
        strength, instantly dispelled those supposed and surmised mists, and gave unto all that
        were well affected, exceeding cause of comfort; especially when we beheld the government
        established in your HIGHNESSE, and your hopefull Seed, by an undoubted Title, and this
        also accompanied with Peace and tranquillitie, at home and abroad.</p>
    
    <p> But amongst all our Joyes, there was no one that more filled our hearts, then the
        blessed continuance of the Preaching of GODS sacred word amongst us, which is that
        inestimable treasure, which excelleth all the riches of the earth, because the fruit
        thereof extendeth it selfe, not onely to the time spent in this transitory world, but
        directeth and disposeth men unto that Eternall happinesse which is above in Heaven.</p>
    
    <p> Then, not to suffer this to fall to the ground, but rather to take it up, and to
        continue it in that state, wherein the famous predecessour of your HIGHNESSE did leave
        it; Nay, to goe forward with the confidence and resolution of a man in maintaining the
        trueth of CHRIST, and propagating it farre and neere, is that which hath so bound and
        firmely knit the hearts of all your MAJESTIES loyall and Religious people unto you, that
        your very Name is precious among them, their eye doeth behold you with comfort, and they
        blesse you in their hearts, as that sanctified person, who under GOD, is the immediate
        authour of their true happinesse. And this their contentment doeth not diminish or
        decay, but every day increaseth and taketh strength, when they observe that the zeale of
        your Majestie towards the house of GOD, doth not slacke or goe backward, but is more and
        more kindled, manifesting it selfe abroad in the furthest parts of Christendome, by
        writing in defence of the Trueth, (which hath given such a blow unto that man of Sinne,
        as will not be healed) and every day at home, by Religious and learned discourse, by
        frequenting the house of GOD, by hearing the word preached, by cherishing the teachers
        therof, by caring for the Church as a most tender and loving nourcing Father.</p>
    
    <p> There are infinite arguments of this right Christian and Religious affection in your
        MAJESTIE: but none is more forcible to declare it to others, then the vehement and
        perpetuated desire of the accomplishing and publishing of this Worke, which now with all
        humilitie we present unto your MAJESTIE. For when your Highnesse had once out of deepe
        judgment apprehended, how convenient it was, That out of the Originall sacred tongues,
        together with comparing of the labours, both in our owne and other forreigne Languages,
        of many worthy men who went before us, there should be one more exact Translation of the
        holy Scriptures into the English tongue; your MAJESTIE did never desist, to urge and to
        excite those to whom it was commended, that the worke might be hastened, and that the
        businesse might be expedited in so decent a maner, as a matter of such importance might
        justly require.</p>
    
    <p> And now at last, by the Mercy of GOD, and the continuance of our Labours, it being
        brought unto such a conclusion, as that we have great hope that the Church of England
        shall reape good fruit thereby; we hold it our duety to offer it to your MAJESTIE, not
        onely as to our King and Soveraigne, but as to the principall moover and Author of the
        Worke. Humbly craving of your most Sacred Majestie, that since things of this quality
        have ever bene subject to the censures of ill meaning and discontented persons, it may
        receive approbation and Patronage from so learned and judicious a Prince as your
        Highnesse is, whose allowance and acceptance of our Labours, shall more honour us and
        incourage us, then all the calumniations and hard interpretations of other men shall
        dismay us. So that, if on the one side we shall be traduced by Popish persons at home or
        abroad, who therefore will maligne us, because we are poore Instruments to make GODS
        holy Trueth to be yet more and more knowen unto the people, whom they desire still to
        keepe in ignorance and darknesse: or if on the other side, we shall be maligned by
        selfe-conceited brethren, who runne their owne wayes, and give liking unto nothing but
        what is framed by themselves, and hammered on their Anvile; we may rest secure,
        supported within by the trueth and innocencie of a good conscience, having walked the
        wayes of simplicitie and integritie, as before the Lord; And sustained without, by the
        powerfull Protection of your Majesties grace and favour, which will ever give
        countenance to honest and Christian endevours, against bitter censures, and uncharitable
        imputations. </p>
    
    <p> The LORD of Heaven and earth blesse your Majestie with many and happy dayes, that as his
        Heavenly hand hath enriched your Highnesse with many singular, and extraordinary Graces;
        so you may be the wonder of the world in this later age, for happinesse and true
        felicitie, to the honour of that Great GOD, and the good of his Church, through JESUS
        CHRIST our Lord and onely Saviour. </p>
</div>
