<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sow's Ear to Silk Purse</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published at http://foxglove.hypothese.org/524 (wouldn't it be nice if I could
            just upload this TEI XML to that site, but ... )</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source: an original work</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><change when="2017-03-20">Blog entry first posted</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>How to make a sow's ear into a silk purse/Comment faire d'une buse un épervier</head>
         <p>As the proverb says, you can't turn a buzzard into a sparrow-hawk. But here's how I went about producing a TEI-conformant
            minimally encoded edition of the 1611 King James bible, starting from an all-singing,
            all-dancing, vastly over-complicated, web site to the existence of which Martin Mueller
            had alerted me last Friday in <ref
               target="http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/1611-King-James-Bible-tp4029494.html"> a
               plaintive posting to TEI-L<graphic url="mueller-mail.png"/></ref>
         </p>
         <p>The problem with web sites like this is that they expose only various HTML views of
            their underlying data, usually heavily infested with javascript, often deploying all
            sorts of nonstandard gizmos to make the pages look just so. I've no quarrel with their
            doing that, I just wish they'd make it a bit easier to get at the real data, i.e. the
            transcribed text and the pointers to the images that go with them. This site is a case
            in point: after spending some time looking at some of the gazillion HTML files a
            simple-minded <ident>wget -r</ident> starts hoovering up, I hypothesize that the data is
            actually stashed away somewhere inaccessible and all that you see on the site is a bunch
            of variously configured static web pages which have been created from it. The good thing
            about that is that the static web pages were created by an automaton, and the process
            can therefore be reversed by another automaton. The bad thing is that (in this case at
            least) clearly different automata have been used to generate vaguely different versions
            of the same page. For example: the following three URLs all show subtly different
            versions of the same first page of the 1611 bible :
               <ref>https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/1611_Genesis-Chapter-1/</ref>
            <ref>https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Genesis-Chapter-1_Original-1611-KJV/</ref>
            <ref>https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Genesis_1_1611/</ref> These are not simple
            redirects: each URL delivers a file in a different format. Well, I could have asked
            whoever runs this site what was going on, but that would have spoiled the fun, so I
            chose the format I liked best (the last of the three above) and wrote a script to
            generate requests for just those pages. I had to assume that the URLs would follow a
            consistent naming format, encouraged by a table of the names of the books of the bible I
            found in one of the chunks of embedded javascript, and which I moved into <ref
               target="https://github.com/lb42/KJV_1611/blob/master/work/grab.prl">my little perl
               script</ref>. Running this script produced a bash script which grabbed each page
            using <ident>curl</ident> and saved it as an HTML file on my machine. </p>
         <p>What went wrong with this process? Surprisingly little: I didn't find out till Sunday
            lunchtime that not only had I completely overlooked the Apocryphal books, but also that
            the file naming conventions used for these were not <emph>quite</emph> the same as for
            the canonical chapters ("Judith" for example is actually spelled "Iudeth"), but for the
            bulk of the 1300 or so chapters my guesses about the URL to use were spot on.</p>
         <p>The real challenge was disentangling the useful data from the resulting screen-scraped
            mess of pottage. My usual approach here is to run the HTML I get through Dave Ragget's
            utterly wonderful <ident>tidy</ident> utility to turn it into kosher XML, and then write
            an XSLT script to pick out the bits I want. In this case, however, the pottage I got was
            so messy even tidy threw up its metaphorical hands and refused to proceed with it, so I
            had to concoct <ref
               target="https://github.com/lb42/KJV_1611/blob/master/work/extract.prl">a little perl
               script</ref> to pre-process each file and extract just the useful part, before
            running it through tidy, and processing the resulting XML into conformant TEI by means
            of <ident>saxon</ident> and <ref
               target="https://github.com/lb42/KJV_1611/blob/master/work/postGrab.xsl">a little XSLT
               stylesheet</ref>. Like this: <eg><code>for f in webScraped/*.html; do \
                  FNAME=`basename $f .html`;\ echo ${FNAME} ;\ perl extract.prl $f | \ tidy -q
                  --error-file tidyerrs --doctype omit --numeric-entities yes -asxml | \ saxon
                  -o:chaps/${FNAME}.xml -s:- -xsl:postGrab.xsl chapId=${FNAME};\ done;</code></eg>
         </p>
         <p>And what went wrong with <emph>this</emph> process? Well, quite a lot, as you might
            expect, but nothing that couldn't be fixed by tweaking and rerunning the process (this
            is why I always put the effort into writing bash scripts for jobs like this: they can be
            rerun till I get it right). For example, I was deriving an XML id for each chapter from
            the name of the input file, but some of the files had names beginning with digits. My
            plan was to put each chapter into a separate XML file and then use xInclude to munge
            them together into a TEI document (to maximize the flexibility of said mungeing) -- but
            for this to work I had to get namespace declarations in the right place, and as anyone
            who has used them knows, anything involving namespace declarations never works the first
            time. To say nothing of unexpected inconsistencies in the data : which in fact were
            really very few. In fact so far, the only thing that has so far caught me out was a
            handful of chunks which looked like biblical data in the HTML markup but were not.
            Fortunately these were detectable because they wound up with an invalid <att>n</att>
            attribute in the XML output and could therefore be weeded out after the event.</p>
         <p>While all this was going on, I wrote my driver file and did some further sniffing around
            on the interwebs for sources from which to complete the work. The 1611 Bible has a title
            page and loads of prefatory matter not all of which is available on
            www.kingjamesbibleonline.org (for the record, I found the title page on Wikimedia, and
            the rest of the front matter at several places, but in page image form only). </p>
         <p>How should the Bible be modelled as a TEI document? In my first view, each verse is an
               <gi>ab</gi>, each chapter is a <gi>div</gi>, each book is a <gi>text</gi>, each
            testament is a <gi>group</gi>. This made sense to me, but then I realised that
            processing would be simpler if instead each book were regarded as a <gi>div</gi> of a
            different type; hence, that is what the current versions of both driver file and ODD
            say. Considerations of where to put the genealogies, tables for Easter, almanachs etc.
            which arguably do not belong in the front matter may lead me to review that decision, so
            I have left <gi>group</gi> lurking in my ODD. It should also be possible to produce a
            separate driver file representing that alternative view.</p>
         <p>A more pressing need, however, is to sort out the placement of the page image links: in
            the HTML source, and therefore in my XML, links to the page images for the whole of a
            chapter are given as a sequence at the start of the transcribed text for that chapter,
            rather than being placed at the point in the transcript where that page begins. In some
            cases that point is identifiable because the transcribers have chosen to include part of
            the running page header in the transcription there (it winds up as <gi>fw</gi>); but in
            many it isn't. Most chapters only occupy a few pages so sorting this out would not be a
            major effort, just a rather tedious one, and not-easily-automatable one. </p>
         <p>So what have we learned? Actually it's not that hard to make a usable TEI document even
            from something as idiosyncratic as this web site. Which is encouraging. Let me also
            hasten to add that I mean no disrespect for the hard work (still less for the
            generosity) which must have gone into the production of that website: everyone is
            entitled to their own design decisions. I am pleased to express my thanks to the
            anonymous people who have put in that effort, and decided to share its fruits even with
            the godless multitude. As the 1611 translators say in their preface <q>Zeale to promote
               the common good, whether it be by devising any thing our selves, or revising that
               which hath bene laboured by others, deserveth certainly much respect and esteeme</q>.
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
